<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17478509</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1904277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm248</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>RNA</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Post-transcriptional modification mapping in the <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA by mass spectrometry and reverse transcriptase assays</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Emmerechts</surname><given-names>Gert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barb&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Sofie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herdewijn</surname><given-names>Piet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ann&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Jozef</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rozenski</surname><given-names>Jef</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Laboratory for Medicinal Chemistry and <sup>2</sup>Laboratory of Bacteriology, Rega Institute for Medical Research, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Minderbroedersstraat 10, B-3000 Leuven, Belgium</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: <email>Gert.Emmerechts@rega.kuleuven.be</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3494</fpage><lpage>3503</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Post-transcriptional modifications in ribosomal RNA are believed to fine-tune the RNA functions. The present study describes the characterization of the post-transcriptional modifications in <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA, using high-pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC) coupled to electrospray ionization mass spectrometry and reverse transcriptase assays. The combination of these techniques allowed the identification of eleven modified nucleosides, which were mapped onto the rRNA sequence. The <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> modification map is similar to that of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, with the majority of the modifications near functionally important sites in the rRNA. Although, in general, the number of modifications in rRNA is smaller than in tRNA, the conservation of the modification sites seems to indicate that the post-transcriptional modifications in 16S rRNA provide a necessary prerequisite for the ribosomal function.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>One of the most intriguing aspects of non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) is their post-transcriptional modification. Post-transcriptional modifications in RNAs are of three main types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>): (i) conversion of uridine to pseudouridine (5-ribosyluracil, &#x003a8;); (ii) methylation of 2&#x02032; hydroxyls (Nm) and (iii) alterations to bases, generally methylations of different positions (mN). High-pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC) coupled to mass spectrometry (MS) is the first method of choice for the analysis of post-transcriptional modifications because it is both very sensitive and specific. Furthermore, nearly all modifications cause a change in mass, making detection with LC/MS fairly straightforward.</p><p>Up till now, post-transcriptional modifications have been studied mostly in tRNA and oligonucleotide models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2 B3 B4">2&#x02013;4</xref>). On the other hand, 16S rRNA is much less investigated and consequently, the number of organisms for which the post-transcriptional modifications in the 16S rRNA are characterized is much smaller (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> is the only mesophilic bacterium for which the rRNA (16S and 23S) appears to be fully characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) and recently, the 16S rRNA modification map of <italic>Thermus thermophilus</italic> was published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>).</p><p>The collective importance of post-transcriptional modifications for efficient protein synthesis has been demonstrated by the superior performance of authentic rRNAs compared to unmodified 16S rRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) and 23S rRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) counterparts. Further analysis of the function of post-transcriptional modifications in 16S rRNA would most definitely benefit from a larger number of fully characterized organisms to allow comparison of the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). As a first step in the production of these data, we analyzed the <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA. <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> was selected in order to add a Gram-positive, anaerobic and mesophilic bacterium to the short list of bacteria for which the 16S rRNA modification map has been completed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Furthermore, the rather low-G content of the <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA (30%) leads to larger oligonucleotides when the rRNA is hydrolyzed with the G-specific endonuclease T1 and this facilitates the localization of modifications.</p><p>At first, modified nucleosides were identified solely based on their chromatographic mobility (e.g. <sup>32</sup>P and/or <sup>14</sup>C-labeling and 2D electrophoresis combined with thin layer chromatography (TLC), anion exchange chromatography and HPLC). However, these methods suffer from poor specificity and reproducibility and identification becomes problematic as the number of modifications or RNA chain length increases. In contrast, MS is a better technique for the analysis of post-transcriptional modifications, because nearly all modifications produce a change in mass of the canonical nucleosides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). The application of MS to nucleic acids has long been restricted due to the experimental difficulties associated with the ionization of polar compounds such as nucleosides, nucleotides and oligonucleotides. Since the development of electrospray ionization (ESI) and matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization (MALDI), these molecules can be ionized and analyzed by MS. ESI currently holds the advantage because of its greater accuracy and ease with which it can be coupled to chromatographic separation systems. Combining the high-resolving power of the HPLC system and the high specificity of the mass measurement offers a method which is superior to either method alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). More than a hundred different modifications are known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) and the majority have been characterized by some form of MS.</p><p>The general setup for identification and sequence placement of post-transcriptional modifications in large RNAs is based on the LC/ESI-MS analysis of two enzymatic digests. First the rRNA strand is digested to the nucleoside-level and analyzed by LC/ESI-MS. The combination of chromatographic retention times and mass measurements allows identification of nearly all the modifications that are present in the original intact RNA strand. Distinction between isomers (e.g. m<sup>5</sup>C and m<sup>4</sup>C) is made based on comparison to tandem MS (pseudo MS<sup>3</sup>, see the Methods section) analysis of reference samples. In a second step, sequence-specific endonucleases are used to cleave the intact RNA at specific positions (e.g. RNase T1 cleaves the 3&#x02032;-side of all unmodified guanosines and RNase A cleaves at the 3&#x02032; end of all pyrimidine nucleotides). This way, oligonucleotides restricted to one or two 3&#x02032;-nucleotide types are produced, which are subsequently analyzed by LC/ESI-MS. Comparison of the observed mass data with data predicted from the gene sequence identifies oligonucleotides that contain modifications. These anomalous oligonucleotides are analyzed by MS/MS for exact sequence placement of the modification in the oligonucleotide and thus in the RNA sequence. Two types of MS/MS experiments were used: In a first condition without precursor selection in the quadrupole, a higher collision energy is used to release monomer ions from the oligonucleotide. These monomers are often base ions, but also nucleoside phosphates and cyclic phosphates can be used. The Time-of-Flight (TOF) analyzer screens both the low-mass region for the modified monomer and the high-mass region for the intact oligonucleotide. Corresponding signals in the reconstructed ion chromatograms (RICs) identify the nature of the modification in the oligonucleotide. In a second condition, MS/MS analysis, with precursor selection, is used for sequencing of the oligonucleotide and exact sequence placement of the modification that was identified in the base-release experiments.</p><p>Using LC/ESI-MS nearly all the post-transcriptional modifications can be mapped in the RNA sequence. Pseudouridine, however, does not allow straightforward analysis by MS because it is isobaric to the omnipresent uridine. Patteson <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) and Mengel-J&#x000f6;rgenson <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>) reported addition of a mass tag to all &#x003a8; by specific derivatization. We developed a method to increase &#x003a8; detection sensitivity by derivatization with methyl vinyl sulfone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Pomerantz and McCloskey identified &#x003a8; solely based on identification of signature masses for &#x003a8; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Unfortunately, the presence of &#x003a8; in the sequence G&#x003a8;G (as in the case of <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA) makes these methods not useful because they are all based on preliminary RNase T1 digestion, which will produce numerous UG isomers. Pomerantz and McCloskey propose in this case to replace RNase T1 by nuclease U2, but this enzyme is no longer commercially available. Therefore, a reverse transcriptase assay was used for placement of pseudouridines in the 16S rRNA sequence. Pseudouridine bases were selectively derivatized with <italic>N</italic>-cyclohexyl-<italic>N</italic>&#x02032;-&#x003b2;-(4-methylmorpholinium) ethylcarbodiimide <italic>p</italic>-tosylate (CMCT). Upon subsequent reverse transcription, CMC derivatized &#x003a8; blocks elongation of radioactively labeled primers, highlighting the position of the &#x003a8; on a PAGE gel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16 B17 B18">16&#x02013;18</xref>).</p><p>Even without CMC derivatization, the reverse transcriptase approach can be used for sequence confirmation of modifications found by LC-MS, because most modifications block the reverse transcriptase elongation. Therefore, reverse transcriptase assays can be used to determine the sequence location of modifications when this is not possible by LC-MS analysis. Examples are the identification of a modified oligonucleotide in a group of isomers or when problems arise during MS/MS sequencing (for examples, see the result section below). In any case, the reverse transcriptase stops should be checked by simultaneous analysis of <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed RNA, because stops can be caused by secondary structure of the RNA, even at elevated temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Cells</title><p><italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> (ATCC824) was grown in 2 &#x000d7; YT medium containing 16&#x02009;g bacto-tryptone, 10&#x02009;g yeast extract, 4&#x02009;g NaCl and 10&#x02009;g glucose per liter. Cultures were grown anaerobically in a modular atmosphere-controlled system (MACS, Don Whitley Scientific, Shipley, UK) at 37&#x000b0;C in 50&#x02009;ml medium. Growth phase was monitored by turbidity measurement at 600&#x02009;nm and cells were harvested at an OD of &#x000b1;1.5 by centrifugation at 10&#x02009;000 r.p.m. for 10&#x02009;min. Multiple isolates of these 50&#x02009;ml batches were combined and pellets were stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of rRNA</title><p>16S rRNA was isolated in two steps. A first step consisted of the isolation of total RNA from the bacterial pellet using lysozyme digestion and phenol/chloroform extraction. In a second step, the 16S rRNA was purified from this total RNA mixture by rate zonal centrifugation through a 10&#x02013;30% sucrose gradient. The samples were centrifuged at 94 000<italic>g</italic> on a Beckman L7-55 ultracentrifuge (SW 28 rotor) for 24&#x02009;h, and 750&#x02009;&#x003bc;l fractions were collected.</p><p>Purity of the isolated 16S rRNA was assessed by formaldehyde-agarose gel electrophoresis (1.85% formaldehyde, 1.3% agarose) using a Bio-Rad Mini Sub DNA Cell electrophoresis system.</p></sec><sec><title>Enzymatic digestion of rRNA</title><p>To produce the nucleoside mixture, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g (3&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l) 16S rRNA was hydrolyzed with 10 U nuclease P1 (Amersham, Chalfont, UK), 0.01 U snake venom phosphodiesterase I (E.C.3.1.15.1, Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA), and 2.5 U shrimp alkaline phosphatase (E.C. 3.1.3.1., Amersham) as described by Crain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Digests were stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until analysis by LC/ESI-MS.</p><p>To produce the oligonucleotide mixture, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g 16S rRNA (10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l in 10&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA acid, pH 7.4) was hydrolyzed with RNase T1 (E.C. 31.27.3, Amersham-GE Healthcare) at 37&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min. The amount of enzyme was 1 U RNase T<sub>1</sub>/3&#x02009;&#x003bc;g rRNA and digests were also stored at &#x02013;80&#x000b0;C until analysis by LC/ESI-MS. With these conditions, m<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>G and m<sup>7</sup>G modifications were resistant to RNase T1 hydrolysis.</p></sec><sec><title>LC/ESI-MS of the nucleosides</title><p>The instrument used for all studies was an orthogonal acceleration quadrupole time of flight, oa-qTOF (Q-Tof 2 Micromass, Manchester, UK), with an ESI source, interfaced to a capillary liquid chromatograph with a diode array detector (Waters, Milford, MA, USA). Both the mass spectrometer and the CapLC are controlled by the MassLynx 3.4 software (Micromass, Manchester, UK).</p><p>For the nucleosides mixture, 2&#x02013;5 pmol of rRNA hydrolysate were injected directly onto an Atlantis dC18 column (0.32 &#x000d7; 150&#x02009;mm, 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;m diameter particles, Waters, Milford, USA). The column was eluted at a flow rate of 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;l/min using an ammonium acetate (50&#x02009;mM in Millipore Milli-Q water, pH 6.0)/acetonitrile gradient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Diode array UV absorbance data were acquired from 240&#x02013;300&#x02009;nm.</p><p>The chromatographic effluent was conducted without splitting into the mass spectrometer and two different scan functions were used. For the first scan function, the cone voltage and collision energy were set to 30&#x02009;V and 10&#x02009;eV, respectively, allowing mass measurement of the intact nucleoside. Qualitative interpretation of data was carried out as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Data were acquired over a mass range of <italic>m/z</italic> 100&#x02013;700. For the second scan function, pseudo MS<sup>3</sup> was accomplished by fragmentation in the source, selection of the base anion in the quadrupole and fragmentation in the collision cell. The cone voltage used for MS<sup>3</sup> was 30&#x02013;40&#x02009;V and the collision energy 30&#x02009;eV. Data were acquired in positive mode over a mass range of <italic>m/z</italic> 50&#x02013;250. With this second scan function, distinction between nucleoside isomers (e.g. m<sup>5</sup>C and m<sup>4</sup>C) is possible.</p><p>The capillary voltage for both scan functions was 3&#x02009;kV, and data were acquired in continuum mode during 1.9&#x02009;s (with 0.1&#x02009;s interscan delay, giving a cycle time of 2&#x02009;s).</p></sec><sec><title>LC/ESI-MS of an oligonucleotides mixture</title><p>The same instruments were used as for the analysis of the nucleoside mixture. 2&#x02013;5 pmol of the oligonucleotide mixture were injected directly onto a PepMap C18 column (0.3 &#x000d7; 150&#x02009;mm, 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m-diameter particles, LC-Packings, Amsterdam, The Netherlands). The column was eluted at a flow rate of 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;l/min, using a 1,1,1,3,3,3-hexafluoro-2-propanol (HFiP, Acros, Geel, Belgium) based solvent system (60&#x02009;mM HFiP in MQ water, adjusted to pH 7.5 with triethylamine) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). The organic modifier was acetonitrile and a 2-step linear gradient (0.5%/min during 50&#x02009;min and 5%/min during 10&#x02009;min.) was used. Diode array UV absorbance data were acquired from 230 to 320&#x02009;nm.</p><p>Different scan functions were used for data acquisition. During the first scan function, cone voltage and collision energy were kept at 30 and 10&#x02009;eV, respectively. Thus, minimizing fragmentation, intact oligonucleotide molecular masses can be detected. Data were recorded in continuum mode over a <italic>m/z</italic> 500&#x02013;1500 mass range. For the second scan function, the collision energy was increased to 40&#x02009;eV to release monomers from oligonucleotides. Data were acquired over a <italic>m/z</italic> 100&#x02013;1500 mass range and modified bases and intact precursor ions (the modification containing oligonucleotides) are recorded simultaneously. Oligonucleotide sequencing was performed in a third scan function at 30&#x02009;V cone voltage and collision energies varying from 20 to 40&#x02009;eV. During this scan function, precursor ions were selected in the quadrupole. Finally, to confirm the detection of sugar methylated nucleosides, a fourth scan function was used: The cone voltage was increased to 60&#x02009;V in order to release modified nucleoside cyclic phosphate ions. After selection of these ions in the quadrupole, a collision energy of 20&#x02009;eV was used to release the unmodified base and the methylated ribose ion (pseudo MS<sup>3</sup>).</p><p>During all scan functions, samples were recorded in negative mode and the capillary voltage was kept at &#x02212;2850&#x02009;V.</p></sec><sec><title>Software</title><p>Mongo Oligo Mass Calculator (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://medlib.med.utah.edu/massspec/mongo.htm">http://medlib.med.utah.edu/massspec/mongo.htm</ext-link>) generated a mass-ordered list of all oligonucleotides produced by RNase T1 digestion of 16S rRNA of <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>. This list is calculated based on the gene sequence (GenBank accession number NC_003030) and the software allows calculation of the electrospray series and the selection of modified nucleosides.</p><p>In-house software was used to search the <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA sequence for oligonucleotides corresponding to masses that were found in the mass data from the samples analyzed. It allows the user to restrict the search on the basis of the 5&#x02032; or 3&#x02032; end, number and residue masses of modifications, undercut residues and phosphorylation state.</p><p>Simple oligonucleotide sequencer (SOS) was used for the sequencing of modified oligonucleotides based on the fragmentation spectra produced by CID (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> production of 16S rRNA</title><p>The gene sequence corresponding to <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA was isolated from genomic DNA by a PCR with primer 27f: 5&#x02032;-AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG-3&#x02032; and primer 1492r: 5&#x02032;-GGCTACCTTGTTACGACT-3&#x02032; (Sigma Genosys). For this PCR, a mixture of 10:1 Taq: Pfu Turbo polymerases was used and primer concentrations were 0.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. Buffer conditions were as provided by the TOPO cloning protocol. After 3&#x02009;min at 94&#x000b0;C, 20 cycles of 1&#x02009;min at 94&#x000b0;C, 1&#x02009;min at 55&#x000b0;C and 3&#x02009;min incubation at 72&#x000b0;C were used. Incubation of the samples for 7&#x02009;min at 72&#x000b0;C guaranteed full-length PCR products with 3&#x02032;-A overhangs, necessary for TOPO cloning. After purification with a PCR purification kit (Qiagen, Crawley, UK), the amplified 16S rRNA gene was cloned, downstream of the T7 promotor sequence, into a pCR4-TOPO vector (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) following the protocol provide by the supplier. After heat shock transformation of TOP10 cells, distinct colonies were incubated overnight in 0.01% ampicillin containing LB. For the selection of colonies with inserts in the correct direction, PCR was performed with two combinations of primers. For a first PCR (the positive control), these primers were 27f (sequence as above) and M13r: 5&#x02032;-GGAAACAGCTATGACCATG-3&#x02032;. If the insert is in the correct position, a band should be visible at 1.6 kB after agarose gel electrophoresis. A second PCR (negative control) with primers 27f and M13f: 5&#x02032;-GTAAAACGACGGCCAGT-3&#x02032; was used for confirmation. If the insert is in the correct position, no band should be visible after agarose gel electrophoresis. Conditions were as above, except that primer concentrations were 0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;M and no final 7-min incubation step at 72&#x000b0;C was necessary. Correct clones were digested with PmeI, which produces blunt ends downstream of the rRNA sequence. After cleanup with a PCR purification kit (Qiagen), <italic>in vitro</italic> RNA was produced using the Ribomax T7 kit (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). After RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) purification, 1&#x02013;2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l 16S rRNA was obtained.</p></sec><sec><title>CMC derivatization and reverse transcription</title><p>Fifteen to twenty-five microgram of total RNA was derivatized as in ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). To remove the CMC groups of U and G, the mixture was placed for 4.5&#x02009;h at pH 10.4 on 37&#x000b0;C. After precipitation with sodium acetate and ethanol the RNA was reverse transcribed with Avian Myeloblastosis Virus (AMV) reverse transcriptase (GE Healthcare, Brick, NJ, USA) using 5&#x02032;-<sup>33</sup>P-labeled primers. The primer complementary to residues 548&#x02013;569 (<italic>E. coli</italic> numbering) was used for identification of &#x003a8;-516. Other primers used for &#x003a8;-screening were complementary to residues 1098&#x02013;1219, 1221&#x02013;1243, 1435&#x02013;1475 and 1492&#x02013;1510. For hybridization, the mixture containing 6 pmol RNA, 0.3 pmol primer and hybridization buffer (55.5&#x02009;mM HEPES Potassium salt pH 7.0 and KCl 111&#x02009;mM) in a total volume of 13.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;l was heated at 80&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;min and cooled gradually to 40&#x000b0;C in 30&#x02009;min. For the extension reaction, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l hybridization mixture and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M ddNTP were added to 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;l extension mix containing: 0.166&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl pH 8.4, 13.3&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 13.3&#x02009;mM DTT, 0.066&#x02009;mM each dGTP, dATP, dCTP and dTTP (GE Healthcare) and 0.33 U AMV reverse transcriptase. Samples were incubated 5&#x02009;min at room temperature and 35&#x02009;min at 42&#x000b0;C. After reaction and precipitation with sodium acetate and ethanol, the samples were dissolved in 6&#x02009;&#x003bc;l urea loading buffer containing 8&#x02009;M urea, 20&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl pH 7.8, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA and 0.02% xylene cyanol and bromophenol blue dyes. The samples were loaded on 7&#x02009;M urea &#x02212;&#x02009;8% polyacrylamide gels and run in 1&#x000d7; TBE buffer at 45&#x02009;W until the bromophenol blue dye reached the bottom of the gel. Radioactive products were visualized using a PhosphorImager.</p><p>Except for the CMC derivatization, sequence location of m<sup>5</sup>C at position 1409 (<italic>E. coli</italic> numbering) was performed by reverse transcription of radiolabeled primers as described above. The radiolabeled primer was: 5&#x02032;-CCAAAAGGTTACCTCACGGG-3&#x02032; complementary to nucleotides 1435&#x02013;1475 (<italic>E. coli</italic> numbering).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Mapping of modified nucleosides by LC/MS</title><p>Modified nucleosides were identified by LC/ESI-MS analysis of the <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA. The chromatographic separation of a total nucleoside digest is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. The presence of nine different modified nucleosides in the 16S rRNA of <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> is indicated, &#x003a8;, D, m<sup>5</sup>C, Cm, m<sup>7</sup>G, m<sup>3</sup>U, m<sup>4</sup>Cm, m<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>G and m<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>A. Most of the assignments could be derived from relative retention times and correspondence of RICs for the protonated base and nucleoside masses. For m<sup>5</sup>C, m<sup>4</sup>Cm and m<sup>3</sup>U, specific placement of the modifications on the base or sugar residue was done based on LC/ESI-pseudo MS<sup>3</sup> comparison to standard samples (data not shown). The absence of specific tRNA nucleosides (in particular <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-threonylcarbamoyl-adenosine) indicates that no tRNA contamination is present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>HPLC chromatogram after total nucleoside digestion of purified <italic>C</italic>. <italic>acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA. UV trace at 260&#x02009;nm with annotation of modified nucleosides and other components. (*) Are non-nucleoside artefacts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm248f1"/></fig></p><p>The mass silent modification pseudouridine (&#x003a8;) was not detected by LC/ESI-MS of the nucleosides digest and it was added in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> based on literature data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Even with the method described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>), no reliable identification was possible, probably because of the very low concentration, short retention time on the reversed phase column and higher number of fragment ions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). The structures of the modified nucleosides that were characterized in this study can be viewed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://medlib.med.utah.edu/RNAmods">http://medlib.med.utah.edu/RNAmods</ext-link> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>).</p><p>The modified nucleosides depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> were mapped onto the 16S rRNA sequence by LC/ESI-MS analysis of an RNase T1 digest of the intact purified 16S rRNA. Comparison of the measured data to data predicted from the gene sequence identified eight modified oligonucleotides. These oligonucleotides and the <italic>m/z</italic> values for modified monomers inside these oligonucleotides are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. The modified monomers are released during LC/ESI-MS/MS analysis with fragmentation in the collision cell, without precursor selection in the quadrupole. This experimental setup allows detection of the released modified bases and nucleotide monomers at the same time as the molecular ion signals of the oligonucleotides from which they originate. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> illustrates these experiments for the oligonucleotide AAm<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>Gm<sup>5</sup>CAACGp. Exact sequence placement of these modifications and of the sugar modifications was done in a third step where fragmentation with precursor selection was used to sequence the modified oligonucleotides. Using sequencing software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) unambiguous mapping of the modification in the modification containing oligonucleotides and thus in the rRNA could be established (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>).
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>HPLC-MS analysis of an RNase T1 hydrolysis mixture of <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA. Analysis was performed at 40&#x02009;eV collision energy without precursor selection. (<bold>A, B, C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) Reconstructed ion chromatograms for the oligonucleotide AAGCAACGp + 3 methyl groups, showing co-elution of signature ions for the intact oligonucleotide and base ions for m<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>G and m<sup>5</sup>C. (<bold>E</bold>) UV trace at 260&#x02009;nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm248f2"/></fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Product ion mass spectrum from CID of AAGCAACGp + 3 methyl groups (<italic>m/z</italic> 1337.2) at 45&#x02009;eV. Signature ion series are indicated and place the modifications at AA<bold>m<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>Gm<sup>5</sup>C</bold>AACGp (for ion series nomenclature see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm248f3"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Assignments of oligonucleotides from RNase T<sub>1</sub> digestion of <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligonucleotide</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence location<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Mass</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calculated<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measured</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monomer ions (<italic>m/z</italic>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF4"><sup>d</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCm<sup>7</sup>GCG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">525&#x02013;529</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1623.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1637.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 [B-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAm<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>Gm<sup>5</sup>CAACG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">964&#x02013;971</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2634.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2676.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178, 124 [B-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UCmAAAUCAUCAUG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1194&#x02013;1206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4147.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4161.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">336 [Np-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCCCUUAUG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF6"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1207&#x02013;1215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2830.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2832.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">307 [N &#x0003e; p-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">m<sup>4</sup>CmCCG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1402&#x02013;1405</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1278.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1306.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 [B-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UCAm<sup>5</sup>CACCAUG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1406&#x02013;1415</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3182.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3196.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">318 [N &#x0003e; p-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">m<sup>5</sup>UAACAAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1498&#x02013;1504</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2290.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2304.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 [B-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">m<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>Am<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>ACCUG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1518&#x02013;1523</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1937.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 [B-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p><sup>a</sup>Unmodified oligonucleotides contain guanosines and should have been hydrolyzed by RNase T<sub>1</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="TF2"><p><sup>b</sup>Sequence location utilizes <italic>E. coli</italic> numbering.</p></fn><fn id="TF3"><p><sup>c</sup>Predicted, monoisotopic masses, calculated from the 16S rRNA gene sequence.</p></fn><fn id="TF4"><p><sup>d</sup><italic>m/z</italic> Values for monomers released in the collision cell at higher collision energy, [B-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>: base, [Np-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>: nucleoside phosphate, [N &#x0003e; p-H]<sup>&#x02212;</sup>: nucleoside cyclic phosphate.</p></fn><fn id="TF5"><p><sup>e</sup>Cm1195 is identified by Pseudo MS<sup>3</sup> with fragmentation of N &#x0003e; p (<italic>m/z</italic>) 318.</p></fn><fn id="TF6"><p><sup>f</sup>The exact location of the dihydrouridine could not be determined, it is position 1211 or 1212.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Sequencing analysis by MS/MS of the oligonucleotide UCACACCAUGp (mass: 3196.4), for sequence placement of the extra methyl group, was problematic. Both precursor ions with sufficient intensity for MS/MS fragmentation (<italic>m/z</italic> values 1064.5 and 798.1) co-eluted with other oligonucleotides with nearby <italic>m/z</italic> values (e.g. the 3&#x02032;-terminal AUCACCUCCUUUCU, without 3&#x02032; phosphate, with mass 4262.5 and <italic>m/z</italic> 1064.6 and the oligonucleotide AUUAAUACCGp at pos. 155 with mass 3204.4 and <italic>m/z</italic> 800.9). The masses of the precursor ions could not be selected separately without sacrificing sensitivity. Fortunately, m<sup>5</sup>C blocks reverse transcription and sequence location of this modification could be confirmed by a reverse transcriptase assay (result not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Mapping of pseudouridine in the 16S rRNA sequence by CMC derivatization and reverse transcription</title><p>The phosphorimage of reversed transcriptase products identifying &#x003a8;516 in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>. This figure also shows a band caused by m<sup>7</sup>G, which is also important because of the redundancy of the CCGCGp oligonucleotide produced by RNase T1 (three occurrences). With the reversed transcriptase technique, &#x0223c;30% of the 16S rRNA, containing the &#x003a8; modification sites in other organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>), were scanned. No other &#x003a8;s were detected in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Phosphorimage of reverse transcriptase products of the radiolabeled primer complementary to residues 548&#x02013;569 (<italic>E. coli</italic> numbering). C, U, A and G indicate (dideoxy-)sequencing lanes, <italic>wt.</italic> + CMC: CMC derivatized and alkali treated 16S rRNA purified from <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> bacteria. <italic>wt.</italic> &#x02212; CMC: alkali treated 16S rRNA purified from <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> bacteria. <italic>In vitro</italic>: T7 RNA polymerase transcribed 16S rRNA from the cloned 16S rRNA gene. Arrows indicate bands corresponding to modified nucleosides or secondary structure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm248f4"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Of the 11 post-transcriptionally modified nucleosides that were reported in <italic>E. coli</italic> 16S rRNA, seven were also detected in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA, while position 966 contains a m<sup>2</sup>G in <italic>E. coli</italic> and a m<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>G in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>. Interestingly, the same seven modifications, and the m<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>G at position 966, were recently reported in the 16S rRNA of <italic>T. thermophilus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), indicating that these modifications are perhaps indispensable for the ribosomal biosynthesis or maturation. Indeed, they are situated in or near helices 18, 31, 34, 44, 45 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>), which are functionally important sites in the small subunit (SSU), where contacts to tRNA and the large subunit (LSU) are made (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). This location would allow them to directly influence these interactions or play a role in the 3D folding of these important domains. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>, three modifications in <italic>E. coli</italic> are not present in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>, while three modifications in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> are absent in <italic>E. coli</italic>. Some of these differences are situated in helix 34 in the head domain of the SSU. The Cm at position 1195 (<italic>E. coli</italic> numbering) in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> is not present in <italic>E. coli</italic>, although the base sequence is nearly the same: &#x02026; AGACGU<bold><underline>C</underline></bold>AAGUCA&#x02009;&#x02026; in <italic>E. coli</italic> and &#x02026;&#x02009;UGACGU<bold><underline>Cm</underline></bold>AAAUCA&#x02009;&#x02026; in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>. The m<sup>2</sup>G modification at position 1207 in <italic>E. coli</italic> is not present in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>, but this is not a surprise as the primary sequence of the 16S rRNA is different at this position (C in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>, G in <italic>E. coli</italic>). Helix 34 interacts with A site tRNA, but the influence of these differences in modification maps on ribosomal function is unclear.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Secondary structure from bacterial 16S rRNA, important helices are numbered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm248f5"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Comparison of modifications in 16S rRNA of <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> with <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>T. thermophilus</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pos.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF7"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. Thermophilus</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">516</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudouridine (&#x003c8;)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudouridine (&#x003c8;)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudouridine (&#x003c8;)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">527</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-methylguanosine (m<sup>7</sup>G)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-methylguanosine (m<sup>7</sup>G)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-methylguanosine (m<sup>7</sup>G)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">966</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>-methylguanosine (m<sup>2</sup>G)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>-dimethylguanosine (m<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>G)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>-dimethylguanosine (m<sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>G)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">967</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1195</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">no modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-dimethylcytidine (Cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>-methylguanosine (m<sup>2</sup>G)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>-methylguanosine (m<sup>2</sup>G)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">no modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dihydrouridine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">no modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1402</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>4</sup>,2&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-dimethylcytidine (m<sup>4</sup>Cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>4</sup>,2&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-dimethylcytidine (m<sup>4</sup>Cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>4</sup>,2&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-dimethylcytidine (m<sup>4</sup>Cm)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1404</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">no modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1407</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1409</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">no modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-methyluridine (m<sup>3</sup>U)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-methyluridine (m<sup>3</sup>U)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-methyluridine (m<sup>3</sup>U)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1516</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>2</sup>-methylguanosine (m<sup>2</sup>G)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1518</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-dimethyladenosine (m<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-dimethyladenosine (m<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-dimethyladenosine (m<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>A)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1519</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-dimethyladenosine (m<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-dimethyladenosine (m<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-dimethyladenosine (m<sup>6</sup><sub>2</sub>A)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">no modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudouridine</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1541</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">no modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No modification present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudouridine</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF7"><p><sup>a</sup>Sequence position utilizes <italic>E. coli</italic> numbering.</p></fn><fn id="TF8"><p><sup>b</sup>X: 1211 or 1212.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Our data also indicate the presence of a dihydrouridine nucleoside at position 1211 or 1212, in between helices 32 and 34. However, both the LC/MS/MS data and RT assays do not allow identification of the exact location site. This is the first report on the presence of this modification in 16S rRNA, but further research is necessary to confirm the exact location of this modification and to determine its function.</p><p>Other differences are located in the 3&#x02032; minor domain. In helix 44 of <italic>E. coli</italic> 16S rRNA, a m<sup>5</sup>C is present at position 1407, while in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> this modification is present at position 1409 (<italic>E. coli</italic> numbering). Alignment of incomplete modification maps of all organisms in the SSU database indicates that both are rather conserved modification sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Why these two adjacent cytosines are so often modified is not known, both are situated in the functionally important helix 44, at either site of the bulged out A1406. G1516 in helix 45 of <italic>E. coli</italic> 16S rRNA, is methylated at position 2 of the base, while <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> contains an unmodified A at this position. Probably the purine at this position requires a rather hydrophobic site at position 2. Again, no further insight in the role of this modification is known.</p><p>In general, the level of modification appears to be equal in <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA (each 11 modification sites), while <italic>T. thermophilus</italic> 16S rRNA is more extensively modified (14 modification sites). However, it appears that <italic>E. coli</italic> can only represent mesophilic bacteria to a certain extent as some <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> modifications are absent from <italic>E. coli</italic> 16S rRNA, while some <italic>E. coli</italic> modifications are absent from <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA.</p><p>The bacterial ribosomal SSU is a target for many antibiotics. Both aminoglycoside (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) and cyclic peptide antibiotics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) target the top of helix 44 and tetracyclines bind multiple sites in the SSU, e.g. helix 34. It has been reported that some post-transcriptional modifications alter the resistance to these ribosome-targeting antibiotics. Therefore, knowledge of the natural modification maps might be interesting for the analysis of this type of resistance mechanism. As <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> is an important industrial bacterium, novel antibiotic resistance genes might be used for plasmid maintenance during genetic engineering. Furthermore, more information on this resistance mechanism is also interesting from a therapeutic point of view, because the <italic>Clostridium</italic> genus contains several pathogenic species. The influence of post-transcriptional modifications on the sensitivity to aminoglycosides has been the best studied, however, anaerobic <italic>Clostridium</italic> species are resistant to these antibiotics because they lack active membrane transport. Furthermore, resistance to the cyclic peptide antibiotics (capreomycin and viomycin) has been reported to be caused by the loss of a 2&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-methyl group from C1409 (<italic>E. coli</italic> numbering) in <italic>Mycobacteria</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>), other species without this modification (e.g. <italic>E. coli</italic>) are less sensitive. The influence of the 5-methylation of C1409 in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> or the loss of this methylation on the sensitivity to capreomycin or viomycin remains to be studied. <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> is sensitive to tetracyclines, but no links between resistance to these antibiotics and rRNA methylation has been reported yet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>).</p><p>The results for <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> were compared to the T1 catalog data, detected by Tanner <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>) and compiled in the SSU database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) These short sequences were used in early studies to establish patterns of phylogenetic relatedness. Although <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> itself was not determined, good correspondence was found with the other gram-positive anaerobic species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Not surprisingly, the best correspondence was found with <italic>C. butyricum</italic>, phylogenetically closest to <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>.
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>SSU database modifications list for the gram-positive anaerobes listed</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Gram-positive anaerobes</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">1: <italic>Clostridium barkeri</italic>, 2: <italic>Eubacterium limosum</italic>, 3: <italic>Acetobacterium woodii</italic>, 4: <italic>Clostridium lituseburense</italic>, 5: <italic>Eubacterium tenue</italic>, 6: <italic>Clostridium butyricum</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligonucleotide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>aa</bold>G<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA<bold>g</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF10"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 3&#x02013;5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>g</bold>CCG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC<bold>g</bold>CG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF11"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>c</bold>AACG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF10"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<bold>u</bold>UAG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>aa</bold>CCUG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF11"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>u</bold>AACAAG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF11"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UACACA(<bold>c</bold>,C)G<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCCC(<bold>u</bold>,U)AUG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UCA<bold>c</bold>ACCACG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UCA<bold>c</bold>ACCAUG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF11"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, 6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U<bold>c</bold>AAAUCAUCAUG<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF11"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Predicted modified nucleosides are in bold and small caps.</p></fn><fn id="TF9"><p><sup>a</sup>Were not detected in the <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> samples.</p></fn><fn id="TF10"><p><sup>b</sup>Were detected as the oligonucleotide AAGCAACG (see Table 1).</p></fn><fn id="TF11"><p><sup>c</sup>Were detected in the <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>During the last decade, several methods have been published that use MS for the analysis of post-transcriptional modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33 B34 B35 B36">33&#x02013;36</xref>). Quadrupole instruments are very popular because of the flexibility of their scan functions. Unfortunately, some of these scan functions are not available on a oa-qTof instrument. On the other hand, to determine the nature of modified bases in an oligonucleotide, the oa-qTof allows the use of a different scan function from the quadrupole scan functions. In quadrupole instruments, an increased cone voltage is applied to release modified bases or nucleotides from the oligonucleotides. Careful time alignment of chromatic profiles of runs with and without increased cone voltages is needed to identify modified oligonucleotides from which the modified bases or fragments originated. In contrast, in oa-qTof instruments, the release of these fragments can be initiated by increasing the collision voltage in the collision cell, thus producing monomer ions, which are measured in the TOF analyzer. The broad mass range of the TOF analyzer allows the simultaneous detection of the small base ions (<italic>m/z</italic> 100&#x02013;150) and the large oligonucleotide molecular ions (<italic>m/z</italic> 500&#x02013;1500) from which the base ions originate. With this different method of collision cell fragmentation without precursor selection, time alignment of chromatographic profiles is no longer necessary and nearly unambiguous connection of modified base ions and modification containing oligonucleotides is possible. It is another extension of the already wide variety of MS based methods for the analysis of post-transcriptional modifications in large RNAs. In source fragmentation instead of collision cell fragmentation is not an option on the oa-qTof, because the quadrupole filter, even when used in rf-only mode, restricts the transmission of a wide <italic>m/z</italic> range. This makes it impossible to simultaneously detect base and oligonucleotide anions.</p><p>Although LC/ESI-MS is extremely powerful in the analysis of post-transcriptional modifications, it seems that in some cases the combination with reverse transcriptase assays is necessary. For example, if both RNase T1 and RNase A digests produce redundant oligonucleotides (e.g. CCGCGp) or when MS/MS sequencing is problematic because of co-eluting oligonucleotides with the same <italic>m/z</italic> values (e.g. <italic>m/z</italic> 1064.5 for UCACACCAUGp, <italic>z</italic> = &#x02212;3, and the 3&#x02032; terminal oligonucleotide AUCACCUCCUUUCU, without 3&#x02032; phosphate with <italic>m/z</italic> 1064.6 and <italic>z</italic> = &#x02212;4). As was illustrated in this study for the oligonucleotide CCm<sup>7</sup>GCGp, reverse transcriptase is stopped at base modified nucleosides and, although exact identification of the modification is not possible, it can be used to discriminate redundant modified oligonucleotides, when comparison to data predicted from the gene sequence can not reveal the exact location of the modification.</p><p>Furthermore, analysis of pseudouridine by LC/MS is not straightforward because it is isobaric to uridine. Given the fact that the only known pseudouridylation site in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> 16S rRNA is present at position 516 (<italic>E. coli</italic> numbering) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>) and given the great correspondence between modifications in <italic>E. coli</italic> and modifications found in <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic>, &#x003a8; was expected to be present at position 516 in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA as well. Therefore, all methods based on preliminary RNase T1 digestion can not be used as they will produce 35 UG isomers from the <italic>C. acetobutylicum</italic> 16S rRNA. Pomerantz and McCloskey propose in this case to replace RNase T1 by nuclease U2, but this enzyme is no longer commercially available. We have chosen the approach described by Bakin and Ofengand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>): All U-like and G-like residues were derivatized with CMC followed by an alkaline removal of all CMC groups except those linked to the N3 of &#x003a8;. CMC derivatized &#x003a8; blocks the reverse transcription reaction of radiolabeled primers, highlighting the position of the &#x003a8; on a PAGE gel.</p><p>For both the analysis of pseudouridine and other modifications by reverse transcription assays, comparison of wild-type 16S rRNA to <italic>in vitro</italic> produced 16S rRNA is necessary to differentiate between bands on the gel that are caused by secondary structure of the 16S rRNA and bands that are caused by post-transcriptional modifications. Thus unambiguous identification of modification sites is possible.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><p>The authors thank the Fonds voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek&#x02014;Vlaanderen for financial support through grant 1.5.014.02 and Prof. B. Vester for advice with the reverse transcription reaction. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by FWO-Vlaanderen.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decatur</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>rRNA modifications and ribosome function</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12114023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprinzl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioudovitch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compilation of tRNA sequences and sequences of tRNA genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9399820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Studies). (Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Benne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biophysical and conformational properties of modified nucleosides in RNA</article-title><source>Modification and Editing of RNA</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rk</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ericson</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>CED</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagervall</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f6;nsson</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wikstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transfer RNA modification</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem</source><year>1987</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3304135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The small subunit rRNA modification database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>D135</fpage><lpage>D138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalak</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ofengand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The single pseudouridine residue in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> 16S RNA is located at position 516</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3681</fpage><lpage>3684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7524026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guymon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of phylogeny on posttranscriptional modification of rRNA in thermophilic prokaryotes: the complete modification map of 16S rRNA of <italic>Thermus thermophilus</italic></article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>4888</fpage><lpage>4899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16605256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krzyzosiak</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Denman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Boublik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehrke</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Agris</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ofengand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> synthesis of 16S ribosomal RNA containing single base changes and assembly into a functional 30S ribosome</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1987</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2353</fpage><lpage>2364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3304424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Noller</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstitution of functional 50S ribosomes from <italic>in vitro</italic> transcripts of <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic> 23S rRNA</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1772</fpage><lpage>1779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10026257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Benne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection and structure analysis of modified nucleosides in RNA by mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Modification and Editing of RNA</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rozenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RNA modification database: 1999 update</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patteson</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodicio</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Limbach</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the mass-silent post-transcriptionally modified nucleoside pseudouridine in RNA by matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>E49</fpage><lpage>E49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11353094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mengel-Jorgensen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirpekar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of pseudouridine and other modifications in tRNA by cyanoethylation and MALDI mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>200</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>e135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12466567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emmerechts</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Herdewijn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudouridine detection improvement by derivatization with methyl vinyl sulfone and capillary HPLC-mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J. Chromatogr. B Analyt. Technol. Biomed. Life Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>825</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>238</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of the common RNA nucleoside pseudouridine in mixtures of oligonucleotides by mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Anal. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>4687</fpage><lpage>4697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16053277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>NWY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilham</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reaction of pseudouridine and inosine with N-Cyclohexyl-N&#x02019;-b-(4-methylmorpholinium)ethylcarbodiimide</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1971</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>3651</fpage><lpage>3657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4328867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ofengand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Campo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping pseudouridines in RNA molecules</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>373</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ofengand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Four newly located pseudouridylate residues in <italic>E. coli</italic> 23S Ribosomal RNA are alle at the peptidyltransferase center: analysis by application of new sequencing technique</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1993</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>9754</fpage><lpage>9762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8373778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirpekar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritterbusch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Vester</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Posttranscriptional modifications in the A-loop of 23S rRNAs from selected archaea and eubacteria</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11911366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation and enzymatic hydrolisis of DNA and RNA for mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1990</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1706062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of RNA hydrolyzates by liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1990</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1706064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apffel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtenwalter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of Oligonucleotides by HPLC-electrospray ionization mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Anal. Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1320</fpage><lpage>1325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21639339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rozenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SOS: a simple interactive program for ab initio oligonucleotide sequencing by mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J. Am. Soc. Mass Spectrom</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11908799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noon</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruenger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mccloskey</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Posttranscriptional modifications in 16S and 23S rRNAs of the archaeal hyperthermophile <italic>Sulfolobus solfataricus</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1998</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>2883</fpage><lpage>2888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9603876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuytten</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemi&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gareth Brenton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmans</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of the mass spectrometric fragmentation of pseudouridine: comparison of fragmentation data obtained by matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionisation post-source decay, electrospray ion trap multistage mass spectrometry, and by a method utilising electrospray quadrupole time-of-flight tandem mass spectrometry and in-source fragmentation</article-title><source>Rapid Commun. Mass Spectrom</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3075</fpage><lpage>3085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16206154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLuckey</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Habibi-Goudarzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decompositions of multiple charged oligonucleotide anions</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>1993</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>12085</fpage><lpage>12095</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ofengand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Benne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pseudouridine residues of rRNA: number, location, biosynthesis, and function</article-title><source>Modification and Editing of RNA</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>253</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannone</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The accuracy of ribosomal RNA comparative structure models</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12127448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusupov</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusupova</surname><given-names>GZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baucom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Earnest</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cate</surname><given-names>JHD</given-names></name><name><surname>Noller</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the Ribosome at 5.5&#x02009;&#x000c5; Resolution</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>883</fpage><lpage>896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Douthwaite</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourmy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshizawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleotide methylations in rRNA that confer resistance to ribosome-targeting antibiotics</article-title><source>Fine-Tuning of RNA Functions by Modification and Editing</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>307</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Maus</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Plikaytis</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Douthwaite</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capreomycin binds across the ribosomal subunit interface using <italic>tlyA</italic>-encoded 2&#x02032;-O-methylations in 16S and 23S rRNA</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16857584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stackebrandt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Woese</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phylogenetic analysis of acetobacterium woodii, Clostridium barkeri, Clostridium butyricum, Clostridium lituseburense, Eubacterium limosum, and Eubacterium tenue</article-title><source>Curr. Microbiol</source><year>1981</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehill</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New techniques for the rapid characterization of oligonucleotides by mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Nucleosides Nucleotides</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1549</fpage><lpage>1553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10474232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Peltier</surname><given-names>JMPDR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Burlingame</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of posttranscriptional modification in nucleic acid by tandem mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Mass Spectrometry in the Biological Sciences</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>Clifton, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>517</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applications of mass spectrometry to the characterization of oligonucleotides and nucleic acids</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Biotechnol</source><year>1998</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9503584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruffner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Burlingame</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Problems and prospects in the characterization of posttranscriptional modifications in large RNAs</article-title><source>Mass Spectrometry in Biology and Medicine</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Clifton, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>551</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wrzesinski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ofengand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification, cloning, and properties of the 16S RNA Pseudouridine 516 Synthase from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1995</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>8904</fpage><lpage>8913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7612632</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
