<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17395642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1874660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm039</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Structural insight into repair of alkylated DNA by a new superfamily of DNA glycosylases comprising HEAT-like repeats</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dalhus</surname><given-names>Bj&#x000f8;rn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Helle</surname><given-names>Ina H&#x000f8;ydal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Backe</surname><given-names>Paul H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alseth</surname><given-names>Ingrun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rognes</surname><given-names>Torbj&#x000f8;rn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f8;r&#x000e5;s</surname><given-names>Magnar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laerdahl</surname><given-names>Jon K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Centre for Molecular Biology and Neuroscience (CMBN) and Institute of Medical Microbiology, Rikshospitalet-Radiumhospitalet Medical Centre, N-0027 Oslo, Norway, <sup>2</sup>Institute of Clinical Biochemistry, University of Oslo, N-0027 Oslo, Norway and <sup>3</sup>Department of Informatics, University of Oslo, PO Box 1080 Blindern, N-0316 Oslo, Norway</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+47 22844784</phone><fax>+47 22844782</fax><email>j.k.lardahl@medisin.uio.no</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2451</fpage><lpage>2459</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>3-methyladenine DNA glycosylases initiate repair of cytotoxic and promutagenic alkylated bases in DNA. We demonstrate by comparative modelling that <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> AlkD belongs to a new, fifth, structural superfamily of DNA glycosylases with an alpha&#x02013;alpha superhelix fold comprising six HEAT-like repeats. The structure reveals a wide, positively charged groove, including a putative base recognition pocket. This groove appears to be suitable for the accommodation of double-stranded DNA with a flipped-out alkylated base. Site-specific mutagenesis within the recognition pocket identified several residues essential for enzyme activity. The results suggest that the aromatic side chain of a tryptophan residue recognizes electron-deficient alkylated bases through stacking interactions, while an interacting aspartate&#x02013;arginine pair is essential for removal of the damaged base. A structural model of AlkD bound to DNA with a flipped-out purine moiety gives insight into the catalytic machinery for this new class of DNA glycosylases.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The integrity of DNA in all living cells is constantly challenged by damaging agents of exogenous and endogenous origin. Damage to DNA can lead to mutations or may interfere with normal cellular processes such as DNA replication and transcription. To avoid the deleterious effects of DNA base damage, there has been a strong driving force for the evolution of enzymatic pathways that recognize and repair DNA base lesions. Damage to single DNA bases due to processes such as oxidation, alkylation or deamination are principally handled by the highly conserved multistep base excision repair (BER) pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3">1&#x02013;3</xref>). BER is initiated by DNA glycosylases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) which locate damaged and, in some cases, mispaired bases and excise them by hydrolyzing the <italic>N</italic>-glycosylic bond between the 2&#x02032;-deoxyribose and the base. Monofunctional DNA glycosylases use an activated water molecule to attack the anomeric carbon of the damaged nucleotide, while bifunctional DNA glycosylases use an active site amine nucleophile and, in a concerted fashion, also nick the DNA backbone 3&#x02032; to the nascent abasic site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). In the subsequent steps, abasic site endonucleases cleave 5&#x02032; to the abasic nucleotide and the DNA ends are processed by phosphodiesterases. Finally, DNA polymerase and DNA ligase activities result in the complete restoration of the DNA sequence.</p><p>All organisms express several DNA glycosylases, each with unique substrate specificities. In human cells 10 distinct DNA glycosylases have now been characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Despite the wide range of base lesion targets for the DNA glycosylases, nature has employed a limited number of protein folds for these enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Four structural superfamilies of DNA glycosylases are currently recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>); the helix-hairpin-helix (HhH) and helix-two-turn-helix (H2TH) superfamilies termed after characteristic active site motifs, and the uracil DNA glycosylase (UDG) and alkyladenine DNA glycosylase (AAG) superfamilies named after structural similarity to two well-characterized human DNA glycosylases.</p><p>Members of the H2TH and HhH superfamilies contain multiple protein domains, and the active site and DNA-binding region is located at the junction between these domains. Examples of H2TH DNA glycosylases are <italic>E. coli</italic> formamidopyrimidine DNA glycosylase (Fpg) and endonuclease VIII (Nei), as well as the recently discovered vertebrate enzymes NEIL1 and NEIL2 (Nei-like), which all recognize and excise various oxidized base lesions. The HhH DNA glycosylase superfamily comprises a wide range of enzymes that excise oxidized bases, e.g. 8-oxoguanine DNA glycosylase (OGG1) and endonuclease III (Nth), alkylated bases, e.g. bacterial 3-methyladenine (3mA) DNA glycosylase II (AlkA) and mismatches, e.g. the adenine DNA glycosylase (MutY) that removes A from A/G mismatches. DNA glycosylases of the UDG and AAG structural superfamilies are compact single-domain enzymes. The members of the widely studied UDG superfamily contain a core of a four-stranded parallel twisted &#x003b2;-sheet flanked by &#x003b1;-helices. AAG consists of a single domain with an antiparallel &#x003b2;-sheet surrounded by &#x003b1;-helices. The major repair enzymes for removal of uracil in DNA belong to the UDG superfamily, while AAG is the only known mammalian DNA glycosylase specific to alkylated bases.</p><p>Recently, Alseth <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) characterized two novel 3mA DNA glycosylases from <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>, AlkC and AlkD, which are without sequence similarity to any protein of known function. Both proteins are monofunctional DNA glycosylases specific for removal of <italic>N</italic>-alkylated bases and without affinity for other base lesions such as deamination and oxidation products. In the present work we demonstrate that <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD and AlkC are members of a new and uncharacterized structural superfamily of DNA glycosylases with an alpha&#x02013;alpha superhelix fold. A structural model of AlkD based on homology modelling has been generated, and the location of a putative active site pocket has been determined by investigating residue conservation. Residues participating in alkylated DNA recognition and catalysis were detected by functional and biochemical analysis of mutant proteins generated on the basis of the structural model. Finally, a model of AlkD in complex with DNA containing a flipped-out purine moiety is analysed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Computational structure prediction and analysis</title><p>The accession numbers for the <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkC and AlkD proteins are CAJ31884 and CAJ31885, respectively. Single iteration sequence similarity searching in the NCBI non-redundant protein database were performed with PARALIGN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) and NCBI BLAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) and gave a set of approximately 80 significant hits (<italic>E</italic>-value &#x0003c;0.01) for <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD. After removal of erroneous and redundant sequences, the remaining 43 AlkD homologs were aligned with the multiple sequence alignment (MSA) program T-Coffee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). The MSAs were viewed and manipulated with Jalview (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Protein secondary structure predictions were generated with PSIPRED (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), PROF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), Jnet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>) and SSpro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>), and protein structural disorder predictions were performed with DISOPRED2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) and VSL1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>).</p><p>Fold recognition protein structure predictions were obtained with mGenTHREADER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), Phyre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) and SAM-T02 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Experimental structures for proteins homologous to <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD were obtained from the Protein Data Bank (PDB) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), including the structure of the hypothetical protein EF3068 of <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> V583 (PDB identifier 2B6C) determined by J. Osipiuk, C. Hatzos, S. Moy, F. Collart and A. Joachimiak. 2B6C is a 2.1&#x02009;&#x000c5; resolution X-ray structure generated as a part of the structural genomics effort of the Midwest Center for Structural Genomics (MCSG; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mcsg.anl.gov">http://www.mcsg.anl.gov</ext-link>). No accompanying publication or details about the structure have been released yet, apart from the experimental procedure and the coordinates in the PDB. A structural model for the <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD target was generated from the 2B6C template employing standard comparative modelling with SwissModel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>), and the model was analysed with WhatCheck (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>).</p><p>The SCOP structural classification of proteins database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) was used to investigate the relationships between the various repeat-rich structural protein families. Electrostatic potentials were calculated with APBS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) using the structure prepared for continuum electrostatistics calculations with PDB2PQR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>) and employing PROPKA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) for the pK<sub>a</sub> calculations. Amino acid conservation mapped onto the protein surface was generated with ConSurf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). All illustrations of protein structure were generated with PyMOL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Modelling of the AlkD&#x02013;DNA complex</title><p>DNA coordinates were extracted from the structure of AlkA in complex with a 15-mer double-stranded DNA incorporating the abasic site (AP-site) analogue 1-azaribose (PDB structure 1DIZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>)). A normal adenine nucleotide was superimposed onto the ribose of the flipped-out AP-site analogue, and the base was oriented to approximate a proposed model of 3mA inserted into the AlkA active site pocket (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). Subsequently, this DNA model with a flipped-out adenine, was manually docked onto the surface of AlkD making sure that the widened DNA minor groove was facing the protein and with complementary surfaces. Various orientations involving the flipped-out purine stacked with either Trp109 or Trp187 and with the anomeric carbon atom in reasonable distance to Asp113 were examined. The solution with the extrahelical adenine stacking with Trp109 appeared superior to the other orientations. This initial model complex was solvated using SYBYL (Tripos Inc.) and the protein&#x02013;DNA interface was optimized, removing a few steric clashes, using 500 steps of conjugated gradient minimization in CNS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). Initially, DNA from several DNA glycosylases as well as AP endonucleases were examined, but only DNA from AlkA and human OGG1 gave sensible, essentially equivalent, models without suffering from substantial steric conflicts or limited protein&#x02013;DNA contacts.</p></sec><sec><title>Site-directed mutagenesis and cloning</title><p>The Quick Change site-directed mutagenesis kit (Stratagene) was used to introduce mutations with the pUC18-AlkD construct as template (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Eight different oligonucleotides were designed using the manufacturer's protocol (from 5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032;, new codon in bold): gcagaaccgatggcacgt<bold>gct</bold>atgaaaaatcacttccta (Y27A), attgtaacaaaatcttgg<bold>gcg</bold>gacactgtcgatagcatc (W109A), tcttggtgggacactgtc<bold>aat</bold>agcatcgtccctacattt (D113N), attgcatcagataacata<bold>gcg</bold>ttacaacgggccgctatt (W145A), gataacatatggttacaa<bold>gcg</bold>gccgctattttattccag (R148A), ctacattcttcgaaagaa<bold>gct</bold>ttcattcaaaaagcgatt (F179A), cattcttcgaaagaattt<bold>gcc</bold>attcaaaaagcgattgga (F180A), attcaaaaagcgattggc<bold>gcg</bold>gtccttcgtgaatatgca (W187A). The AlkD mutant W187A was designed using a pT7-SCII AlkD construct as template. Mutant constructs were verified by DNA sequencing.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of crude cell extracts</title><p>AlkD mutant and wild-type constructs, as well as the pUC18 vector (control) were transformed into the 3mA DNA glycosylase deficient strain <italic>E. coli</italic> BK2118 (<italic>tag alkA</italic>), described by Clarke <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), grown in 1 l LB medium containing 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ampicillin to an OD<sub>600</sub> of &#x0223c;1.0 and induced with 0.3&#x02009;mM isopropyl-&#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactopyranoside for 2&#x02009;h at 37&#x000b0;C. Cells were harvested by centrifugation and protein extracts were prepared by sonication of the suspended cell pellets in 50&#x02009;mM NaCl, 10&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 7.0 and 10&#x02009;mM &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol. The cell debris was separated from the protein extract by centrifugation at 15&#x02009;000&#x02009;rpm for 20&#x02009;min at 4&#x000b0;C. Extracts prepared from the strains expressing AlkD showed a strong band corresponding to the molecular weight of AlkD on denaturing protein gels stained with Coomassie blue. This protein band was absent in extracts of the strain transformed with empty vector. The AlkD protein concentrations of each extract were quantified from the band intensity and showed that all mutant constructs and wild-type construct expressed equal amounts of soluble AlkD protein. The activities of the crude extracts were assessed by the DNA glycosylase assay.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA glycosylase assay</title><p>Calf thymus DNA alkylated with <italic>N</italic>-[<sup>3</sup>H]-methyl-<italic>N</italic>-nitrosourea ([<sup>3</sup>H]-MNU) (1.5 Ci&#x02009;mmol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was incubated with different amounts of cell extracts within the linear range, for 30&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). DNA was precipitated with ethanol and the radioactivity in the supernatant was quantified in a liquid scintillation counter (Tri-Carb 2900TR, Packard).</p></sec><sec><title>Alkylation survival of <italic>E. coli</italic> BK2118 (<italic>tag alkA</italic>) and transformed derivatives</title><p>BK2118 cells transformed with the expression constructs pUC18-AlkD, pUC18-Y27A, pUC18-W109A, pUC18-D113N, pUC18-W145A, pUC18-R148A, pUC18-F179A, pUC18-F180A and pT7-W187A were grown in LB medium with ampicillin (100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) to an OD<sub>600</sub> of &#x0223c;1.0 and diluted in M9-buffer to form a density gradient from 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> to 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. One microlitre aliquots of the diluted cultures were spotted onto LB agar plates without (control) and with 1&#x02009;mM methyl methanesulfonate (MMS) as well as 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ampicillin. BK2118 cells transformed with empty pUC18-vector were used as a control. Following incubation for 1&#x02009;day at 37&#x000b0;C, the plates were inspected for growth of colonies.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>AlkD and AlkC have an alpha&#x02013;alpha superhelix fold</title><p>Several PSI-BLAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) search iterations with <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD in the NCBI non-redundant protein database pick up many homologous proteins and demonstrate that AlkD belongs to a large family of prokaryotic proteins with currently more than 200 members in the sequence databases. <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkC is also in this family, but it is a remote homolog of AlkD with sequence identity below 20%. Eukaryotic homologs have been identified in <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic> and <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>).</p><p>Structural disorder predictions suggest that <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD (237 residues) folds into a regular, well-defined tertiary structure, with only the C-terminal 15&#x02013;20 amino acids being structurally flexible and disordered. <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkC (256 residues) is predicted to have no regions with significant structural disorder. Several secondary structure prediction tools concurrently show that AlkD consists of 13 &#x003b1;-helices connected by short loops (Supplementary Figure 1). The AlkC secondary structure appears to comprise 13 or 14 &#x003b1;-helices although there is less consensus between the various predictions compared with those for AlkD (Supplementary Figure 2).</p><p>The mGenTHREADER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) and Phyre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) fold recognition servers predict with high confidence <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD to have the same overall structure as a family of all-alpha proteins&#x02014;e.g. PDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>) structures 1T06, 1OYZ and 1BK5&#x02014;categorized in SCOP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) as belonging to the alpha&#x02013;alpha superhelix fold. They are further classified as being members of a superfamily with a fold similar to ARM- and HEAT-repeat-containing proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). The results are less clear-cut for AlkC, but even so, 9 out of the 10 best similarity hits are for proteins belonging to the ARM/HEAT-repeat containing superfamily.</p><p>The SAM-T02 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) fold recognition server also predicts both AlkD and AlkC to be ARM- or HEAT-repeat-containing proteins. In addition, the SAM-T02 server shows with very high confidence (SAM-T02 <italic>E</italic>-value below 10<sup>&#x02212;20</sup>) that AlkD has the same fold as the <italic>E. faecalis</italic> V583 hypothetical protein EF3068 (PDB structure 2B6C). The experimental structure 2B6C was released in November 2005, and was not detected by mGenTHREADER and Phyre due to its absence in the data set of these programs. 2B6C is also the best SAM-T02 hit for the AlkC structure (SAM-T02 <italic>E</italic>-value is 6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>). The amino acid sequences of <italic>E. faecalis</italic> EF3068 and <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD have 35% sequence identity for a length of more than 200 residues, and with just one single insertion/deletion (Supplementary Figure 3). Proteins with this level of similarity generally have the same overall structure and protein fold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). These predictions demonstrate that AlkD and AlkC are proteins comprising ARM/HEAT-like repeats and that a reliable model of AlkD can be generated with standard comparative modelling based on the structure of EF3068 from <italic>E. faecalis</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>AlkD has a groove lined with positively charged residues, ideally shaped for accommodating DNA</title><p>Based on the sequence alignment between <italic>E. faecalis</italic> EF3068 and <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD (Supplementary Figure 3), a structural model for AlkD was generated from the 2B6C chain B template employing standard comparative modelling with SwissModel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>), including backbone generation, loop building and side-chain optimization (Supplementary data file in PDB format). EF3068 is shorter than AlkD at both ends, and no reliable structure could be built for the 10&#x02013;15 N- and C-terminal residues. However, the C-terminal region is predicted to be structurally disordered, and the N-terminal region, including &#x003b1;1, most likely packs against &#x003b1;3 and &#x003b1;4 as in another recently solved ARM/HEAT-repeat structure (PDB identifier 1T06). No abnormalities, not to be expected in a homology-based model, were detected by the WhatCheck (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>) standard evaluation checks.</p><p>A cartoon representation of the <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD model is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>a, with the APBS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) calculated electrostatic potential mapped onto the protein surface in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>b (see also Supplementary Video 1 online). A multiple sequence alignment of AlkD and homologs (Supplementary Figure 4) highlights conserved residues that probably are involved in catalysis and substrate recognition and binding (Supplementary Table 1). The dense packing of the AlkD &#x003b1;-helices results in a scoop-shaped overall structure containing a wide groove with a diameter of &#x0223c;20&#x02013;25&#x02009;&#x000c5; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and Supplementary Video 1). The groove, or front side of the protein, is positively charged and has a number of conserved Lys and Arg residues along the edges of this feature (Supplementary Figure 4 and Table 1). The groove region of the protein is ideally shaped and charged for accommodating double-stranded DNA through a salt-bridge network involving some of the conserved Lys/Arg residues and the DNA phosphate groups. The rear side of the protein is mainly negatively charged, making the protein overall neutral.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Structural model with proposed active site and lesion recognition pocket of <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD. The model contains residues 11 through to 226 and is lacking &#x003b1;-helix &#x003b1;1 and the 11 C-terminal residues (predicted to be disordered). (<bold>a</bold>) Cartoon rendering of the protein which comprises 13 &#x003b1;-helices contributing to the six repeats in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. (<bold>b</bold>) APBS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) calculated electrostatic potential mapped onto the protein surface (red = negative, white = neutral and blue = positive) showing the 20&#x02013;25&#x02009;&#x000c5; wide, positively charged, putative DNA binding groove. (<bold>c</bold>) Amino acid residue conservation in 43 AlkD homologs mapped onto the space filling representation of the model generated with ConSurf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The scale extends from magenta (highly conserved), through white to cyan (highly variable). There is a nest of conserved residues in the putative DNA binding groove, and several conserved basic amino acid residues (Arg and Lys) are sited along the upper and lower edge of the groove. (<bold>d</bold>) Stereo view of a close-up of the highly conserved nest shows the eight conserved residues that were mutated by site-directed mutagenesis. The catalytic activity and MMS sensitivity of the resulting mutants were determined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). The eight conserved residues have identical geometry in the experimental structure 2B6C. The orientation of the protein in space is identical in all panels. The model is also available as Supplementary Video 1 online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm039f1"/></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD has six HEAT-like tandem repeats. Structure-based multiple alignment of repeats R1 (&#x003b1;1 and &#x003b1;3), R2 (&#x003b1;4 and &#x003b1;5), R3 (&#x003b1;6 and &#x003b1;7), R4 (&#x003b1;8 and &#x003b1;9), R5 (&#x003b1;10 and &#x003b1;11) and R6 (&#x003b1;12 and &#x003b1;13) of AlkD with conserved residues shown on a coloured background; hydrophobic residues blue, basic residues orange, acidic residues magenta and polar Tyr and Gln residues light blue and green, respectively. Each &#x003b1;-helix (H_in) of the putative DNA binding surface of AlkD is linked to the two rear side &#x003b1;-helices (H_out), the one preceding it (same repeat) and the other succeeding it (next repeat), through short loops. There is an additional inserted &#x003b1;-helix, &#x003b1;2 (boxed, magenta), between the first and second &#x003b1;-helices of R1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm039f2"/></fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Identification of Trp109, Asp113 and Arg148 as active site residues. (<bold>a</bold>) AlkD active site mutants have strongly reduced 3mA DNA glycosylase activity. Release of alkylated bases was measured in protein extracts from <italic>E. coli tag alkA</italic> cells expressing wild-type AlkD, mutants Y27A, W109A, D113N, R148A, F180A and W187A, and empty pUC18 (negative control). One microgram extract was incubated with [<sup>3</sup>H]-MNU-treated calf thymus DNA for 30&#x02009;min, the DNA was ethanol precipitated and the supernatant subjected to scintillation counting. (<bold>b</bold>) The MMS sensitive phenotype of the <italic>E. coli</italic> BK2118 <italic>tag alkA</italic> strain is not complemented by expression of AlkD active site mutants. One microlitre of serially diluted mid-log phase cultures of <italic>E. coli</italic> BK2118 transformed with pUC18-AlkD wild-type, mutants Y27A, W109A, D113N, R148A, F180A and W187A, or empty pUC18 vector, were spotted onto LB agar plates with or without MMS as indicated. The undiluted samples correspond to 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> cells&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm039f3"/></fig></p><p>A structural alignment of the tandem repeats of <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD was generated manually from the model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Each repeat of AlkD, as in <italic>E. faecalis</italic> hypothetical protein EF3068, consists of only two antiparallel helices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>a and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) and is clearly more closely related to the standard HEAT repeat than to the ARM repeat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). AlkD comprises six HEAT-like repeats, each with &#x0223c;35 residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). The similarity is very low between the repeats and is mainly limited to the conserved location of hydrophobic residues.</p></sec><sec><title>Site-specific mutagenesis identifies active site residues</title><p>The degree of conservation of the various amino acid residues among the AlkD family members was calculated from a multiple sequence alignment of 43 AlkD homologs. Amino acid conservation was mapped onto the protein surface by employing the ConSurf program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) in order to identify patches of conservation that might be functionally important (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>c). A nest of conserved residues in <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD is located at one end of the putative DNA binding groove, near the C-terminus of &#x003b1;2 and the N-termini of &#x003b1;7, &#x003b1;9 and &#x003b1;11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>c and d and Supplementary Table 1). Eight of these residues were selected for mutational studies in order to characterize their role in catalysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>d).</p><p>Mutant AlkD proteins were expressed in the <italic>E. coli tag alkA</italic> mutant strain BK2118 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) in order to avoid interference from endogenous 3mA DNA glycosylase activity. Crude extracts loaded on denaturing SDS&#x02013;PAGE gels stained with Coomassie blue showed that all mutant proteins and wild-type AlkD were equally expressed (data not shown). The crude extracts were examined for the ability to remove alkylated bases from DNA treated with [<sup>3</sup>H]-MNU. Extracts of mutants Y27A and F180A displayed DNA glycosylase activities comparable to the wild-type, whereas the activity of the W187A extract was reduced to approximately one-third of the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>a). Extracts expressing AlkD mutants W109A, D113N and R148A had lost all DNA glycosylase activity for alkylated bases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>a), suggesting that these three residues are essential for the catalytic mechanism and/or recognition of the modified base. The three residues Trp109, Asp113 and Trp187 form a structural motif in AlkD with a configuration comparable to Trp272, Asp 238 and Trp218, respectively, in AlkA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). It is tempting to speculate that these three residues play similar roles in AlkD as in AlkA, which is, &#x003c0;&#x02013;&#x003c0; and/or &#x003c0;-cation stacking with the extrahelical alkylated base (Trp109), a function in the nucleophilic attack on the glycosylic bond (Asp113) and coordination and stabilization of the DNA backbone around the alkylated nucleotide (Trp187).
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Coordination around the catalytic Asp residue in AlkA and AlkD. View of the Trp218/Asp238/Trp272 triad in the active site of <italic>E. coli</italic> AlkA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>) and their structural counterparts Trp187/Asp113/Trp109 in <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm039f4"/></fig></p><p>In another set of experiments, we tested the mutant constructs by functional complementation of the alkylation sensitive phenotype of the <italic>E. coli</italic> strain BK2118 (<italic>tag alkA</italic>) upon exposure to the alkylating agent MMS. No rescue was observed with plasmids expressing mutants W109A, D113N and R148A, while constructs expressing Y27A, F180A and W187A complemented the MMS sensitivity of BK2118 in the same way as the wild-type construct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>b). Finally, cells transformed with mutant constructs W145A and F179A had a growth comparable to cells expressing wild-type AlkD (data not shown). These survival studies support our biochemical analysis and computational predictions that Trp109, Asp113 and Arg148 are active site residues.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular modelling of AlkD in complex with DNA proposes a partially open recognition pocket with specificity for electron deficient alkylated bases</title><p>Based on our AlkD model and the experimental structures of several DNA glycosylases in complex with DNA, an approximate model of AlkD in complex with DNA incorporating an extrahelical purine was constructed. The model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> and Supplementary Video 2) suggests that the DNA backbone interacts with several strongly conserved Lys and Arg residues (Supplementary Figure 4 and Table 1) along the edges of the wide AlkD groove. The lesion-containing strand is partially buried in the AlkD groove with contacts primarily on the 3&#x02032; side of the lesion. The flipped-out base fits nicely into the partially open recognition pocket with Trp109 forming the base of a platform onto which the electron deficient alkylated bases may stack. The side-chain of Trp187 is positioned in the vicinity of the ribose ring of the flipped-out base. Finally, the rough model shows that Asp113 is positioned within a reasonable distance to facilitate hydrolytic cleavage of the <italic>N</italic>-glycosylic bond in the extrahelical nucleotide.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Stereo view of the proposed AlkD&#x02013;DNA complex. Selected amino acid side chains are coloured as follows: Arg and Lys residues with a high degree of conservation in the AlkD family (dark blue), additional Lys residues lining the DNA binding groove (light blue), residues with no impact on DNA glycosylase activity as shown by alkylbase DNA assay (green), residues with reduced or impaired DNA glycosylase activity when mutated (dark red), docked DNA (orange) and flipped-out DNA base (yellow). The model is also available as Supplementary Video 2 online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm039f5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p><italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD and AlkC are 3mA DNA glycosylases specific for excision of <italic>N</italic>-alkylated DNA bases and without significant sequence similarity to any other protein of known function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). The present study was initiated in order to determine the structure of proteins belonging to this novel family of DNA glycosylases. Our attempts at crystallizing the proteins for X-ray crystallographic structure determination have so far been unsuccessful. However, the release of the atomic coordinates for the crystal structure of the hypothetical protein EF3068 from <italic>E. faecalis</italic> provided the necessary input to determine the overall structure of <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD with a high level of confidence by computational methods. The scoop-shaped overall structure of AlkD consists of an arrangement of &#x003b1;-helices forming a wide groove with a diameter of &#x0223c;20&#x02013;25&#x02009;&#x000c5;, lined with positively charged residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>a and b). The shape and electrostatic environment of the groove seem suitable to accommodate double-stranded DNA. Identification of a single nest of highly conserved residues at one end of the putative DNA binding cavity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>c and d) strongly suggests that the active site of AlkD is located in this region. Functional analysis of site-specific mutant proteins support the structural model of AlkD, and elucidates residues involved in DNA binding and alkylated base recognition (Trp109) and catalysis (Asp113 and Arg148). The mechanistic and catalytic features are further illuminated by a computational model of AlkD complexed with DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>Alseth <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) found that AlkD was specific for the excision of the <italic>N</italic>-alkylated purine bases 3mA, 3-methylguanine (3mG) and 7-methylguanine (7mG). A common feature of these lesions is that the bases are electron deficient and positively charged. <italic>N</italic>-alkylation of a purine base also significantly destabilizes the <italic>N</italic>-glycosylic bond, making the base susceptible to spontaneous hydrolysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). Finally, normal Watson&#x02013;Crick base pairing and base stacking ability is affected, which may lower the barrier for extrahelical flipping. Unlike the majority of DNA glycosylases, 3mA DNA glycosylases only need a catalytic rate enhancement of a few orders of magnitude (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) due to the destabilized <italic>N</italic>-glycosylic bond. Several 3mA DNA glycosylases have been subjected to extensive structural and biochemical studies, including 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylase I (Tag) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>) and AlkA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43 B44 B45">43&#x02013;45</xref>) from <italic>E. coli</italic>, human AAG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>), as well as the 3mA DNA glycosylase MagIII from <italic>Heliobacter pylori</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>). Like all previously studied DNA glycosylases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), these enzymes employ a DNA-bending and base-flipping strategy that exposes the damaged base in a recognition pocket or cleft. A common feature of all the studied 3mA DNA glycosylases is that they have extensive aromatic networks in the respective substrate pockets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). This may allow for alkylated base specificity due to favourable &#x003c0;&#x02013;&#x003c0; and/or &#x003c0;&#x02013;cation interactions between the positively charged base lesion and the aromatic residues lining the catalytic pockets. Alternatively, the activation barrier for glycosylic bond cleavage for alkylated bases may be lowered due to destabilization of the ground-state upon insertion of the charged base lesion into the non-polar active site pocket (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). Interestingly, the proposed pocket region in AlkD also contains several highly conserved aromatic residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>d)&#x02014;Trp109, Trp145, Phe179, Phe180 and Trp187. Mutants W145A, F179A and F180A showed catalytic activities comparable to the wild-type enzyme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> and data not shown). This observation is in line with our model of AlkD bound to DNA, where these residues are not part of the protein-DNA interface despite the close proximity to the catalytic Asp113 and Arg148 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>Both AlkA and AAG can excise a variety of base lesions, including 3mA, 3mG, 7mG and other alkylated bases as well as uncharged lesions such as cyclic 1,<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-ethenoadenine (&#x003b5;A) and deaminated adenine (hypoxanthine) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). AlkA has a wide and open recognition pocket that forms few specific contacts with the substrate bases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). AAG has a tight pocket that snugly accommodates neutral &#x003b5;A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). The specificity of AlkA and AAG towards <italic>N</italic>-alkylated bases appears to be due to the weak <italic>N</italic>-glycosylic bonds and a recognition pocket rich in aromatic residues that can stack with electron-deficient bases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>), in addition to modified base stacking and Watson&#x02013;Crick base pairing for these lesions. In contrast, Tag and MagIII are specific for removal of 3-methyl purines from DNA, and are unable to excise 7mG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>). Steric hindrance excludes 7mG from the active site pocket of MagIII (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). Unlike the other 3mA DNA glycosylases, Tag appears to specifically sense the purine 3-methyl group and undergoes an induced fitting conformational change that makes base excision possible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). AlkD excises both 3- and 7-methylated purines and thus has a specificity that lies between AlkA/AAG and Tag/MagIII. It appears unlikely that AlkD is able to specifically recognize methyl groups both at N3 and N7 while excluding all other normal or damaged bases from the recognition pocket employing a similar strategy for base discrimination as does Tag for purines methylated at N3 only. More likely AlkD recognizes its targets in a fashion more similar to AlkA and AAG, with electron rich aromatic residues interacting with electron deficient <italic>N</italic>-alkylated bases. Mutational analysis of aromatic residues in AlkD indicates that Trp109 is important for recognition of the alkylated base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Trp272 of AlkA forms stacking interactions with the electron deficient alkylated bases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>) and we propose that Trp109 has a similar role in AlkD. The exact shape of the lesion recognition pocket and the details of the base orientation can not be determined from our approximate docking-model of the AlkD&#x02013;DNA complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). However, it appears that AlkD primarily recognizes <italic>N</italic>-alkylated purines through interactions in an open catalytic pocket that is rich in aromatic residues.</p><p>Most structures of monofunctional DNA glycosylases suggest a catalytic mechanism in which an Asp or Glu residue deprotonates and activates a water molecule. Following an S<sub>N</sub>2-like substitution mechanism this leads to a simultaneous base release and attack by the activated nucleophile on the C1&#x02032; of the sugar group. This appears to be the mechanism, for example, of mammalian AAG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). However, the structure of <italic>E. coli</italic> AlkA in complex with abasic DNA appears to better fit an alternative S<sub>N</sub>1-like mechanism, in which the catalytic Asp238 assists base removal by direct stabilization of a oxacarbenium-like transition state or intermediate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). There are two strong hydrogen bonds between Arg148 and the putative catalytic Asp113 in our model of <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>d) which also appear between the corresponding residues in the experimental structure of <italic>B. faecalis</italic> EF3068. The estimated pK<sub>a</sub> for Asp113 in wild-type AlkD is 1.0, while it is 4.0 in the R148A mutant, approximately the same as for free Asp, indicating that Arg148 regulates the catalytic performance of Asp113. The interaction between Arg148 and the carboxylate group of Asp113 stabilizes the charged form of both residues, thus the Asp residue cannot gain protons easily. In order to activate a water molecule for nucleophilic attack (S<sub>N</sub>2 mechanism), the salt bridge between Asp113 and Arg148 probably have to be abrogated upon substrate binding. AlkD would in this case be catalytically activated only upon binding DNA. Interestingly, the catalytic site general base of AAG, Glu125, is located next to a conserved Arg182 in the AAG:&#x003b5;A-DNA structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>) with both residues forming hydrogen bonds to the water molecule that is activated for S<sub>N</sub>2-like nucleophilic attack. Alternatively, the reduced pK<sub>a</sub> of AlkD Asp113 can ensure that the residue is not protonated and thus stabilizes the transition state in a fashion similar to the AlkA S<sub>N</sub>1-like cleavage mechanism.</p><p>In AlkA and AAG the side chains of Leu125 and Tyr162, respectively, protrude from the protein surfaces and intercalate into the DNA at the position of the flipped-out nucleotide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>), thereby reducing the possibility of re-entry of the extrahelical base into the DNA duplex. A candidate residue for a similar role in AlkD could be Tyr27 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>d). However, mutant Y27A shows catalytic activity comparable to the wild-type AlkD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Indeed, the current model of the AlkD&#x02013;DNA complex does not have any clear candidate for an intercalating residue. This may in part explain why AlkD can only excise positively charged alkylated bases that have weak <italic>N</italic>-glycosylic bonds.</p><p>The present study demonstrates that <italic>B. cereus</italic> AlkD and AlkC are single domain proteins belonging to a superfamily of proteins with a right-handed alpha&#x02013;alpha superhelix fold related in structure to ARM/HEAT-repeat containing proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>a and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). These proteins are built from imperfect tandem repeats of a sequence motif containing &#x0223c;40 amino acid residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). The canonical ARM repeat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>) has three &#x003b1;-helices, while the HEAT repeat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>) has only two antiparallel &#x003b1;-helices which form a hairpin. The repeated units of two (HEAT) or three (ARM) helices are packed together to form a superhelix of helices. The number of repeats may be greater than 20, but can also be below 6, and it has been estimated that 1 in 500 eukaryotic proteins contains these repeats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). ARM repeats are found, for example, in mammalian &#x003b2;-catenin and importin &#x003b1;, while the HEAT motif is found in&#x02014;and takes its name from&#x02014;proteins such as <bold>h</bold>untingtin, <bold>e</bold>longation factor 3, a protein phosphatase 2<bold>A</bold> subunit and the lipid kinase <bold>T</bold>OR (target of rapamycin), in addition to a diverse family of other proteins. These proteins are involved in many different cellular processes. A common theme appears to be interactions with other proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>), but HEAT-repeat containing enzymes have recently been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>). While AlkD and AlkC appears to be more similar to the HEAT than to the ARM family, they do not appear to be closely related to any of the eukaryotic HEAT subfamilies described by Andrade <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, AlkD and AlkC are DNA glycosylases built from HEAT-like repeats. To the authors&#x02019; knowledge, no other DNA glycosylases, nor indeed any BER proteins, have been shown to belong to this structural class. Proteins of both the UDG and AAG superfamilies have a core built around a &#x003b2;-sheet, while the H2TH DNA glycosylases have two protein domains that both contain important &#x003b2;-sheet regions. Some of the HhH DNA glycosylases are all-alpha proteins (e.g. <italic>E. coli</italic> Nth), but they invariably consist of at least two domains and have no superhelix of &#x003b1;-helices forming the overall solenoid fold of AlkD and AlkC. Consequently, AlkD and AlkC are members of a new, fifth, structural superfamily of DNA glycosylases.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm039_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="nar_gkm039_1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"
xlink:href="nar_gkm039_nar-02592-f-2006-File010.pdb"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><p>This work was supported by the Research Council of Norway, the Norwegian Cancer Society and the Consortium for Advanced Microbial Sciences and Technologies (FUGE-CAMST). We are grateful to the scientists of the Midwest Center for Structural Genomics for making their solved structures available to the community, and thereby making studies like the present work possible. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charge was provided by the Research Council of Norway.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seeberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Eide</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f8;r&#x000e5;s</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The base excision repair pathway</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci</source><year>1995</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8533150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krokan</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Skorpen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Otterlei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Slupphaug</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Base excision repair of DNA in mammalian cells</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2000</year><volume>476</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10878254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repair and genetic consequences of endogenous DNA base damage in mammalian cells</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15568983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stivers</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mechanistic perspective on the chemistry of DNA repair glycosylases</article-title><source>Chem. Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>2729</fpage><lpage>2759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12848584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unified catalytic mechanism for DNA glycosylases</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>32709</fpage><lpage>32712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7806489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human DNA repair genes, 2005</article-title><source>Mutat. Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>577</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15922366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fromme</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdine</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA glycosylase recognition and catalysis</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15102448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huffman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundheim</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tainer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA base damage recognition and removal: new twists and grooves</article-title><source>Mutat. Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>577</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15941573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alseth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindb&#x000e4;ck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Solberg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Mainieri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lillehagen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolst&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>A-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f8;r&#x000e5;s</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new protein superfamily includes two novel 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylases from <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>, AlkC and AlkD</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1602</fpage><lpage>1609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16468998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e6;b&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Myrseth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laerdahl</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARALIGN: rapid and sensitive sequence similarity searches powered by parallel computing technology</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W535</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poirot</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Notredame</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tcoffee@igs: a web server for computing, evaluating and combining multiple sequence alignments</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3503</fpage><lpage>3506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clamp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Jalview Java alignment editor</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuffin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sodhi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein structure prediction servers at University College London</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W36</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein secondary structure prediction based on position-specific scoring matrices</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10493868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of protein secondary structure at better than 70% accuracy</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8345525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of multiple sequence alignment profiles to improve protein secondary structure prediction</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2000</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>502</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10861942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollastri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Przybylski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving the prediction of protein secondary structure in three and eight classes using recurrent neural networks and profiles</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2002</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11933069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sodhi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuffin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction and functional analysis of native disorder in proteins from the three kingdoms of life</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15019783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obradovic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vucetic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Radivojac</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunker</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploiting heterogeneous sequence properties improves prediction of protein disorder</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16187360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGuffin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement of the GenTHREADER method for genomic fold recognition</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>874</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>MacCallum</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>MJE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced genome annotation using structural profiles in the program 3D-PSSM</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10860755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Karchin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandel-Gutfreund</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Diekhans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combining local-structure, fold-recognition, and new fold methods for protein structure prediction</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2003</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14579338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shindyalov</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Protein Data Bank</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwede</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guex</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Peitsch</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SWISS-MODEL: an automated protein homology-modeling server</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3381</fpage><lpage>3385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hooft</surname><given-names>RWW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vriend</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Abola</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Errors in protein structures</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>272</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8692262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Howorth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>TJP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chothia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Murzin</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SCOP database in 2004: refinements integrate structure and sequence family data</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>D226</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sept</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrostatics of nanosystems: application to microtubules and the ribosome</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>10037</fpage><lpage>10041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11517324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolinsky</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PDB2PQR: an automated pipeline for the setup of Poisson-Boltzmann electrostatics calculations</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>W665</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Very fast empirical prediction and rationalization of protein pK<sub>a</sub> values</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>721</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16231289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayrose</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Martz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pupko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Tal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ConSurf 2005: the projection of evolutionary conservation scores of residues on protein structures</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W299</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayrose</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Graur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Tal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pupko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of site-specific rate-inference methods for protein sequences: empirical Bayesian methods are superior</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1781</fpage><lpage>1791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15201400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delano</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><source>The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>San Carlos, CA, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>DeLano Scientific</publisher-name><comment>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA bending and a flip-out mechanism for base excision by the helix-hairpin-helix DNA glycosylase, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> AlkA</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>758</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunger</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clore</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLano</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosse-Kunstleve</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuszewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilges</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystallography &#x00026; NMR System: a new software suite for macromolecular structure determination</article-title><source>Acta Cryst. D</source><year>1998</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9757107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Kvaal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> genes encoding 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylases I and II</article-title><source>Mol. Gen. Genet</source><year>1984</year><volume>197</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6098799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjelland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylase I from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1987</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2787</fpage><lpage>2801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3550703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Petosa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of ARM and HEAT protein repeats</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11491282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Twilight zone of protein sequence alignments</article-title><source>Protein Eng</source><year>1999</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10195279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissecting the broad substrate specificity of human 3-methyladenine-DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>9750</fpage><lpage>9757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14688248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjelland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different efficiencies of the Tag and AlkA DNA glycosylases from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in the removal of 3-methyladenine from single-stranded DNA</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1996</year><volume>397</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8941728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stivers</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure and base perturbation studies reveal a novel mode of alkylated base recognition by 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylase I</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>48012</fpage><lpage>48020</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13129925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labahn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaerer</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezaz-Nikpay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdine</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for the excision repair of alkylation-damaged DNA</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8706136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylase AlkA has a remarkably versatile active site</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>26876</fpage><lpage>26884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15126496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamagata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Odawara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokuno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasumura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>K-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional structure of a DNA repair enzyme, 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylase II, from Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8706135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;rer</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdine</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of a human alkylbase-DNA repair enzyme complexed to DNA: mechanisms for nucleotide flipping and base excision</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9790531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Glassner</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis for discriminating between normal and damaged bases by the human alkyladenine glycosylase, AAG</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>13573</fpage><lpage>13578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11106395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eichman</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Rourke</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Radicella</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structures of 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylase MagIII and the recognition of alkylated bases</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4898</fpage><lpage>4909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14517230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Rourke</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Boiteux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Labigne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ielpi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Radicella</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel 3-methyladenine DNA glycosylase from <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> defines a new class within the endonuclease III family of base excision repair glycosylases</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>20077</fpage><lpage>20083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10777493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional structure of the Armadillo repeat region of &#x003b2;-catenin</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9298899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HEAT repeats in the Huntington's disease protein</article-title><source>Nat. Genet</source><year>1995</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7550332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaevel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning, expression, and structural prediction of deoxyhypusine hydroxylase: A HEAT-repeat-containing metalloenzyme</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16371467</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
