<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17430968</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1885660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm131</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Thermodynamics and NMR studies on <italic>Duck, Heron</italic> and <italic>Human</italic> HBV encapsidation signals</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>Frederic C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ottink</surname><given-names>Otmar M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ampt</surname><given-names>Kirsten A.M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tessari</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>Sybren S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Physical Chemistry/Biophysical Chemistry, Radboud University, Toernooiveld 1 6525 ED Nijmegen, The Netherlands</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed <phone>+31 24 3653384/2678</phone><fax>+31 24 3652112</fax><email>s.wijmenga@nmr.ru.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2800</fpage><lpage>2811</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Hepatitis B virus (HBV) replication is initiated by binding of its reverse transcriptase (P) to the apical stem-loop (<italic>AL</italic>) and primer loop (<italic>PL</italic>) of epsilon, a highly conserved RNA element at the 5&#x02032;-end of the RNA pregenome. Mutation studies on <italic>duck/heron</italic> and <italic>human in vitro</italic> systems have shown similarities but also differences between their P&#x02013;epsilon interaction. Here, NMR and UV thermodynamic data on <italic>AL</italic> (and <italic>PL</italic>) from these three species are presented. The stabilities of the <italic>duck</italic> and <italic>heron AL</italic>s were found to be similar, and much lower than that of <italic>human</italic>. NMR data show that this low stability stems from an 11-nt internal bulge destabilizing the stem of <italic>heron AL</italic>. In <italic>duck</italic>, although structured at low temperature, this region also forms a weak point as its imino resonances broaden to disappearance between 30 and 35&#x000b0;C well below the overall <italic>AL</italic> melting temperature. Surprisingly, the <italic>duck- and heron AL</italic>s were both found to be capped by a stable well-structured UGUU tetraloop. All <italic>avian ALs</italic> are expected to adhere to this because of their conserved sequence. <italic>Duck PL</italic> is stable and structured and, in view of sequence similarities, the same is expected for <italic>heron</italic> - and <italic>human PL</italic>.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The Hepatitis B virus (HBV) is the most common cause of liver infection in the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). More than 300 million people worldwide are estimated to be chronically infected by HBV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) and chronic HBV infection carriers have a great risk to develop severe liver diseases, including cirrhosis and liver cancer, resulting in a million deaths annually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). No treatment for the efficient elimination of HBV in infected patients exists as yet. HBV is a member of the <italic>Hepadnaviridae</italic> family, consisting of hepatotropic DNA-viruses, which also includes related animal viruses such as <italic>duck</italic> HBV (DHBV) and <italic>heron</italic> HBV (HHBV). HBV has a small (3.2&#x02009;kb), relaxed circular, partially double-stranded DNA genome. It replicates its DNA genome by reverse transcription of an RNA intermediate, the pregenomic RNA (pgRNA), for reviews see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5 B6 B7">3&#x02013;7</xref>). The pgRNA also serves as mRNA for the capsid (or core) and viral polymerase (P protein). The P protein contains the evolutionarily conserved reverse transcriptase (RT) domain, a middle spacer region, a C-terminal RNase H (RH) domain and a unique template domain (TP) at its N-terminus, which acts as a primer for reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). Replication is initiated by binding of the P protein to the viral encapsidation signal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), a 60-nt stem-loop, called epsilon, located at the 5&#x02032;-end of the pgRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7 B8 B9">7&#x02013;9</xref>). Binding of P to &#x003b5; triggers two main events: recruitment of core proteins to form the viral capsid and synthesis of a 3&#x02013;4-nt DNA primer, covalently attached to a tyrosine residue in the TP domain, using the &#x003b5; primer loop as a template (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). The resulting complex subsequently translocates to a 3&#x02032;-proximal &#x003b5; RNA element of the pgRNA where full-length DNA synthesis is primed using the 4-nt DNA primer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7 B8 B9 B10 B11">7&#x02013;11</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>HBV encapsidation signal. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic of the replication initiation, showing the P&#x02013;&#x003b5; interaction, which leads to encapsidation of the pgRNA and subsequent priming. (<bold>B</bold>) RNA constructs studied by NMR and UV melting corresponding to apical stem-loop of <italic>duck</italic> HBV (<italic>ALD</italic>), <italic>heron</italic> HBV (<italic>ALH</italic>), <italic>human</italic> HBV (<italic>ALHu</italic>) and primer loop of <italic>duck</italic> HBV (<italic>PLD</italic>). To aid in assignment of ALD and PLD, two additional shorter RNAs were expressed (<bold>S6</bold>). The gray-boxed residues represent structurally silent mutations from wild-type, introduced at the 5&#x02032;- and 3&#x02032;-ends to aid for expression or to cap and stabilize the upper stem (<italic>PLD</italic>). For ease of comparison the sequence numbering of Hu <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) is also indicated, e.g. U<sub>15</sub> of <italic>ALD</italic> (and <italic>ALH</italic>) is then numbered U<sub>2590</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm131f1"/></fig></p><p>Detailed knowledge on the crucial P&#x02013;&#x003b5; interaction has been derived from biochemical studies on a cell-free and chaperone-dependent reconstituted system based on <italic>duck</italic> HBV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12 B13 B14 B15 B16">12&#x02013;16</xref>). The <italic>in vitro</italic> system shows both P&#x02013;&#x003b5; binding and priming. Using truncated P protein constructs, it was demonstrated that P&#x02013;&#x003b5; interaction requires sequences from both RT and TP protein domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). On the RNA side, it was established that the loop at the apex of apical stem-loop of DHBV-&#x003b5; is essential for binding and primer synthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Recent SELEX experiments using this system further defined the structure and sequence elements in the apical stem-loop of DHBV crucial for binding and/or priming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). For instance, the middle of the stem underlying the loop should be weakly- or not base paired at all. Based on these biochemical studies, Nassal cs. proposed that replication initiation is a two-step process in which initial physical RNA binding (and recognition) is followed by a structural rearrangement leading to a priming- competent complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Interestingly, in this <italic>in vitro</italic> system, the P protein binds to both <italic>duck</italic> &#x003b5;, with a well-defined upper stem structure, and <italic>heron</italic> &#x003b5;, characterized by a lack of base pairing in its upper stem, but it does not bind to <italic>human</italic> &#x003b5;.</p><p>Most recently, a cell-free and chaperone-dependent <italic>in vitro</italic> reconstitution system was also developed for <italic>human</italic> HBV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). It shows P&#x02013;&#x003b5; binding, but in contrast to the DHBV system, not priming. Similarly to DHBV, in <italic>human</italic> HBV, sequences from both the RT and TP domains are required for binding of P to &#x003b5;. Surprisingly, the &#x003b5;-apical loop is not needed for P&#x02013;&#x003b5; binding, in contrast to DHBV where it is essential. The &#x003b5;-apical loop is, however, required for encapsidation. Moreover, the structural features, i.e. requirements for base pairing in the stem part of the apical stem-loop, differ from those in DHBV. In <italic>human</italic> HBV, the upper part of the stem of the apical stem-loop needs to be base paired and the bulged out U (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B) is essential for binding, while the corresponding bulged U in DHBV is dispensable.</p><p>Although the structural basis and sequence requirements for P&#x02013;&#x003b5; binding and priming are emerging, several questions remain and a full understanding of the molecular basis for the specific interactions between P and &#x003b5; awaits high-resolution structural and thermodynamic data. The importance of high-resolution structural data is underlined by the NMR studies of the <italic>human</italic> HBV &#x003b5; apical stem-loop, which showed that its conserved apical loop folds into a pseudo-triloop, whereas secondary structure programs predicted a hexaloop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Hairpin loops with the potential to form pseudo-triloops are found in many RNA sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>); their involvement in protein interactions and common appearance suggest that they may be an important protein-binding motif (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). This highly conserved structure motif is thus likely to be important for the interaction with P and/or capsid protein. Moreover, the <italic>duck</italic> P-protein can carry out binding and primer synthesis using <italic>duck</italic> &#x003b5; as well as <italic>heron</italic> &#x003b5;, but not <italic>human</italic> &#x003b5;. This is remarkable considering that <italic>duck</italic> and <italic>heron</italic> &#x003b5; are predicted to have completely different structural organization and thus stabilities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). Probing data on free <italic>heron</italic> &#x003b5; suggest a fully open apical stem-loop, in contrast to <italic>duck</italic> &#x003b5;, which appears to have a folded stem and loop region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). This again raises the question concerning the exact structure or sequence determinants that trigger the &#x003b5;&#x02013;P binding interaction.</p><p>In this article, we present and compare structural (NMR) and thermodynamic data of the apical stem-loop and primer loop of &#x003b5; RNAs from <italic>duck, heron</italic> and <italic>human</italic>. These data more precisely define the structure and stability of these RNA elements crucial for &#x003b5;&#x02013;P interaction and may aid in further understanding its molecular basis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The &#x003b5; RNA element contains two main structural features (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A) common to all HBV strains: (i) an apical stem-loop (<italic>AL</italic>), recognized by the P protein to which it binds, triggering the reverse transcription process; (ii) an internal asymmetric loop, here referred to as primer-loop (<italic>PL</italic>), consisting of seven unpaired residues from which four residues are used by the polymerase as a template to synthesize a covalently bound DNA primer (5&#x02032;-GTAA-3&#x02032; for <italic>avian</italic>, 5&#x02032;-TGAA-3&#x02032; for <italic>human</italic>). Several of these RNA sequences were designed and expressed (see the Materials and methods section), based on the sequence of the wild-type strains reported for the <italic>duck</italic>-, <italic>heron</italic>- and <italic>human</italic> HBV. For sake of clarity, they are here referred to as <italic>ALD</italic> (<italic>&#x003b5; Apical Loop of Duck</italic>), <italic>ALH</italic> (<italic>&#x003b5; Apical Loop of Heron</italic>), <italic>ALHu</italic> (<italic>&#x003b5; Apical Loop of Human</italic>) and <italic>PLD</italic> (<italic>&#x003b5; Primer Loop of Duck</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B).</p><sec><title>NMR-based structure investigations</title><sec><title>Duck HBV epsilon apical stem-loop (ALD)</title><p>Resonance assignment was performed according to standard procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Of the 20 observed imino resonances (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A), 16 could be unambiguously assigned by combining data from [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY and [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>15</sup>N]-HSQC spectra in H<sub>2</sub>O (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B and C, and S1) and extended to non-exchangeable resonances using [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY spectra and [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>13</sup>C]-HSQC in D<sub>2</sub>O (Materials and Methods and Supplementary Data S1). The secondary structure as derived from NMR data is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>D.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Solution-NMR investigation of the <italic>duck</italic> apical stem-loop structure (<italic>ALD</italic>). (<bold>A</bold>) <sup>1</sup>H-imino spectra (5&#x000b0;C, H<sub>2</sub>O); assigned peaks are labeled by residue numbers, unassigned peaks are labeled with *. (<bold>B</bold>) [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>15</sup>N]-HSQC of the selectively <sup>15</sup>N-U-labeled <italic>ALD</italic> (5&#x000b0;C, H<sub>2</sub>O); (<bold>C</bold>) Imino region of <italic>ALD</italic> [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY spectrum (15&#x000b0;C, H<sub>2</sub>O); (<bold>D</bold>) Secondary structure model derived from NMR data: thick gray bars, base-pair; dark double arrows, NOEs involving non-exchangeable protons; dashed gray double arrows, NOEs involving exchangeable protons; pentagons, sugar rings (open, N-pucker, filled, S-pucker). (<bold>E</bold>) Structure model of UGUU tetraloop based on NMR classical restraints and after chemical shift refinement: Left: overlay of 10 lowest-energy structures; Middle: structure details, major groove view; Right: comparison of experimental &#x00394;&#x003b4; (light gray) and back-calculated &#x00394;&#x003b4; (dark gray). &#x00394;&#x003b4; equals the mean of (&#x003b4;<sub>calc{H1&#x02032;, H5, H6, H8}</sub>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;&#x003b4;<sub>helix{H1&#x02032;, H5, H6, H8}</sub>) or (&#x003b4;<sub>exp{H1&#x02032;, H5, H6, H8}</sub>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;&#x003b4;<sub>helix{H1&#x02032;, H5, H6, H8}</sub>); the chemical shifts, &#x003b4;<sub>calc</sub>, were averaged over the 10 lowest-energy structures. Residues for which &#x00394;&#x003b4;&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;0, experience ring current and thus stacking as in an A-helix; &#x00394;&#x003b4;&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0 and &#x0003c;0 indicate reduced and increased ring current and thus stacking, respectively, as compared to an A-helix environment. The error bars on the back-calculated &#x00394;&#x003b4;s correspond to &#x000b1;1.5&#x02009;<italic>&#x003c3;</italic> of back-calculated and experimental chemical shifts of loop residues in a large data base of pdb-deposited RNA structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm131f2"/></fig></p><p>The lower stem (residues 1&#x02013;4/26&#x02013;29) conforms to an A-type helix as evidenced by the typical sequential and cross-strand NOE contacts (e.g. A<sub>6</sub>-H2&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;G<sub>24</sub>-H1&#x02032;, A<sub>27</sub>-H2&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;C<sub>4</sub>-H1&#x02032;), and by chemical shift values close to standard helix values (S2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). The central stem (residues 5&#x02013;9/20&#x02013;24) also forms an A-helix, again evidenced by the typical sequential and cross-strand NOE contacts of exchangeable and non-exchangeable protons (e.g. A<sub>8</sub>-H2&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;G<sub>22</sub>-H1&#x02032;/G<sub>22</sub>-H8/G<sub>22</sub>-NH1, A<sub>8</sub>-H1&#x02032;&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;G<sub>22</sub>-NH1, A<sub>6</sub>-H2&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;G<sub>24</sub>-H8, A<sub>6</sub>-H1&#x02032;&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;G<sub>24</sub>-NH1) and standard A-helix chemical shifts. The lower and central stem experience stacking interaction as evidenced by the sequential NOE contacts (G<sub>26</sub>-NH1&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;U<sub>5</sub>-NH3 and between non-exchangeable protons of residues 4 and 5). Residue U<sub>25</sub> is bulged out of the helix, because U<sub>25</sub>-H5 proton resonates close to 6.0&#x02009;p.p.m., experiencing little or no ring current (S2) and sequential NOE contacts between G<sub>24</sub>/U<sub>25</sub> and U<sub>25</sub>/G<sub>26</sub> are absent. Finally, a short A-helical upper stem (residues 11&#x02013;12/17&#x02013;18) is found as typical NOE contacts and A-helix chemical shifts are observed here. The residues of potential non-canonical base pair U<sub>10</sub>:C<sub>19</sub> shows sequential NOE contacts to both U<sub>9</sub>:G<sub>20</sub> and G<sub>11</sub>:U<sub>18</sub> characteristic for helical stacking. Furthermore, the H1&#x02032;/H5/H6 chemical shifts of U<sub>10</sub> and C<sub>19</sub> are nearly A-helical, demonstrating the presence of ring current and thus, stacking interactions (S2). Therefore, both U<sub>10</sub> and C<sub>19</sub> must be inserted into the helix. Although one of two unassigned imino resonances could be the U<sub>10</sub> imino, it exchanges too fast to allow the observation of NOEs. The NMR data for the structured tetraloop and its calculated structure are presented in the relevant section below.</p><p>COSY spectra show that most residues in the <italic>ALD</italic> adopt C3&#x02032;-endo sugar puckering [<italic>J</italic><sub>H1&#x02032;-H2&#x02032;</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;3&#x02009;Hz, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>)] characteristic for an A-helix, only the sugar moieties of loop residues G<sub>14</sub>, U<sub>15</sub> and U<sub>16</sub> adopt an C2&#x02032;-endo conformation [<italic>J</italic><sub>H1&#x02032;-H2&#x02032;</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;6&#x02009;Hz, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>)]. Finally, the narrow spread around A-helix-like values of <sup>31</sup>P chemical shifts (data not shown), indicate that (on average) the phosphate backbone conforms to regular A-helix-like conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Heron HBV epsilon apical stem-loop (ALH)</title><p>In the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR imino spectra of <italic>ALH</italic>, &#x0223c;10 imino resonances are observed, of which 8 could be assigned (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, top). Of these, four could be assigned to the top stem-loop G<sub>11</sub>C<underline>UGUU</underline>GU<sub>18</sub> via chemical shift comparison with the <italic>ALD</italic> spectra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, bottom). The presence of imino resonances at the regular (Watson&#x02013;Crick) chemical shifts shows the existence of a structured G<sub>11</sub>C<underline>UGUU</underline>GU<sub>18</sub> stem-loop, analogous to what is observed for <italic>ALD.</italic> We do observe relative broadening compared to <italic>ALD</italic>, probably caused by increased solvent exchange, indicating a somewhat lower stability. The other four were sequentially assigned to the lower 4-bp stem based on NOEs. The large internal loop must be unstructured, as no evidence for base pairing was found within this region. The unassigned 2 broad resonances at &#x0223c;11&#x02009;p.p.m. (indicated by asterisks) have chemical shifts typical of slightly protected iminos, not involved in base pairing. In conclusion, <italic>ALH</italic> conforms to the secondary structure displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Comparison of the <sup>1</sup>H-imino NMR spectra (5&#x000b0;C, H<sub>2</sub>O) of <italic>heron-</italic> (top) and <italic>duck</italic> (bottom) apical stem-loop. Assigned peaks are labeled by residue numbers and unassigned peaks by asterisks. Residue numbers in the upper part of <italic>ALH</italic> are superscripted with an asterisk for clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm131f3"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Avian epsilon apical stem-loop: structure of the UGUU motif</title><p>Structure calculations were carried out on the highly conserved G<sub>11</sub>C<underline>UGUU</underline>GU<sub>18</sub>
<italic>avian</italic> top loop sequence, using the experimental NMR data collected for <italic>ALD</italic> (Materials and methods section; Structural Statistics in S7). After initial calculation using only classical NMR restraints, the resulting structures were further refined using chemical shifts as additional restraints (CS refinement). A well-defined tetraloop structure was found with RMSDs to the mean of 1.73 and 0.74&#x02009;&#x000c5;, including either all residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11 B12 B13 B14 B15 B16 B17 B18">11&#x02013;18</xref>) or excluding flexible residues 14 and 15, respectively. The back-calculated chemical shifts agree generally well with the observed chemical shifts.</p><p>The resulting structure models indicate the formation of a U<sub>13</sub>:U<sub>16</sub> base pair stacked onto the C<sub>12</sub>:G<sub>17</sub> closing base pair, as well as stacking of G<sub>14</sub> onto U<sub>13</sub> on the major groove side, while U<sub>15</sub> does not stack (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E, left, center). The stacking of the pertinent residues is confirmed by their back-calculated and experimental &#x025b5;&#x003b4; values close to 0 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E, right). U<sub>15</sub> does not stack at all, so that &#x025b5;&#x003b4;&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0. This lack of stacking of U<sub>15</sub> also leads to U<sub>16</sub> &#x025b5;&#x003b4;&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0, because aromatic chemical shifts are mostly affected by the residue on the 5&#x02032; side (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). Residues 11&#x02013;13 and 16&#x02013;18 converge well (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E, left). The convergence for G<sub>14</sub> is somewhat less (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E, left), suggesting a certain degree of mobility. No convergence is reached for U<sub>15</sub>, suggesting a large degree of flexibility. For this residue the experimental &#x025b5;&#x003b4; fall just outside the error bar of the back-calculated &#x00394;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E, right). This can be explained by occasional stacking of U<sub>15</sub> not fully accounted for in the ensemble of calculated structures.</p><p>The U<sub>13</sub>:U<sub>16</sub> base pair in the UGUU tetraloop is slightly buckled and of the &#x02018;cis-wobble&#x02019; type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). It is comparable after initial calculation to that found in 1NA2, and in the final structure after CS refinement to that in 1MZP, [1NAZ and 1MZP accession codes in RCSB databank (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>)]. The &#x02018;cis-wobble&#x02019; conformation contains H-bonds between U<sub>13</sub>-O2:U<sub>16</sub>-NH3 and U<sub>13</sub>-NH3:U<sub>16</sub>-O4. Efficient H-bonding of U<sub>13</sub>-NH3:U<sub>16</sub>-O4 in the U<sub>13</sub>:U<sub>16</sub> pair together with stacking of G<sub>14</sub> can account for the protection of the U<sub>13</sub>-NH3 (see above, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). In the derived structure model, the U<sub>16</sub>-NH3, although H-bonded, is more solvent exposed due to the high flexibility and lack of stacking of U<sub>15</sub>. This may explain why the U<sub>16</sub>-NH3 resonance is not detected in the [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY.</p><p>In conclusion, NMR experimental data show that the top part of the <italic>avian</italic> epsilon apical stem-loop folds into a well-defined UGUU tetraloop motif: characterized by a non-canonical closing U<sub>13</sub>:U<sub>16</sub> base-pair (type cis-wobble) onto which G<sub>14</sub> stacks, while U<sub>15</sub> is flexible, highly solvent exposed and easily accessible to intermolecular interactions. The initial and refined structures are deposited in the pdb-bank with accession codes, 2OJ7 and 2OJ8, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Human HBV epsilon apical stem-loop (ALHu)</title><p>The (3D) structure of the <italic>ALHu</italic> stem-loop (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B) has been previously investigated with NMR by Flodell <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). It consists of a stem formed by 10&#x02009;bp with one bulged-out U and capped with a stable pseudo tri-loop also called a &#x02018;lone pair UGU tri-loop&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Structural Investigation of the duck HBV primer loop (PLD)</title><p>Combining data from [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C) and [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>15</sup>N]-HSQC (Figure 4B) spectra allowed for unambiguous assignment of 13 of the 15 imino resonances observed in the 1D NMR spectrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, and S3). From these data, we derived the secondary structure model of <italic>PLD</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D). Base pairs are formed in the <italic>lower stem</italic> up to A<sub>6</sub>:U<sub>32</sub>. The U<sub>7</sub>:G<sub>31</sub> wobble base pair at the top of the lower stem, closing the lower part of the primer loop, was not observed in the [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY. It is thus open or in fast exchange with an open form. In the <italic>upper stem</italic> the G<sub>14</sub>:C<sub>29</sub> base pair is formed, thereby locking the primer loop in its upper region. The remaining unassigned imino signals in the 1D NMR spectrum, at &#x0223c;11.8 and 11.2&#x02009;p.p.m., can thus either be from U<sub>7</sub>:G<sub>31</sub> or by exclusion be assigned to Us from the primer loop region.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>The <italic>duck</italic> primer loop secondary structure (<italic>PLD</italic>) from NMR data. (<bold>A</bold>) <sup>1</sup>H-imino spectra (5&#x000b0;C, H<sub>2</sub>O); (<bold>B</bold>) [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>15</sup>N]-HSQC of the selectively <sup>15</sup>N-U labeled <italic>PLD</italic> (5&#x000b0;C, H<sub>2</sub>O); (<bold>C</bold>) Imino region of <italic>PLD</italic> [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY spectrum (15&#x000b0;C, H<sub>2</sub>O); (<bold>D</bold>) Secondary structure model derived from experimental NMR data. The same coding is used as in Figure 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm131f4"/></fig></p><p>The primer loop region is well folded as follows from the extensive network of long-range NOE contacts: U<sub>9</sub>-H6&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;G<sub>31</sub>-H1&#x02032;, U<sub>10</sub>-H6&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;G<sub>31</sub>-H1&#x02032;, U<sub>10</sub>-H6&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;A<sub>12</sub>-H1&#x02032;, U<sub>11</sub>-H6&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;U<sub>30</sub>-H1&#x02032; and A<sub>12</sub>-H2&#x02009;&#x02194;&#x02009;C<sub>29</sub>-H1&#x02032; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D). Furthermore, most primer loop residues experience A-helix-like stacking interactions, as evidenced by ring currents close to that in an A-helix; only A<sub>12</sub> and C<sub>13</sub> show reduced ring currents and thus reduced stacking (S4).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Thermodynamics</title><sec><title>Human and avian epsilon HBV apical loops display significantly different thermodynamics</title><p>The thermodynamic properties of <italic>ALD, ALH</italic> and <italic>ALHu</italic> RNA structures were investigated by UV melting and analyzed following the practical recommendations of Puglisi and Tinoco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>) as described in more detail in the Materials and Methods section. The raw experimental melting curves are presented in Figure S5. The first derivatives of the fitted experimental curves are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>, their melting temperatures and associated thermodynamic parameters are compiled in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. All thermal denaturation curves were analyzed assuming an all-or-none (or two-state) model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>) to derive the thermodynamic parameters. This approximation is appropriate for melting of non-interacting short helices as investigated here (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). The absence of intermolecular interactions was assessed for each individual RNA sequence by recording melting curves at high and low RNA concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Because the sequences are all single stranded, the melting is mono-molecular and must be independent of concentration. In addition, the effect of salt (monovalent, Na<sup>+</sup> as well as divalent, Mg<sup>2+</sup>) was investigated. As no significant effect was observed when using Mg<sup>2+</sup>, we do not present these data, except in the case of <italic>ALHu</italic> below. The analysis was completed by comparison of experimentally derived values of free energy changes with those computed from NMR-derived secondary structure and using the thermodynamic parameter tables published by Serra and Turner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Thermodynamic parameters of the apical loop sequences derived for different Na<sup>+</sup>- and RNA concentrations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">[RNA]&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol&#x000b7;1<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Na<sup>+</sup>]&#x02009;mol&#x000b7;1<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>&#x000b0;C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;H&#x000b0;&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;S&#x000b0;&#x02009;cal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000b7;K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;G&#x000b0;&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ALD</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;64.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;190.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.3/&#x02212;6.3<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;95.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;279.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;63.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;193.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;63.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;190.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ALH</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;31.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;93.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;53.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;158.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;111.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;27.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ALHu</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.d.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;96.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;273.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;92.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;263.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;96.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;273.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>The values followed by * and ** are computed values derived with <italic>Mfold</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>) and with tables by Serra and Turner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>), respectively. <sup>a</sup>Value corrected for dangling end-effect in <italic>ALD</italic> (see text). For <italic>ALH</italic>, the predicted &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0; computed with <italic>Mfold</italic> is found to be slightly lower (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;4.2&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) than using Serra and Turner's tables, because <italic>Mfold</italic> considers the internal loop region in the structure less destabilizing than the experimental tables by Serra and Turner.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>UV melting transition recorded for <italic>ALD, ALH, ALHu</italic>, and <italic>PLD</italic>. On the figure are displayed the first derivatives of the fitted experimental melting curves as described in the Materials and Methods section; original experimental data are presented in S5.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm131f5"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>ALD sequence is less stable than expected on the basis of the NMR model</title><p>Thermal denaturation of <italic>ALD</italic> in 1.0&#x02009;M NaCl occurs via a single transition with a melting temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>) of 64.9&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, S5). The transition is mono-molecular because RNA concentration does not affect <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>The standard Gibbs free energy change (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;<sub>exp</sub>) of the transition is &#x02212;5.3&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as follows from a van't Hoff plot (Materials and Methods section). However, both full-length (<italic>ALD<sub>n</sub></italic>) and the <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1 abortive (<italic>ALD<sub>n</sub></italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub>) products were combined into one sample to compensate for the low <italic>in vitro</italic> expression. The absence of C<sub>29</sub> in the <italic>ALD<sub>n</sub></italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub> sequence increases &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0; with 2.1&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as follows from Turner's tables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). The relative concentrations of <italic>ALD<sub>n</sub></italic> and <italic>ALD<sub>n</sub></italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub> were estimated to be equal, based on denaturing PAGE and NMR analysis. The presence of this 50% <italic>ALD<sub>n</sub></italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub> requires a correction of &#x02212;1.05&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, leading to a final &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;<sub>exp</sub> of &#x02212;6.3&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for full-length <italic>ALD</italic>.</p><p>Using Turner's tables and the NMR-derived secondary structure model, we computed a predicted &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;<sub>calc</sub> of &#x02212;9.3&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Thus <italic>ALD</italic> is predicted to be 2.0&#x02013;3.0&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> more stable than what is experimentally observed. This is a significant difference as &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;<sub>calc</sub> can typically be predicted with an error margin of 10% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). The 2.0&#x02013;3.0&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> difference in stability corresponds to a loss of 2&#x02013;3 Watson&#x02013;Crick bp, or alternatively to the presence of an additional 2-nt bulge in the sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). Hence we must conclude that one or more unidentified elements within the ALD structure are less stable than expected; our NMR melting studies (see below) demonstrate that it is the middle part of the ALD stem that is relatively unstable.</p></sec><sec><title>ALH sequence: thermodynamics fully supports the NMR model</title><p>Thermal denaturation of <italic>ALH</italic> occurs via a broad transition with a <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of 63.1&#x000b0;C in standard 1.0&#x02009;M NaCl conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The absence of an RNA concentration effect on the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> indicates that the transition is mono-molecular (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). We derived in standard conditions a &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0; of &#x02212;2.5&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. This value matches perfectly with the one computed using Turner's tables and the NMR-derived secondary structure model (&#x02212;2.4&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Strikingly, even though <italic>ALH</italic> is clearly less structured than <italic>ALD</italic>, their experimentally derived melting temperatures are in the same range: 63.1&#x000b0;C for <italic>ALH</italic> and 64.9&#x000b0;C for <italic>ALD</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). They nevertheless display a significant difference in free energy change (&#x0223c;4&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The width of the transition's first derivative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>) is much larger for <italic>ALH</italic> than for <italic>ALD</italic>, indicating a smaller &#x00394;<italic>H</italic>&#x000b0; for <italic>ALH</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). This smaller &#x00394;<italic>H</italic>&#x000b0; must be compensated by a smaller &#x00394;<italic>S</italic>&#x000b0;, because &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0&#x02009;at the melting temperature and both sequences have approximately the same <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> values. Both sequences have the same length and thus a similar entropy in the denatured form. Hence the initial entropy of <italic>ALH</italic> must be larger than that of <italic>ALD</italic>. This is consistent with the NMR secondary structure models, which show that <italic>ALH</italic> has a large floppy internal loop and <italic>ALD</italic> does not have (see above).</p></sec><sec><title>ALHu sequence: highly thermodynamically stable</title><p>The thermal denaturation of <italic>ALHu</italic> shows a narrow transition with a <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of 79.5&#x000b0;C (with 0.15&#x02009;M NaCl). The absence of an RNA concentration effect on the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> indicates that the transition is mono-molecular. The &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;<sub>exp</sub> is &#x02212;11.8&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (0.15&#x02009;M NaCl, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Thermodynamic parameters from a melting curve under standard conditions could not be determined (i.e. 1.0&#x02009;M NaCl), as the sequence was so stable that the base line in the high-temperature domain could not be defined with reasonable confidence. The &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;<sub>exp</sub> is in good agreement with &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;<sub>calc</sub>, which is based on the NMR-derived secondary structure (&#x02212;12.2&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>NMR melting analysis shows <italic>ALD</italic> structural instability</title><p>To identify the residues involved in the thermal melting, the process was followed by solution NMR. In a nucleic acid base pair, the iminos (from G and U residues) are hydrogen bonded and protected from exchange with water in this closed state. Exchange can only take place in the open state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Raising the temperature shifts the equilibrium towards the open state. Proton exchange between the imino proton and the solvent, broadens, but does not shift, the imino proton resonance. In contrast, the alteration between closed and open states produces a shift, but usually no appreciable broadening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). Usually the line broadening is much more pronounced than the change in chemical shift. Therefore, broadening of the imino resonances (and small changes in their chemical shifts) directly proves a shift towards the open state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>).</p><p>The <sup>1</sup>H-imino NMR spectra of <italic>ALD</italic> were followed from 5 to 40&#x000b0;C in steps of 5&#x000b0;C (Materials and Methods section, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). At 40&#x000b0;C, i.e. below the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> observed by UV melting (see above), the imino resonances assigned to G<sub>2</sub>-NH1, U<sub>3</sub>-NH3 and G<sub>26</sub>-NH1 are still intense and narrow. Also, the peaks assigned to G<sub>11</sub>-NH1, G<sub>17</sub>-NH1 and U<sub>18</sub>-NH3, although broadened, are still observable, even at 40&#x000b0;C. This indicates that both the top loop and the basal stem regions are relatively stable. On the other hand, the U<sub>21</sub>-NH3, G<sub>22</sub>-NH1 and U<sub>23</sub>-NH3 resonances, in the middle region already broaden and vanish between 30 and 35&#x000b0;C. Thus, these central base pairs open before the top loop and basal stem region. In conclusion, a relatively unstable motif is located in the middle region of the sequence, lowering the apparent overall stability as derived from UV melting.
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>NMR melting study. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>ALD</italic>
<sup>1</sup>H-imino spectra; (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>PLD</italic>
<sup>1</sup>H-imino spectra; (<bold>C</bold>) Structural weakness of <italic>ALD</italic> is highlighted using the following color coding: <italic>blue</italic>, stable base pair, imino peak visible at 40&#x000b0;C; <italic>yellow</italic>, base pair affected by enhanced exchange at 40&#x000b0;C, imino broadened; <italic>red</italic>, base pair highly affected by exchange at 40&#x000b0;C, imino peak vanished. The central region (red) &#x02018;melts&#x02019; between 30 and 35&#x000b0;C. (<bold>D</bold>) Structural weakness of <italic>PLD</italic> is highlighted using the same color coding as in C, except for: <italic>orange</italic>, residues from the primer loop region, non-specifically assigned, affected by exchange in the low temperature range. Imino resonances in A and B are indicated by residue type and number with color code corresponding to that used in C and D.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm131f6"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Thermodynamic properties of <italic>PLD</italic></title><p>The thermal denaturation of <italic>PLD</italic> is characterized by two well-resolved transitions. The first (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> 45.7&#x000b0;C, &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0; of &#x02212;1.38&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) gives rise to an increase of only &#x0223c;1% in UV absorbance (hyperchromicity) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). For comparison, the complete unfolding of a double-stranded RNA typically causes an increase in overall UV absorbance of 15&#x02013;20% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The first transition is thus related to a structural element where only partial unpacking of nucleic bases occurs, e.g. the primer loop. The second transition is of much larger amplitude, &#x0223c;15% hyperchromicity, and centered at &#x0223c;85&#x000b0;C (S5). Although it is well separated from the first, its high <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> does not allow us to obtain a well-defined base line in the high temperature domain. Consequently, its <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> and associated thermodynamic parameters cannot be accurately derived. The upper stem of <italic>PLD</italic> is capped with a highly stable UUCG tetraloop [<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;70&#x000b0;C, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>)] to facilitate NMR assignment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). Because of its high <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> and its relatively large hyperchromicity, the second transition most likely includes as RNA elements, the UUCG loop and the stems.</p><p>To unambiguously identify the residues involved in the first and second melting transitions, the melting process was followed by <sup>1</sup>H imino NMR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). At 40&#x000b0;C, all broad resonances between 11.7 and 10.5&#x02009;p.p.m. (orange in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B) as well as the U<sub>32</sub>
<sup>1</sup>H-imino resonance at 14.3&#x02009;p.p.m. (red in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B) have completely vanished. All other <sup>1</sup>H-imino resonances remain sharp and intense. The <sup>1</sup>H-imino of U<sub>20</sub>, engaged in the closing UG base pair of the UUCG tetraloop, is also broadened, but remains detectable (red in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). In summary, we observe that the resonances that vanish at 40&#x000b0;C are within/or close to the epsilon primer loop. The first transition can thus unambiguously be assigned to a conformational rearrangement affecting the primer loop residues. The sharpness of the remaining imino resonances demonstrates the existence of well-formed upper and lower stems above the transition (45.7&#x000b0;C).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Although knowledge of the molecular basis for P&#x02013;&#x003b5; binding and priming is emerging from biochemical probing methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>), several questions remain concerning the exact structure or sequence determinants of &#x003b5; that trigger the P&#x02013;&#x003b5; interaction. A full understanding of the molecular basis for P&#x02013;&#x003b5; binding and priming awaits high-resolution structural and thermodynamic data. Our NMR results and thermodynamic data define and compare the structure and stability characteristics of the <italic>AL</italic> (and <italic>PL</italic>) segments of &#x003b5; RNAs from <italic>human, duck</italic> and <italic>heron</italic> HBV. They are discussed below in terms of structure motifs important for P&#x02013;&#x003b5; interaction.</p><sec><title>The apical stem-loop of epsilon in avian HBV is capped by a well-structured UGUU tetraloop</title><p>We first discuss the structure of the top of the <italic>avian</italic> &#x003b5; apical stem-loop with sequence: GC<bold>UGU</bold><sub>2590</sub><bold>U</bold>GU [for ease of comparison definition and numbering of Hu <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>)]. Our NMR data and structure calculations show that in the <italic>duck</italic> &#x003b5; apical stem- loop the above sequence folds into a well-defined tetraloop structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E). It contains a non-canonical U<sub>2588</sub>:U<sub>2591</sub> base pair (type cis-wobble) stacked onto the closing base pair C<sub>2587</sub>:G<sub>2592</sub>, while residue G<sub>2589</sub> is in turn stacked onto U<sub>2588</sub> on the major groove side. Most interesting is the flexible U<sub>2590</sub>, which is solvent exposed and thus available for intermolecular interaction. The UGUU tetraloop is new as far as we are aware; for instance, no UGUU tetraloop is observed in the ribosome.</p><p>Although the structure calculations were carried out on the <italic>duck</italic> sequence, our NMR data also show the presence of G<sub>2592</sub> and G<sub>2586</sub> imino resonances in the <italic>heron</italic> apical stem-loop and with similar chemical shifts as in <italic>duck</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). This unequivocally demonstrates the formation of base pairs C<sub>2587</sub>:G<sub>2592</sub> and G<sub>2586</sub>:U<sub>2593</sub> with similar conformation in <italic>duck</italic> and <italic>heron</italic> strains. Hence, the sequence UGUU, closed by the C<sub>2587</sub>:G<sub>2592</sub>/G<sub>2586</sub>:U<sub>2593</sub> base pairs, must take on this UGUU tetraloop fold (albeit possibly with some dynamics in the loop itself) not only in <italic>duck</italic> but also in <italic>heron</italic>. The formation of a tetraloop in <italic>heron</italic> was unexpected because the middle part of the apical stem has no complementary base pairs, predicting it to be non- or loosely folded.</p><p>The following conclusions can now be drawn: (a) Given the high conservation of the GC<bold>UGU</bold><sub>2590</sub><bold>U</bold>GU sequence among all <italic>avian</italic> HBV strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), one can reasonably conclude that the prototypic <italic>avian</italic> &#x003b5; signal contains a well-defined tetraloop structure with two underlying base pairs at the top of the apical stem-loop (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>E and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). In terms of P&#x02013;&#x003b5; interaction, we can further conclude and propose the following: (b) Given the observation that in all SELEX-generated binders one or two closing base pairs are seen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), one can reasonably conclude that efficient <italic>avian</italic> P&#x02013;&#x003b5; binding requires formation of a tetraloop closed by one or two underlying base pairs. (c) Given the observation of a tetraloop sequence in all SELEX-generated binders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), we propose that this tetraloop fold is required and acts as a recognition determinant for the RT-domain of protein P, although alternatively interaction(s) with chaperone proteins cannot be excluded. (d) Given that mutation U<sub>2590</sub>C causes complete loss of binding, without likely affecting the tetraloop structure, we propose that the solvent-exposed U<sub>2590</sub> interacts with the RT-domain of protein P upon initial binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>).
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Schematic of the functional prototypic <italic>avian</italic> HBV &#x003b5; signal. It summarizes our structural and thermodynamic data and some pertinent mutation/probing and sequence data from Nassal cs.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), who proposed as the functional prototypic &#x003b5; signal an open structure of the <italic>AL</italic> as in H&#x003b5;. Combined with our data this model can now be refined. The functional prototypic <italic>avian</italic> &#x003b5; signal appears to be: an <italic>AL</italic>, unstructured or weakly structured in the middle stem (gray) and capped with a structured UGUU tetraloop closed by two underlying base pairs; a structured pimer loop (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> 47&#x000b0;C, light gray) closed at its tip by a stable C:G base pair, whereas the U:G closing base pair at its bottom is absent or not stably formed. U<sub>2590</sub> (dark gray circle) in the conserved UGUU tetraloop is a key recognition element in initial binding (see text). Binding is followed by structural rearrangements to obtain a priming competent complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). This should involve residues G<sub>2586</sub>, C<sub>2594</sub> and U<sub>2604</sub> (open circle), as they are not P accessible upon initial binding and have been proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) to be part of a network of anchor residues, enabling precise positioning of P over the initiation site (see text).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm131f7"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>An unstable region is present in the middle of all avian epsilon apical stem-loops: this recurrent functional motif is required for P-binding</title><p>The second motif involves the middle part of the apical stem. From their pool of SELEX-generated RNA, Hu <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) found that mutants, which bind P with high affinity, present poor base pairing within the middle stem region. This finding is substantiated by mutagenesis experiments, which introduced more efficient base pairing in the <italic>duck</italic> apical stem. According to the authors, this absence of base pairing, and thus instability or flexibility, is a general characteristic of all <italic>avian</italic> strains except the <italic>duck</italic> strain. The existence of relatively extensive base pairing in the <italic>duck</italic> sequence appeared to be an exception to the rule among <italic>avian</italic> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). However, our NMR data show that, although the <italic>ALD</italic> structure is well defined and structured at low temperature (&#x0003c;ca. 30&#x000b0;C), it does contain a weak middle stem region, which undergoes a &#x02018;melting&#x02019; transition between 30 and 35&#x000b0;C, i.e. the imino resonances of this region broaden to disappearance in this temperature range in contrast to those of the upper and lower stems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A and C). Thus, our data show that the &#x003b5;-apical stem-loop of DHBV is not an exception but has characteristics similar to that of all <italic>avian</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Initial binding is followed by structural changes, which lead to a priming- competent complex</title><p>A priming-competent complex requires initial binding to be followed by structural rearrangements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). The DHBV &#x003b5;&#x02013;P complex was investigated by chemical probing in an isolated state obtained just after a 2/4-nt primer was synthesized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). In this state, the stem of the &#x003b5;-apical stem-loop is melted and interacts with the RT-domain of the P-complex. Due to this interaction, many residues in the apical stem are protected, but its middle region, identified by NMR melting as a structurally weak point, contains a central GU<sub>2598</sub>G hotspot, more reactive to Pb<sup>2+</sup> attack, showing it is solvent exposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>).</p><p>The SELEX data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) show that three residues, G<sub>2586</sub>, C<sub>2594</sub> and U<sub>2604</sub>, are of special interest as their mutation abrogates priming but not binding and they, except for G<sub>2586</sub>, are part of the P footprint (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). This suggests that these residues represent anchoring points directing or relaying, after initial binding, the necessary structural rearrangements leading up to the priming-competent complex as proposed by Hu <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Our structural data on <italic>AL</italic> and <italic>PL</italic> show that these residues are not accessible to P interactions upon initial binding. Initial binding must therefore be followed by structural rearrangements to obtain a priming-competent complex. Interestingly, these residues are located at the border of or just outside the more stable stem regions. These rearrangements could be triggered by higher dynamics of these residues, which would populate the low-populated states where these residues are P accessible. We are currently investigating their dynamics.</p><p>The free energy (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;) cost for complete opening of the primer loop and apical stem-loop is &#x0223c;13, &#x0223c;8 and &#x0223c;4&#x02009;kcal&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the <italic>human, duck</italic> and <italic>heron</italic> sequences, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). These values define an upper bound on the free energy required for priming considering that partial conformational rearrangement(s) may as well suffice. The &#x0223c;8&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for <italic>duck</italic> appears to be the maximum that can be accommodated by the <italic>duck</italic> P protein complex, since further stabilization of the middle part of the apical stem abrogates binding. Why <italic>human</italic> &#x003b5; RNA is not binding competent in the DHBV <italic>in vitro</italic> system could be due to its high stability. The study by Hu and Boyer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) on a recently developed <italic>in vitro human</italic> HBV system appears to indicate that in <italic>human</italic> HBV, the apical loop is not needed for binding of &#x003b5; to P, but instead for encapsidation. This interaction with core proteins may in <italic>human</italic> &#x003b5; RNA be needed to enforce the structural rearrangements required for priming.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>In this article, the structures and stabilities of the apical stem-loops (<italic>AL</italic>) of <italic>human, duck</italic> and <italic>heron</italic> HBV epsilon RNA elements have been investigated. UV melting shows that the <italic>avian AL, duck</italic> and <italic>heron</italic>, are much less stable than <italic>human AL</italic>. NMR data show that this low stability stems from the unstructured 11-nt internal bulge in the middle of the stem of <italic>heron AL</italic>. In <italic>duck</italic>, this region, although structured at low temperature, also forms a structural weak point, as evidenced by broadening to disappearance of their imino resonances between 30 and 35&#x000b0;C, well below the overall melting temperature of ca. 60&#x000b0;C. The <italic>duck and heron AL</italic>s are both capped by a stable UGUU tetraloop closed by two underlying base pairs. All <italic>avian AL</italic> are expected to adhere to this because of their sequence conservation. The seven-residue primer-loop of &#x003b5; <italic>duck</italic> HBV is structured, having a melting temperature of 45.7&#x000b0;C and a Gibbs free energy change equal to &#x02212;1.4&#x02009;kcal&#x000b7;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. In view of sequence similarities the same is expected for <italic>heron</italic>- and <italic>human PL</italic>. The present structure and thermodynamic data combined with mutation data thus refine the model for the functional prototypical <italic>avian</italic> &#x003b5; signal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>RNA sample preparation</title><p>RNA sequences <italic>ALD, ALH, ALHu</italic> and <italic>PLD</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B) were synthesized by standard <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription using a single-stranded DNA template and T7 RNA polymerase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). Both full-length (<italic>ALD<sub>n</sub></italic>) and the <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1 abortive (<italic>ALD<sub>n</sub></italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub>) products were combined into one sample to compensate for the low <italic>in vitro</italic> expression. A selectively U-labeled <italic>ALD</italic> sample was also prepared following the same procedure, using <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>15</sup>N/<sup>2</sup>H<sub>1&#x02032;, 3&#x02032;, 4&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;&#x02032;</sub>-UTP. It was prepared according to Cromsigt <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). In addition, segments of the <italic>AL</italic> as well as a <italic>PLD-U30</italic> mutant were synthesized to support and confirm NMR resonance assignments (S6). <italic>PLD</italic> and <italic>PLD-U30</italic> were each expressed in 3 different forms, for instance non-isotopically labeled, <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>15</sup>N/<sup>2</sup>H<sub>1&#x02032;, 3&#x02032;, 4&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;&#x02032;</sub>-Uracil and <sup>2</sup>H<sub>1&#x02032;, 3&#x02032;, 4&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;&#x02032;</sub>-Uracil labeled.</p></sec><sec><title>UV melting experiments</title><p>RNA samples were re-suspended in the appropriate <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> buffer (50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 7, 150&#x02009;mM NaCl). Prior to the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> experiment, samples were snap-cooled after 1&#x02009;min denaturation at 90&#x000b0;C. For each sample (<italic>ALD, ALH, ALHu</italic> and <italic>PLD</italic>), experiments were carried out at high and low RNA concentrations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The thermal denaturation/renaturation curves were recorded at 260&#x02009;nm over a temperature range of 20&#x02013;90&#x000b0;C using a fixed rate of 0.5&#x000b0;C&#x000b7;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> on a Varian Cary 300-Bio UV-Vis spectrometer. The melting curves were analyzed following closely the recommendations described by Puglisi and Tinoco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Briefly, the experimental melting curves were baseline corrected by fitting a linear function to its pre-transition part and subsequently subtracting the slope over the whole temperature range. The baseline-corrected experimental curves were normalized and subsequently fitted in MATLAB with a general sigmoidal function as shown in Equation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), which includes baseline (<italic>x</italic><sub>4</sub>) and offset (<italic>x</italic><sub>5</sub>),
<disp-formula id="M1"><label>1</label><graphic xlink:href="gkm131m1"/></disp-formula>
The normalization constant (<italic>x</italic><sub>1</sub>) should now be 1, while baseline (<italic>x</italic><sub>4</sub>) and offset (<italic>x</italic><sub>5</sub>) terms should be zero. If not, the pre-transition part should be adjusted and the baseline correction and normalization iterated. In this way a careful baseline correction at low and high temperature of the experimental melting curves was achieved. Melting temperatures were derived from the maximum of the fitted curves&#x02019; first derivative. Thermodynamics parameters (&#x00394;<italic>H</italic>&#x000b0;, &#x00394;<italic>S</italic>&#x000b0; and &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x000b0;) were subsequently derived from the van't Hoff plot of the normalized and baseline-corrected melting curves, again all according to Puglisi and Tinoco's recommendations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Thermodynamic parameters of each RNA sequence were also computed using either Turner's tables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>) and the NMR-derived secondary structure and/or secondary structure prediction using Zuker's algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>NMR spectroscopy</title><p>All NMR samples were prepared in the appropriate NMR buffer (10&#x02009;mM Na-Phosphate pH 6.7, 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA), to a final concentration of 1.2, 1.0, 0.4, 0.8, 0.8 and 0.8&#x02009;mM for <italic>ALD</italic>, <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>15</sup>N/<sup>2</sup>H-U labeled <italic>ALD, ALH, PLD</italic>, <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>15</sup>N/<sup>2</sup>H-U labeled <italic>PLD</italic> and <sup>2</sup>H-U labeled <italic>PLD</italic>, respectively. Spectra in water (95:5, H<sub>2</sub>O:D<sub>2</sub>O) were recorded at 5 and 15&#x000b0;C on a 500&#x02009;MHz Varian Inova spectrometer. Water suppression was achieved with a Watergate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>) sequence combined with water flip-back pulse (WFB) based on a SINC-type-shaped pulse. The 2D [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY spectra in water, used for resonance assignment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>), were recorded with 100 and 200&#x02009;ms mixing time, collecting 2048&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;700 complex points for a spectral width of 14&#x02009;kHz in both dimensions. For the NMR melting experiments, 1D-WFB/watergate <sup>1</sup>H spectra were recorded every 5&#x000b0;C from 5 to 40&#x000b0;C, collecting 128 scans and using 2000 complex points for a spectral width of 14&#x02009;kHz. For the U-labeled <italic>ADL</italic> sequence, [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>15</sup>N]-HMQC-WFB was recorded on a 600&#x02009;MHz Varian Inova spectrometer, collecting 2048&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;400 points for a spectral width of 15 and 2.5&#x02009;kHz, respectively. In D<sub>2</sub>O, all spectra were recorded on an 800&#x02009;MHz Varian Inova spectrometer. A set of 2D [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY experiments was carried out at 15 and 25&#x000b0;C using 30, 120, 300 and 500&#x02009;ms mixing time. For each spectrum, 2048&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;800 complex points were acquired over a spectral width of 8&#x02009;kHz in both direct and indirect dimensions. [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-DQF-COSY experiments, acquired in a constant time fashion using a refocusing delay of 40&#x02009;ms, were recorded with the same respective spectral width and resolution. Sugar puckering modes were derived from observable/non-observable H1&#x02032;-H2&#x02032; coherences in the COSY spectra. [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>13</sup>C]-HSQC and <sup>13</sup>C-decoupled [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>1</sup>H]-NOESY spectra of the U-labeled <italic>ALD</italic> sample were recorded for assignment purposes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Finally, 1D <sup>31</sup>P and [<sup>1</sup>H,<sup>31</sup>P]-HMBC spectra were recorded to derive information on phosphate backbone conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). The spectra were processed with NMRpipe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>) prior to resonance assignment using Sparky software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Structure calculations</title><p>Structure calculations on G<sub>11</sub>CUGUUGU<sub>18</sub> of <italic>ALD</italic> were carried out with X-PLOR 3.851 using a torsion angle dynamics protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). Starting from an extended structure, 800 structures were generated using classical NMR restraints (Table S7). The 10 lowest- energy structures (Table S7) were selected for further refinement employing chemical shifts as additional restraints as described in the legend of Table S7, generating 10 refined structures out of each selected structure. From the resulting 100 refined structures, the 10 with lowest energy were selected and their <sup>1</sup>H chemical shifts analyzed using Nuchemics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>). The calculated <sup>1</sup>H shifts were averaged among the ensemble to account for motional averaging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>) and subsequently for each nucleotide &#x025b5;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> values were computed as described in the legend of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary data is available at NAR Online.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm131_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="nar_gkm131_nar-00082-r-2007-File002.doc"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>Valuable discussions with Prof. Michael Nassal (Freiburg, Germany) on different aspects of the HBV P&#x02013;&#x003b5; recognition are gratefully acknowledged. This work was supported by grants from the Dutch Science Foundation (SW), the EU (FP6 STREP, FSG-V-RNA, SW), the Swedish Natural Science Research Council (SW), Biotechnology Fund Umea University (SW) and the Foundation for Strategic Research Sweden/I&#x00026;V (SW). Funding to pay the Open Access publication charge was provided by EU FP6, FSG-V-RNA.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buendia</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B viruses and hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Adv. Cancer Res.</source><year>1992</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1325733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical progress &#x02013; hepatitis B virus infection</article-title><source>New Engl. J. Med.</source><year>1997</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>1733</fpage><lpage>1745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9392700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganem</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fields Virology</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott, Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>DNA Virus Replication</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B virus replication: novel roles for virus-host interactions</article-title><source>Intervirology</source><year>1999</year><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10516465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganem</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Varmus</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular-biology of the hepatitis-B viruses</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>1987</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3039907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B virus replication &#x02013; an update</article-title><source>J. Viral Hepat.</source><year>1996</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8914001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental confirmation of a hepatitis B virus (HBV) epsilon-like bulge-and-loop structure in avian HBV RNA encapsidation signals</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>1997</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9018150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tavis</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Perri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganem</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepadnavirus reverse transcription initiates within the stem-loop of the RNA packaging signal and employs a novel strand transfer</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>1994</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>3536</fpage><lpage>3543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8189492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation of a functional hepatitis B virus replication initiation complex involves a major structural alteration in the RNA template</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>6265</fpage><lpage>6272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9774643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel mechanism for reverse transcription in hepatitis B viruses</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>1993</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>6507</fpage><lpage>6512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7692081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence- and structure-specific determinants in the interaction between the RNA encapsidation signal and reverse transcriptase of avian hepatitis B viruses</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>4971</fpage><lpage>4980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9188560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstitution of a functional duck hepatitis B virus replication initiation complex from separate reverse transcriptase domains expressed in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>7410</fpage><lpage>7419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11462013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient hsp90-independent <italic>in vitro</italic> activation by Hsc70 and Hsp40 of duck hepatitis B virus reverse transcriptase, an assumed Hsp90 client protein</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>36128</fpage><lpage>36138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12851401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anselmo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> reconstitution of a functional duck hepatitis B virus reverse transcriptase: posttranslational activation by Hsp90</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>11447</fpage><lpage>11455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11090140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SELEX-derived aptamers of the duck hepatitis B virus RNA encapsidation signal distinguish critical and non-critical residues for productive initiation of reverse transcription</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>4377</fpage><lpage>4389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15314208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leber</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiens</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutagenesis of a hepatitis B virus reverse transcriptase yields temperature-sensitive virus</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>1996</year><volume>222</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8806527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Toft</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Requirement of heat shock protein 90 for human hepatitis B virus reverse transcriptase function</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>13122</fpage><lpage>13131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15542664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flodell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zdunek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd-Ljunggren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleucher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of the apical stem-loop of the human hepatitis B virus encapsidation signal</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>4449</fpage><lpage>4457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16945960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flodell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleucher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cromsigt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ippel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd-Ljunggren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The apical stem-loop of the hepatitis B virus encapsidation signal folds into a stable tri-loop with two underlying pyrimidine bulges</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>4803</fpage><lpage>4811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12409471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannone</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The lonepair triloop: a new motif in RNA structure</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12473452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haasnoot</surname><given-names>PCJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsthoorn</surname><given-names>RCL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bol</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Brome mosaic virus subgenomic promoter hairpin is structurally similar to the iron-responsive element and functionally equivalent to the minus-strand core promoter stem-loop C</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11873757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>van Buuren</surname><given-names>BNM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of NMR methods for conformational studies of nucleic acids</article-title><source>Prog. Nucl. Magn. Reson. Spectrosc.</source><year>1998</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>387</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cromsigt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Buuren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleucher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resonance assignment and structure determination for RNA</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11460559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cromsigt</surname><given-names>JAMTC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilbers</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of proton chemical shifts in RNA &#x02013; their use in structure refinement and validation</article-title><source>J. Biomol., NMR</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11693565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leontis</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhof</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conserved geometrical base-pairing patterns in RNA</article-title><source>Q. Rev. Biophys.</source><year>1998</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemieux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA canonical and non-canonical base pairing types: a recognition method and complete repertoire</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>4250</fpage><lpage>4263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12364604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theimer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Finger</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Trantirek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Feigon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations linked to dyskeratosis congenita cause changes in the structural equilibrium in telomerase RNA</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12525685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikulin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliseikina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tishchenko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nevskaya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Davydova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Platonova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Piendl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Selmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liljas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure of the L1 protuberance in the ribosome</article-title><source>Nat. Struct. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12514741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flodell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cromsigt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleucher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd-Ljunggren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure elucidation of the hepatitis B virus encapsidation signal by NMR on selectively labeled RNAs</article-title><source>J. Biomol. Struct. Dyn.</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11843624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puglisi</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinoco</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Absorbency melting curves of RNA</article-title><source>Methods.Enzymol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2482421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Applequist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Damle</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermodynamics of helix-coil equilibrium in oligoadenylic acid from hypochromicity studies</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>1965</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1450</fpage><lpage>1455</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breslauer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturtevant</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinoco</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calorimetric and spectroscopic investigation of helix-to-coil transition of a ribo-oligonucleotide &#x02013; Ra7u7</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1975</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1214299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting thermodynamic properties of RNA</article-title><source>Energ. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>261</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marky</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallenbach</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcdonough</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeman</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Breslauer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The melting behavior of a DNA junction structure &#x02013; a calorimetric and spectroscopic study</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>1987</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1621</fpage><lpage>1634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3663876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gueron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochoyan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single-mode of DNA base-pair opening drives imino proton-exchange</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1987</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3037381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nonin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gueron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terminal base-pairs of oligodeoxynucleotides &#x02013; imino proton-exchange and fraying</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1995</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>10652</fpage><lpage>10659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7654719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental and computational studies of the G[UUCG]C RNA tetraloop</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10764572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B virus reverse transcriptase and epsilon RNA sequences required for specific interaction <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>2141</fpage><lpage>2150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16474122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhlenbeck</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of RNA protein contacts using thiophosphate substitutions</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1989</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2849</fpage><lpage>2855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2663062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cromsigt</surname><given-names>JAMTC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleucher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd-Ljunggren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of specifically deuterated nucleotides for NMR studies on RNA</article-title><source>J. Biomol. Struct. Dyn</source><year>2000</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22607427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3406</fpage><lpage>3415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On finding all suboptimal foldings of an RNA molecule</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1989</year><volume>244</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2468181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piotto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saudek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sklenar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gradient-tailored excitation for single-quantum NMR-spectroscopy of aqueous-solutions</article-title><source>J. Biomol. NMR</source><year>1992</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1490109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaglio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grzesiek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuister</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nmrpipe &#x02013; a multidimensional spectral processing system based on unix pipes</article-title><source>J. Biomol. NMR</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8520220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kneller</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuntz</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ucsf Sparky &#x02013; an NMR display, annotation and assignment tool</article-title><source>J. Cell. Biochem</source><year>1993</year><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>254</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunger</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Torsion-angle molecular dynamics as a new efficient tool for NMR structure calculation</article-title><source>J. Magn. Reson.</source><year>1997</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9424305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van Buuren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleucher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global structure of a DNA three-way junction by solution NMR: towards prediction of 3H fold</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>3228</fpage><lpage>3239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15199171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruithof</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilbers</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of H-1 chemical shifts in DNA: assessment of the reliability of H-1 chemical shift calculations for use in structure refinement</article-title><source>J. Biomol. NMR</source><year>1997</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20859781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huthoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for a base triple in the free HIV-1 TAR RNA</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14970387</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
