<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17259222</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1807966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl1096</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>RNA</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of new noncoding RNAs in <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> and prediction of mRNA targets</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mandin</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Repoila</surname><given-names>Francis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vergassola</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geissmann</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>Pascale</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Institut Pasteur, Unit&#x000e9; des Interactions Bact&#x000e9;ries-Cellules, Paris, F-75015 France; INSERM, U604, Paris, F-75015 France; INRA, USC2020, Paris, F-75015 France, <sup>2</sup>CNRS URA 2171, Institut Pasteur, UP G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique in silico, Paris, F-75015 France and <sup>3</sup>UPR 9002 du CNRS, Institut de Biologie Mol&#x000e9;culaire et Cellulaire, Universit&#x000e9; Louis Pasteur, Srasbourg, F-67084 France</aff><author-notes><fn id="FN1"><label><sup>&#x02021;</sup></label><p>Authors contributed equally</p></fn><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>(33) 145688841</phone>; Fax: <fax>(33) 145688706</fax>; E-mail: <email>pcossart@pasteur.fr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>962</fpage><lpage>974</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>To identify noncoding RNAs (ncRNAs) in the pathogenic bacterium <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, we analyzed the intergenic regions (IGRs) of strain EGD-e by <italic>in silico</italic>-based approaches. Among the twelve ncRNAs found, nine are novel and specific to the <italic>Listeria</italic> genus, and two of these ncRNAs are expressed in a growth-dependent manner. Three of the ncRNAs are transcribed in opposite direction to overlapping open reading frames (ORFs), suggesting that they act as antisense on the corresponding mRNAs. The other ncRNA genes appear as single transcription units. One of them displays five repeats of 29 nucleotides. Five of these new ncRNAs are absent from the non-pathogenic species <italic>L. innocua</italic>, raising the possibility that they might be involved in virulence. To predict mRNA targets of the ncRNAs, we developed a computational method based on thermodynamic pairing energies and known ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids. Three ncRNAs, including one of the putative antisense ncRNAs, were predicted to have more than one mRNA targets. Several of them were shown to bind efficiently to the ncRNAs suggesting that our <italic>in silico</italic> approach could be used as a general tool to search for mRNA targets of ncRNAs.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Noncoding RNAs (ncRNAs), other than ribosomal (rRNAs) and transfer RNAs (tRNAs), are recognized as important regulators in eukaryotes and prokaryotes. In bacteria, ncRNAs usually regulate gene expression either by pairing to mRNAs and affecting their stability and/or translation or by binding to proteins and modifying their activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). ncRNAs mostly function as coordinators of adaptation processes in response to environmental changes, integrating environmental signals and controlling target gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Few ncRNAs controlling virulence in bacteria have been identified, the best-documented example being RNAIII of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>).</p><p><italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, a Gram-positive bacterium, is the etiologic agent of listeriosis, a severe human infection with an overall 30% mortality rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). A number of virulence-related genes have been identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). They are regulated either by PrfA, a master transcriptional activator whose expression is under the control of an RNA thermosensor, or by the stress sigma factor SigB, or by two-component systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8 B9 B10 B11 B12">8&#x02013;12</xref>). A <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> strain deficient for Hfq, a protein involved in the pairing of ncRNAs with their mRNA targets in E. coli, is affected in tissue colonization in mouse, suggesting that ncRNAs might be involved in the control of virulence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Very recently an Hfq-immunoprecipitation method allowed the identification of three ncRNAs in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). This approach being restricted to Hfq-binding ncRNAs, we had decided to undertake a global search for ncRNAs.</p><p>The identification of mRNA targets of ncRNAs is essential to understand their functions, although it remains a challenging issue. Known examples of bacterial ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids generally feature internal loops and bulges, a major obstacle in predicting ncRNA targets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). A computational method has been developed in <italic>E. coli</italic>, to search for complementarities between a ncRNA and mRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). The empirical alignment score employed in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) equally weights A&#x02013;U and C&#x02013;G pairings, despite the stronger pairing energy of the latter. This may not be optimal for genomes with low GC content, such as that of <italic>Listeria</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).</p><p>Among possible approaches to search for ncRNAs (reviewed in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>)), we employed computer-based methods, followed by northern blots and 5&#x02032; end mapping. This allowed us to identify 12 ncRNAs in the <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> genome EGD-e (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). We also developed a novel computational method to predict mRNA targets of ncRNAs and were able to predict mRNA targets for three of our novel ncRNAs. These predictions were experimentally validated, strongly suggesting regulatory functions for these ncRNAs in <italic>Listeria</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title><italic>In silico</italic> analysis of IGR candidates for ncRNAs</title><p><list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p><italic>Selection of intergenic region candidates for ncRNA genes.</italic> Sequences between annotated open reading frames, i.e. <underline>i</underline>nter<underline>g</underline>enic <underline>r</underline>egions (IGRs), in the <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> EGD-e genome available at the ListiList web site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genolist.pasteur.fr/ListiList/">http://genolist.pasteur.fr/ListiList/</ext-link>) were considered in this study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). We restricted our analysis to IGRs with a minimal size of 150&#x02009;bp. Regions carrying rRNAs, tRNAs and within the A118 cryptic phage were excluded. A total of 694 IGRs were retained and analyzed using the BLAST program for their degree of conservation with sequences of microbial genomic sequences available at the NCBI web site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/BLAST/">http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/BLAST/</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Three kinds of conservation were observed:
<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>IGRs displaying portions of relatively long sequences (&#x02265;80&#x02009;bp) highly conserved between EGD-e and other <italic>Listeria</italic> genomes (magenta or red according to the BLAST color code), while the remaining parts were not similar. In these alignments (&#x0223c;8% of the total IGRs), conservations within IGRs concerned the <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> genomes and <italic>L. innocua</italic> occasionally, but no other bacterial genome. Since conservation may reveal the presence of a transcribed region, all of the IGRs in this group were kept for further analysis using folding predictions.</p></list-item><list-item><p>IGRs entirely conserved between <italic>Listeria</italic> species (&#x0223c;2% of the total IGRs), with portions of the sequence repeated elsewhere in the <italic>Listeria</italic> genomes and in other Gram-positive bacteria, mainly <italic>Bacillus</italic> species. In general, such type of conservation signed riboswitches (see below). However, three of these IGRs were predicted to carry the ncRNA genes <italic>rnpB</italic>, <italic>ssrA</italic> and <italic>ssrS</italic> and were kept as controls.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remaining IGRs (&#x0223c;90% of the total IGRs) were entirely conserved among <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> isolates (EGD-e and F6854, serotypes 1/2a; F2365 and H7858, serotypes 4b) and occasionally in the non-pathogenic species <italic>L. innocua</italic> (isolate CLIP11262). A few of these IGRs were kept for further analysis on the basis of qualitative criteria such as their size (&#x02265;350 bp) and the orientation of flanking genes (either both convergent or both divergent open reading frames (ORFs)). A total of 99 IGRs were thus selected for folding prediction analysis (Table S1).</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Screening IGRs by RNA folding predictions</italic>. Each strand of the DNA sequence from the 99 IGRs previously selected, was assimilated to a RNA molecule and was folded by using the MFOLD program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). Folding analysis indicated that 29 IGRs displayed on one of the strands, at least two consecutive stem-loops, distant by at least 50&#x02009;nt from the adjacent ORFs, spaced by a maximum of 50&#x02009;nt. Within these stem-loops, at least five bases were forming the stem including at least one G:C pairing and a loop smaller than 10&#x02009;nt (Table S1).</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Orphan transcription terminators</italic>. We searched for Rho-independent terminators with standard pattern-recognition algorithms using criteria defined for <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). The pattern was modified to include stems with at least six pairings containing three G:Cs to compensate for the high AT content of <italic>Listeria</italic> genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Seven IGRs containing a predicted transcription terminator (indicative of a potential transcriptional unit) flanked by two divergent ORFs, were kept for further analysis (Table S1).</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>ORF predictions.</italic> ORFs were predicted within the IGRs using the NEBcutter program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tools.neb.com/NEBcutter2/index.php">http://tools.neb.com/NEBcutter2/index.php</ext-link>), setting the minimum ORF length to 30 residues and searching for a potential ribosome binding site preceding the initiation codon (AUG, GUG, UUG, CUG or AUU). Once the 5&#x02032; ends of ncRNAs were mapped, translatable ORFs were sought on transcribed sequences, with a threshold on their minimal length set to 10 residues.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Identification of riboswitches</italic>. We identified riboswitches and ncRNAs, RnpB, SsrA and SsrS in the selected IGRs using the Rfam database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/Rfam/index.shtml">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/Rfam/index.shtml</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), (Table S1).</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec><title>Predictions of mRNA targets</title><p>ncRNA targets were found by searching the whole genome for strong ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA duplexes. The strengths of the duplexes were quantified by a pairing score <italic>S</italic>, constructed as a sum of both positive contributions due to pairing nucleotides and negative contributions due to bulges and internal loops (Table S2). The contribution of A&#x02013;U, G&#x02013;C and G&#x02013;U pairs was taken as the absolute value of thermodynamic binding energies, considering stacking effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). The score <italic>S</italic> will therefore coincide with the absolute value of the free energy for a perfectly pairing duplex (without bulges and internal loops). As for the cost of bulges and internal loops, we empirically gauged it by maximizing the significance of four known hybrid pairings characterized <italic>in vivo</italic>, RyhB&#x02013;<italic>sodB</italic> mRNA, DsrA&#x02013;<italic>rpoS</italic> mRNA, Spot42&#x02013;<italic>galEK</italic> mRNA in <italic>E. coli</italic> and RNAIII&#x02013;<italic>spa</italic> mRNA in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, (17, 42&#x02013;44) as compared to other genes in the respective genomes. ncRNA targets were sought in 5&#x02032; regions spanning 140 bases upstream of the translation start codon and 90 bases within all the coding regions, and in 3&#x02032; regions spanning 60 bases upstream of the translation stop codon and 90 bases downstream of all the annotated ORFs of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> genome. DNA regions were converted to RNA and their best alignments with ncRNAs searched by standard dynamic programming. Various pairing lengths were considered since our alignment scores do not have zero average over random sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). Statistical significance of the pairings was assessed with respect to an ensemble of random sequences (230&#x02009;nt and 150&#x02009;nt long), generated by a Markov chain model gauged on the pentanucleotide statistics of the aforementioned sequences. The threshold of statistical significance was empirically set to the ratio five between the number of genes with a pairing score &#x02265;<italic>S</italic> and those expected by chance. Predictions for the <italic>trans</italic> targets of the RliE ncRNA were below the threshold, yet they were kept for further analysis due to the functional relationship among the target genes. The computer program to compute the best RNA alignments is available as a supplementary material file (Document S3).</p></sec><sec><title>Strains and plasmids</title><p>All strains used were derivatives of the <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> strain EGD-e (BUG1600 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>)). &#x00394;<italic>hfq</italic> (BUG2213), &#x00394;<italic>prfA</italic> (BUG2214) and &#x00394;<italic>sigB</italic> (BUG2215) mutants were obtained by deletion of the corresponding ORF using the suicide vector pMAD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). Deletions were generated by PCR-ligation and amplicons were cloned at the <italic>SmaI</italic> restriction site of the pMAD vector. Overexpression of RliB and RliI were obtained by cloning the genomic loci into the pAT18 vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) resulting in strains BUG 2348(EGD-e/pAT18-rliB), BUG2349(EGD-e/pAT18-rliI) and BUG2347 (EGD-e/pAT18). Oligonucleotides flanking the corresponding <italic>rli</italic> loci were designed so that &#x0223c;200&#x02009;bp of DNA sequence from the most upstream 5&#x02032; extremity mapped by RACE were included in the construct. Amplicons were introduced at the <italic>SmaI</italic> restriction site of the pAT18. All constructs on the plasmid and on the chromosome were verified by sequencing (Genomexpress). Oligonucleotides used in this study are listed Table S4.</p></sec><sec><title>Bacterial growth</title><p>Bacteria from a single fresh colony on a brain&#x02013;heart infusion (BHI) agar plate, were grown aerobically overnight and a 1/500 dilution of the preculture was made into 60&#x02009;ml of prewarmed liquid BHI at 37&#x000b0;C. Growth was then monitored. Total RNA was extracted as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), from bacteria grown to an OD<sub>600</sub> between 0.4 and 0.55 for the exponential growth phase, and between 1.2 and 1.4 for the stationary growth phase. No significant growth defect was observed for any of the EGD-e derivative strains used. When required, erythromycin was used at 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml as final concentration.</p></sec><sec><title>Northern blots and 5&#x02032; end mapping</title><p>Northern blots were performed as described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>), using oligonucleotides described in Table S4. Briefly, for northern analysis of IGR candidates in low stringency conditions, double-stranded DNA probes were generated by PCR from a colony of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> EGD-e strain. PCR amplification was realized with annealing at 50&#x000b0;C for 30 cycles in 1&#x000d7; PCR buffer (1&#x02009;mM each dCTP, dGTP, and dTTP; 2.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M dATP; 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;Ci [&#x003b1;<sup>32</sup>P]dATP; 1U taq polymerase) (INVITROGEN). Probes were purified over G-50 microspin columns (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) prior to usage. Northern membranes were prehybridized in a 1:1 mixture of Hybrisol I and Hybrisol II (Intergen) at 40&#x000b0;C. DNA probes were heated for 3&#x02009;min at 95&#x000b0;C and directly added to the prehybridization solution; membranes were hybridized overnight at 40&#x000b0;C. Membranes were washed by rinsing twice with 4&#x000d7; SSC/0.1% SDS at room temperature followed by three washes with 2&#x000d7; SSC/0.1% SDS at 40&#x000b0;C. Northern blot analysis in high stringency conditions was realized using an oligonucleotide probe and Ultrahyb solution (AMBION), as described by the manufactured protocol (AMBION). Oligonucleotides were 5&#x02032; labeled with [&#x003b3;<sup>32</sup>P]ATP using the T4 Polynucleotide Kinase as recommended by the manufactured protocol (New England Biolabs). Northern membranes were prehybridized in Ultrahyb at 40&#x000b0;C, followed by addition of labeled oligonucleotide probe and hybridization overnight at 40&#x000b0;C. Membranes were washed twice with 2&#x000d7; &#x02009;SSC/0.1% SDS at room temperature followed by two washes with 0.1&#x000d7; &#x02009;SSC/0.1%SDS for 15&#x02009;min each at 40&#x000b0;C. Northern blots shown in the figures are a representative experiment repeated at least twice for each one of three independent RNA preparations. Signals were quantified by using the NIH Image program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/nih-image/">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/nih-image/</ext-link>).</p><p>The 5&#x02032; RACE method allows discriminating a 5&#x02032; end generated by transcription initiation, from a 5&#x02032; end provided by RNA processing. 5&#x02032; RACE mapping was performed as described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) with slight modifications. Reactions were conducted on RNA extracted in exponential phase. Once the cDNA was amplified by PCR, products were cloned into the pCRIITOPO vector (INVITROGEN). Clones were screened by PCR using oligonucleotides FR.T7 and FR.SP6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Fifteen clones carrying an insert were selected for each cDNA. Sizes of amplicons were compared and three clones of each size were sequenced (Genomexpress).</p></sec><sec><title>Gel shift assays</title><p>RNA gel shift assays were performed as described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Briefly, uniformly <sup>32</sup>P- labeled ncRNA and predicted mRNA target fragments were synthesized <italic>in vitro</italic> using the T7 RNA polymerase and PCR fragments as template (see Table S2). ncRNA fragments synthesized were from the transcription start site (+1) mapped by 5&#x02032; RACE: nt 48 to 113 for RliE; nt 113 to 273 for RliB; nt 55 to 120 for RliI. mRNA targets were from the AUG of corresponding ORFs: <italic>comEA</italic> (nt &#x02212;60 to +6), <italic>comFA</italic> (nt &#x02212;56 to +6) and <italic>lmo0945</italic> (nt &#x02212;44 to +4) for assays with RliE, <italic>lmo1035</italic> (nt +1781 to +1850) for assays with RliI, and <italic>lmo2104</italic> (nt +17 to +177) for assays with RliB. Complex formation assays were performed at 37&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;min. in a buffer containing Tris-HCl 25&#x02009;mM pH 7.5, MgCl<sub>2</sub> 5&#x02009;mM, KCl 50&#x02009;mM in the presence of uniformily labeled ncRNA (&#x0003c;1&#x02009;nM) and increasing concentrations of the cold target mRNA (10&#x02009;nM to 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M). Before mixing, RNAs were renatured separately in the appropriate buffer.</p></sec><sec><title>Supporting information</title><p>Table S1: IGRs selected for northern blots.</p><p>Table S2: Parameters used for target selection.</p><p>Document S3: Computer program for mRNA target predictions.</p><p>Table S4: Oligonucleotides used in this study.</p><p>Document S5: Rli loci in EGD-e.</p><p>Document S6: Predicted folding of Rli ncRNAs by MFOLD.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title><italic>In silico</italic> search for ncRNAs</title><p>ncRNA genes are located in IGRs of the genomes, i.e. sequences present between annotated ORFs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29 B30 B31 B32">29&#x02013;32</xref>), we therefore searched for ncRNAs in the IGRs of the <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> EGD-e genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) aware that this approach excludes detection of ncRNAs located within annotated genes. We first analyzed the IGRs for their conservation across bacterial species by using BLAST alignments. Out of 694 IGRs, 99 were selected based on the following criteria: (i) IGRs carrying a portion of highly conserved sequence (&#x02265;80&#x02009;bp) among <italic>Listeria</italic> species, since the conservation may sign a transcribed region and therefore a putative noncoding gene. (ii) Long IGRs (&#x02265;350&#x02009;bp) entirely conserved among <italic>Listeria</italic> species, flanked by two divergent or two convergent ORFs, since the length of the IGR might increase the chances of finding a non-coding-protein gene. Then we performed predictions for RNA secondary structure and &#x02018;orphan&#x02019; transcription terminators (see description in Materials and Methods). Thus, 36 IGRs were selected. Among these, six IGRs containing potential ORFs that had not been annotated in the EGD-e genome due to their relatively short length were removed from the data set, yielding 30 IGR candidates. These IGRs were screened by using the Rfam database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), enabling us to identify one riboswitch and the three IGRs carrying the predicted three ncRNAs conserved in all bacteria that we kept as controls: RnpB, the ribozyme component of RNaseP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>), SsrA, the RNA rescuing stalled ribosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>), and SsrS, the RNA polymerase modulator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Thus 29 IGRs were kept for further investigation (Table S1).</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of IGR-encoded transcripts</title><p>To detect ncRNAs in the 29 selected IGRs, we performed northern blots on total RNA extracted from <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> EGD-e grown in BHI in exponential and stationary phases, using low stringency hybridization conditions with PCR products corresponding to the entire IGRs as probes. Signals were analyzed by taking into account the length of the transcripts compared to the size of the corresponding IGR, the orientation of the flanking genes and the presence of transcription terminators. The three controls were nicely detected. For four IGRs, transcripts could not be detected. Thirteen IGRs displaying long transcripts that could be part of operons, 5&#x02032;- or 3&#x02032;UTR mRNAs were not kept for further analysis.</p><p>The nine remaining IGRs encoded transcripts that could not be assigned to any of the above categories, indicating that they could carry previously unknown ncRNAs. These transcripts were named Rli for <underline>R</underline>NA in <italic><underline>Li</underline>steria</italic> (from A to I).</p><p>To determine the transcription orientation of the potential ncRNAs, northern blots in high stringency hybridization conditions were performed using oligonucleotide probes chosen on both strands of the IGRs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). A high expression was observed for the predicted ubiquitous ncRNAs, RnpB, SsrA and SsrS. RliB, E, F, G, H and I, showed distinct bands ranging from 110 to 430&#x02009;nt, consistent with the length of the corresponding IGRs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Three candidates, RliA, C and D, could not be detected using oligonucleotide probes but were kept for further analysis, since highly stable RNA stem-loop structures may prevent their detection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Detection of ncRNAs by northern blots. The name of the ncRNA is indicated on top of each panel. Total RNA was extracted from <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> EGD-e strain grown to exponential (E) or stationary (S) phase in BHI at 37&#x000b0;C. Blots were performed with 12&#x02009;&#x000b5;g of total RNA per lane and strand-specific probes, except for RliA, RliC and RliD where PCR products corresponding to the IGRs were used. &#x02018;L&#x02019; indicates the DNA ladder used to estimate length. One lane of DNA molecular weight markers is shown for estimation of RNA size, since DNA and RNA run slightly differently on gel. Numbers on the right side of each panel indicate the estimated lengths of the transcripts in nucleotides. Exposure times were optimized for each panel and signal intensity does not indicate relative abundance between ncRNAs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1096f1"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Expression of ncRNAs</title><p>Northern blots presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> allowed to compare the levels of the Rli transcripts in exponential and stationary growth phases in BHI. Levels of RliF and RliI were higher in stationary than in exponential phase, reminiscent of ncRNA expression in other bacteria, i.e. varying according to environmental conditions and growth phases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>).</p><p>In <italic>E. coli</italic>, Hfq usually affects the stability of ncRNAs that interact with mRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). We compared levels of Rli in a &#x00394;<italic>hfq</italic> mutant and the isogenic wild-type EGD-e strain using northern blots. No variations were observed, indicating that Hfq does not affect the abundance of our ncRNAs under the conditions used (not shown).</p><p>Since PrfA and SigB are two important transcription regulators involved in the virulence of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>monocytogenes</italic>, we also tested the <italic>prfA</italic>- and <italic>sigB</italic>-dependent expression of <italic>rli</italic> genes by northern blots, comparing levels of Rli ncRNAs in &#x00394;<italic>prfA</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>sigB</italic> mutants to the isogenic wild-type strain. No PrfA- or SigB-dependent expression was observed in exponential and stationary growth phases at 37&#x000b0;C in BHI medium (not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>5&#x02032; end mapping</title><p>5&#x02032; ends of Rli ncRNAs were mapped by RACE experiments to discriminate between primary 5&#x02032; ends, i.e. transcriptional start sites, and 5&#x02032; extremities generated by processing. 5&#x02032; ends were mapped for all candidates except RliF. In particular, we identified 5&#x02032; ends for RliA, RliC and RliD, which were not detected earlier by northern blots using oligonucleotide probes, therefore demonstrating their existence. Transcriptional start sites were mapped for <italic>rli</italic>A, B, C, E, G, H and I, enabling us to predict RpoD-dependent promoters for these genes except for <italic>rliE.</italic> Based on the 5&#x02032; ends mapped, transcript length observed on gel and folding predictions (in particular transcription terminators), 3&#x02032; ends could be assigned. Rho-independent transcription terminators could be detected for RliF, G, H and I. In the case of RliA, the observed length on northern blots and the proximity of the downstream ORF (<italic>lmo0477</italic>) with the same orientation (136&#x02009;nt), did not allow us to rule out the possibility that RliA may be derived from the processing of <italic>lmo0477</italic> mRNA. Collectively, these data enabled us to estimate the lengths for all ncRNAs, e.g. RliA (225&#x02009;nt), B (360&#x02009;nt), C (360&#x02009;nt), D (&#x02265;380&#x02009;nt), E (225&#x02009;nt), F (&#x0223c;180&#x02009;nt) G (280&#x02009;nt), H (430&#x02009;nt) and I (240&#x02009;nt), as well as their positions on the EGD-e genome (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, Documents S4 and S5). No translatable ORF with a minimal length of 10 residues could be found on Rli transcripts, indicating that most likely these transcripts do not encode small peptides and constitute <italic>bona fide</italic> noncoding RNAs.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Distribution of the <italic>rli</italic> genes along the <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> genome of EGD-e strain. Nucleotide position, in Megabase (Mb), is indicated. <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic>rli</italic> loci in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>. Red arrows represent the <italic>rli</italic> transcripts and their orientation; black arrows indicate the flanking ORFs. Maps are at scale, based on 5&#x02032; RACE mapping data, sizes estimated on gel and transcription terminator predictions. For RliD and RliF, transcription start sites have not be determined; positions and lengths are estimated. Document S4 provides information on sequences and the genomic location of <italic>rli</italic> genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1096f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Features of <italic>rli</italic> genes</title><p>The nine <italic>rli</italic> sequences were found in the four known <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> genomes (strains EGD-e, F6854, F2365 and H7858) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). We also sought for the presence of <italic>rli</italic> genes in the genome of <italic>L. innocua</italic> (strain CLIP11262), a non-pathogenic species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), and <italic>L. ivanovii</italic> (strain PAM55), an ovine pathogenic species (sequence provided by P. Glaser) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Four classes of <italic>rli</italic> genes could be distinguished according to their conservation across <italic>Listeria</italic> species, their location on the chromosome, and their structural particularities.
<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p><bold>Four rli genes are specific to <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> species</bold>. <italic>rliA</italic>, <italic>rliC</italic>, <italic>rliF</italic> and <italic>rliG</italic> were present in <italic>L</italic>. <italic>monocytogenes</italic> and absent from <italic>L. innocua</italic> and <italic>L. ivanovii</italic>. The absence of <italic>rli</italic> sequences was associated with the absence of surrounding ORFs, except for the <italic>rliF</italic> and <italic>rliG</italic> loci for which upstream genes were present (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Presence of the <italic>rli</italic> loci in <italic>Listeria</italic> species</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkl1096i1.jpg" mimetype="image"/></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The first column provides the ncRNA loci in the <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> EGD-e genome. &#x02018;<bold>&#x0003c;</bold>&#x02019; and &#x02018;<bold>&#x0003e;</bold>&#x02019; indicate the orientation of the genes marked on the left. ncRNA are noted in red. The second and third columns correspond to the genomic position of the most upstream 5&#x02032; end mapped by RACE, and the approximate length estimated on northern blot, respectively. The fourth column indicates the size of the corresponding Rli ncRNA deduced from the 5&#x02032; end mapping, the transcription terminator prediction and the length observed on gel. The last three columns correspond to the <italic>Listeria</italic> species; corresponding isolates are mentioned in parenthesis. &#x02018;<bold>+</bold>&#x02019; and &#x02018;<bold>&#x02212;</bold>&#x02019; indicate the presence or the absence of the genes.</p></fn><fn><p>*<italic>rliB</italic> is conserved and duplicated in <italic>L. ivanovii</italic>. The length and the genomic location of Rli transcripts is provided in Document S4.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>a</sup>5&#x02032; end mapped corresponds to a transcription start site;</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>5&#x02032; end mapped is a processing site; N.D.: not determined;</p></fn><fn><p><sup>c</sup>not mapped and estimated from length observed on gel and transcription terminator prediction;</p></fn><fn><p><sup>d</sup>deduced from sequence conservation available at Rfam web site.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Three <italic>rli</italic> genes encode antisense ncRNAs</bold>. In contrast to the other <italic>rli</italic> genes, <italic>rliD</italic>, <italic>rliE</italic> and <italic>rliH</italic> partially overlap with and are transcribed divergently to the ORFs of their flanking genes <italic>pnpA</italic>, <italic>comC</italic> and <italic>lmo1150</italic>, respectively, indicating that these ncRNAs may act as antisense (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). <italic>pnpA</italic> encodes the polynucleotide phosphorylase (PNPase) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>), <italic>comC</italic> encodes a putative type IV prepilin peptidase analogous to the <italic>comC</italic> gene of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>), and <italic>lmo1150</italic> encodes a putative transcription regulator similar to <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> PocR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>), (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). <italic>rliD</italic>, <italic>E</italic> and <italic>H</italic> are also present in <italic>L. innocua</italic> and <italic>L. ivanovii</italic> species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><italic>rliB</italic> carries five long repeats</bold>. In <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>, RliB displays five repeats of 29&#x02009;nt spaced by 35&#x02013;36&#x02009;nt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). <italic>rliB</italic> is absent in <italic>L. innocua</italic>, but two copies were found in <italic>L. ivanovii</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>): the first one, <italic>rliBiv1</italic>, is flanked by the same ORFs as in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> and is highly homologous to <italic>rliB</italic>; the second, <italic>rliBiv2</italic> is located elsewhere on the chromosome and is flanked by ORFs absent in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>. <italic>rliBiv2</italic> would encode a ncRNA carrying seven repeats of 29&#x02009;nt.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Sequence of <italic>rliB</italic> locus. In red, the <italic>rliB</italic>-transcribed sequence; arrows show the transcription orientations. The five RliB repeats (guuuuaguuacuuauUGugaaauRuaaau) are underlined and numbered with roman numerals. The transcription start site of <italic>rliB</italic> (+1) and a processing site (&#x02193;) mapped are shown. Deduced &#x02013;10 and &#x02013;35 hexamers of a putative RpoD-dependent promoter are boxed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1096f3"/></fig></p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><italic>rliI</italic> gene</bold> is a single transcription unit within the corresponding IGR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) and is conserved in <italic>L. innocua</italic> and <italic>L. ivanovii</italic> species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec><title>Prediction of mRNA targets</title><p>We developed a computational method to identify mRNA targets of ncRNAs, based on thermodynamic pairing energies and experimentally validated ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids (see Materials and Methods). The hybrids used were RyhB&#x02013;<italic>sodB</italic>, DsrA&#x02013;<italic>rpoS</italic> and Spot42&#x02013;<italic>galEK</italic> mRNAs from <italic>E. coli</italic> and RNAIII&#x02013;<italic>spa</italic> mRNA from <italic>S. aureus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42 B43 B44">42&#x02013;44</xref>). Our program scans a bacterial genome searching for mRNAs forming stable duplexes with a given ncRNA. Deviations from random expectations indicate putative mRNA targets. This approach biases our predictions to strong duplexes formed between the ncRNA and its targets. We limited our search to genomic regions spanning 140 bases upstream of the translation start codon and 90 bases within the coding region, and to regions spanning 60 bases upstream of the translation stop codon and 90 bases downstream of all the annotated ORFs in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> genome EGD-e.</p><p>We searched for potential mRNA targets for the nine Rli ncRNAs of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>. Significant predictions were found for RliB, RliE and RliI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). For each of these three ncRNAs several targets were identified, suggesting that these ncRNAs could have pleiotropic effects. Besides the antisense pairing with <italic>comC</italic>, the strongest predicted pairings of RliE were with <italic>comEA-EB-EC</italic>, <italic>comFA-FC</italic> and <italic>lmo0945</italic> mRNAs. These mRNAs encode proteins highly homologous (&#x0003e;40% identity) to factors of the competence machinery in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). Remarkably, the same sequence of RliE (nt 49 to 113) would pair with the 5&#x02032; leader region of the other mRNA targets, including the translation start codon and the Shine&#x02013;Dalgarno (S.D.) sequence of the predicted operons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A).
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Prediction of mRNA targets for RliE, RliB and RliI. On the left: the pairing scores are computed as described in the text. In blue, the corresponding number of genes expected by chance, according to a null Markov model of length five. In red, the number of genes in EGD-e genome having a pairing strength &#x02265;<italic>S</italic>, the value on the abscissas. Arrows indicate transcripts showing strongest pairings with the corresponding Rli sequence. On the right: list and function of genes whose mRNA are predicted targets for the corresponding ncRNA. *Two pairing regions are predicted between RliB and <italic>lmo2104-2105</italic> mRNA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1096f4"/></fig>
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Hybrids between RliE and mRNA targets. (<bold>A</bold>) For each hybrid, the upper part shows the region of RliE (red) that pairs with the mRNA (black). Numbers in parenthesis indicate the first and the last bases of RliE involved in the pairing. The lower part shows the predicted pairings of RliE with the mRNA at the nucleotide level. Boxes indicate translation start codons, and S.D. the Shine&#x02013;Dalgarno sequence is shown. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>In vitro</italic> duplex formation between RliE and predicted mRNA targets indicated at the top of each panel. At the top of each lane, numbers indicate the concentration used (nM) of unlabeled RNA with &#x0003c;1&#x02009;nM of labeled RliE. Unbound radioactive RliE* is indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1096f5"/></fig></p><p>RliI showed the strongest predicted pairing with the 3&#x02032; ends of the first genes of three putative bicistronic transcripts: <italic>lmo2660-2659</italic>, carrying two overlapping ORFs and encoding a transketolase and a ribulose-phosphate epimerase, <italic>lmo1035-1036</italic>, encoding a beta-glucoside transporter subunit of a PTS system and a beta-glucosidase, respectively, and <italic>lmo2124-2123</italic>, encoding components of a maltodextrine ABC transporter system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). The location of the predicted pairing on the mRNAs strongly suggests that RliI regulates polarity. Two distinct regions of RliI would be involved in these pairings, one spanning nt 60 to 125 and pairing with the 3&#x02032; end of <italic>lmo2660</italic> and <italic>lmo1035</italic>, the other from nt 130 to 185 hybridize with the 3&#x02032; end of <italic>lmo2124</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). Remarkably, predicted mRNA targets of RliI have biological functions related to sugar metabolism and transport. In relationship with the function of predicted targets of RliI, it is also important to note that <italic>rliI</italic> is transcribed in the opposite direction to the flanking gene <italic>lmo2761</italic> encoding a &#x003b2;-glucosidase located at the end of a putative operon encoding cellobiose and xylose PTS systems, an other set of genes involved in sugar metabolism and transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Hybrids between RliI and mRNA targets. <bold>(A)</bold> For each hybrid, the upper part shows the region of RliI (red) that pairs with the mRNA (black). On the nucleotidic sequence, the translation start codon of <italic>lmo2659</italic> is indicated by a grey box, the translation stop codon of <italic>lmo2660</italic> by an open box. Data are otherwise presented as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A. (<bold>B</bold>) Duplex formation between RliI and <italic>lmo1035</italic> mRNA. Data are presented as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B. <bold>(C)</bold> northern blots on 15 &#x000b5;g of total RNA extracted from <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> EGD-e (WT), EGD-e harboring the empty vector pAT18 (vector) and pAT18 carrying the <italic>rliI</italic> gene (RliI) grown to exponential (E) or stationary (S) phase in BHI at 37&#x000b0;C. The RNA probed is indicated on the left of each panel. RliI is probed with a specific oligonucleotide, <italic>lmo1035</italic> and <italic>lmo1036</italic> transcripts were probed with PCR fragments. Estimated sizes of the transcripts are indicated on the right side of each panel. As loading control, gels were stained with EtBr before transfer to evaluate 16S rRNA levels (16S RNA).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1096f6"/></fig></p><p>RliB showed the strongest predicted pairing with the putative bicistronic transcripts <italic>lmo1172-1173</italic>, encoding a two component system, <italic>lmo0512-0513</italic> that encodes a protein of unknown function and a putative transcription regulator, and <italic>lmo2104-2105</italic>, encoding the ferrous iron transport proteins FeoA and FeoB, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). The overlapping regions at the end of <italic>lmo1172</italic> and the beginning of <italic>lmo1173</italic>, and the IGR between <italic>lmo0512</italic> and <italic>lmo0513</italic> would be engaged in the pairing with RliB, suggesting that the ncRNA might regulate polarity of these mRNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A). For <italic>lmo2104-2105</italic> mRNA, RliB is predicted to pair with two long regions (&#x0003e;70&#x02009;nt) within the encoding sequence of <italic>lmo2104</italic>, involving 146&#x02009;nt out of the 228&#x02009;nt encoding the short protein FeoA (75 aa), and suggesting a tight regulation of this mRNA by RliB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A).
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Hybrids between RliB and mRNA targets. <bold>(A)</bold> Hybrids between RliB (red) and predicted mRNA targets (black). Data are otherwise presented as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A. (<bold>B</bold>) Duplex formation between RliB and <italic>lmo2104</italic> mRNA. Data are presented as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B. <bold>(C)</bold> northern blots on total RNA was extracted from bacteria grown to exponential phase in BHI at 37&#x000b0;C. Data are presented as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1096f7"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Gel shift assays of predicted mRNAs with ncRNAs</title><p>We then tested <italic>in vitro</italic> the pairing of RliB, E and I with their predicted mRNA targets by RNA gel shift assays using RNA fragments corresponding to the sequences predicted to interact.</p><p>For RliE, <italic>in vitro</italic> duplex formations were assessed using a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled ncRNA fragment and the three unlabeled counterpart <italic>comEA</italic>-, <italic>comFA</italic>- and <italic>lmo0945</italic> RNAs. Remarkably, RliE was found to bind efficiently the three predicted mRNAs with an apparent dissociation constant ranging between 20 to 100 nM, indicating an interaction as stable as those reported for other validated ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). For the three RliE&#x02013;mRNA complexes, a double band was visualized that may correspond to different conformers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B).</p><p>For RliI, among the three predicted mRNA targets, <italic>in vitro</italic> duplex formation was tested for <italic>lmo1035</italic>. A complex was observed between a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled RliI fragment and an unlabeled RNA fragment containing the predicted RliI targeted region of <italic>lmo1035</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). The apparent dissociation constant observed was &#x0223c;100 nM, very similar to those observed for RliE and <italic>com</italic>-like mRNAs.</p><p>Since RliB was predicted to pair with two regions within <italic>lmo2104</italic> mRNA, we tested the duplex formation with a 173-nt long fragment encompassing the two complementary regions of <italic>lmo2104</italic>. A complex was observed between a labeled RliB fragment and the unlabeled RNA fragment containing the two predicted RliB-targeted regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B). This result showed the possibility of the interaction between the two RNAs. However, the formation of the complex between RliB and <italic>lmo2104</italic> was poorly efficient since the apparent dissociation constant was about 10-fold higher (&#x0003e;1&#x02009;&#x003bc;M) than that for RliE&#x02013;<italic>com</italic>-like mRNAs and RliI&#x02013;<italic>lmo1035-1036</italic> mRNA, indicating that the structures of both RNA are not promoting efficient binding.</p><p>In summary, the five predicted mRNA targets tested were able to bind RliE, RliI and RliB <italic>in vitro</italic>, suggesting that <italic>in vivo</italic> the ncRNAs may interact and regulate the expression of their mRNA targets.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vivo</italic> effects of the overexpression of ncRNAs</title><p>Since <italic>in vitro</italic> data suggested that hybrids between RliB, E and I and their predicted mRNA targets can form <italic>in vivo</italic>, we searched for effects of the ncRNAs on their respective targets. Assuming that the action of the ncRNAs could result in changes in the mRNA stability, we analyzed by northern blots levels of the predicted mRNA targets when the ncRNAs were overexpressed. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>C, we were able to overexpress RliI and RliB by cloning the corresponding genomic loci in a multicopy plasmid (pAT18) under the control of their endogenous promoters. The expression of these two ncRNAs and their lengths observed by northern blot agreed with the lengths of RNAs expressed from the chromosome, definitively establishing that <italic>rliB</italic> and <italic>rliI</italic> genes are contained within the genomic fragment cloned into the vector. For unknown reasons, we were unable to overexpress RliE from its own or from an inducible promoter, suggesting a complex transcriptional control of the <italic>rliE</italic> gene.
<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p><bold>RliI</bold>. We first tested the expression of the mRNA targets of RliI in BHI medium at 37&#x000b0;C. northern blots on total RNAs in the wild-type EGD-e strain, showed a single transcript for <italic>lmo1035</italic> and <italic>lmo1036</italic>, migrating around 3.2 kb, indicating a co-transcription of the two genes. An increased level was observed in stationary phase compared to the exponential phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). The presence of the empty vector (pAT18) increased the basal level of the transcript, but preserved the growth-phase-dependent expression. An effect on the level of <italic>lmo1035-1036</italic> mRNA was observed when the vector carrying <italic>rliI</italic> was used. Overexpression of RliI decreased the level of <italic>lmo1035</italic>-<italic>1036</italic> mRNA, in both exponential (1.5-fold) and stationary growth phases (2.5-fold) as compared to levels obtained with the empty vector (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). Thus, this situation is similar to that of many ncRNAs targeting mRNAs that generate ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids that are rapidly degraded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Together, the effect observed when RliI was overexpressed suggested the possible interaction of the ncRNA with <italic>lmo1035-1036</italic> mRNA <italic>in vivo</italic>, in agreement with the duplex formation observed <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). In the growth conditions that we assayed, we could not detect <italic>lmo2124-2123</italic> and <italic>lmo2660-2659</italic> mRNAs by northern blots.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>RliB</bold>. We tested the effect of the overexpression of RliB on its three mRNA targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A). We could not detect any significant effect of the overexpression of RliB on targets <italic>lmo0512-0513</italic> and <italic>lmo1172-1173</italic> mRNAs (data not shown). Two major bands at 2.7 and 2 kb were detected when probing either for <italic>lmo2104</italic> or <italic>lmo2105</italic> transcripts in the EGD-e wild-type strain, indicating that the two genes are co-transcribed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>C). A weaker transcript of 0.8 kb was also observed for <italic>lmo2104.</italic> As observed earlier for RliI, the vector alone (pAT18) led to an increase of the transcript levels compared to the wild-type strain. However, the presence of <italic>rliB</italic> gene on that vector, led to a reproducible further increase of the mRNA levels (about 2-fold for each transcript compared to the vector), suggesting that an interaction of RliB with <italic>lmo2104-2105</italic> mRNA may occur <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>C).</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>New noncoding RNAs in <italic>Listeria</italic></title><p>Here we report the first genomic search for ncRNA in the Gram-positive pathogen <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>. We identified and characterized nine novel ncRNAs (from RliA to RliI), whose size ranges from 110 to 430&#x02009;nt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). <italic>rli</italic> genes appear specific to the <italic>Listeria</italic> genus since no homologs were detected in other sequenced bacterial genomes. Our <italic>rli</italic> genes fall into four classes. One class is represented by <italic>rliA</italic>, <italic>C</italic>, <italic>F</italic> and <italic>G</italic> which are present in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> and absent in L. ivanovii and in the non-pathogenic species <italic>L. innocua</italic>. <italic>rliB</italic> is a representative of a second class; it contains five repeats of 29&#x02009;nt. <italic>rliB</italic> is duplicated in <italic>L. ivanovii</italic>, an ovine pathogen, but is absent from <italic>L. innocua</italic>. It is thus tempting to hypothesize that those two classes of genes, being absent from <italic>L. innocua</italic> species, might encode ncRNAs involved in adaptation to the host during infection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The third class includes antisense ncRNAs (RliD, E and H). The fourth class is represented by RliI which is encoded in the middle of an IGR. These two last classes are present in the three species of <italic>Listeria</italic> genus, suggesting that these ncRNA genes would control more global adaptation processes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Recently, three ncRNAs (LhrA, LhrB and LhrC) in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> have been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). These three ncRNAs did not appear among our ncRNA candidates for the following reasons: LhrA is expressed within an annotated ORF (Lmo2257) and we only analyzed IGRs; LhrB is carried by an IGR entirely conserved between <italic>Listeria species</italic>, and the five copies of LhrC ncRNAs are located in two IGRs that we did eliminate from our candidates since translatable ORFs can be predicted therein.</p></sec><sec><title>mRNA targets</title><p>We developed a computational approach to search for mRNA targets of ncRNAs in bacteria. Our method introduces a major improvement over other alternatives based on complementarities between the mRNA target and the ncRNA via BLAST- or FASTA-based programs (e.g. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>)), since the energetic score employed in our alignments permits scanning of genomes with high AT content, e.g. &#x0003e;60% in <italic>Listeria</italic>.</p><p>Using this approach, we have searched for new mRNA targets of already known ncRNAs in bacteria other than <italic>Listeria</italic>. We discovered new targets for which experimental evidence already existed. For example, DsrA of <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) was predicted to pair, in addition to <italic>rpoS</italic> mRNA, with the translation initiation region of <italic>dcuS</italic> and rbsA mRNAs. <italic>dcuS</italic> encodes the histidine kinase of the DcuS/R two-component system, involved in the control of C4-dicarboxylate usage, and <italic>rbsA</italic> encodes the ATPase subunit of the d-ribose ABC transporter. Assuming that DsrA would decrease the translation or the stability of these mRNAs, our predictions may explain previous observations, i.e. the overexpression of DsrA impairs <italic>E. coli</italic> growth when succinate or ribose are used as carbon source (Repoila, F. and Gottesmann, S. unpublished data). The RNAIII of <italic>S. aureus</italic> was also predicted to form a hybrid with a novel target the <italic>SA1000</italic> mRNA, an interaction that has now been demonstrated experimentally ((<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) and unpublished data).</p><p>LhrA, B and C in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> EGD-e strain have been described as Hfq-binding ncRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), suggesting that they could have mRNA targets. Our computational method did not predict statistically significant mRNA targets for Lhr ncRNAs. This might either be due to a real absence of mRNA targets or to the fact that our prediction method selects ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids with strong pairing energies, but not other weaker interactions such as loop&#x02013;loop contacts (kissing complex), as described for OxyS and <italic>fhlA</italic> mRNA in <italic>E. coli</italic> for instance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>).</p><p>mRNA targets were predicted, in addition to the antisense targets of RliD, RliE and RliH, for three of the nine novel ncRNAs, RliB, RliE, and RliI. Thus, in total we have predicted targets for five of our ncRNAs. No targets were predicted for RliA, C, F and G, indicating either that these ncRNAs may act on proteins rather than on mRNAs, or that interactions between these Rli ncRNAs and mRNA targets cannot be detected by our method. Out of the nine predicted mRNA targets for RliB, E and I, we tested duplex formation for RliB and <italic>lmo2104</italic> mRNA, RliE and <italic>comEA</italic>-, <italic>comFA</italic>- and <italic>lmo0945</italic> mRNAs, and RliI and <italic>lmo1035</italic> mRNA. Our <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments demonstrate pairing between the ncRNAs and each predicted target tested, validating our <italic>in silico</italic> predictions. Unexpectedly, while the &#x025b5;<italic>G</italic> predicted for the complex between RliB and <italic>lmo2104-2105</italic> was rather low (&#x02212;44&#x02009;kcal/mol, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A), the binding <italic>in vitro</italic> was not efficient. These data argue that structural constraints in both RNA partners prevented efficient pairing. It is to be noted that although the predicted hybrids Rli&#x02013;mRNA are relatively long and stable (&#x0003c;&#x02212;38&#x02009;kcal/mol), none of the mRNA targets can be predicted by the previously reported alternative method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5 F6 F7">Figures 5&#x02013;7</xref>). Together these data revealed that our computational method could be of a general use to find mRNA targets of ncRNAs.</p></sec><sec><title>Towards the mode of action and functions of <italic>rli</italic> genes</title><p>Taking into account both our <italic>in vitro</italic> gel shift assays and our <italic>in vivo</italic> data, several modes of action of our Rli ncRNAs can be distinguished.</p><sec><title>RliD and RliH act as antisense RNAs</title><p><italic>rliD</italic> and <italic>rliH</italic> overlap with and are transcribed in the opposite direction to <italic>pnpA</italic> and <italic>lmo1050</italic> genes, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). More than 178&#x02009;nt of RliD are perfectly complementary to the coding sequence of the PNPase, and the first 221&#x02009;nt of RliH extend into the coding sequence of <italic>lmo1050</italic>, a transcription regulator similar to PocR in <italic>S. typhimurium</italic>. Since the 3&#x02032; ends of RliD and RliH also extend into the 5&#x02032; leader regions containing the ribosome-binding site of <italic>pnpA</italic> and <italic>lmo1050</italic> mRNAs, these ncRNAs probably repress translation by sequestring the S.D. sequence. Interestingly as <italic>rliD</italic> in <italic>Listeria</italic>, <italic>sraG</italic> in <italic>E. coli</italic> is transcribed divergently from <italic>pnpA</italic>. <italic>rliD</italic> and <italic>sraG</italic> are not homologous but it is possible that they ensure similar functions on PNPase expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>RliI and RliB act in trans</title><p>For RliB and RliI, we provided <italic>in vitro</italic> data showing the interaction of the ncRNAs and their predicted targets, <italic>lmo2104</italic> and <italic>lmo1035</italic> mRNAs, respectively. <italic>In vivo</italic>, when RliB and RliI were overexpressed, we observed a measurable change (either positive or negative) in the abundance of the corresponding targets, as compared to the empty plasmid vector used as negative control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>C). The empty vector increased the levels of mRNAs, but the effects on the respective targets were opposite when RliB or RliI were overexpressed from the same multicopy vector, highlighting the specific action of the ncRNAs. Although the effects observed <italic>in vivo</italic> for these two ncRNAs on their respective targets cannot be taken as a comprehensive physiological study, the combination of the data obtained <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> definitely support our <italic>in silico</italic> predictions. In addition, effects observed <italic>in vivo</italic> for RliB and RliI are reminiscent of observations reported for other ncRNAs acting on mRNA targets, increasing or decreasing the stability of their counterpart mRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47 B48 B49">47&#x02013;49</xref>).</p><p>Recently, it was demonstrated that mRNA degradation and translation involving ncRNAs in <italic>E. coli</italic> are independent events, suggesting that ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids are not necessarily a substrate for degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>). The levels of <italic>lmo0512-0513</italic> and <italic>lmo1172-1173</italic> mRNAs, two predicted targets for RliB, were not modified by the overexpression of the ncRNA (not shown). This might either be due to the fact that these predicted targets are false positives, or that RliB modulates the translation process without degradation of the mRNAs.</p><p>RliB is remarkable by its five repeats of 29&#x02009;nt, also entirely conserved in the two copies found in <italic>L. ivanovii</italic>, suggesting an important function of both the ncRNA and its repeats. Similar transcripts (CRISPR elements) generated on direct DNA repeats (21&#x02013;47 bp in length), interspaced with unrelated sequences of similar length, have been described in many prokaryotes and archeae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51 B52 B53">51&#x02013;53</xref>). CRISPR elements are flanked by genes coding for proteins involved in DNA and RNA metabolism (Cas proteins), reminiscent of the players involved in the eukaryotic RNA interference phenomenon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>). This observation led the authors to propose that the CRISPR&#x02013;Cas system might constitute a gene arsenal for a mechanism of defense against phages and plasmids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>). Although this point should be further investigated, a PSI&#x02013;BLAST analysis of protein-encoding genes in the vicinity of the <italic>rliB</italic> locus, did not show any particular homology to <italic>cas</italic> genes that have been defined so far (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>).</p><p>In <italic>Enterobacteria</italic>, the CsrB and CsrC ncRNAs carry short repeats, 5&#x02032;-CAGGA(U/A)CG-3&#x02032;, that mimic a S.D. sequence and bind CsrA, an RNA-binding protein regulating genes involved in carbon storage and other functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>). PSI&#x02013;BLAST analysis did not detect any homolog to CsrA protein in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>. Similarly, repeats in RliB could be recognized and bound by a specific protein. We have shown a weak interaction of RliB with <italic>lmo2104-2105</italic> mRNA, reinforcing the possibility of a protein partner involved in the interaction <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B).</p></sec><sec><title>RliE is a pleiotropic antisense ncRNA of com genes</title><p>RliE probably acts as an antisense on <italic>comC</italic> mRNA and pairs with <italic>comEA</italic>, <italic>comFA</italic> and <italic>lmo0945</italic> mRNAs which are expressed from different loci. mRNA targets of RliE encode proteins similar to those of the competence machinery in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). All four mRNA targets of RliE are polycistronic and their 5&#x02032; leaders may be sequestered in hybrids formed with the ncRNA, suggesting a global translation repressor effect of RliE on the entire set of genes (at least seven ORFs) carried by the four polycistronic mRNAs.</p><p>Although the <italic>Listeria</italic> genome carries numerous orthologs required for the early (i.e. <italic>codY</italic>, <italic>abrB</italic>, <italic>degU</italic>, <italic>spoOKA</italic>, <italic>B</italic>, <italic>C</italic>) and late (<italic>comC</italic>, <italic>comEA</italic>, <italic>comFA</italic>, <italic>comGA</italic>, <italic>mecA</italic>, <italic>clpC</italic>, <italic>clpP</italic>) steps of competence in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>), <italic>Listeria</italic> is not known to be competent. Regulatory genes controlling competence in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> are absent in <italic>Listeria</italic>, including <italic>comX</italic> and <italic>comQ</italic>, encoding a key pheromone that turns-on the competence system and the protein required for its proper expression and secretion, respectively. In addition, the two-component system responding to <italic>ComX</italic>, <italic>comA/P</italic>, and <italic>comS</italic>, encoding a small peptide essential for competence are absent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>). Moreover, <italic>comK</italic>, is disrupted by the insertion of the A118 cryptic phage in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> strain EGD-e and <italic>L. innocua</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). The absence of these genes in <italic>Listeria</italic>, in addition to the possible negative effect of RliE on <italic>comC</italic>, probably explains why this bacterium is not competent. However, the absence of a <italic>rliE</italic> homolog in <italic>B. subtilis</italic> indicates that a ncRNA-dependent regulation has evolved in <italic>Listeria</italic>. Whether this regulation is essential for competence control remains to be determined.</p></sec><sec><title>Is Hfq playing a role?</title><p>In <italic>E. coli</italic>, Hfq generally facilitates the pairing of ncRNAs, e.g. DsrA, RhyB, RprA, OxyS, Spot42, with their mRNA targets. It is also observed that levels of ncRNAs interacting with Hfq are usually decreased in a <italic>hfq</italic>-deficient strain as compared to the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). The level of Rli ncRNAs was not affected by the deletion of <italic>hfq</italic> in the EGD-e strain (not shown), even for RliB, E and I which are able to form hybrids with their counterpart mRNAs. This could reflect biological differences between <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>Listeria</italic> in the mode of action of Rli ncRNAs or in the involvement of Hfq. ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids in the two bacteria may have different properties. Hybrids described for RliB, E and I are longer (&#x0003e;40&#x02009;nt) than those involving Hfq found in <italic>E. coli</italic> (&#x0003c;30&#x02009;nt) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). This feature might permit to overcome the requirement of Hfq, as described for long and stable ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids in <italic>E. coli</italic> for plasmidic systems or antisense ncRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). Alternatively, Hfq could be involved in the formation of Rli&#x02013;mRNA duplexes, but the ncRNA would only affect translation of the mRNA, and the ncRNA&#x02013;mRNA hybrids would not be substrate for degradation. Finally, we cannot rule out that a protein different from Hfq may play a similar role in the formation of Rli&#x02013;mRNA hybrids.</p><p>In conclusion, we have identified nine novel ncRNAs in <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> and provided a new computational approach to predict mRNA targets of ncRNAs in bacteria. This tool could be a major improvement in understanding the functions of regulatory ncRNAs. It is not yet known whether any of the <italic>rli</italic> genes modulates <italic>Listeria</italic> virulence and the identification of ncRNAs involved in virulence is now our major challenge.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data is available at NAR online</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkl1096_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="nar_gkl1096_1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="nar_gkl1096_2.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application"
mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed"
xlink:href="nar_gkl1096_nar-01634-g-2006-File002.tar"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank M. Hamon, J. Johansson, G. Lindahl, P. Romby and A. Toledo-Arana for discussions. We are grateful to P. Romby for helpful comments on the manuscript and technical advices. This work was supported by Institut Pasteur (GPH9), ANR-05-MIIM-026-01, E.U. FP6-LSHM-CT-2005-018618. PM was granted by &#x02018;La Fondation pour la Recherche M&#x000e9;dicale&#x02019; and PC is an international research scholar from the Howard Hugues Medical Institute.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Altuvia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wassarman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An abundance of RNA regulators</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem</source><year>2005</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15952886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Repoila</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Majdalani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small non-coding RNAs, co-ordinators of adaptation processes in Escherichia coli: the RpoS paradigm</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wassarman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small RNAs in bacteria: diverse regulators of gene expression in response to environmental changes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12007399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA-mediated control of virulence gene expression in bacterial pathogens</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12823945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenesch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of RNAs in the regulation of virulence-gene expression</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16529986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vazquez-Boland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berche</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez-Bernal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Zorn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreft</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Listeria pathogenesis and molecular virulence determinants</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Rev</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11432815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pizarro-Cerda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subversion of cellular functions by Listeria monocytogenes</article-title><source>J. Pathol</source><year>2006</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16362984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dussurget</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pizarro-Cerda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular determinants of Listeria monocytogenes virulence</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15487949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Renzoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiaruttini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An RNA thermosensor controls expression of virulence genes in Listeria monocytogenes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12230973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Boor</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SigmaB contributes to Listeria monocytogenes invasion by controlling expression of inlA and inlB</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>3215</fpage><lpage>3222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16207905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fsihi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dussurget</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergassola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Milohanic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo-Arana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>VirR, a response regulator critical for Listeria monocytogenes virulence</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16102006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction and characterization of Listeria monocytogenes mutants with in-frame deletions in the response regulator genes identified in the genome sequence</article-title><source>Infect. Immun</source><year>2005</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>3152</fpage><lpage>3159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sogaard-Andersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalslipolitis</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RNA-binding protein Hfq of Listeria monocytogenes: role in stress tolerance and virulence</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>3355</fpage><lpage>3362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15150220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valentin-Hansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Udesen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bacterial Sm-like protein Hfq: a key player in RNA transactions</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1525</fpage><lpage>1533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15009882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebersbach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentin-Hansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sogaard-Andersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallipolitis</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of small Hfq-binding RNAs in Listeria monocytogenes</article-title><source>Rna</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1383</fpage><lpage>1396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16682563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The small RNA regulators of Escherichia coli: roles and mechanisms*</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15487940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huntzinger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Boisset</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saveanu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Geissmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Namane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Etienne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Staphylococcus aureus RNAIII and the endoribonuclease III coordinately regulate spa gene expression</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>824</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15678100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tjaden</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Opdyke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Target prediction for small, noncoding RNAs in bacteria</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2791</fpage><lpage>2802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16717284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Frangeul</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchrieser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusniok</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Amend</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baquero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berche</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of Listeria species</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11679669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How to find small non-coding RNAs in bacteria</article-title><source>Biol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>386</volume><fpage>1219</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16336117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3406</fpage><lpage>3415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>d&#x02019;Aubenton Carafa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thermes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of rho-independent Escherichia coli transcription terminators. A statistical analysis of their RNA stem-loop structures</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>216</volume><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1702475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rfam: annotating non-coding RNAs in complete genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>D121</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological Sequence Analysis, Probabilistic Models of Proteins and Nucleic acids</article-title><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chastanet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Debarbouille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New vector for efficient allelic replacement in naturally nontransformable, low-GC-content, gram-positive bacteria</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>6887</fpage><lpage>6891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trieu-Cuot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Poyart-Salmeron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Courvalin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pair of mobilizable shuttle vectors conferring resistance to spectinomycin for molecular cloning in Escherichia coli and in gram-positive bacteria</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1990</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>4296</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2143017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janabi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective inhibition of cyclooxygenase-2 expression by 15-deoxy-delta(12,14)(12,14)-prostaglandin J(2) in activated human astrocytes, but not in human brain macrophages</article-title><source>J. Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>4747</fpage><lpage>4755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11971025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wassarman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Repoila</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of novel small RNAs using comparative genomics and microarrays</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1637</fpage><lpage>1651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11445539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Argaman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hershberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bejerano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Margalit</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Altuvia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel small RNA-encoding genes in the intergenic regions of Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Curr. Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11448770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Axmann</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kensche</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Herzel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of cyanobacterial non-coding RNAs by comparative genome analysis</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>R73</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16168080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pichon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small RNA genes expressed from Staphylococcus aureus genomic and pathogenicity islands with specific expression among pathogenic strains</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>14249</fpage><lpage>14254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Ribonuclease P Database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>314</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Withey</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A salvage pathway for protein structures: tmRNA and trans-translation</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trotochaud</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wassarman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>6S RNA function enhances long-term cell survival</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>4978</fpage><lpage>4985</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15262935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wassarman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>6S RNA regulates E. coli RNA polymerase activity</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10892648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingreen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassler</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The small RNA chaperone Hfq and multiple small RNAs control quorum sensing in Vibrio harveyi and Vibrio cholerae</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouts</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongodin</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>DeBoy</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolonay</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasko</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Angiuoli</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole genome comparisons of serotype 4b and 1/2a strains of the food-borne pathogen Listeria monocytogenes reveal new insights into the core genome components of this species</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2386</fpage><lpage>2395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15115801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos-Guillen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bralley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bechhofer</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Olmedo-Alvarez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addition of poly(A) and heteropolymeric 3&#x02032; ends in Bacillus subtilis wild-type and polynucleotide phosphorylase-deficient strains</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>4698</fpage><lpage>4706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15995184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA uptake during bacterial transformation</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15083159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobik</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ailion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single regulatory gene integrates control of vitamin B12 synthesis and propanediol degradation</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1992</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>2253</fpage><lpage>2266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1312999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Escorcia</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coupled degradation of a small regulatory RNA and its mRNA targets in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2374</fpage><lpage>2383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12975324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majdalani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sledjeski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DsrA RNA regulates translation of RpoS message by an anti-antisense mechanism, independent of its action as an antisilencer of transcription</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>12462</fpage><lpage>12467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9770508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Franch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Udesen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentin-Hansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spot 42 RNA mediates discoordinate expression of the E. coli galactose operon</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1696</fpage><lpage>1706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12101127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Flardh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antisense RNAs everywhere?</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12047936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Argaman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Altuvia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>fhlA repression by OxyS RNA: kissing complex formation at two sites results in a stable antisense-target RNA complex</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10903857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lease</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Belfort</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A trans-acting RNA as a control switch in Escherichia coli: DsrA modulates function by forming alternative structures</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>9919</fpage><lpage>9924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10954740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opdyke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GadY, a small-RNA regulator of acid response genes in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>6698</fpage><lpage>6705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Opdyke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling mRNA stability and translation with small, noncoding RNAs</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15063850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Aiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational repression is sufficient for gene silencing by bacterial small noncoding RNAs in the absence of mRNA destruction</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>4858</fpage><lpage>4863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16549791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godde</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bickerton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The repetitive DNA elements called CRISPRs and their associated genes: evidence of horizontal transfer among prokaryotes</article-title><source>J. Mol. Evol</source><year>2006</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16612537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haft</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Selengut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongodin</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A guild of 45 CRISPR-associated (Cas) protein families and multiple CRISPR/Cas subtypes exist in prokaryotic genomes</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>e60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16292354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makarova</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Grishin</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabalina</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A putative RNA-interference-based immune system in prokaryotes: computational analysis of the predicted enzymatic machinery, functional analogies with eukaryotic RNAi, and hypothetical mechanisms of action</article-title><source>Biol. Direct</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16545108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majdalani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderpool</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial small RNA regulators</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Biochem. Mol. Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15814430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borezee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Msadek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Durant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Berche</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification in Listeria monocytogenes of MecA, a homologue of the Bacillus subtilis competence regulatory protein</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>5931</fpage><lpage>5934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11004200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamoen</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Venema</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuipers</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling competence in Bacillus subtilis: shared use of regulators</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12576575</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
