<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15452142</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1534123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200403036</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200403036</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Loss of KLP-19 polar ejection force causes misorientation and missegregation of holocentric chromosomes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>Debra J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dunkelbarger</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saxton</surname><given-names>William M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1cddce0N0x3920a60">Department of Biology, Indiana University, Bloomington, IN 47405</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to William M. Saxton, Dept. of Biology, Indiana University, 1001 E 3rd St., Bloomington, IN 47405. Tel.: (812) 855-0294. Fax: (812) 855-6705. email: <email>bsaxton@bio.indiana.edu</email>; or Susan Strome, email: <email>sstrome@bio.indiana.edu</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>166</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Holocentric chromosomes assemble kinetochores along their length instead of at a focused spot. The elongated expanse of an individual holocentric kinetochore and its potential flexibility heighten the risk of stable attachment to microtubules from both poles of the mitotic spindle (merotelic attachment), and hence aberrant segregation of chromosomes. Little is known about the mechanisms that holocentric species have evolved to avoid this type of error. Our studies of the influence of KLP-19, an essential microtubule motor, on the behavior of holocentric <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> chromosomes suggest that it has a major role in combating merotelic attachments. Depletion of KLP-19, which associates with nonkinetochore chromatin, allows aberrant poleward chromosome motion during prometaphase, misalignment of holocentric kinetochores, and multiple anaphase chromosome bridges in all mitotic divisions. Time-lapse movies of GFP-labeled mono- and bipolar spindles demonstrate that KLP-19 generates a force on relatively stiff holocentric chromosomes that pushes them away from poles. We hypothesize that this polar ejection force minimizes merotelic misattachment by maintaining a constant tension on pole&#x02013;kinetochore connections throughout prometaphase, tension that compels sister kinetochores to face directly toward opposite poles.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>chromokinesin; kinetochore; merotelic; congression; kinesin</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>Abbreviations used in this paper: AP, antipoleward; P, poleward.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Equal distribution of genetic material during nuclear division in eukaryotic cells depends on the precise organization of chromosomes in the mitotic spindle before the actual act of chromatid separation and segregation (for reviews see <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Nicklas, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Rieder and Salmon, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">McIntosh et al., 2002</xref>). At the beginning of prometaphase, spindle microtubules interact with chromosomes to initiate congression movements that accomplish that organization. In mitotic animal cells, spindle microtubules emanate in aster-shaped arrays from two microtubule-organizing centers that comprise the poles of the spindle. The minus-ends of microtubules are at or near the poles, whereas dynamic plus-ends extend outward, away from the poles. Plus-ends and microtubule walls can interact with chromosomes to move them toward or away from each pole via polymer-based ratcheting or by the action of plus- and minus-end&#x02013;directed motor proteins. During prometaphase, such radial movements, biased away from the poles, move chromosomes to a plane at the equator known as the metaphase plate. Accompanying this &#x0201c;congression,&#x0201d; duplicated chromosomes become &#x0201c;oriented&#x0201d; such that each chromatid of a back-to-back sister chromatid pair makes stable attachments with the plus-ends of microtubules from just one spindle pole. Those plus-end interactions are mediated by kinetochores, complex protein structures that assemble on centromeric DNA. Proper orientation (amphitelic) ensures that when sister chromatids release one another at the start of anaphase, they are pulled by their kinetochore microtubules in opposite directions, segregating to form two identical nuclei.</p><p>Three forms of misorientation are known to occur. First, a failure of plus-end attachment to one or both kinetochores of a pair prevents the generation of opposing pulling forces, and thus segregation cannot occur. However, the kinetochore-dependent spindle checkpoint, sensing a lack of plus-end occupancy and/or bipolar tension across the kinetochore pair, commonly delays anaphase until the problem is corrected (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Li and Nicklas, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Waters et al., 1998</xref>; for reviews see <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Nicklas, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Rieder and Salmon, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">McIntosh et al., 2002</xref>). Second, sister kinetochores can capture microtubules from the same pole (syntelic orientation), causing them to segregate together. This form of misorientation too is detected by the checkpoint, perhaps because of a lack of bipolar tension across the sister kinetochores. In the third case, merotelic orientation, a single kinetochore captures microtubules from both poles, resulting in a tug-of-war that often leaves the chromosome lagging at the equator during anaphase. Merotelic orientation causes little or no delay in the onset of anaphase, perhaps because the spindle checkpoint cannot distinguish aberrant bipolar tension on a single kinetochore from correct bipolar tension across a back-to-back kinetochore pair. Hence, merotelism is a serious source of chromosome segregation errors (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Cimini et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kline-Smith et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>To gain insight into mechanisms of chromosome movement and their relationship to orientation, we have used various function disruption and light microscopy approaches to study mitosis in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. Among the commonly studied model systems, the chromosomes of <italic>C. elegans</italic> are unique in that they are holocentric and thus have kinetochores that extend along the entire length of each chromatid (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Albertson and Thomson, 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Dernburg, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Moore and Roth, 2001</xref>). Holocentric chromosomes are also found in many less commonly studied organisms (for review see <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Lima-de-Faria, 1949</xref>). As discussed eloquently by <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Nicklas (1997)</xref>, monocentric chromosomes reduce the probability of misorientation by assembling discrete disc-shaped sister kinetochores back-to-back, each in a pit-shaped depression. Chromatin surrounding the depression restricts access by microtubules, favoring contact and stable attachment only with those that approach from the front. After initial random attachment of one kinetochore to a pole, tension on that connection encourages it to face that pole and thus rotates its sister to face the other. This minimizes the likelihood that either kinetochore will make or maintain aberrant microtubule contacts (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Nicklas, 1997</xref>).</p><p>In principle, the elongated kinetochores of holocentric chromosomes should have a high risk of misorientation. They present a large target for microtubule plus ends. Also, twisting or bending of chromatids could allow distant parts of individual kinetochores to face in opposite directions. <italic>C. elegans</italic> appears to have solved the twisting problem by making its chromosomes relatively stiff, via HCP-6&#x02013;dependent condensation before kinetochores interact with microtubules (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Stear and Roth, 2002</xref>). However, the stiffness does not solve the oversized plus-end target. Compounding this problem in <italic>C. elegans</italic> is the fact that the elongated kinetochore actually protrudes from the chromosome surface rather than being recessed (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Albertson and Thomson, 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">O'Toole et al., 2003</xref>). Perhaps the elongated, exposed architecture evolved to speed the capture of microtubules and thus facilitate a fast pace of mitosis. However, the range of angles for microtubule&#x02013;kinetochore attachment should be quite wide, being blocked only from the rear. Even modest rotation of the sister kinetochore axis away from alignment with the pole&#x02013;pole axis would invite merotelic microtubule attachments. Clearly, holocentric chromosomes in general and <italic>C. elegans</italic> chromosomes in particular face kinetochore orientation challenges that are exaggerated relative to monocentric chromosomes, suggesting that holocentrics offer new insights into mechanisms designed to prevent misorientation.</p><p>Here, we report an analysis of <italic>C. elegans</italic> mitotic chromosome behavior centered around KLP-19, whose sequence is related to plus-end microtubule motors of the kinesin-4 family. KLP-19 has a dynamic relationship with the spindle during mitosis. It accumulates around chromosomes in prometaphase and metaphase and becomes concentrated in the spindle interzone during anaphase. Depletion of KLP-19 allows aberrant poleward (P) chromosome motions during prometaphase, misorientation of kinetochores, and dramatic anaphase chromatin bridges. Analysis of chromosome movements in bipolar and monopolar spindles suggests that there are two stages of prometaphase chromosome congression: an early stage during which a polar ejection force immediately pushes chromosomes antipoleward (AP) and toward the equator, and then a second stage in which a KLP-19&#x02013;dependent polar exclusion force competes with kinetochore-driven P forces to hold chromosomes near the metaphase plate. We suggest that the KLP-19 polar ejection force maintains constant tension on pole&#x02013;kinetochore connections to rotate the sister kinetochore axis onto the pole&#x02013;pole axis, minimizing merotelic connections by forcing sister kinetochores to always face directly toward opposite spindle poles.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>KLP-19 sequence and predicted structure</title><p>Polar exclusion force generation has been demonstrated most directly for vertebrate Kid (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Levesque and Compton, 2001</xref>), a member of the kinesin-10 family (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Lawrence et al., 2004</xref>). Similar forces may be produced by some members of the kinesin-4/chromokinesin family (e.g., <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Vernos et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Kwon et al., 2004</xref>; and references therein). A clear Kid homologue has not been identified in <italic>C. elegans</italic>. However, there are two chromokinesin-like genes: <italic>klp-12</italic> (GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z92811">Z92811</ext-link>) and <italic>klp-19</italic> (GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AL021481">AL021481</ext-link>). KLP-19 has an NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal motor domain, whereas KLP-12 has an internal motor domain. Both have conserved neck residues consistent with plus-end&#x02013;directed motion (Fig. S1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>). One recent phylogenetic analysis of kinesin motor domains (&#x0223c;340 amino acids) placed KLP-19 in a divergent chromokinesin clade with Kid (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Lawrence et al., 2002</xref>) and placed KLP-12 with the classic chromokinesins (kinesin-4 family; e.g., mammalian Kif4, <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> Xklp1, and <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> KLP3A). Another analysis grouped both KLP-19 and KLP-12 with the classic chromokinesins and left Kid as an orphan kinesin (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dagenbach and Endow, 2004</xref>). The sequence of the neck region of kinesins (&#x0223c;40 amino acids), which is a key element in force transduction, may provide insights into class-specific relatedness (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Vale and Fletterick, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Vale, 2003</xref>). Within the neck region, KLP-19 has 41% identity with Kif4 and 44% identity with KLP3A; KLP-12 shows 29 and 38% identity with Kif4 and KLP3A, respectively. The KLP-19 and -12 neck regions are less similar to that of Kid (18% identical; Fig. S1). This finding reinforces the idea that KLP-19 is a Kif4-like plus-end motor.</p><p>Studies of various chromokinesins using a variety of approaches have produced a surprising mix of function predictions, including roles in microtubule dynamics, spindle assembly, metaphase chromosome alignment, spindle pole separation, cytokinesis, and nonmitotic neuronal vesicle transport (e.g., <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Theurkauf and Hawley, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Sekine et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Vernos et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Heald, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Antonio et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Funabiki and Murray, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Peretti et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Levesque and Compton, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Goshima and Vale, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Bringmann et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Kwon et al., 2004</xref>). A genome-wide RNAi screen for microtubule motor functions (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Powers et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Segbert et al., 2003</xref>) suggested that KLP-19 was essential whereas KLP-12 was not. Therefore, our analysis of chromosome movement and orientation focused mainly on KLP-19.</p></sec><sec><title>KLP-19 concentrates around chromosomes and in the spindle</title><p>Some kinesins have been shown to interact with chromosomes via DNA-binding motifs in their stalk regions (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Afshar et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Adler, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Tokai et al., 1996</xref>). Others have stalk sequences consistent with DNA binding, but direct binding has not yet been demonstrated (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Vernos and Karsenti, 1995</xref>). Analysis of KLP-19 cDNAs and relevant genomic sequences failed to reveal a recognizable DNA-binding motif. To gain insight into possible chromosome and other associations, KLP-19 distribution was studied with antibodies raised against a nonconserved COOH-terminal peptide. Strong antibody staining was seen primarily in areas with dividing cells; i.e., the gonad and embryos (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). In the gonad, staining was bright in germline nuclei of the distal mitotic zone, dim in early meiotic prophase nuclei, and then bright again in late prophase nucleoplasm. Just before fertilization, KLP-19 concentrated on prophase chromosomes. During metaphase of meiosis I, staining concentrated slightly in the body of the spindle, more around the periphery of chromosomes, and most between homologous chromosomes (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> D). A similar pattern was seen in meiosis II. In embryos, during most of mitotic prophase, KLP-19 concentrated in nucleoplasm (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A). In prometaphase, it concentrated slightly in the body of the spindle and more strongly around the periphery of chromosomes (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, B and C</xref>). In anaphase, it left chromosomes and concentrated in the spindle interzone (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, D and E</xref>). These dynamic patterns predict that KLP-19 functions in meiotic and mitotic spindles and suggest that, despite the lack of a recognizable DNA-binding motif, it can associate with chromosomes during prometaphase congression.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>
<bold>KLP-19 localization in the germline.</bold> (A) Hermaphrodite gonad arm, showing DNA (top) and anti&#x02013;KLP-19 staining (bottom). Germ nuclei undergo mitosis in the distal tip of the gonad, exit mitosis and enter meiosis in the transition zone, and then progress through prophase I in the remainder of the gonad. KLP-19 accumulates in distal and late prophase nuclei. (B) High magnification image of the nucleus of a single immature oocyte, showing KLP-19 in the nucleoplasm. (C) Two oocytes approaching the spermatheca (to the left), where fertilization occurs. KLP-19 became concentrated on chromosomes just before fertilization. (D) Female meiosis I metaphase spindle in a newly fertilized embryo. KLP-19 is concentrated most between homologues. In merged panels, DAPI is blue and anti&#x02013;KLP-19 is green. Bars: (A) 50 &#x003bc;m; (B&#x02013;D) 5 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200403036f1"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>
<bold>KLP-19 localization during mitosis in early embryonic blastomeres.</bold> Embryos isolated from adult worms were fixed and stained with DAPI (DNA, blue), antitubulin (red), and anti&#x02013;KLP-19 (green). (A) Prophase. (B) Prometaphase. (C) Metaphase. (D) Anaphase. (E) Telophase. KLP-19 in the nucleoplasm (A) became concentrated along the edges of chromosomes during prometaphase and metaphase (B and C) and in the spindle interzone during anaphase and telophase (D and E). Bars, 5 &#x003bc;m. (F) A multicellular wild-type embryo. (G) A multicellular <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> embryo. The absence of detectable KLP-19 staining after RNAi affirmed the specificity of the anti&#x02013;KLP-19 antibody and the effectiveness of RNAi. In panels F and G and for whole embryos in other figures, <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos are &#x0223c;50 &#x003bc;m in length.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200403036f2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Chromosome association of KLP-19 is independent of kinetochores</title><p>The concentration of KLP-19 at the edges of condensed chromosomes was similar to that of MCAK (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>), a protein known to associate with the holocentric <italic>C. elegans</italic> kinetochore as well as with spindle poles (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oegema et al., 2001</xref>). To determine if KLP-19 chromosome localization depends on kinetochores, the effects of kinetochore disruption were studied. The <italic>hcp-3</italic> gene encodes <italic>C. elegans</italic> CENP-A, a histone H3-like protein required for recruiting <italic>C. elegans</italic> kinetochore proteins (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oegema et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Desai et al., 2003</xref>). Depletion of HCP-3 by RNAi causes a &#x0201c;kinetochore null&#x0201d; phenotype: mitotic chromosomes appear normal during prophase, but in prometaphase they form two or occasionally more spherical clusters near the spindle equator and do not segregate during anaphase (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oegema et al., 2001</xref>). In <italic>hcp-3(RNAi)</italic> embryos, MCAK is present at poles but is absent from chromosomes (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> C; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oegema et al., 2001</xref>). In contrast, KLP-19 remained concentrated around individual chromosomes (not depicted) and the spherical chromosome clusters (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> D) as well as between chromosomes and poles. These results indicate that KLP-19 spindle localization is independent of kinetochores and suggest that its association with chromosomes is via nonkinetochore chromatin.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>
<bold>KLP-19 relationship to <italic>C. elegans</italic> kinetochores.</bold> (A) In a metaphase blastomere, MCAK, a kinetochore protein, and KLP-19 are seen concentrated on the P edges of chromosomes. (B) In an anaphase blastomere, MCAK remained on chromosomes, whereas KLP-19 concentrated in the spindle interzone. Bar, 5 &#x003bc;m. (C) After disruption of kinetochores by RNAi depletion of HCP-3 (CENP-A), association of MCAK with chromosomes was not detected. (D) KLP-19 localization around chromosomes was not prevented by HCP-3 depletion. Color panels show merged images with colors as indicated by labeling.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200403036f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>KLP-19 is required for proper mitotic chromosome behavior</title><p>To study the effects of a loss of KLP-19 function, both genetic and RNAi approaches were used. A recessive lethal mutation, <italic>klp-19</italic>(<italic>bn126)</italic>, was identified in a PCR-deletion screen. The mutation is an in-frame deletion beginning in &#x003b1;-helix 4 of the motor domain and ending near the carboxyl limit of the neck region (Fig. S1). Homozygous mutant <italic>klp-19</italic> progeny from heterozygous hermaphrodite parents arrested as L1 larvae, verifying that KLP-19 is essential and suggesting that inherited maternal gene products are sufficient for embryogenesis.</p><p>To test for function in embryos, we used gene-specific RNAi to deplete KLP-19 from wild-type hermaphrodite germlines. Embryos from <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> worms lacked detectable KLP-19 immunofluorescence (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> G), indicating that the RNAi approach was effective. RNAi embryos underwent early mitotic divisions but later displayed aberrant patterns of nuclei and arrested before morphogenesis. To test for defects in spindle architecture like those caused by inhibition of KLP3A and Xklp1 (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Vernos et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Kwon et al., 2004</xref>), microtubule patterns were studied with antitubulin immunofluorescence in fixed embryos (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A) or with GFP::&#x003b2;-tubulin fluorescence in live embryos (not depicted). The bipolar organization of spindle microtubules and their dynamic progression through mitosis appeared normal. Spindle pole separation in anaphase was normal, and no failures in cytokinesis or aberrant cleavage patterns were observed.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>
<bold>KLP-19 depletion causes chromosome segregation defects.</bold> (A) Antitubulin staining of fixed wild-type (N2) and <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> one-cell embryos. Depletion of KLP-19 did not noticeably alter mitotic spindle structure. (B) A Nomarski DIC image of a live <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> four-cell embryo. Micronuclei (arrows) are visible in two cells. (C and D) Time-lapse confocal images of chromosomes in live one-cell embryos expressing GFP::histone. (C) A wild-type (N2) embryo in metaphase (top) and then in anaphase (bottom; see Video 1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>). (D) A <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> embryo showing a disordered metaphase plate (top) and then lagging anaphase chromatin (bottom; see Video 2). Bar, 5 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200403036f4"/></fig><p>The formation of micronuclei in some <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> embryos (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B) suggested defects in chromosome segregation. To investigate mitotic chromosome behavior directly, embryos expressing a GFP::histone fusion protein were imaged by time-lapse confocal microscopy (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, C and D</xref>; see Videos 1 and 2, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>). In prophase, during condensation, chromosomes often appeared bent. However, after prophase, bending was slight and rarely seen, consistent with the findings of <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Stear and Roth (2002)</xref>, which suggested that proper condensation limits chromosome flexibility. Stiff rod-like behavior was observed for chromosomes in <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> as well as wild-type embryos. In every <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> mitosis observed, chromosomes formed a slightly disordered metaphase plate, and then multiple chromosomes lagged, forming bridges during anaphase. The chromosome bridges stretched, often appeared to break, and sometimes formed micronuclei. These anaphase defects are similar to those reported for vertebrate cells that enter anaphase with individual kinetochores pulled in two directions because of merotelic misorientation (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Cimini et al., 2003</xref>).</p><p>To address the question of kinetochore orientation, fixed embryos were stained with anti-MCAK and observed by deconvolution microscopy (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). In wild-type anaphase spindles, holocentric kinetochores were on the P sides of the chromosomes, aligned perpendicular to the spindle axis. In <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> anaphase, kinetochores were not well aligned and some were stretched across the interzone, parallel to the pole&#x02013;pole axis, suggesting that single chromatids were subjected to opposing anaphase forces. This finding is consistent with merotelic kinetochore misattachment.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Kinetochore misorientation with lagging chromatin.</bold> (A) Wild-type (N2) and B) <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> multicellular embryos were fixed and stained with anti-MCAK, which binds kinetochores and spindle poles, and with DAPI for DNA. Single optical sections generated by deconvolution microscopy of anaphase blastomeres are shown. The arrow in B indicates a kinetochore that lies along lagging chromatin that was stretched between two recently separated groups of anaphase chromosomes. Other kinetochores in B are also misoriented. Colors in the merge panels reflect the colors of the labels. Bar, 5 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200403036f5"/></fig><p>We considered several alternative explanations for disordered metaphase plates and anaphase bridges. Chromatids might fail to disjoin properly because of aberrant chromosome condensation, as seen in studies of SMC-1, a <italic>C. elegans</italic> condensin (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hagstrom et al., 2002</xref>), and of HCP-6 (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Stear and Roth, 2002</xref>). SMC-1 depletion allows normal homologous chromosome segregation in meiosis I and causes defects in sister chromatid segregation in meiosis II. KLP-19 depletion causes anaphase bridges in both meiosis I and II. SMC-1 and HCP-6 depletion both cause a striking impairment of chromosome condensation during prophase. KLP-19 depletion does not noticeably alter chromatin condensation during prophase nor chromosome flexibility during the rest of mitosis (compare Videos 1 and 2).</p><p>We also considered and tested the possibility that chromosome bridges in embryos were due to earlier chromatin damage from missegregation in the germline during the RNAi treatment. In <italic>mei-1</italic> mutant embryos, female meiosis fails, occasionally resulting in the complete absence of an oocyte-derived pronucleus and a subsequent haploid mitosis involving solely the paternal chromosomes (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Mains et al., 1990</xref>). By subjecting <italic>mei-1</italic> hermaphrodites to <italic>klp-19</italic> RNAi after sperm formation was complete, we were able to study the mitotic behavior of &#x0201c;naive&#x0201d; paternal chromosomes in KLP-19&#x02013;depleted embryos. In three embryos that excluded all oocyte-derived chromatin, the male pronucleus entered mitosis, produced disordered metaphase plates, and then showed lagging/stretched chromosomes in anaphase (Video 3, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>). This result confirms that KLP-19 is needed directly in the embryo to prevent chromosome misorientation and anaphase bridges.</p><p>Work with cultured mammalian cells has shown that bridging can be caused by premature entry into anaphase, before random merotelic attachments are corrected (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Cimini et al., 2003</xref>). To determine if this was the basis of <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> chromatin bridges, the start of anaphase was timed relative to the first clear prometaphase chromosome movement (Table S1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>). In wild-type embryos, the prometaphase&#x02013;anaphase period was remarkably short (P<sub>0</sub> = 189 &#x000b1; 16 s, P<sub>1</sub> = 148 &#x000b1; 18 s). KLP-19 depletion caused no significant change (P<sub>0</sub> = 228 &#x000b1; 36 s, P<sub>1</sub> = 142 &#x000b1; 11 s), indicating that precocious anaphase was not the cause of merotelism and chromosome bridging.</p></sec><sec><title>KLP-19 resists P forces on prometaphase chromosomes</title><p>To gain insight into how KLP-19 influences chromosome behavior, chromosome movement relative to spindle poles was analyzed in embryos expressing GFP::histone and GFP::&#x003b3;-tubulin (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> and Video 4, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>). In wild-type embryos, the end of prophase and start of prometaphase was marked by immediate movement of chromosomes AP and toward the equator (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A, 0&#x02013;81 s). This initial polar ejection, or &#x0201c;early congression,&#x0201d; which lasted an average of 30 s, often moved chromosomes to the periphery of the equator where they briefly formed a loose ring. This is consistent with AP polar ejection forces radiating outward from each pole. When opposing AP forces from two poles combine on a chromosome that is off the direct spindle axis, a resultant force vector will be directed away from the axis and toward the periphery (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Ostergren et al., 1960</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Rieder et al., 1986</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>
<bold>KLP-19 influences prometaphase congression and anaphase segregation of chromosomes.</bold> Images are single confocal optical sections from time-lapse movies of GFP::&#x003b3;-tubulin (spindle poles, long arrow) and GFP::histone (chromosomes, short arrow) in the first mitotic divisions of (A) wild-type (N2) and (B) KLP-19&#x02013;depleted embryos. Numbers represent seconds before or after the end of prophase (0), selected as the last frame before directed movement of at least one chromosome was observed. Early AP chromosome movements toward the equator were not substantially affected by KLP-19 depletion (A and B, 0&#x02013;81 s). In wild type, short P and AP movements completed congression (A, 81&#x02013;225 s). In contrast, the first P movements in KLP-19&#x02013;depleted spindles were usually substantial, scattering chromosomes widely between the poles (B, 81&#x02013;123 s). However, subsequent bidirectional oscillations accomplished congression to a disordered metaphase plate, and then anaphase resulted in multiple lagging strands of chromatin (B, 276&#x02013;387 s). See Videos 4 and 5, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>. Bar, 5 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200403036f6"/></fig><p>The first evidence of P force generation was either a short, fast chromosome movement directly toward one centrosome, which suggested microtubule attachment and P force generation by one kinetochore (mono-orientation), or slower movement of chromosomes from the periphery of the equator toward the spindle axis, which suggested microtubule attachment and opposing P force generation by both kinetochores (bi-orientation). Chromosomes remained fairly close to the equator, and short-range oscillations completed congression to a thin, well-defined metaphase plate (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A, 225 s). Segregation was accomplished by anaphase B pole separation with no sign of chromosome-to-pole movement, confirming a previous report that anaphase A does not occur in <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oegema et al., 2001</xref>).</p><p>After <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> by feeding, chromosomes in most embryos showed normal early AP movement (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> B, 0&#x02013;81 s; and Video 5, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>), although it occasionally appeared less robust. After that early congression, multiple chromosomes scattered dramatically back toward the poles (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> B, 123 s), while a few remained near the equator and displayed normal, short-range bipolar oscillations. Shortly after scattering, the displaced chromosomes engaged in bipolar oscillations, recongressed to a loose metaphase plate, and engaged in anaphase B with normal timing (Table S1). The P scattering suggests that KLP-19 creates an AP force that resists the P movement of chromosomes that first attach to microtubules from just one pole. The post-scattering recongression may reflect attachment to microtubules from the second pole, followed by kinetochore-driven P movements in both directions. The recongression, although imperfect, suggests that chromosomes can find the equator with little input from the putative KLP-19 polar ejection force.</p></sec><sec><title>Early AP movement requires microtubules but only minor chromokinesin contributions</title><p>The minimal effects of <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> by feeding on early AP chromosome movement raised questions about the mechanism of early AP force generation. To test the assumption that microtubules are involved, partially flattened wild-type P<sub>0</sub> embryos were treated with 20 &#x003bc;g/ml nocodazole (Encalada, S., and B. Bowerman, personal communication; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Strome and Wood, 1983</xref>) and imaged by time-lapse microscopy. At that concentration, prophase chromosome condensation and centrosome separation appeared normal and centrosomes maintained their separation after nuclear envelope breakdown (Video 6, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>). Chromosomes did show small oscillations and a gradual drift toward the equator, but early AP congression and subsequent active movements were not evident. This confirms that microtubules are critical for early congression as well as the rest of mitosis.</p><p>To determine if kinetochores contribute force for the early movement, kinetochore assembly was disrupted by RNAi depletion of HCP-3. Chromosomes showed normal early AP motion, congressing into two or more clusters, usually near the periphery of the equator. However, subsequent chromosome movements were rare (Video 7, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>), and chromosomes were left at the equator during anaphase, as expected for kinetochore disruption (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oegema et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Desai et al., 2003</xref>). This result indicates that, although kinetochores are critical for P oscillation movements later in prometaphase, they are not needed for early AP chromosome movement.</p><p>To determine if KLP-12, the other chromokinesin, might contribute to early chromosome congression, either alone or redundantly with KLP-19, we studied the effects of single and double RNAi. To maximize depletion, RNAi was done by injecting young hermaphrodites with high-concentration double-strand RNA. Effects on early AP congression were quantified by measuring chromosome-to-pole distances in half-spindles at 24 s after nuclear envelope breakdown (wild type = 5.96 &#x000b1; 0.18 &#x003bc;m, <italic>n</italic> = 48). Injection of <italic>klp-12</italic> dsRNA alone did not have a significant effect on the early congression (5.64 &#x000b1; 0.24 &#x003bc;m, <italic>n</italic> = 29) or on subsequent chromosome behavior. Injecting <italic>klp-12</italic> and <italic>klp-19</italic> RNA together (1/2 concentration of each) generated phenotypes similar to those seen with <italic>klp-19</italic> RNAi by feeding, but had no significant effect on early congression (5.61 &#x000b1; 0.23 &#x003bc;m, <italic>n</italic> = 26). Injection of <italic>klp-19</italic> dsRNA alone (full concentration) caused a small reduction in early chromosome-to-pole distance (5.28 &#x000b1; 0.16 &#x003bc;m, <italic>n</italic> = 59) that was significant (wild-type vs. <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic>, P = 0.011). In summary, our results suggest that microtubules are critical, that kinetochores and KLP-12 are not required, and that KLP-19 serves a minor role in early AP chromosome motion, perhaps redundant with forces generated by microtubule polymerization-based ratcheting.</p></sec><sec><title>Chromosome movement in monopolar spindles</title><p>In bipolar spindles, a rigorous determination of whether a given chromosome movement is driven by AP or P forces is confounded by the presence of two poles; movements that are AP relative to one pole are P relative to the other. Interpretations that predict AP force production by chromokinesins have usually relied on observation of defective metaphase chromosome positioning in bipolar spindles after inhibition of motor function. However, similar positioning/congression defects can be caused by inhibition of a variety of proteins that are not microtubule motors, including EAST (a &#x0201c;nucleoskeletal&#x0201d; component), Nup358 (a nuclear pore component), and centromeric MCAK (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Salina et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Wasser and Chia, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kline-Smith et al., 2004</xref>). This uncertainty, in light of the diverse functions reported for Kif4-like chromokinesins, highlighted the need for a more critical test of whether or not KLP-19 produces AP forces in our system.</p><p>To distinguish AP versus P forces, we studied chromosome movements in embryos with monopolar spindles, a strategy based on tests of Kid function in cultured human cells by <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Levesque and Compton (2001)</xref>. Embryos from <italic>zyg-1</italic> mutant hermaphrodites are defective in centrosome duplication (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">O'Connell et al., 2001</xref>). We used a conditional allele of <italic>zyg-1</italic> and a temperature-shift regime that produced a bipolar spindle in P<sub>0</sub> and a monopolar spindle in P<sub>1</sub>, AB, and later blastomeres. Using time-lapse microscopy of <italic>zyg-1</italic> mutant embryos containing GFP::&#x003b3;-tubulin and GFP::histone, we determined that chromosome behavior and anaphase timing in P<sub>0</sub> were similar to wild type (compare Videos 4 and 8, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>; Table S1). In P<sub>1</sub> and AB, chromosomes congressed to a normal-appearing metaphase plate on one side of the single spindle pole and then failed in anaphase segregation (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A and Videos 8 and 9, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>). The pole&#x02013;chromosome axis in AB was parallel to the plane of view and remained relatively stationary. In P<sub>1</sub>, the spindle axis often shifted and rotated unpredictably, so most monopolar observations were focused on AB. At the prophase&#x02013;prometaphase transition, early AP motion cleared chromosomes away from the single pole, pushing them into the distal half of the remnant nucleus (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A, 0&#x02013;70 s). Subsequently, chromosomes oscillated toward and away from the single pole for an extended period, eventually producing a metaphase plate with a mean pole&#x02013;chromosome distance of 6.66 &#x000b1; 0.43 &#x003bc;m (Table S1). The start of anaphase, which could be recognized by a small split in the metaphase plate, was delayed approximately twofold (Table S1). The delay may reflect prolonged activation of the spindle checkpoint by distal kinetochores that lack microtubules and tension (for reviews see <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Nicklas, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Rieder and Salmon, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">McIntosh et al., 2002</xref>). No substantial P or AP movement of anaphase chromosomes was observed after the split. The lack of P migration by the proximal chromosomes is consistent with a lack of anaphase A in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, as noted above for bipolar spindles.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>
<bold>KLP-19 generates polar exclusion forces in monopolar spindles.</bold> Single optical sections of monopolar AB spindles in <italic>zyg-1</italic> mutant embryos containing GFP::&#x003b3;-tubulin (centrosomes) and GFP::histone (chromosomes). Spindles in a control <italic>zyg-1</italic> embryo (A) and a <italic>zyg-1</italic> embryo depleted of KLP-19 (B) are shown from prophase to metaphase with times after the end of prophase in seconds. In both spindles, chromosomes initially moved AP (0&#x02013;70 s). In the control, subsequent oscillations toward and away from the pole (70&#x02013;290 s) drove congression to a well-ordered metaphase plate. In the KLP-19&#x02013;depleted spindle, after the initial AP movement, chromosomes moved back toward the pole (180 s) and failed to form an ordered metaphase plate (290 s). See Videos 8 and 9, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>. Bar, 5 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200403036f7"/></fig><p>To determine if KLP-19 generates AP forces on chromosomes, <italic>zyg-1</italic> hermaphrodites were subjected to <italic>klp-19(RNAi)</italic> by feeding. The formation of extensive anaphase chromatin bridges in P<sub>0</sub> (bipolar) confirmed that depletion had been effective in each embryo studied (Video 8). In the next mitotic cycle, early AP forces cleared chromosomes away from the single pole (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> B, 0&#x02013;70 s; and Videos 8 and 9), but then chromosomes immediately moved back P to form a disordered group spaced 4.17 &#x000b1; 0.65 &#x003bc;m from the pole (Table S1). They remained there, and additional movements were insubstantial. These results confirm that KLP-19 produces an AP force on chromosomes, which is needed to resist P forces that are produced by kinetochores following the early AP congression movement. The fact that chromosomes did not move all the way to the pole may be due to steric hindrance by a high density of microtubules near the centrosome (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Rieder and Salmon, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">O'Toole et al., 2003</xref>) or it may reflect a down-regulation of P force production as kinetochores approach the pole.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Microtubule-based movements of chromosomes have been studied intensively for many years, and complete sets of microtubule motors have been identified in several organisms through genome sequencing. Nevertheless, our understanding of how individual motors contribute to spindle function remains sparse, particularly for higher eukaryotes. We have focused here on the contributions of <italic>C. elegans</italic> KLP-19 to the movement and orientation of holocentric prometaphase chromosomes. Depletion of KLP-19 from wild-type embryos leads to abnormal congression movements, slightly disordered metaphase plates, and anaphase segregation defects, evident as chromatin bridges. The bridges and the appearance of holocentric kinetochores aligned parallel to the spindle axis, rather than perpendicular, are consistent with merotelic attachment. Analysis of chromosome movements in bipolar and monopolar spindles suggests two periods of AP force generation: a brief early period that has a strong dependence on microtubules and a minor dependence on KLP-19, and then a second period persisting until anaphase that has a major dependence on KLP-19. We suggest below that the AP polar ejection forces provided by KLP-19 combat merotelic chromatid attachments by compelling sister kinetochores to face opposite poles.</p><p>Given that chromosome movement is dependent on microtubules, AP pushing forces might be generated by tubulin polymerization at microtubule ends, by plus-end motors walking along microtubule walls, or by a combination of the two (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Rieder and Salmon, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">McIntosh et al., 2002</xref>). Clear support for the idea that a plus-end motor can contribute to AP forces on chromosomes, poetically termed &#x0201c;polar winds&#x0201d; (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Carpenter, 1991</xref>), has been provided by studies of monocentric chromosomes in human cultured cells by <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Levesque and Compton (2001)</xref>: Kid pushes chromosome arms away from the pole in monopolar spindles. However, inhibition of Kid in bipolar spindles had surprisingly mild effects. Although chromosome arms did not align at the equator, kinetochores did, showing that polar ejection force is not necessary for their congression. Furthermore, anaphase chromosome segregation appeared normal, suggesting that kinetochore orientation was normal (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Antonio et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Funabiki and Murray, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Levesque and Compton, 2001</xref>). Those observations and the lack of compelling evidence that polar ejection force is essential has left the biological purpose of polar winds uncertain (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Carpenter, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Marshall, 2002</xref>).</p><p>Our studies of <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos indicate that KLP-19 generates Kid-like AP force on chromosomes, in this case with an essential purpose in combating merotelic misorientation of kinetochores. This role for polar ejection force may be highlighted in <italic>C. elegans</italic> because each holocentric, exposed kinetochore can interact with microtubules from wide angles (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Albertson and Thomson, 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">O'Toole et al., 2003</xref>). In contrast, microtubule access to a vertebrate monocentric kinetochore is thought to be restricted to a more face-on, narrow range of angles because it is shielded by surrounding nonkinetochore chromatin (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Nicklas, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Rieder and Salmon, 1998</xref>). The elongated, exposed kinetochore of a <italic>C. elegans</italic> chromatid may facilitate fast mitosis by efficient capture of microtubules, but the trade-off is a high probability of merotelic attachment to microtubules from both poles. One way the spindle could minimize such misattachments is to maintain a constant AP force on nonkinetochore chromatin (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). Then, as soon as one kinetochore captures microtubules from a pole, regardless of whether or not the kinetochore is in an active P force&#x02013;generating state, tension on the connection would compel that kinetochore to face directly toward that pole and its sister to face the opposite pole. Exposure of individual kinetochores to both poles would be minimized, and any merotelic misattachment of a microtubule would be strained by a bend that might make it unstable (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Nicklas, 1997</xref>). Thus, rather than polar wind blowing on a chromosome as on a sailboat (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Ostergren et al., 1960</xref>), with the purpose of pushing it toward the spindle equator (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Rieder et al., 1986</xref>), a better analogy for chromokinesins like KLP-19 might be that of polar wind blowing on a chromosome as on a kite, with the purpose of proper orientation. By keeping constant tension on the string, wind forces a kite to face directly toward the hand of the flyer.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>
<bold>A model for the roles of prometaphase polar exclusion forces in <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos.</bold> Only half-spindles are shown, for simplicity. (A) At the beginning of prometaphase, kinetochores are inactive (shaded gray) and a polar exclusion force that requires microtubules, pushes chromosomes AP. That early force may be generated primarily by microtubule plus-end pushing with some help from KLP-19. (B and C) Kinetochores become active, capture microtubules, and alternate between active P force generation (short black arrows) and a neutral state. KLP-19 on chromosomes generates AP force on nonkinetochore chromatin that creates tension on the microtubule&#x02013; kinetochore connection. The constant tension forces the attached kinetochore to face directly toward its pole, even when the kinetochore is not generating P forces (noted by the absence of black arrows in C). This minimizes the probability that microtubules from opposite poles will attach to the same kinetochore. A KLP-19&#x02013;generated torque could also increase the probability that incorrect microtubule&#x02013;kinetochore attachments are bent and thus unstable. The centrosome diameter and the pole&#x02013;chromosome distances in B and C were derived from measurements of GFP-tagged centrosomes and chromosomes in bipolar spindles. The sizes and geometry for chromosomes and kinetochores were derived from the electron micrographs of <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Albertson and Thomson (1982)</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200403036f8"/></fig><p>This orientation role may also be important for polar ejection force in spindles with monocentric chromosomes. In <italic>Drosophila</italic> mitosis, which is monocentric, the chromokinesin KLP3A is known to contribute to pole&#x02013;pole separation, organization of the anaphase spindle interzone, and cytokinesis (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Kwon et al., 2004</xref>). However, it has also been noted that inhibition of KLP3A can cause congression defects and lagging anaphase chromosomes (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Goshima and Vale, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Kwon et al., 2004</xref>). This finding is consistent with a KLP-19&#x02013;like role for KLP3A in producing AP forces that help prevent merotelic kinetochore attachment of monocentric chromosomes. As discussed above, lagging chromosomes and other anaphase defects have not been noted in reports of the effects of Kid inhibition in a cultured human cell line (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Levesque and Compton, 2001</xref>). However, the duration of prometaphase&#x02013;metaphase in those cells is &#x0223c;30 min, compared with 2&#x02013;3 min for the early mitotic divisions of <italic>Drosophila</italic> and <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Table S1; <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Sharp et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Levesque and Compton, 2001</xref>). The less exposed monocentric kinetochores of human chromatids should make them less prone to initial merotelic attachment, and the leisurely prometaphase could allow intermittent bipolar tension generated solely by kinetochores to bend, and so correct aberrant microtubule connections. Thus, inhibition of a polar ejection force in slow, monocentric spindles might cause only a low incidence of merotelism-associated aneuploidy. Although not noticeable in cultured cells, a small increase in aneuploidy would place whole organisms at a selective disadvantage, which could explain the evolutionary retention of polar ejection force generation mechanisms by species that have monocentric, slow mitotic divisions.</p><p>The study of mitosis in early <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos promises continued insights. A unique combination of features, including holocentric chromosomes, a fast mitotic cycle, lack of anaphase A, and the importance of cleavage plane orientation, places special demands on the mitotic machinery and offers exciting opportunities to study the mechanisms that have evolved to meet those demands. The availability of expressed fluorescent markers for chromosomes, spindle poles, and microtubules (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Oegema et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Strome et al., 2001</xref>); continued improvements in the speed and resolution of live cell imaging; and the ability to inhibit the functions of most proteins through mutation or RNAi (e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://celeganskoconsortium.omrf.org/">http://celeganskoconsortium.omrf.org/</ext-link>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kamath and Ahringer, 2003</xref>) provide powerful tools to address questions about the mechanisms that ensure accurate chromosome segregation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Worm strains</title><p>
<italic>C. elegans</italic> N2 variety Bristol was used for RNAi analysis except where noted. GFP strains used were WH204 <italic>pie-1</italic>::<italic>GFP::tbb-2</italic> (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Strome et al., 2001</xref>); AZ212 <italic>pie-1</italic>::<italic>GFP::histone H2B</italic> (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Praitis et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Strome et al., 2001</xref>); and TH32 <italic>pie-1::GFP::histone H2B; pie-1::GFP::tbg-1</italic> (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Desai et al., 2003</xref>). Strain HR75 <italic>mei-1(b284)unc-29(e1072)/mei-1(cf46)unc-13(e1091)</italic> I was crossed to AZ212 to create a <italic>mei-1</italic> strain expressing GFP::histone. Strain OC0010 <italic>zyg-1(b1)</italic> II (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">O'Connell et al., 2001</xref>) was crossed to stain TH32 to create the <italic>zyg-1</italic> strain expressing GFP::histone and GFP::&#x003b3;-tubulin. To generate embryos with bipolar P<sub>0</sub> spindles and monopolar spindles thereafter, <italic>zyg-1</italic> larvae were grown to L3 stage at 16&#x000b0;C and then transferred to 25&#x000b0;C and grown to adulthood.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of the <italic>klp-19(bn126)</italic> deletion mutant</title><p>Worm libraries mutagenized with trimethylpsoralen and UV irradiation were screened for a deletion mutation in <italic>klp-19</italic> (Y43F4B.6) according to the protocols of M. Koelle et al. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://info.med.yale.edu/mbb/koelle/protocols/protocol_Gene_knockouts.html">http://info.med.yale.edu/mbb/koelle/protocols/protocol_Gene_knockouts.html</ext-link>) and the <italic>C. elegans</italic> Knock-Out Consortium (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://celeganskoconsortium.omrf.org/">http://celeganskoconsortium.omrf.org/</ext-link>). PCR primers used in the screen were as follows: external primer set, forward 5&#x02032;-ATTGTGCGTGAACTCTGACG-3&#x02032; and reverse 5&#x02032;-GCGATCTGCTTCTCCAAGTC-3&#x02032;; poison primer, 5&#x02032;-ATCCGAGAGGCTGAAGAAGAC-3&#x02032;; and internal primer set, forward 5&#x02032;-GTCCGTAAATACACTCGCGG-3&#x02032; and reverse 5&#x02032;-TCATCTTGTCCACCAAGTGC-3&#x02032;.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA interference</title><p>For <italic>klp-19</italic> RNAi, the cDNA clones yk105a12, yk111h5, and yk35b11 were obtained from Y. Kohara (National Institute of Genetics, Mishima, Japan). Phagemid DNA and sense and antisense strands of RNA were prepared as described previously (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Strome et al., 2001</xref>). dsRNA from the three clones gave identical phenotypes. Clone yk111h5, which BLAST comparisons indicate will produce gene-specific transcripts, was used for all <italic>klp-19</italic> RNAi experiments. dsRNA was introduced into worms by injection or feeding. For injection, 0.5&#x02013;1 mg/ml of dsRNA was injected into young adult hermaphrodites. RNAi embryos were obtained from injected mothers 22&#x02013;28 h after injection. For feeding, a 756-bp fragment of yk111h5 was inserted into the L4440 feeding vector and transformed into the RNase III-deficient <italic>E. coli</italic> strain HT115, and feeding plates were prepared as in protocol I of <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kamath et al. (2001)</xref>. L1 stage larvae were placed on feeding plates and grown to adulthood at 22&#x000b0;C. For <italic>klp-12</italic> RNAi, the primer pair 5&#x02032;-CCACGTGCAATCCAACATAC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-TTTTCCGTTCGAAGGATGTC-3&#x02032; was used to amplify a gene-specific template that was used to generate dsRNA for injection (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kamath and Ahringer, 2003</xref>). For <italic>hcp-3</italic> RNAi, the primer pair 5&#x02032;-ATGGCCGATGACACCCC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-TCAGAGATGTCGAAGGC-3&#x02032; was used to amplify full-length <italic>hcp-3</italic> from N2 genomic DNA. The &#x0223c;1.0-kb product was inserted into the L4440 feeding vector. HCP-3 RNAi was done by feeding.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibodies and immunofluorescence microscopy</title><p>To generate antisera against KLP-19, a COOH-terminal peptide (amino acids 1061&#x02013;1080) was synthesized, conjugated to keyhole limpet hemocyanin (Research Genetics), and injected into rabbits (Cocalico Biologicals). Antibodies were affinity purified by passing serum over a column of the peptide coupled to epoxy-activated agarose (Pierce Chemical Co.), eluting with 0.2 M glycine and 150 mM NaCl, pH 2.0, dialysis in PBS, and concentration. Western blot analysis of embryonic protein extracts showed specificity for a single band of &#x0223c;120 kD, which is consistent with the predicted size of KLP-19. Staining of the band was reduced substantially by preincubation of the anti-KLP-19 antibody with a molar excess of the peptide. These results and elimination of KLP-19 immunofluorescence by RNAi (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> G) demonstrated that the affinity-purified antibodies were specific for KLP-19.</p><p>For immunofluorescence staining of gonads and embryos, gravid adult hermaphrodites were cut just behind the pharynx, fixed, and stained as described previously (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Strome et al., 2001</xref>). Primary antibodies used were affinity-purified rabbit anti&#x02013;KLP-19 at 1:4,000, mouse 4A1 anti&#x02013;&#x003b1;-tubulin at 1:45 (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Piperno and Fuller, 1985</xref>), mouse E7 anti&#x02013;&#x003b2;-tubulin at 1:100 (Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank), mouse PA3 anti-nucleosome at 1:100 (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Monestier et al., 1994</xref>), and rat anti&#x02013;KLP-7 (CeMCAK) at 1:50. Secondary antibodies used were Alexa Fluor 594&#x02013;conjugated goat anti&#x02013;mouse and goat anti&#x02013;rabbit IgG at 1:250, and Alexa Fluor 488&#x02013;conjugated goat anti&#x02013;rat and goat anti&#x02013;rabbit IgG at 1:500 (Molecular Probes).</p><p>Images of fixed specimens were collected on one of three microscopes. For two-wavelength images, a scanning confocal microscope (model MRC600; Bio-Rad Laboratories) was used with a 60&#x000d7; (1.4 NA) objective. Stacks of 0.5-&#x003bc;m optical sections were collected and displayed as projections. For three-wavelength images, either a microscope (model Eclipse E800; Nikon) equipped with a CCD camera (model Orca-ER; Hamamatsu) and Metamorph Imaging software (Universal Imaging Corp.) or a widefield deconvolution system (Deltavision; Applied Precision) was used. On the Deltavision system, stacks of 0.2-&#x003bc;m optical sections were collected, deconvolved using the Softworx (Applied Precision) software, and displayed as projections. Images for figures were processed using Photoshop (Adobe Systems).</p></sec><sec><title>Imaging live embryos</title><p>Embryos were mounted in M9 buffer on 2% agarose pads and covered with a coverslip. Observation by Nomarski optics was done on a microscope (model Axioplan; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.). Images were captured using a camera (model C2400-00; Hamamatsu) and video controller with an Argus-10 image processor (Hamamatsu) and NIH Image (version 1.62f). Time-lapse imaging of GFP::&#x003b3;-tubulin and GFP::histone fluorescence was done using a scanning confocal microscope. To minimize photodamage, a single optical plane was imaged once every 3 s, except as noted. Images were captured at the maximum pinhole aperture to enhance depth of field. Stacks of images were manipulated in NIH Image (version 1.62f, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/nih-image/">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/nih-image/</ext-link>). Images for figures were processed using Adobe Photoshop.</p></sec><sec><title>Online supplemental material</title><p>Fig. S1 shows comparisons of structural and sequence features of chicken chromokinesin, mouse Kif4, <italic>Drosophila</italic> KLP3A, <italic>C. elegans</italic> KLP-19, <italic>C. elegans</italic> KLP-12, and human Kid. Table S1 displays timing of mitotic events and measurements of pole-to-chromosome distances from fluorescence movies of GFP::histone and GFP::&#x003b3;-tubulin in <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos. All videos show time-lapse confocal microscopy of mitosis in <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos. Videos 1 and 2 show GFP::histone in untreated and KLP-19&#x02013;depleted two-cell embryos. Video 3 shows mitosis of paternal chromosomes after depletion of KLP-19. Videos 4 and 5 show GFP::histone and GFP::&#x003b3;-tubulin in untreated and KLP-19&#x02013;depleted embryos. Video 6 shows chromosome behavior after partial depolymerization of microtubules by Nocodazole. Video 7 shows mitosis in a P<sub>0</sub> cell after inhibition of kinetochore assembly. Videos 8 and 9 show two pairs of movies comparing monopolar AB mitosis in control and KLP-19&#x02013;depleted <italic>zyg-1</italic> mutant embryos. Online supplemental material is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200403036/DC1</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Kevin O'Connell, Paul Mains, Arshad Desai, Yuji Kohara, Margaret Fuller, Marc Monestier, and the Caenorhabditis Genetics Center for reagents and helpful advice.</p><p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grant GM58811 to W.M. Saxton and S. Strome, GM46295 to W.M. Saxton, and GM34059 to S. Strome.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Afshar, K., J. Scholey, and R.S. Hawley. <year>1995</year>. Identification of the chromosome localization domain of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> nod kinesin-like protein. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>833</fpage>&#x02013;843.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7490288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Albertson, D.G., and J.N. Thomson. <year>1982</year>. The kinetochores of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. <source>Chromosoma.</source>
<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>&#x02013;428.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7172865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Antonio, C., I. Ferby, H. Wilhelm, M. Jones, E. Karsenti, A.R. Nebreda, and I. Vernos. <year>2000</year>. Xkid, a chromokinesin required for chromosome alignment on the metaphase plate. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;435.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bringmann, H., G. Skiniotis, A. Spilker, S. Kandels-Lewis, I. Vernos, and T. Surrey. <year>2004</year>. A kinesin-like motor inhibits microtubule dynamic instability. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>303</volume>:<fpage>1519</fpage>&#x02013;1522.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15001780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carpenter, A.T. <year>1991</year>. Distributive segregation: motors in the polar wind? <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>885</fpage>&#x02013;890.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2001589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chang, C.J., S. Goulding, W.C. Earnshaw, and M. Carmena. <year>2003</year>. RNAi analysis reveals an unexpected role for topoisomerase II in chromosome arm congression to a metaphase plate. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>4715</fpage>&#x02013;4726.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14600258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cimini, D., B. Howell, P. Maddox, A. Khodjakov, F. Degrassi, and E.D. Salmon. <year>2001</year>. Merotelic kinetochore orientation is a major mechanism of aneuploidy in mitotic mammalian tissue cells. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;527.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11331303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cimini, D., D. Fioravanti, E.D. Salmon, and F. Degrassi. <year>2002</year>. Merotelic kinetochore orientation versus chromosome mono-orientation in the origin of lagging chromosomes in human primary cells. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;515.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cimini, D., B. Moree, J.C. Canman, and E.D. Salmon. <year>2003</year>. Merotelic kinetochore orientation occurs frequently during early mitosis in mammalian tissue cells and error correction is achieved by two different mechanisms. <source>J Cell Sci</source>. <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>4213</fpage>&#x02013;4225.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12953065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dagenbach, E.M., and S.A. Endow. <year>2004</year>. A new kinesin tree. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;7.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14657268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dernburg, A.F. <year>2001</year>. Here, there, and everywhere: kinetochore function on holocentric chromosomes. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>F33</fpage>&#x02013;F38.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Desai, A., S. Rybina, T. Muller-Reichert, A. Shevchenko, A. Hyman, and K. Oegema. <year>2003</year>. KNL-1 directs assembly of the microtubule-binding interface of the kinetochore in <italic>C. elegans</italic>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>2421</fpage>&#x02013;2435.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14522947</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Funabiki, H., and A.W. Murray. <year>2000</year>. The <italic>Xenopus</italic> chromokinesin Xkid is essential for metaphase chromosome alignment and must be degraded to allow anaphase chromosome movement. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;424.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Goshima, G., and R.D. Vale. <year>2003</year>. The roles of microtubule-based motor proteins in mitosis: comprehensive RNAi analysis in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> S2 cell line. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>1003</fpage>&#x02013;1016.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12975346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hagstrom, K.A., V.F. Holmes, N.R. Cozzarelli, and B.J. Meyer. <year>2002</year>. <italic>C. elegans</italic> condensin promotes mitotic chromosome architecture, centromere organization, and sister chromatid segregation during mitosis and meiosis. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>729</fpage>&#x02013;742.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11914278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Heald, R. <year>2000</year>. Motor function in the mitotic spindle. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;402.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kamath, R.S., and J. Ahringer. <year>2003</year>. Genome-wide RNAi screening in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. <source>Methods</source>. <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;321.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12828945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kamath, R.S., M. Martinez-Campos, P. Zipperlen, A.G. Fraser, and J. Ahringer. 2001. Effectiveness of specific RNA-mediated interference through ingested double-stranded RNA in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>
<italic>Genome Biol</italic>. 2:RESEARCH0002.1&#x02013;0002.10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kline-Smith, S.L., A. Khodjakov, P. Hergert, and C.E. Walczak. <year>2004</year>. Depletion of centromeric MCAK leads to chromosome congression and segregation defects due to improper kinetochore attachments. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1146</fpage>&#x02013;1159.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14699064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kwon, M., S. Morales-Mulia, I. Brust-Mascher, G.C. Rogers, D.J. Sharp, and J.M. Scholey. <year>2004</year>. The chromokinesin, KLP3A, drives mitotic spindle pole separation during prometaphase and anaphase and facilitates chromatid motility. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;233.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14528012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lawrence, C.J., R.L. Malmberg, M.G. Muszynski, and R.K. Dawe. <year>2002</year>. Maximum likelihood methods reveal conservation of function among closely related kinesin families. <source>J. Mol. Evol.</source>
<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;53.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11734897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lawrence, C.J., R.K. Dawe, K.R. Christie, D.W. Cleveland, S.C. Dawson, S.A. Endow, L.S.B. Goldstein, H.V. Goodson, N. Hirokawa, J. Howard, et al. <year>2004</year> A standardized kinesin nomenclature. <source>J. Cell Biol</source>. <volume>In press</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Levesque, A.A., and D.A. Compton. <year>2001</year>. The chromokinesin Kid is necessary for chromosome arm orientation and oscillation, but not congression, on mitotic spindles. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>1135</fpage>&#x02013;1146.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11564754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Li, X., and R.B. Nicklas. <year>1995</year>. Mitotic forces control a cell-cycle checkpoint. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>373</volume>:<fpage>630</fpage>&#x02013;632.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7854422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lima-de-Faria, A. <year>1949</year> Genetics, origin and evolution of kinetochores. <source>Hereditas.</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;444.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mains, P.E., K.J. Kemphues, S.A. Sprunger, I.A. Sulston, and W.B. Wood. <year>1990</year>. Mutations affecting the meiotic and mitotic divisions of the early <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> embryo. <source>Genetics.</source>
<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;605.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2249759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marshall, W.F. <year>2002</year> Polar wind left flapping in the breeze? <source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McIntosh, J.R., E.L. Grishchuk, and R.R. West. <year>2002</year>. Chromosome-microtubule interactions during mitosis. <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;219.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Monestier, M., K.E. Novick, and M.J. Losman. <year>1994</year>. D-penicillamine- and quinidine-induced antinuclear antibodies in A.SW (H-2s) mice: similarities with autoantibodies in spontaneous and heavy metal-induced autoimmunity. <source>Eur. J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>723</fpage>&#x02013;730.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8125139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Moore, L.L., and M.B. Roth. <year>2001</year>. HCP-4, a CENP-C&#x02013;like protein in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, is required for resolution of sister centromeres. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>1199</fpage>&#x02013;1208.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nicklas, R.B. <year>1997</year>. How cells get the right chromosomes. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>632</fpage>&#x02013;637.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9005842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">O'Connell, K.F., C. Caron, K.R. Kopish, D.D. Hurd, K.J. Kemphues, Y. Li, and J.G. White. <year>2001</year>. The <italic>C. elegans</italic> zyg-1 gene encodes a regulator of centrosome duplication with distinct maternal and paternal roles in the embryo. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;558.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">O'Toole, E.T., K.L. McDonald, J. Mantler, J.R. McIntosh, A.A. Hyman, and T. Muller-Reichert. <year>2003</year>. Morphologically distinct microtubule ends in the mitotic centrosome of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>163</volume>:<fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;456.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14610052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Oegema, K., A. Desai, S. Rybina, M. Kirkham, and A.A. Hyman. <year>2001</year>. Functional analysis of kinetochore assembly in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>1209</fpage>&#x02013;1226.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ostergren, G., J. Mole-Bajer, and A. Bajer. <year>1960</year>. An interpretation of transport phenomena at mitosis. <source>Ann. NY Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;408.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13731492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Peretti, D., L. Peris, S. Rosso, S. Quiroga, and A. Caceres. <year>2000</year>. Evidence for the involvement of KIF4 in the anterograde transport of L1-containing vesicles. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;152.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Piperno, G., and M.T. Fuller. <year>1985</year>. Monoclonal antibodies specific for an acetylated form of &#x003b1;-tubulin recognize the antigen in cilia and flagella from a variety of organisms. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>2085</fpage>&#x02013;2094.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2415535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Powers, J., O. Bossinger, D. Rose, S. Strome, and W. Saxton. <year>1998</year>. A nematode kinesin required for cleavage furrow advancement. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1133</fpage>&#x02013;1136.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9778533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Praitis, V., E. Casey, D. Collar, and J. Austin. <year>2001</year>. Creation of low-copy integrated transgenic lines in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. <source>Genetics.</source>
<volume>157</volume>:<fpage>1217</fpage>&#x02013;1226.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rieder, C.L., and E.D. Salmon. <year>1998</year>. The vertebrate cell kinetochore and its roles during mitosis. <source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;318.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9704407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rieder, C.L., E.A. Davison, L.C. Jensen, L. Cassimeris, and E.D. Salmon. <year>1986</year>. Oscillatory movements of monooriented chromosomes and their position relative to the spindle pole result from the ejection properties of the aster and half-spindle. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#x02013;591.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3733881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Salina, D., P. Enarson, J.B. Rattner, and B. Burke. <year>2003</year>. Nup358 integrates nuclear envelope breakdown with kinetochore assembly. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>991</fpage>&#x02013;1001.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Segbert, C., R. Barkus, J. Powers, S. Strome, W.M. Saxton, and O. Bossinger. <year>2003</year>. KLP-18, a Klp2 kinesin, is required for assembly of acentrosomal meiotic spindles in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>4458</fpage>&#x02013;4469.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12937278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sekine, Y., Y. Okada, Y. Noda, S. Kondo, H. Aizawa, R. Takemura, and N. Hirokawa. <year>1994</year>. A novel microtubule-based motor protein (KIF4) for organelle transports, whose expression is regulated developmentally. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;201.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7929562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sharp, D.J., H.M. Brown, M. Kwon, G.C. Rogers, G. Holland, and J.M. Scholey. <year>2000</year>. Functional coordination of three mitotic motors in <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;253.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10637305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stear, J.H., and M.B. Roth. <year>2002</year>. Characterization of HCP-6, a <italic>C. elegans</italic> protein required to prevent chromosome twisting and merotelic attachment. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1498</fpage>&#x02013;1508.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12080088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Strome, S., and W. B. Wood <year>1983</year>. Generation of asymmetry and segregation of germ-line granules in early <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;25.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6684994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Strome, S., J. Powers, M. Dunn, K. Reese, C.J. Malone, J. White, G. Seydoux, and W. Saxton. <year>2001</year>. Spindle dynamics and the role of &#x003b3;-tubulin in early <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> embryos. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1751</fpage>&#x02013;1764.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11408582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Theurkauf, W.E., and R.S. Hawley. <year>1992</year>. Meiotic spindle assembly in <italic>Drosophila</italic> females: behavior of nonexchange chromosomes and the effects of mutations in the nod kinesin-like protein. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>1167</fpage>&#x02013;1180.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1740471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tokai, N., A. Fujimoto-Nishiyama, Y. Toyoshima, S. Yonemura, S. Tsukita, J. Inoue, and T. Yamamota. <year>1996</year>. Kid, a novel kinesin-like DNA binding protein, is localized to chromosomes and the mitotic spindle. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;467.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8599929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vale, R.D. <year>2003</year>. The molecular motor toolbox for intracellular transport. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#x02013;480.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12600311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vale, R.D., and R.J. Fletterick. <year>1997</year>. The design plan of kinesin motors. <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>745</fpage>&#x02013;777.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vernos, I., and E. Karsenti. <year>1995</year>. Chromosomes take the lead in spindle assembly. <source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;301.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14732087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vernos, I., J. Raats, T. Hirano, J. Heasman, E. Karsenti, and C. Wylie. <year>1995</year>. Xklp1, a chromosomal <italic>Xenopus</italic> kinesin-like protein essential for spindle organization and chromosome positioning. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;127.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7720067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang, S.Z., and R. Adler. <year>1995</year>. Chromokinesin: a DNA-binding, kinesin-like nuclear protein. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>761</fpage>&#x02013;768.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7876303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wasser, M., and W. Chia. <year>2003</year>. The <italic>Drosophila</italic> EAST protein associates with a nuclear remnant during mitosis and constrains chromosome mobility. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>1733</fpage>&#x02013;1743.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12665554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Waters, J.C., R.H. Chen, A.W. Murray, and E.D. Salmon. <year>1998</year>. Localization of Mad2 to kinetochores depends on microtubule attachment, not tension. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>1181</fpage>&#x02013;1191.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9606210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Williams, B.C., M.F. Riedy, E.V. Williams, M. Gatti, and M.L. Goldberg. <year>1995</year>. The <italic>Drosophila</italic> kinesin-like protein KLP3A is a midbody component required for central spindle assembly and initiation of cytokinesis. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;723.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7730406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
