<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17308346</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1865047</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm046</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>RNA</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The availability of the primer activation signal (PAS) affects the efficiency of HIV-1 reverse transcription initiation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ooms</surname><given-names>Marcel</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cupac</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abbink</surname><given-names>Truus E. M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huthoff</surname><given-names>Hendrik</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>Ben</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Laboratory of Experimental Virology, Department of Medical Microbiology, Center for Infection and Immunity Amsterdam (CINIMA), Academic Medical Center of the University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+31&#x02009;205&#x02009;664&#x02009;822</phone><fax>+31&#x02009;206&#x02009;916&#x02009;531</fax><email>b.berkhout@amc.uva.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1649</fpage><lpage>1659</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Initiation of reverse transcription of a retroviral RNA genome is strictly regulated. The tRNA primer binds to the primer binding site (PBS), and subsequent priming is triggered by the primer activation signal (PAS) that also pairs with the tRNA. We observed that <italic>in vitro</italic> reverse transcription initiation of the HIV-1 leader RNA varies in efficiency among 3&#x02032;-end truncated transcripts, despite the presence of both PBS and PAS motifs. As the HIV-1 leader RNA can adopt two different foldings, we investigated if the conformational state of the transcripts did influence the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation. However, mutant transcripts that exclusively fold one or the other structure were similarly active, thereby excluding the possibility of regulation of reverse transcription initiation by the structure riboswitch. We next set out to determine the availability of the PAS element. This sequence motif enhances the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation, but its activity is regulated because the PAS motif is initially base paired within the wild-type template. We measured that the initiation efficiency on different templates correlates directly with accessibility of the PAS motif. Furthermore, changes in PAS are critical to facilitate a primer-switch to a new tRNA species, demonstrating the importance of this enhancer element.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Reverse transcription of the human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) RNA genome is a critical step in the viral replication cycle. Upon infection of a host cell, the single-stranded viral RNA (vRNA) genome is reverse transcribed into a double-stranded DNA with duplicated long terminal repeats (LTR), which integrates into the host cell genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Reverse transcription is mediated by the viral enzyme reverse transcriptase (RT) and the cellular tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> is used as a primer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Although reverse transcription initiation can take place shortly after budding of the viral particle from the producer cell, there is evidence suggesting that reverse transcription is restricted until infection of a new host cell, possibly by limitation of dNTP building blocks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4 B5 B6 B7 B8">4&#x02013;8</xref>).</p><p>Reverse transcription initiation is mediated by multiple HIV-1 RNA&#x02013;tRNA interactions. The first step in reverse transcription is the hybridization of the 3&#x02032; end of the tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> molecule to a complementary 18-nt sequence in the 5&#x02032;-untranslated leader region of the HIV-1 RNA genome termed the primer binding site (PBS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Several additional sequence motifs in the untranslated leader have been proposed to interact with the primer tRNA, including a single-stranded A-rich motif, located in the U5 region immediately upstream of the PBS that was proposed to interact with the U-rich anticodon of tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11 B12 B13 B14 B15 B16">11&#x02013;16</xref>). Another interaction between the anticodon stem and variable loop of tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> and a sequence upstream of the A-rich loop in the template forms in the presence of the viral nucleocapsid protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). We identified another enhancer element that is located further upstream in the leader, the 8-nt PAS motif that is complementary to the T&#x003c8;C arm of the tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> primer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18 B19 B20 B21">18&#x02013;21</xref>). The PAS motif is not involved in tRNA placement, but enhances its usage as a primer. Hence it is termed the <italic>p</italic>rimer <italic>a</italic>ctivation <italic>s</italic>ignal (PAS) and the complementary sequence in the T&#x003c8;C arm is termed anti-PAS. There is accumulating evidence for the importance of this PAS motif, e.g. its role in facilitating priming by a non-self tRNA primer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). As the PAS sequence is masked in the HIV-1 leader RNA by base pairing within the extended PBS stem that encompasses the PBS domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C), this provides the virus with a mechanism to regulate the initiation of reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Motifs in the HIV-1 RNA genome that regulate reverse transcription. (<bold>A</bold>) The HIV-1 DNA genome is shown with the nine open reading frames. The untranslated leader encoding multiple regulatory elements is schematically depicted. A 3&#x02032;-nested set of transcripts used as template for reverse transcription initiation are shown with the PAS and PBS motifs. (<bold>B</bold>) Alternative structures of the HIV-1 leader RNA. The ground state conformation contains a long-distance interaction (LDI) between the polyA and DIS domains. The alternate conformation exposes the polyA and DIS hairpins and takes the form of a branched structure (BMH). (<bold>C</bold>) Model of PAS-mediated tRNA primer activation. First, the tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> primer anneals to the PBS (indicated in blue), subsequently the anti-PAS sequence in tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> must anneal to the PAS (purple) before efficient reverse transcription initiation can take place.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f1"/></fig></p><p>The conformational state of the HIV-1 leader RNA has also been suggested to influence reverse transcription initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). The sequence of the leader RNA is highly conserved among virus isolates and contains several sequence and structure motifs that are involved in many replication steps (e.g. transcription, splicing, translation, RNA dimerization, packaging and reverse transcription) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). Multiple lines of evidence indicate that the leader region can adopt two distinct structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27 B28 B29">27&#x02013;29</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). In the ground state conformation, the polyA and DIS regions are base paired through a long distance interaction (LDI). Disruption of this long-distance interaction rearranges the leader region into a branched structure with multiple hairpins (BMH). This BMH conformation presents the DIS hairpin that facilitates dimerization of the RNA genome through a kissing loop interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The RNA packaging signal &#x003c8; is also differently presented by the two leader conformations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). This RNA switch has been proposed to regulate the appropriate timing of RNA dimerization and packaging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). We now set out to test the impact of the HIV-1 leader RNA structure, either through the LDI-BMH switch or PAS accessibility, on the initiation of reverse transcription.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</title><sec><title>DNA synthesis</title><p>The HIV-1 LAI wild type (wt) and mutant pBluescript 5&#x02032;-LTR plasmids that were used in this study as template for PCR amplification have been described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). The DNA templates for <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription were obtained through PCR amplification of the 5&#x02032;-LTR leader region with the T7-2 sense primer, with a 5&#x02032;-flanking T7 RNA polymerase promoter sequence, and the corresponding antisense primers. Sense T7-2 50-TAATACGACTCACTATAGGGTCTCCTGGTTAGACCAT-30 (T7-promotor underlined, start site transcription in bold and italic). Antisense primers: 202 5&#x02032;-CAAGTCCCTGTTCGGGCGCC-3&#x02032; 248 5&#x02032;-GCCGAGTCCTGCGTCGAGAG-3&#x02032; 256 5&#x02032;-TTCAGCAAGCCGAGTCCTGC-3&#x02032; 263 5&#x02032;-TGCGCGCTTCAGCAAGCCGA-3&#x02032; 270 5&#x02032;-CTTGCCGTGCGCGCTTCAGC-3&#x02032; 281 5&#x02032;-TCCCCTCGCCTCTTGCCGTG-3&#x02032; 290 5&#x02032;-CCAGTCGCCTCCCCTCGCCT-3&#x02032; 368 5&#x02032;-TCCCCCGCTTAATACTGACG-3&#x02032;. The PCR fragments were ethanol precipitated and dissolved in water.</p><p>We made five sets of 3&#x02032;-truncated leader RNA transcripts. The first set is based on the wt HIV-1 LAI sequence, but with 3&#x02032; truncations (1&#x02013;202/248/256/263/270/281/290/368). The second set (J1&#x02013;J10 1&#x02013;368, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>) contains mutations in the 3&#x02032;-end of the leader (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). Three mutant sets have mutations in PAS (2L) or opposite to the PAS (2R) and the double mutant (2LR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription was performed with the Ambion MegaShortscript T7 transcription kit according to the manufacturer's instructions. The transcripts were separated on a 6% denaturing polyacrylamide gel containing urea, visualized by UV shadowing, subsequently excised, and eluted from the gel fragments by overnight incubation at 30&#x000b0;C in 1&#x000d7; TBE and phenol. The RNA was subsequently ethanol precipitated and dissolved in water. The dissolved RNA was quantified by UV absorbance measurement and set to an equal molarity of 0.044&#x02009;pmol/&#x003bc;l that corresponds to 5&#x02009;ng/&#x003bc;l RNA for the wt 1&#x02013;368 transcript. Radiolabeled transcripts were synthesized by performing the transcription reaction in the presence of 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l &#x003b1;<sup>32</sup>P-dUTP and were quantified by scintillation counting.</p></sec><sec><title>Primer extension assay</title><p>Reverse transcription was performed by incubating the <italic>in vitro</italic> synthesized RNA templates (0.088&#x02009;pmol) with either 1.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g calf liver tRNA (6&#x02009;pmol total tRNA, of which &#x0223c;1.2&#x02009;pmol tRNA<sup>lys3</sup>, Roche Molecular Biochemicals), 10&#x02009;ng DNA Lys21 primer (complementary to the PBS, 5&#x02032;-CAAGTCCCTGTTCGGGCGCCA-3&#x02032;) or 10&#x02009;ng RNA Lys18 primer (complementary to the PBS, 5&#x02032;-GUCCCUGUUCGGGCGCCA-3&#x02032;) in 12&#x02009;&#x003bc;l annealing buffer (83&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 125&#x02009;mM KCl). The samples were heated for 2&#x02009;min at 85&#x000b0;C and then slowly cooled to room temperature. The primer was extended by addition of 6-&#x003bc;l 3&#x000d7; RT buffer, which contains 9&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 30&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol, 150&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml actinomycin D, 0.33&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]dCTP and 0.5 units of HIV-1 RT (Medical Research Council AIDS Reagent Project). Samples were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min and the reaction was stopped by adding one volume of denaturing loading buffer containing formamide (Ambion). The samples were heated for 2&#x02009;min at 95&#x000b0;C and subsequently separated on a 6% denaturing polyacrylamide gel (19:1 acrylamide gel containing urea, 1&#x000d7; TBE) at 50&#x02009;W. Gels were dried and applied to a Storm PhosphorImager. Quantification of band intensities was performed with ImageQuant 5.0 (Amersham Biosciences). The data was corrected for the amount of input RNA by dividing the tRNA extension signal by the DNA-primed extension signal. The value obtained for the wt 1&#x02013;368 sample was arbitrarily set at 1.</p></sec><sec><title>Non-denaturing polyacrylamide electrophoresis</title><p>For electrophoretic analysis, &#x0223c;200 counts/s of radiolabeled transcripts was incubated in a final volume of 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l TEN buffer (100&#x02009;mM NaCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA, 10&#x02009;mM Tris (pH 8.0)). Samples were heated at 85&#x000b0;C and slowly cooled to room temperature. Samples were split (2 &#x000d7; 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;l) and 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of loading buffer (30% glycerol with BFB dye). Control samples were denatured at 90&#x000b0;C with 10-&#x003bc;l formamide loading buffer. Samples were analyzed on a 4% polyacrylamide gel (Sigma) in 0.25 &#x000d7; TBE (22.5&#x02009;mM Tris, 22.5&#x02009;mM boric acid, 0.625&#x02009;mM EDTA), at 150&#x02009;V at room temperature, dried and analyzed.</p></sec><sec><title>UV absorbance measurements</title><p>RNA thermal denaturation was monitored by measuring the absorbance of UV light at 260&#x02009;nm with a Perkin Elmer Lambda 2 spectrophotometer. The temperature of the samples was increased from 25 to 90&#x000b0;C at a rate of 0.5&#x000b0;C/min while measuring the <italic>A</italic><sub>260 nm</sub> at each 0.1&#x000b0;C. The measurements were performed in a 1-cm path length quartz cuvette containing 3.0&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of RNA dissolved in 140&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 50&#x02009;mM Na-cacodylate buffer (pH 7.2).</p></sec><sec><title>RNA secondary structure prediction by Mfold</title><p>For RNA secondary structure prediction, we used the Mfold program 3.2 version offered by Zuker. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.bioinfo.rpi.edu/applications/mfold/old/rna/form1.cgi">www.bioinfo.rpi.edu/applications/mfold/old/rna/form1.cgi</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). The folding jobs were submitted under the following standard conditions: 37&#x000b0;C, 1.0&#x02009;M NaCl and a 5% suboptimality range. Folding restrictions were imposed for some of the folding jobs and the &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> value of the first structure (with lowest &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>) was used for analysis. The LDI versus BMH was defined by inspection of the region encompassing either the polyA hairpin (BMH) or the long distance interaction with the DIS domain (LDI). The &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> value of a structure with an exposed PAS was obtained by restricting base pairing of the 8-nt PAS sequence, the masked PAS value was obtained without restriction. The PBS was restricted from base pairing in both situations.</p></sec><sec><title>Virus production and isolation of viral RNA</title><p>C33A cells were grown in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium with 10% fetal calf serum at 37&#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. For the production of virions, C33A cells were transiently transfected by the calcium phosphate method. Cells were grown to 60% confluence in 20&#x02009;ml of culture medium in a 75-cm<sup>2</sup> flask. Forty micrograms of the proviral construct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) in 880&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of water was mixed with 1&#x02009;ml of 50&#x02009;mM HEPES (pH 7.1), 250&#x02009;mM NaCl, 1.5&#x02009;mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> and 120&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 2&#x02009;M CaCl<sub>2</sub>, incubated at room temperature for 20&#x02009;min, and added to the culture medium. Three days after transfection, the culture medium (20&#x02009;ml) was centrifuged at 2750 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 15&#x02009;min to remove cells. The supernatant was subsequently filtered through a 0.45-&#x003bc;m-pore-size filter (Schleider &#x00026; Schuell), and the viruses were pelleted by centrifugation at 25&#x02009;000&#x02009;r.p.m. for 30&#x02009;min in a Beckman SW28 rotor. Virions were resuspended in 400&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 10&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 100&#x02009;mM NaCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA. To isolate vRNA, the viruses were incubated for 30&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C in the presence of 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of proteinase K/ml, 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate, followed by extraction with phenol&#x02013;chloroform&#x02013;isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1) and precipitation in 0.3&#x02009;M sodium acetate (pH 5.2), ethanol at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C. The vRNA was pelleted by centrifugation (16 000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>, 20&#x02009;min), washed with 70% ethanol, and dried. The pellet was dissolved in 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 10&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 1&#x02009;mM EDTA and stored at &#x02212;70&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Ex vivo</italic> reverse transcription assay</title><p>The vRNA&#x02013;tRNA complex corresponding to 50&#x02009;ng of CA-p24 virions was incubated with or without an oligonucleotide primer (20&#x02009;ng) in 12&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 83&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 125&#x02009;mM KCl at 85&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;min and at 65&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min, followed by cooling to room temperature for 1&#x02009;h to allow primer annealing. The natural tRNA primer or the annealed DNA primer was extended by the addition of 6&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of RT buffer (9&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>; 30&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol; 150&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of actinomycin D/ml; 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;M dGTP, dTTP; 1.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;M dCTP), 0.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]dCTP and 0.5&#x02009;U of HIV-1 RT. The samples were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 45&#x02009;min. The cDNA product was precipitated in 25&#x02009;mM EDTA, 0.3&#x02009;M sodium acetate (pH 5.2), 80% ethanol at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C. The products were analyzed on a denaturing 6% polyacrylamide-urea sequencing gel.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>The efficiency of reverse transcription initiation varies among 3&#x02032;-truncated HIV-1 leader RNA templates</title><p>We set out to test the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation on HIV-1 leader transcripts with varying 3&#x02032; end positions. A nested set of RNA transcripts was made with the wt 5&#x02032;-end (position +1) and a variable 3&#x02032; end: 202, 248, 256, 263, 270, 281, 290 and 368 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). The natural tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> primer and the synthetic oligonucleotide Lys21 were used as primers for reverse transcription. To test the initiation efficiency, the annealed tRNA/DNA primer was extended by 1&#x02009;nt after addition of [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P] dCTP and HIV-1 RT enzyme. One representative primer extension assay is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A. The results of four independent assays were quantified and are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B. The DNA primer acts as a control for the amount of template because the efficiency of DNA-primed reverse transcription initiation is equal on all templates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Compared to the shortest 1&#x02013;202 transcript, the efficiency of tRNA-primed reverse transcription increases for the 3&#x02032;-extended transcripts, with an optimum for the 1&#x02013;263 transcript, after which the activity drops gradually with transcript length. The 1&#x02013;263 transcript consistently exhibits an &#x0223c;2-fold higher activity than 1&#x02013;202 and 1&#x02013;368. These results show that there is a difference in the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation for leader transcripts with different 3&#x02032; ends. We set out to determine the molecular reason for this effect.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Reverse transcription initiation of HIV-1 leader RNA transcripts with variable 3&#x02032; ends. (<bold>A</bold>) DNA (left) or tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> (right) primers were annealed to HIV-1 transcripts. Primers were extended by addition of <sup>32</sup>P-CTP and HIV-1 RT enzyme. Extended primers were separated on a denaturing acrylamide gel. The 1/2 tRNA signal represents a half tRNA species that is discussed in detail in the context of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Relative reverse transcription initiation efficiency with tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> as primer was calculated by comparison with the DNA-primed signal. The relative efficiency of reverse transcription initiation (RTI) of the 1&#x02013;368 template was set at 1. Quantification and standard deviations of four independent experiments are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of the leader RNA conformation</title><p>There are no known sequence motifs 3&#x02032; of the PBS that may play a positive or negative role in tRNA-primed reverse transcription. Thus, the observed effects are likely due to conformational changes of the RNA template, e.g. affecting the LDI-BMH riboswitch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B) and/or influencing the accessibility of the PAS enhancer motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C). We set out to determine the LDI/BMH status of the 3&#x02032;-truncated HIV-1 transcripts by three methods: non-denaturing polyacrylamide electrophoresis, secondary structure prediction by Mfold and UV absorbance melting experiments.</p><p>Electrophoresis on non-denaturing gels separates molecules according to size but also according to structure, as different structures have different migration properties. Previous research has shown that there is a relatively profound migration difference between the LDI and BMH conformations. Compared to a heat/formamide-denatured sample, the LDI-folded leader RNA migrates faster. In contrast, a BMH-folded leader RNA co-migrates with the denatured sample (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). The set of radiolabeled transcripts were analyzed on a non-denaturing TBE gel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). Transcripts 202, 248, 256 and 263 co-migrate with the denatured transcripts, indicating that they adopt the BMH conformation. Transcripts 270 and 281 show both this slow migrating BMH band and the fast migrating LDI form. Only the fast migrating LDI form is observed for 290 and 368. Thus, the shorter transcripts exclusively fold the BMH conformation, but the LDI conformation becomes possible upon inclusion of DIS sequences, which form the long-distance interaction with the polyA domain. The longest transcripts exclusively fold the LDI conformation.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>LDI-BMH status of the leader transcripts with variable 3&#x02032; ends. (<bold>A</bold>) Electric mobility shift assay on a 0.25 &#x000d7; TBE acrylamide gel. Transcripts were incubated in TEN buffer (N), or denatured in formamide containing loading buffer (F). (<bold>B</bold>) The LDI-BMH status of the transcripts as calculated by Mfold. The &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> values of the LDI and the BMH structure were calculated as described in the Materials and methods section and subtracted to obtain the &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic>. (<bold>C</bold>) Thermal melting profiles of the HIV-1 transcripts with variable 3&#x02032; ends. The temperature was increased from 25 to 90&#x000b0;C at a rate of 0.5&#x000b0;C/min, the <italic>A</italic><sub>260 nm</sub> was measured with 0.1&#x000b0;C intervals. The transcript length and melting temperatures (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>) of the transitions are indicated in the plots.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f3"/></fig></p><p>We also used the RNA folding prediction program Mfold 3.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). The thermodynamic stability of the LDI (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>LDI</sub>) and BMH (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>BMH</sub>) conformation was scored, and the difference (&#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>LDI-BMH</sub>) was calculated. A positive &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic> value predicts a preference for BMH folding, a negative &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic> value is predictive of LDI folding, and both structures are in equilibrium when &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic> is close to 0. The &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic> value gradually declines with the length of the leader transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B), indicating a gradual shift from BMH to LDI structure, which is fully consistent with the gel migration results.</p><p>The secondary structure of a transcript can also be analyzed by measuring its UV absorbance at increasing temperature (<italic>T</italic>), as disruption of base pairs results in an increase of UV absorbance (hyperchromicity). This technique can efficiently discriminate between the LDI and BMH conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). All transcripts form the 5&#x02032;-terminal TAR hairpin that produces the characteristic peak at 65&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C), but this does not discriminate between LDI and BMH because both conformations have the TAR hairpin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). The LDI is characterized by a distinct narrow transition while the BMH is reflected by a broad transition at a lower temperature. Transcripts show either the broad peak at 41&#x000b0;C that is typical for BMH (202, 248, 256), or the more intense peak at 46&#x000b0;C that is characteristic for LDI (270, 281, 290, 368). Transcript 263 and 270 show an intermediate pattern (asterisks indicate underlying BMH peak). All conformational tests indicate that shorter transcripts are in the BMH form, with a gradual shift towards LDI upon 3&#x02032;-extension. This suggests that the eventual drop in the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation from 263 to 368 may be due to LDI folding, but the LDI-BMH equilibrium does not explain the initial increase in efficiency from 202 to 263.</p></sec><sec><title>Reverse transcription initiation is not affected by the LDI-BMH switch</title><p>To test the impact of the leader RNA conformation on the initiation of reverse transcription initiation, we used leader mutants that specifically stabilize the LDI or BMH structure. Mutants J1&#x02013;J10 were previously used to study the effect of LDI-BMH on RNA dimerization and mRNA translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). We selected these mutants because they contain precise mutations in the 3&#x02032;-terminal region of the leader RNA and thus do not directly affect the upstream sequences that control reverse transcription initiation (PBS and PAS). The wt and mutant templates were made as 1&#x02013;368 transcripts to exclusively examine the effect of LDI/BMH on the initiation of reverse transcription. The tRNA extension efficiency of the J1&#x02013;J10 mutants is very similar to that of wt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>), despite the fact that some transcripts have a significantly altered LDI/BMH equilibrium. In particular, J8 and J9 that exclusively fold the BMH structure display the same efficiency as the wt transcript, which folds the LDI conformation. We conclude that the LDI/BMH conformation of the HIV-1 leader sequence has no direct effect on reverse transcription initiation.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Reverse transcription initiation efficiency of the wt and J1&#x02013;J10 transcripts. (<bold>A</bold>) DNA or tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> primers were annealed to wt and mutant 1-368 transcripts and extended with <sup>32</sup>P-CTP by the HIV-1 RT enzyme. Extended primers were separated on a denaturing acrylamide gel. The 1/2 tRNA signal represents a half tRNA species that is discussed in detail in the context of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Relative initiation of reverse transcription efficiency of the wt and mutant transcripts, the wt activity was arbitrarily set at 1. The average and standard deviations of three independent experiments were quantified.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f4"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>The efficiency of reverse transcription initiation can be modulated by PAS accessibility</title><p>The availability of the PAS sequence could form an alternative explanation for the different efficiencies in reverse transcription initiation of the 3&#x02032;-nested set of HIV-1 leader transcripts. To test this possibility, we performed the tRNA/DNA primer initiation assay with a 3&#x02032;-nested set of three mutants that differ in PAS accessibility. The 2L mutant inactivates the PAS motif by a 7-nt substitution and serves as a negative control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The 2R mutant has a 7-nt substitution in the opposite strand, thereby opening the stem and exposing the PAS sequence. The 2LR double mutant contains both substitutions that were designed to restore base pairing, but obviously not the correct PAS sequence. Let us first discuss the behavior of the 368 transcripts. We measured very low template activity for the PAS-minus 2L and 2LR mutants, whereas the PAS-exposed 2R template showed increased activity compared to the wt transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). The shortest 202 transcripts also show the defect for 2L and 2LR, but show a different pattern for the 2R mutant, which has the same activity as wt. However, this makes sense as the short wt transcript will have an exposed PAS because the sequences to which it base pairs are not present in the 202 transcript. The effect of 3&#x02032;-extension of the wt transcript has been discussed before; it shows an increase up to 263, followed by a gradual decrease in efficiency. Most importantly, the PAS-exposed 2R mutant did not show the characteristic wt-pattern of reduced efficiency upon 3&#x02032;-extension of the template. Both wt and 2R exhibit increased efficiency of reverse transcription initiation up to position 263, but 2R does not show the subsequent drop in activity up to the 368-nt long transcript. These results suggest that 3&#x02032; leader sequences can mask the PAS motif in the wt transcript, but not in the dominant 2R mutant with a fully exposed PAS motif.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>The secondary structure model of part of the HIV-1 leader RNA and the tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> primer are shown. Mutant 2L has a 7-nt substitution in the PAS motif and mutant 2R has a substitution on the opposite side of the base-paired PAS domain. The 2L and 2R mutations were combined in the 2LR mutant. The asterisks at position 37&#x02013;39 of the tRNA mark the position of a cleavage product that is referred to as 1/2 tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f5"/></fig>
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Reverse transcription initiation on the 3&#x02032;-nested set of wt, 2L, 2R and 2LR transcripts. (<bold>A</bold>) DNA or tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> primers were annealed to the indicated transcripts. Primers were extended by HIV-1 RT with <sup>32</sup>P-CTP and separated on denaturing acrylamide gels. Gel fragments of the DNA- and tRNA-primed extensions are shown. (<bold>B</bold>) Relative reverse transcription initiation efficiency of the different transcripts. Initiation of the wt368 template was set at 1. The average and standard deviation of four independent experiments was quantified.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f6"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>The predicted PAS accessibility correlates with the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation</title><p>We used Mfold to calculate the availability of the PAS sequence for the different templates by calculating the &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic> value of PAS-masked versus PAS-exposed structures. To test and calibrate this method, we first calculated the &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>PAS</sub> values of a large set of RNA structure mutants that were previously tested for tRNA-mediated reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Initiation is very inefficient for transcripts with a low &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>PAS</sub> value, but increases for templates with a value of &#x0223c;&#x02212;3 kcal/mol or higher (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). We also plotted the 2R transcript, which displays a higher &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>PAS</sub> value and increased initiation efficiency when compared to wt, consistent with the idea that the PAS is more accessible. We also analyzed the impact of 3&#x02032;-end variation in this way. However, the &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>PAS</sub> values were not affected by transcript length (results not shown). We conclude that effects of large mutations on reverse transcription initiation can be explained by Mfold, but the rather small effect of 3&#x02032;-truncations do not show a difference in &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic>.
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Mfold-calculated PAS exposure. To calibrate this approach, we first calculated the PAS availability of a well-studied set of mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). The &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> of an open PAS structure was obtained by the restriction of base pairing. The calculated &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic>, which reflects the energy needed to open the PAS sequence, was plotted against the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation as described by Beerens <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). The 2R mutant that is tested in this study is highlighted by a closed circle.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f7"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>PAS-mediated stimulation of reverse transcription is specific for the tRNA primer</title><p>We measured differences in the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation of different templates that correlate with PAS availability. Any PAS effect should be specific for tRNA-primed reverse transcription and should not be observed with short DNA or RNA primers annealed to the PBS. We therefore directly compared these primers on the full-length wt, 2L, 2R and 2LR transcripts. DNA and RNA oligonucleotide-primed initiation is equally efficient on all templates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). Only tRNA-primed reverse transcription varies per template according to the PAS accessibility. The 2R mutant, with a free PAS motif, shows an approximate 2-fold increase in efficiency compared to the wt template. The PAS minus 2L and 2LR mutants exhibit a very low efficiency of reverse transcription initiation. Both these positive and negative effects are specific for the tRNA primer. Interestingly, the tRNA preparation also contains a tRNA fragment that represents the 3&#x02032; half of tRNA<sup>lys3</sup>, &#x0223c;37&#x02013;39&#x02009;nt in length and lacking the typical tRNA cloverleaf structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). This 1/2 tRNA primer includes the sequences complementary to the PBS and the PAS sequences. Indeed, this 1/2 tRNA primer demonstrates the same activity spectrum as the complete tRNA<sup>lys3</sup>.
<fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>DNA-, RNA- and tRNA-primed reverse transcription. (<bold>A</bold>) The 3 primers were tested on the 1&#x02013;368 transcripts of wt and mutants 2L, 2R and 2LR. Primers were extended with <sup>32</sup>P-CTP by HIV-1 RT. Extended primers were separated on a denaturing acrylamide gel. Indicated are cDNA products of DNA, RNA, tRNA and 1/2-tRNA primers. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantified data of three experiments. The efficiency of DNA-primed reverse transcription initiation of wt is set at 1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f8"/></fig></p><p>Thus, we conclude that the observed tRNA-specific differences in template activity reflect their ability to present the PAS motif. We argued that differences in PAS presentation also determine the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation of the nested set of 3&#x02032; extended transcripts. Consistent with this idea, no differences were observed on these templates with the DNA primer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A) and the RNA primer (results not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Contribution of the PAS motif to a switch in tRNA usage</title><p>An HIV-1 variant that stably uses the alternative tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup> primer was recently described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). This virus was obtained in two steps. First, we changed both the PBS and the PAS motif to complement the tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup> primer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>A, mutant M). Long-term culturing resulted in a revertant virus that gained replication capacity by a reversion (R) in the PAS motif. The U126C reversion in the PAS motif stabilizes the interaction with the anti-PAS. To test the effect of this mutation on reverse transcription initiation, we performed primer extension assays on <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed wt, mutant and revertant transcripts and <italic>ex vivo</italic> on vRNA&#x02013;tRNA complexes isolated from the respective virions. For the latter purpose, virions were produced in transfected C33A cells, and the vRNA&#x02013;tRNA complexes were isolated. Equal amounts of wild-type, mutant and revertant complexes (based on CA-p24) were used in the reverse transcription assay. The amount of input vRNA-tRNA in the assay was verified by a control DNA primer extension reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) that we routinely use in our laboratory (results not shown). The tRNA primer was extended on the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcripts with 1 radiolabeled nucleotide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>B). Because the vRNA&#x02013;tRNA duplex from virions may contain tRNA primers that are already extended by 1 or 2&#x02009;nt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), we used a modified protocol to monitor the synthesis of tRNA +5 nucleotides products. The extended tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> runs at a higher position on the denaturing gel than extended tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup> due to different base modifications within the tRNA backbone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> is extended efficiently <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>ex vivo</italic> on the wt template, but not on the M and R templates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>B). A minor tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup> signal is apparent for the M template, but it is significantly enhanced in the R revertant. The point mutation in the PAS motif of the R template clearly enhances usage of the tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup> primer, both in the <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>ex vivo</italic> experiment. Apparently, optimization of the PAS motif enhances usage of the new tRNA primer, which underscores the importance of the PAS motif in reverse transcription initiation.
<fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Reverse transcription assays with <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed transcripts and vRNA&#x02013;tRNA complexes isolated from virions. (<bold>A</bold>) The differences in the anti-PBS and anti-PAS sequences between tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> and tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup> are boxed in the latter molecule. The anti-PAS and anti-PBS motifs are boxed in gray. The HIV-1 PAS and PBS motifs were mutated to complement the tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup> primer in the mutant PAS/PBS-lys1,2 (M). Long-term culturing of the mutant virus resulted in a revertant virus that gained replication capacity by a point mutation in the PAS motif (R). The U to C mutation stabilizes the interaction of the anti-PAS with the PAS motif. (<bold>B</bold>) Reverse transcription initiation of HIV-1 leader RNA transcripts. tRNA primers were annealed to the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed wt, mutant (M) and revertant (R) transcripts or the vRNA&#x02013;tRNA complexes were isolated from the corresponding virions. Primers were extended by addition of HIV-1 RT enzyme and <sup>32</sup>P-dCTP for the <italic>in vitro</italic> extension assay or dTTP, dGTP and <sup>32</sup>P-dCTP for <italic>ex vivo</italic> extension. This results in the extension of the tRNA primer with 1 and 5&#x02009;nt, respectively. The extended primers were separated on a denaturing polyacrylamide gel. The tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> product runs at a higher position in the gel than the tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup> product due to different base modification.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm046f9"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Initiation of HIV-1 reverse transcription is a highly regulated process in which the tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> primer has to interact with different sequence motifs in the template; the PBS for binding and the upstream PAS motif for initiation of reverse transcription. In this study, we observed that sequences downstream of the PBS also affect the initiation of reverse transcription. The 3&#x02032; leader domain could encode additional regulatory sequence motifs, but it is more likely that the observed effects are due to conformational changes in the leader RNA. First, 3&#x02032; sequences may affect the LDI-BMH riboswitch and consequently PBS or PAS availability. We ruled out this possibility by testing specific LDI-BMH mutants. Second, 3&#x02032; sequences could affect the accessibility of the PAS motif, and thus affect reverse transcription initiation. Several lines of evidence support this explanation. The 3&#x02032; sequences inhibit the initiation of reverse transcription for the wt template, but not for a designed PAS-exposed mutant. Furthermore, the variation in efficiency was observed exclusively for the tRNA and 1/2 tRNA primers, and not for DNA/RNA oligonucleotide primers. These combined results demonstrate that differential PAS accessibility is underlying differences in the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation of 3&#x02032;-extended templates.</p><p>We were unable to define a precise structural rearrangement of the PAS motif that causes the inhibitory effect of 3&#x02032; sequences. Mfold was used to calculate the exposure of the PAS motif, but this did not provide an explanation in terms of base pairing. This could be due to the fact that Mfold is a secondary structure prediction program that will miss effects at the tertiary structure level. It also remains unclear why the shortest 202 transcript displays the lowest efficiency in reverse transcription initiation. This has in fact also been observed in previous studies, and it seems that sequences 3&#x02032; of the PBS are required for efficient reverse transcription initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). We argue that the stimulatory effect of the exposed PAS motif is nullified because the U5-leader stem cannot fold properly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>We also analyzed the role of the PAS motif in the context of a tRNA-switch in an evolved virus variant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). An acquired mutation in the PAS motif stabilizes base pairing with the anti-PAS motif of the new tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup>primer. This PAS adaptation increased tRNA<sup>lys1,2</sup>-primed reverse transcription initiation <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>ex vivo</italic>, confirming the importance of the PAS motif in tRNA usage.</p><p>Several HIV-1 RNA&#x02013;tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> interactions have been proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11 B12 B13 B14 B15 B16 B17 B18 B19 B20">11&#x02013;20</xref>). Chemical and enzymatic RNA structure probing suggested that the tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> anticodon loop pairs with the A-rich loop located upstream and adjacent to the PBS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41 B42 B43">41&#x02013;43</xref>). However, a recent publication by Goldschmidt <italic>et al</italic>. argues that this interaction is exclusive for the unusual MAL isolate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). The same authors performed chemical probing of the PBS structure with and without an annealed tRNA primer, and obtained no evidence for the PAS&#x02013;anti-PAS interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). However, we argued that the PAS&#x02013;tRNA interaction is transient in nature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Furthermore, it is quite possible that this relative late initiation step is facilitated by the RT enzyme, which was lacking in these experiments.</p><p>The results obtained in the current study seem to contradict the results described in two other studies. In our assays, the efficiencies of reverse transcription initiation on different templates are equal for an RNA oligonucleotide primer (and a DNA primer). This contrasts with the results of Goldschmidt <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>) and Iwatani <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Goldschmidt <italic>et al</italic>. showed that tRNA-primed (&#x02212;)strand synthesis on PAS-mutated templates is equal to RNA oligonucleotide-primed (&#x02212;)strand synthesis, which seems to contradict the proposed role of the PAS motif. However, close examination of their results indicates that the elongation phase of reverse transcription is affected rather than initiation. Similarly, Iwatani <italic>et al</italic>. observed equal (&#x02212;)strand synthesis on a 3&#x02032;-truncated set of transcripts with a tRNA or RNA primer. They also measured full-length (&#x02212;)strand synthesis, which is the sum of initiation and elongation efficiencies. We think that primer extension measured by single nucleotide addition, as used in our assays, is a better measure for the efficiency of reverse transcription initiation.</p><p>Previous research has presented evidence for the regulation of reverse transcription initiation by occlusion and exposure of the PAS sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18 B19 B20 B21">18&#x02013;21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>). The importance of the PAS motif is underscored by its conservation among all retroviridae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>), and the PAS motif turned out to be critical in attempts to modify tRNA-usage of HIV-1 by alteration of the PBS motif (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). Here we present evidence that HIV-1 transcript length affects the initiation of reverse transcription via variation in the accessibility of the PAS element. These results emphasize the important role of the PAS motif for interaction with the tRNA<sup>lys3</sup> primer in HIV-1 reverse transcription.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank Dr D. Stammers for the gift of purified HIV-1 RT enzyme (obtained through the MRC AIDS Reagent Project). RNA studies in the Berkhout lab are sponsored by ZonMw (VICI-grant) and NWO-Chemical Sciences (TOP-grant). The Open Access publication charge was waived by Oxford University Press.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Telesnitsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Coffin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Varmus</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reverse transcriptase and the generation of retroviral DNA</article-title><source>Retroviruses</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>160</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varmus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanstrom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Teich</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Varmus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication of retroviruses</article-title><source>RNA tumor viruses. Molecular biology of tumor viruses</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>512</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aiyar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobrinik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Skalka</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of initiation of reverse transcription of retroviruses</article-title><source>Reverse Transcriptase</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trono</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Partial reverse transcripts in virions from human immunodeficiency and murine leukemia viruses</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1992</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>4893</fpage><lpage>4900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1378513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lori</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Veronese</surname><given-names>FDM</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vico</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lusso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Reitz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral DNA carried by human immunodeficiency virus type 1 virions</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1992</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>5067</fpage><lpage>5074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1378514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arts</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wainberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA found in human immunodeficiency virus type 1 particles may not be required for infectivity</article-title><source>J. Gen. Virol</source><year>1994</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1605</fpage><lpage>1613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7517431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oude Essink</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV-1 reverse transcriptase discriminates against non-self tRNA primers</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8951374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Khorchid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wainberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primer tRNALys3 on the viral genome exists in unextended and two-base extended forms within mature human immunodeficiency virus type 1</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1997</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>726</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8985405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oude Essink</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural requirements for the binding of tRNA Lys3 to reverse transcriptase of the human immunodeficiency virus type 1</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>23867</fpage><lpage>23874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7559565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tisne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roques</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dardel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The annealing mechanism of HIV-1 reverse transcription primer onto the viral genome</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>3588</fpage><lpage>3595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14602716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhof</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Massire</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Grice</surname><given-names>SFJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for the specificity of the initiation of HIV-1 reverse transcription</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1038</fpage><lpage>1048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10022845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of the U5-PBS of a novel HIV-1 reveals multiple interactions between the tRNA and RNA genome required for initiation of reverse transcription</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>1998</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9630246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleotide substitutions within U5 are critical for efficient reverse transcription of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 with a primer binding site complementary to tRNAHis</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1997</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>6315</fpage><lpage>6322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9261348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanchy</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Isel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Grice</surname><given-names>SFJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of the HIV-1 reverse transcription complex during initiation of DNA synthesis</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>12306</fpage><lpage>12312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10766870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arts</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stetor</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rausch</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>North</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wohrl</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goody</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Initiation of (-) strand DNA synthesis from tRNALys3 on lentiviral RNAs: implications of specific HIV-1 RNA-tRNALys3 interactions inhibiting primer utilization by retroviral reverse trancriptases</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>10063</fpage><lpage>10068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8816751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wainberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of modifying the tRNALys3 anticodon on the initiation of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 reverse transcription</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1996</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>4700</fpage><lpage>4706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8676496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Musier-Forsyth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient initiation of HIV-1 reverse transcription in vitro. Requirement for RNA sequences downstream of the primer binding site abrogated by nucleocapsid protein-dependent primer-template interactions</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>14185</fpage><lpage>14195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12560327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Groot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Initiation of HIV-1 reverse transcription is regulated by a primer activation signal</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>31247</fpage><lpage>31256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11384976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The tRNA primer activation signal in the HIV-1 genome is important for initiation and processive elongation of reverse transcription</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>2002</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>2329</fpage><lpage>2339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11836411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Switching the in vitro tRNA usage of HIV-1 by simultaneous adaptation of the PBS and PAS</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12003495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huthoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bugala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barciszewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the importance of the primer activation signal for initiation of tRNA(lys3)-primed reverse transcription of the HIV-1 RNA genome</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>5186</fpage><lpage>5194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12930970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbink</surname><given-names>TEM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beerens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forced selection of a human immunodeficiency virus type 1 variant that uses a non-self tRNA primer for reverse transcription: involvement of viral RNA sequences and the reverse transcriptase enzyme</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>10706</fpage><lpage>10714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freund</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulme</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Litvak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarrago-Litvak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Initiation of HIV-2 reverse transcription: a secondary structure model of the RNA-tRNA(Lys3) duplex</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>2757</fpage><lpage>2765</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11433020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooms</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beerens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Huthoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro evidence that the untranslated leader of the HIV-1 genome is an RNA checkpoint that regulates multiple functions through conformational changes</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>19967</fpage><lpage>19975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11896057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and function of the human immunodeficiency virus leader RNA</article-title><source>Prog. Nucleic Acid Res. Mol. Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8768071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baudin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Isel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Darlix</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional sites in the 5&#x02032; region of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 RNA form defined structural domains</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>229</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8429553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbink</surname><given-names>TEM</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel long distance base-pairing interaction in human immunodeficiency virus type 1 RNA occludes the gag start codon</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>11601</fpage><lpage>11611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12458192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huthoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two alternating structures for the HIV-1 leader RNA</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11214176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huthoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the TAR hairpin affect the equilibrium between alternative conformations of the HIV-1 leader RNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>2594</fpage><lpage>2600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11410668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laughrea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kissing-loop model of HIV-1 genome dimerization: HIV-1 RNAs can assume alternative dimeric forms, and all sequences upstream or downstream of hairpin 248-271 are dispensable for dimer formation</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1996</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1589</fpage><lpage>1598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8634290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paillart</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Skripkin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A loop-loop &#x0201c;kissing&#x0201d; complex is the essential part of the dimer linkage of genomic HIV-1 RNA</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>5572</fpage><lpage>5577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8643617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooms</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huthoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A riboswitch regulates RNA dimerization and packaging in human immunodeficiency virus type 1 virions</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>10814</fpage><lpage>10819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaver</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Klasens</surname><given-names>BIF</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wamel</surname><given-names>JLB</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A conserved hairpin motif in the R-U5 region of the human immunodeficiency virus type 1 RNA genome is essential for replication</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1997</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>2346</fpage><lpage>2356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9032371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbink</surname><given-names>TEM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooms</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haasnoot</surname><given-names>PCJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The HIV-1 leader RNA conformational switch regulates RNA dimerization but does not regulate mRNA translation</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>9058</fpage><lpage>9066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15966729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3406</fpage><lpage>3415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oude Essink</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fidelity of reverse transcription differs in reactions primed with RNA versus DNA primers</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10087443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wamel</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The leader of the HIV-1 RNA genome forms a compactly folded tertiary structure</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient extension of a misaligned tRNA-primer during replication of the HIV-1 retrovirus</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1319</fpage><lpage>1326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7538660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandok</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Laughrea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parniak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wainberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of sequences downstream of the primer binding site that are important for efficient replication of human immunodeficiency virus type 1</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1997</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>6003</fpage><lpage>6010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9223491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wainberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanistic studies of early pausing events during initiation of HIV-1 reverse transcription</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>21309</fpage><lpage>21315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9694891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modified nucleotides of tRNA(3Lys) modulate primer/template loop-loop interaction in the initiation complex of HIV-1 reverse transcription</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>25269</fpage><lpage>25272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7503978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elgavish</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>VanLoock</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring three-dimensional structures of the HIV-1 RNA/tRNALys3 initiation complex</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9878419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanistic aspects of HIV-1 reverse transcription initiation</article-title><source>Rev. Med. Virol</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11787082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Paillart</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigourd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubertin</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural variability of the initiation complex of HIV-1 reverse transcription</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>35923</fpage><lpage>35931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15194685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehresmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does the HIV-1 primer activation signal interact with tRNA(3)(Lys) during the initiation of reverse transcription?</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>859</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12560480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strict regulation of HIV-1 reverse transcription</article-title><source>Curr. Top. Virol</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>127</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aiyar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobrinik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction between retroviral U5 RNA and the T psi C loop of the tRNA(Trp) primer is required for efficient initiation of reverse transcription</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1992</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>2464</fpage><lpage>2472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1548772</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
