<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17062617</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1781148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl804</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pristionchus.org: a genome-centric database of the nematode satellite species <italic>Pristionchus pacificus</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dieterich</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roeseler</surname><given-names>Waltraud</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sobetzko</surname><given-names>Patrick</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>Ralf J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><aff><institution>Department of Evolutionary Biology, Max-Planck-Institute for Developmental Biology</institution><addr-line>Spemannstrasse 35-37, 72076 T&#x000fc;bingen, Germany</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +49 7071 601 405; Fax: +49 7071 601 498; Email: <email>christoph.dieterich@tuebingen.mpg.de</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><p><sup>*</sup>Correspondence may also be addressed to Ralf J. Sommer. Tel: +49 7071 601 371; Fax: +49 7071 601 498; Email: <email>ralf.sommer@tuebingen.mpg.de</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D498</fpage><lpage>D502</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2006 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Comparative studies have been of invaluable importance to the understanding of evolutionary biology. The evolution of developmental programs can be studied in nematodes at a single cell resolution given their fixed cell lineage. We have established <italic>Pristionchus pacificus</italic> as a major satellite organism for evolutionary developmental biology relative to <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, the model nematode. Online genomic information to support studies in this satellite system can be accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pristionchus.org"/>. Our web resource offers diverse content covering genome browsing, genetic and physical maps, similarity searches, a community platform and assembly details. Content will be continuously improved as we annotate the <italic>P.pacificus</italic> genome, and will be an indispensable resource for <italic>P.pacificus</italic> genomics.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The nematode <italic>Pristionchus pacificus</italic> was established as a comparative counterpart to the reference nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. Direct comparisons in development down to the single cell level are feasible as both nematodes follow distinct fixed programs of cell divisions and cell deaths (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>). Similar to <italic>C.elegans</italic>, <italic>P.pacificus</italic> is an ideal system for forward genetics given its hermaphroditic mode of reproduction and other advantages, such as short generation time, high brood size and the availability of genetic tools. Our satellite system <italic>P.pacificus</italic> has and continues to deliver exciting examples of differences to <italic>C.elegans</italic> in organ development, behavior and ecology [for review, see Ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>)].</p><p><italic>P.pacificus</italic> is a member of the Diplogastridae family, a monophyletic group that possibly includes more than 300 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>). Some diplogastrids show unique morphological features such as mouth form dimorphisms in adult hermaphrodites. The phylogenetic lineages of <italic>P.pacificus</italic> and <italic>C.elegans</italic> have probably diverged 200&#x02013;300 million years ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>). Given their long phylogenetic separation, most conservation signal has vanished on the nucleotide level and protein similarities are at an average level of &#x0223c;60% identity. Preliminary gene order analysis suggests that there is only limited conserved microsynteny between chromosomes of <italic>C.elegans</italic> and <italic>P.pacificus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>). Comparisons of both species may therefore yield valuable insights into the evolution of function relative to divergence in sequence and gene order.</p><p>The genomics era was heralded for <italic>P.pacificus</italic> with the announcement of an NHGRI-funded genome sequencing initiative (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhgri.nih.gov/12511858"/>). The project will be finished in late 2006 and is complemented by a toolkit encompassing a high-density genetic linkage map and physical map (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). All aforementioned genomics resources were bundled and made available online on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.pristionchus.org"/>, our web portal for <italic>P.pacificus</italic> genomics. Genetic and physical map services were moved from the discontinued AppaDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>) to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pristionchus.org"/>.</p><sec><title>Web portal</title><p>The online resource has a consistent layout for each page (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). A navigation bar can be found at the top of each page, a news section to the left and the actual content fills the remaining part of the screen. The navigation bar represents the division of the website into six sections: The Genome&#x02014;providing access to genome assemblies and annotation, BLAST&#x02014;similarity searches against various <italic>Pristionchus</italic> databases, Maps&#x02014;featuring a versatile map viewer of the genetic and physical map, Sequence retrieval&#x02014;download functions, WikiOnchus&#x02014;a community portal, and People&#x02014;a directory of researchers active in the field. Sections are either self-explanatory or provide help pages to the web user.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Overview of web portal division. The Navigation bar is placed to the top of the web page. There is a news board to the left and the main content below the navigation bar. The welcome page is shown, which features an introductory text as to the concepts of comparative evolutionary studies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl804f1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Genome</title><p>We put a preliminary draft assembly plus annotations (repetitive elements, gene predictions, protein similarities) together, which will be subject to future changes. Web users have access to these preliminary data via the Generic Genome Browser framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>), an open-source genome viewing software. Many nematologists are familiar with the Generic Genome Browser framework as it is a key component of Wormbase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>). At the time of writing, the <italic>P.pacificus</italic> genome extends over &#x0223c;4000 supercontigs. Alignments of expressed sequence tags and predicted coding sequences are placed onto these supercontigs. Repetitive elements based on the RECON algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>) and local protein-level similarities to other species are also integrated. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> shows an example of Supercontig 41 containing the homeotic gene <italic>Ppa-lin-39</italic> and corresponding annotations.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Graphical display of <italic>Pristionchus</italic> genome annotation. We employ the highly customizable Generic Genome Browser framework for viewing, analyzing and exporting local sequence annotation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl804f2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Similarity searches</title><p>BLAST searches are a long-standing standard to extract biologically meaningful sequence similarities. This section of the website offers extensive search capabilities of the genomic sequence from <italic>P.pacificus</italic> and related species, such as <italic>Pristionchus maupasi</italic> and <italic>Pristionchus entomophagus</italic>. The Mapping tool provides details on the position of contigs within supercontigs. Furthermore, BAC and Fosmid end mapping onto the genome may be accessed from here as well. Alternatively, one could consult the ContigGraphViewer, a JAVA applet, for a graphical representation of BAC and Fosmid end mappings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>ContigGraphViewer&#x02014;a JAVA applet for graphically representing long-distance relations in the <italic>Pristionchus</italic> genome assembly. BAC and Fosmid end mappings onto contigs are shown as a graph where vertices constitute contigs and arcs carry BAC or Fosmid labels.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl804f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Genetic and physical map</title><p>A major contribution to the success of our model system is the availability of a high-density genetic map (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>). A physical map build from AFLP fingerprints of BAC ends complements this map (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). Both maps are interconnected as many polymorphic markers were generated in BAC end sequences.</p><p>The CMap framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>) provides immediate access to both maps. CMap is a generic open-source map viewer, which offers a multitude of functions to view, compare and download map data. Both maps are manually curated and constantly updated once new markers become available. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> shows a comparative view of genetic and physical map for Chromosome I.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Comparative map view&#x02014;genetic map of Chromosome I is shown in conjunction with all contigs of the physical map that have a corresponding SSCP marker.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl804f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sequence retrieval</title><p>To facilitate local analyses beyond the functionality offered by this web site, complementary sequence data can be retrieved from this section. This part of the web site will undergo many update cycles as more genome sequence and annotation accumulates.</p></sec><sec><title>WikiOnchus</title><p>WikiOnchus constitutes a <italic>Pristionchus</italic> community forum, which is based on the MediaWiki system (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mediawiki.org"/>). WikiOnchus contents are open to all web users. However, editing of pages is restricted to a group of trusted friends of <italic>Pristionchus</italic>. If you are new to nematodes in general and <italic>Pristionchus</italic> in particular, you may find our selection of introductory texts very helpful (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pristionchus.org/wikionchus/index.php/The_beginner%27s_guide_to_the_Pristionchus_universe"/>). Other texts get experimentalists introduced to material and methods of <italic>P.pacificus</italic>. There is also an inventory of <italic>Pristionchus</italic> strains under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pristionchus.org/wikionchus/index.php/Pristionchus_strain_list"/>. If you want to contribute to the growing knowledge base, please contact the first author of this paper.</p></sec><sec><title>Pristionchus people</title><p>Watch how the community is growing and where former lab members set up their own research. An almost complete directory of the <italic>Pristionchus</italic> community gives an idea on active research areas.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Our presented web portal is a unifying resource of <italic>Pristionchus</italic> genomics bringing together genome databases, analyses and visualizations thereof. <italic>P.pacificus</italic> is a well-established satellite organism to <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic> species and offers significant amenities such as the comprehensive tools and resources that were outlined in this article. We are certain that pristionchus.org will meet all requirements with regard to <italic>Pristionchus</italic> genomics of researchers in nematology and beyond.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by the Max Planck Society.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement.</italic> None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of nematode vulval fate patterning</article-title><source>Dev. Biol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8606000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Pristionchus pacificus</italic>: a well-rounded nematode</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16700067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Lieven</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudhaus</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative and functional morphology of the buccal cavity of Diplogastrina (Nematoda) and a first outline of the phylogeny of this taxon</article-title><source>J. Zoolog. Syst. Evol. Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pires-daSilva</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation of the global sex determination gene tra-1 in distantly related nematodes</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1198</fpage><lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15155582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eizinger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandakumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Limited microsynteny between the genomes of <italic>Pristionchus pacificus</italic> and C<italic>aenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2553</fpage><lpage>2560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12736304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandakumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raddatz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kipping</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pires-daSilva</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A BAC-based genetic linkage map of the nematode <italic>Pristionchus pacificus</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesse</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggers-Perebolte</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buntjer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Meulen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrated physical and genetic map of the nematode <italic>Pristionchus pacificus</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Genet. Genomics</source><year>2003</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12884007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>G.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahlow</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geisler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AppaDB: an AcedB database for the nematode satellite organism <italic>Pristionchus pacificus</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>D421</fpage><lpage>D422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caudy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arva</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The generic genome browser: a building block for a model organism system database</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoshechkin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastiani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieri</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blasiar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canaran</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WormBase: better software, richer content</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D475</fpage><lpage>D478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated <italic>de novo</italic> identification of repeat sequence families in sequenced genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12176934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polacco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cMap: the comparative genetic map viewer</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12584129</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
