<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488851</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1920237</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm145</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Nucleic Acid Enzymes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> DNA ligases C and D</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>Stewart</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Molecular Biology Program, Sloan-Kettering Institute, New York, NY 10021, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>212 639 7145</phone><fax>212 717 3623</fax><email>s-shuman@ski.mskcc.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3631</fpage><lpage>3645</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> encodes a single NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent DNA ligase and six putative ATP-dependent ligases. Two of the ligases are homologs of LigD, a bacterial enzyme that catalyzes end-healing and end-sealing steps during nonhomologous end joining (NHEJ). <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigD1 and AtuLigD2 are composed of a central ligase domain fused to a C-terminal polymerase-like (POL) domain and an N-terminal 3&#x02032;-phosphoesterase (PE) module. Both LigD proteins seal DNA nicks, albeit inefficiently. The LigD2 POL domain adds ribonucleotides or deoxyribonucleotides to a DNA primer-template, with rNTPs being the preferred substrates. The LigD1 POL domain has no detectable polymerase activity. The PE domains catalyze metal-dependent phosphodiesterase and phosphomonoesterase reactions at a primer-template with a 3&#x02032;-terminal diribonucleotide to yield a primer-template with a monoribonucleotide 3&#x02032;-OH end. The PE domains also have a 3&#x02032;-phosphatase activity on an all-DNA primer-template that yields a 3&#x02032;-OH DNA end. <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> ligases C2 and C3 are composed of a minimal ligase core domain, analogous to <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> LigC (another NHEJ ligase), and they display feeble nick-sealing activity. Ligation at DNA double-strand breaks <italic>in vitro</italic> by LigD2, LigC2 and LigC3 is stimulated by bacterial Ku, consistent with their proposed function in NHEJ.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>DNA ligases are ubiquitous enzymes that seal DNA nicks via three sequential nucleotidyl transfer reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). In the first step, nucleophilic attack on the &#x003b1; phosphorus of ATP or NAD<sup>+</sup> by ligase results in release of PP<sub>i</sub> or NMN and formation of a covalent ligase-adenylate intermediate in which AMP is linked via a phosphoamide (P&#x02013;N) bond to N&#x003b6; of a lysine. In the second step, the AMP is transferred to the 5&#x02032; end of the 5&#x02032; phosphate-terminated DNA strand to form a DNA-adenylate intermediate. In the third step, ligase catalyzes attack by the 3&#x02032;-OH of the nick on DNA-adenylate to join the two polynucleotides and liberate AMP.</p><p>DNA ligases are grouped into two families, ATP-dependent ligases and NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent ligases, according to the cofactor required for ligase-adenylate formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). An NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent DNA ligase (LigA) is found in every bacterial species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). The structures of several LigA enzymes have been determined by X-ray crystallography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5 B6">3&#x02013;6</xref>). They contain the ligase catalytic core, composed of a nucleotidyltransferase (NTase) domain and an OB-fold domain, flanked by an N-terminal domain (called domain Ia) and three C-terminal domains: a tetracysteine Zn-finger, a helix-hairpin-helix (HhH) domain and a BRCT domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Domain Ia is unique to NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent ligases and required for the reaction of LigA with NAD<sup>+</sup> to form the ligase-adenylate intermediate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). LigA is essential in all bacteria tested to date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8 B9 B10 B11 B12 B13">8&#x02013;13</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Multiple DNA ligases of <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic>. The Atu LigA, LigB, LigC and LigD polypeptides are depicted (left panel) in cartoon form with the N-termini on the left and the C-termini on the right. The core ligase catalytic domains, composed of nucleotidyltransferase (NTase) and OB modules, are shown as rectangles. Flanking domains of known structure or imputed function (variously drawn as ellipses or capsules) are discussed in the text. Aliquots (5&#x02009;&#x000b5;g) of the nickel-agarose preparations of PaeLigD, AtuLigD1, AtuLigD2, AtuLigC2, AtuLigC3 and AtuLigC1 were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. The Coomassie blue-stained gel is shown in the right panel. The positions and sizes (in kDa) of marker polypeptides are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f1"/></fig></p><p>The first identification and characterization of a bacterial ATP-dependent ligase was reported in 1997 for <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). In the ensuing years, putative ATP-dependent ligases have been annotated in scores of bacterial species that have been subjected to genome sequencing, though only a few of them have been studied biochemically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15 B16 B17 B18 B19">15&#x02013;19</xref>). <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> have an exceptionally rich assortment of ATP-dependent ligases (named LigB, LigC and LigD) in addition to NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent LigA. Whereas mycobacterial LigA and LigB display vigorous ligase activity, LigD and LigC are relatively feeble at sealing nicked DNAs <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Genetic and biochemical analyses implicate LigD and LigC in a bacterial pathway of nonhomologous end joining (NHEJ) that is strictly dependent on a bacterial homolog of the NHEJ factor Ku (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16 B17 B18 B19 B20">16&#x02013;20</xref>). The fact that Ku and LigD are jointly encoded by dozens of diverse bacterial genera implies that NHEJ is broadly relevant to bacterial physiology, notwithstanding that neither Ku nor LigD are essential in <italic>Mycobacterium, Bacillus</italic> or <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> under laboratory growth conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16 B17 B18">16&#x02013;18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). However, Ku and LigD are important in protecting <italic>Bacillus</italic> spores against DNA damage incurred under conditions of environmental stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>).</p><p><italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> is a soil bacterium that parasitizes plants and causes crown gall disease. The <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>) consists of a 2.8-Mb circular chromosome, a 2.1-Mb linear chromosome, a 543-kb plasmid (pAT) and a 214-kb virulence plasmid (pTi). Transfer of the Ti plasmid to the host and integration of T DNA into the plant genome are the critical events underlying crown gall disease. T DNA integration is believed to occur via NHEJ, yet ablation of the Ku and Lig4 proteins that comprise the NHEJ machinery of the plant host has no effect on T DNA integration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). One of the striking features of the <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> proteome is the presence of six putative ATP-dependent DNA ligases in addition to the canonical NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent LigA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The predicted product of ORF 0840 on the circular chromosome (which we now designate AtuLigB) is a 541-aa polypeptide homologous to <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> LigB. AtuLigB (like MtuLigB) consists of a core ATP-dependent ligase domain fused to an N-terminal segment that resembles the DNA-binding domain (DBD) of human DNA ligase 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). AtuLigB and MtuLigB are members of a distinct ligase clade that includes mammalian DNA ligase III, archaeal ligases, poxvirus ligases and LigB homologs from diverse bacteria (e.g. <italic>Caulobacter crescentus, Pseudomonas putida, Xanthomonas campestris, Myxococcus xanthus</italic> and many others).</p><p>In the present study, we focus on two <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> homologs of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> LigD, which we designated AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2, respectively. Like PaeLigD, AtuLigD1 (771-aa) and AtuLigD2 (840-aa) consist of a central ATP-dependent ligase domain fused to an N-terminal phosphoesterase module and a C-terminal polymerase-like domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28 B29 B30 B31 B32 B33">28&#x02013;33</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> LigD is composed of the same three domains, albeit arranged in a different order (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16 B17 B18 B19">16&#x02013;19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). AtuLigD1 is encoded by ORF 4632 on the linear chromosome, which is immediately adjacent to ORF 4631 that encodes a homolog of Ku (hereafter named AtuKu1). This operon arrangement suggests an NHEJ function for AtuLigD1 and AtuKu1. AtuLigD2 is encoded by ORF 5055 on the AT plasmid. The AtuLigD2 gene is located next to an oppositely transcribed gene cluster (a putative operon) that encodes two other Ku homologs (ORFs 5049 and 5050; designated AtuKu2 and AtuKu3) and a homolog of mycobacterial LigC (ORF 5051, designated LigC2). There are two additional LigC paralogs in <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic>: one encoded on the AT plasmid (ORF 5097; LigC1) and another on the Ti plasmid (ORF 6090; LigC3). The AtuLigC paralogs are minimal ligases (345&#x02013;353-aa) consisting only of the nucleotidyltransferase and OB modules with no auxiliary flanking domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Genetic evidence implicates mycobacterial LigC (which is nonessential for bacterial growth) in a minor pathway of Ku-dependent NHEJ that is evident when the major LigD-dependent NHEJ pathway is ablated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). We can surmise that neither AtuLigD2, AtuKu2, AtuKu3, AtuLigC2, AtuLigC1 nor AtuLigC3 are essential for viability of <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic>, insofar as strains cured of pAT or pTi, or both plasmids, were reported to grow as well as a wild-type strain containing the pAT and pTi plasmids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>).</p><p>As an initial step in understanding how ligases D and C might contribute to a putative <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> NHEJ pathway, we purified and characterized Atu ligases D1, D2, C1, C2 and C3. We find that four of the five proteins (LigC1 being the exception) are able to seal a nicked duplex DNA substrate <italic>in vitro</italic>, albeit with relatively low turnover. We focus in detail on the additional enzymatic functions associated with AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2, especially their catalysis of 3&#x02032; end-healing reactions relevant to DNA repair, as described previously for <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28 B29 B30 B31 B32 B33">28&#x02013;33</xref>). Whereas AtuLigD2 has an associated polymerase activity, AtuLigD1 does not. We report that bacterial Ku stimulates the repair of DNA double-strand breaks <italic>in vitro</italic> by <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> ligases D2, C2 and C3.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Agrobacterium DNA ligases</title><p>A DNA encoding AtuLigD1 was PCR-amplified from <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain C58 genomic DNA (a gift of Dr Andrew Binns) using primers designed to introduce NheI sites at the start codon and 3&#x02032; of the stop codon. The PCR product was digested with NheI and inserted into pET28b (Novagen). DNA encoding AtuLigD2 was amplified using primers designed to introduce NdeI sites at the start site and 3&#x02032; of the stop codon. The PCR product was digested with NdeI and inserted into pET16b. DNAs encoding AtuLigC1, AtuLigC2 and AtuLigC3 were amplified by PCR with primers designed to introduce an NdeI site at the start site and a BamHI site 3&#x02032; of the stop codon. The PCR products were digested with NdeI and BamHI and inserted into pET16b. The inserts were sequenced completely to exclude the acquisition of unwanted changes during amplification and cloning.</p><p>The pET-AtuLig plasmids were transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> BL21(DE3). Cultures (1&#x02009;l) of <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3)/pET-AtuLig were grown at 37&#x000b0;C in Luria&#x02013;Bertani medium containing either 0.05&#x02009;mg/ml kanamycin (for AtuLigD1) or 0.1&#x02009;mg/ml ampicillin (for AtuLigD2) until the <italic>A</italic><sub>600</sub> reached 0.6. The cultures were adjusted to 0.5&#x02009;mM isopropyl-&#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactopyranoside and then incubated at 17&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;h. Cells were harvested by centrifugation and the pellets were stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. All subsequent steps were performed at 4&#x000b0;C. Thawed bacteria were resuspended in 50&#x02009;ml of lysis buffer (50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 1.5&#x02009;M NaCl, 10% glycerol, 15&#x02009;mM imidazole). Lysozyme and Triton X-100 were added to final concentrations of 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml and 0.1%, respectively. The lysates were sonicated to reduce viscosity and insoluble material was removed by centrifugation. The supernatants were applied to 2-ml columns of Ni<sup>2+</sup>-nitrilotriacetic acid-agarose (Qiagen, Chatsworth, CA, USA) that had been equilibrated with lysis buffer. The columns were washed with 50&#x02009;ml of lysis buffer and then eluted stepwise with 4-ml aliquots of buffer A (50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 0.4&#x02009;M NaCl, 10% glycerol) containing 50, 100, 200 and 500&#x02009;mM imidazole. The polypeptide compositions of the fractions were monitored by SDS-PAGE. The LigC and LigD proteins were recovered predominantly in the 200 and 500&#x02009;mM imidazole eluate fractions, respectively. Protein concentrations were determined by using the Bio-Rad dye reagent with bovine serum albumin as the standard. The recombinant protein preparations were stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. The yields were as follows: AtuLigC1 (32&#x02009;mg), AtuLigC2 (1.3&#x02009;mg), AtuLigC3 (2&#x02009;mg), AtuLigD1 (14&#x02009;mg) and AtuLigD2 (1&#x02009;mg).</p></sec><sec><title>Phosphoesterase domains of LigD1 and LigD2</title><p>Gene fragments encoding LigD1-(1&#x02013;186) and LigD2-(1&#x02013;193) (the PE domains) were amplified by PCR with sense strand primers that introduced an NdeI site at the start codon and antisense primers that introduced a new stop codon and a flanking BamHI site. The PCR products were digested with NdeI and BamHI and inserted into pET16b. Alanine mutations were introduced into the pET-AtuPE plasmids by overlap extension PCR. The pET-AtuPE plasmids were transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3). Induction of protein expression, preparation of soluble bacterial lysates, and purification of the recombinant PE proteins by Ni-agarose affinity chromatography were performed as described above for full-length Atu ligases. The PE proteins were recovered predominantly in the 200 and 500&#x02009;mM imidazole eluates. The yields from 200-ml cultures were as follows: AtuLigD1 PE (14&#x02009;mg) and AtuLigD2 PE (6&#x02009;mg).</p></sec><sec><title>Polymerase domains of LigD1 and LigD2</title><p>Gene fragments encoding LigD1-(536&#x02013;771) and LigD2-(569&#x02013;884) (the POL domains) were amplified by PCR from pET-AtuLigD plasmids with sense strand primers that introduced an NheI site at the new start codon for AtuLigD1 POL and an NdeI site at the new start codon for AtuLigD2 POL. The PCR products were restricted and inserted into pET28b (for AtuLigD1 POL) or pET16b (for AtuLigD2 POL). Protein expression, preparation of soluble bacterial lysates, and purification of the recombinant PE proteins by Ni-agarose affinity chromatography were performed as described above. The POL proteins were recovered predominantly in the 200&#x02009;mM imidazole eluates. The yields from 1-l cultures were as follows: AtuLigD1 POL (6&#x02009;mg) and AtuLigD2 POL (15&#x02009;mg).</p></sec><sec><title>Purification of Ku</title><p>The <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> gene encoding the 293-aa Ku protein (PA2150) was amplified by PCR from genomic DNA with primers designed to introduce an NdeI site at the start site and a BamHI site 3&#x02032; of the stop codon. The PCR product was digested with NdeI and BamHI and inserted into pET16b. Induction of Ku expression, preparation of a soluble bacterial lysate from a 1-l culture, and purification of the recombinant Ku by Ni-agarose affinity chromatography were performed as described above, except that the Ni-agarose column was eluted stepwise with buffers containing 50, 100, 200, 500 and 1300&#x02009;mM imidazole. Ku was recovered predominantly in the 500 and 1300&#x02009;mM imidazole eluates, which contained 2.3 and 1.2&#x02009;mg of protein, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Glycerol gradient sedimentation</title><p>Aliquots (40&#x02009;&#x000b5;g) of the Ni-agarose preparations of AtuLigC, AtuLigD or AtuLigD PE or POL proteins, or PaeKu were mixed with catalase (30&#x02009;&#x000b5;g), bovine serum albumin (30&#x02009;&#x000b5;g) and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> (30&#x02009;&#x000b5;g). The mixtures were applied to 4.8-ml 15&#x02013;30% glycerol gradients containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 0.2&#x02009;M NaCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA, 2.5&#x02009;mM DTT, 0.1% Triton X-100. The gradients were centrifuged at 50 000 r.p.m. in a Beckman SW50 rotor for 16&#x02009;h at 4&#x000b0;C. Fractions (&#x0223c;0.2&#x02009;ml) were collected from the bottoms of the tubes. The polypeptide compositions of the gradient fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. Aliquots of the fractions were assayed for ligase, POL or PE activity as specified in the figure legends.</p></sec><sec><title>Nick-sealing assay</title><p>A 24-bp DNA duplex containing a centrally placed 3&#x02032;-OH/5&#x02032;-PO<sub>4</sub> nick was formed by annealing a 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer DNA strand and an unlabeled 12-mer 3&#x02032;-OH strand to a complementary 24-mer DNA strand as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Ligation reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris buffer as specified, 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 pmol of <sup>32</sup>P-labeled nicked DNA substrate, 250&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP where specified, and ligases as specified were incubated for 20&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C. The reactions were quenched by adjusting the mixtures to 10&#x02009;mM EDTA and 48% formamide. The products were resolved by electrophoresis through a 15-cm 18% polyacrylamide gel containing 7&#x02009;M urea in TBE (90&#x02009;mM Tris-borate, 2.5&#x02009;mM EDTA). The products were visualized by autoradiography and quantified by scanning the gel with a Fujifilm BAS-2500 imaging apparatus.</p></sec><sec><title>3&#x02032;-Ribonuclease and 3&#x02032;-phosphomonoesterase assays</title><p>The 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D10R2 and D11p primer-templates were prepared as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Reaction mixtures (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 0.5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5&#x02009;pmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D10R2 or D11p primer-templates, and AtuLig PE domain as specified were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. The reactions were quenched by adjusting the mixtures to 7&#x02009;mM EDTA and 31% formamide. The products were resolved by electrophoresis through a 40-cm 18% polyacrylamide gel containing 7&#x02009;M urea in TBE.</p></sec><sec><title>Polymerase assay</title><p>Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M each of ATP, GTP, CTP and UTP (rNTPs) or 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M each of dATP, dGTP, dCTP and dTTP (dNTPs), 1 pmol 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer/24-mer primer-template, and AtuPOL proteins were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. The reactions were quenched by adjusting the mixtures to 10&#x02009;mM EDTA and 48% formamide. The products were resolved by electrophoresis through a 15-cm 18% polyacrylamide gel containing 7&#x02009;M urea in TBE.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title><italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigC paralogs</title><p>Ligases C1, C2 and C3 are 350-aa, 345-aa and 353-aa polypeptides composed of N-terminal nucleotidyltransferase and C-terminal OB domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Within the nucleotidyltransferase module is an adenylate-binding pocket composed of six motifs (I, Ia, III, IIIa, IV and V; highlighted in Supplemental Figure S1) that define the polynucleotide ligase/mRNA capping enzyme superfamily of covalent nucleotidyltransferases. Motif I (KWDGYR) includes the lysine nucleophile to which AMP becomes covalently linked in the first step of the ligase reaction. Motifs Ia, III, IIIa, IV and V contain conserved amino acids that contact AMP and play essential roles in one or more steps of the ligation pathway. Located near the C-terminus of the OB domain is motif VI, which is important for formation of the ligase-adenylate intermediate. Motif VI of the AtuLigC paralogs (RExQ) deviates from the canonical motif VI (RxDK) found in the majority of ATP-dependent ligases.</p><p>To evaluate the biochemical properties of the AtuLigC proteins, we produced them in <italic>E. coli</italic> as His<sub>10</sub>-AtuLigC fusions and purified them from soluble extracts by adsorption to nickel-agarose resin and elution with buffer containing imidazole. SDS-PAGE revealed that each preparation contained a predominant 40&#x02009;kDa polypeptide corresponding to His<sub>10</sub>-AtuLigC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). A synthetic duplex DNA substrate containing a single nick (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) was used to gauge the DNA-sealing activity of the AtuLigC proteins, which was evinced by the conversion of the 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer strand to a 24-mer product. We observed no nick-sealing activity for two independent preparations of recombinant AtuLigC1. Therefore, all further studies of AtuLigC were conducted with the LigC2 and LigC3 isozymes. AtuLigC2 catalyzed nick sealing in the absence of added ATP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A); this activity was ascribed to preformed LigC-AMP in the enzyme preparations. The extent of ATP-independent sealing was proportional to input AtuLigC2 and there was little accumulation of the AppDNA intermediate (which migrates &#x0223c;1.5&#x02009;nt steps slower than the 12-mer pDNA strand). From the slope of the titration curve, we estimated that ligase-AMP comprised 16% of the AtuLigC2 preparation. ATP-independent nick sealing by AtuLigC2 required a divalent cation cofactor, which could be manganese, magnesium or cobalt (not shown). Calcium, copper and zinc did not support nick sealing (not shown). Manganese-dependent sealing was optimal over a range of pH values from 6.0 to 8.0 in Tris-acetate or Tris-HCl buffers (not shown). Lowering the pH to 4.5 in Tris-acetate resulted in complete inhibition of sealing and the accumulation of DNA-adenylate (AppDNA) as the sole product (not shown).</p><p>ATP failed to stimulate AtuLigC2 nick-sealing activity under otherwise optimal conditions because it elicited the accumulation of high levels of the DNA-adenylate intermediate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). This effect was more pronounced when magnesium was the divalent cation cofactor. At the highest level of input AtuLigC2 tested in this experiment, in which nearly all the pDNA strand had reacted, AppDNA comprised 56% of total labeled DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, Mg<sup>2+</sup>). This ATP-dependent trapping phenomenon, which was described previously for eukaryotic viral DNA ligases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) and mycobacterial DNA ligases C and D (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), results from dissociation of the enzyme from the DNA-adenylate and immediate reaction of the free ligase with ATP to yield ligase-AMP, which cannot rebind to AppDNA and thus cannot catalyze the phosphodiester formation step (there being only one adenylate-binding pocket on the enzyme).
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Nick-sealing activity of AtuLigC2 and AtuLigC3. (<bold>A</bold>) Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing either 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5) (AtuLigC2) or 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0) (AtuLigC3), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 1&#x02009;pmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled nicked 24-mer DNA substrate (depicted at the top with the labeled 5&#x02032; nucleotide at the nick indicated by filled circle), and increasing amounts of AtuLigC2 (38, 75, 150, 300 and 600&#x02009;ng) or AtuLigC3 (50, 100, 200, 400 and 800&#x02009;ng) were incubated for 20&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C. Enzyme was omitted from a control reaction mixture (lane &#x02212;). The products were resolved by PAGE and visualized by autoradiography. (<bold>B</bold>) Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub> (left panel) or 5&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> (right panel), 250&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP, 1&#x02009;pmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled nicked 24-mer DNA substrate, and increasing amounts of AtuLigC2 (38, 75, 150, 300 and 600&#x02009;ng) were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. Enzyme was omitted from a control reaction mixture (lane &#x02212;). (<bold>C</bold>) Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub> (left panel) or MgCl<sub>2</sub> (right panel), 250&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP, 1&#x02009;pmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled nicked 24-mer DNA substrate, and increasing amounts of AtuLigC3 (50, 100, 200, 400 and 800&#x02009;ng) were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. Enzyme was omitted from a control reaction mixture (lane &#x02212;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f2"/></fig></p><p>AtuLigC3 reacted with the nicked substrate in the absence of ATP, but the major product was the AppDNA intermediate rather than the ligated 24-mer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). At the highest level of LigC3 tested, AppDNA comprised 41% of the labeled material while only 16% of the label was sealed 24-mer. From the slope of the titration curve, we estimated that 12% of the AtuLigC3 preparation was preformed ligase-AMP. Thus, AtuLigC3 appeared to dissociate readily from the AppDNA intermediate and was loathe to rebind and seal the adenylylated strand even in the absence of an ATP trap. ATP-independent sealing by AtuLigC3 was optimal at pH 6.0&#x02013;6.5 with manganese as the cofactor (not shown). Cobalt supported nick sealing by AtuLigC3, but magnesium was less active and calcium, copper and zinc were ineffective (not shown). Inclusion of ATP stimulated formation of the AppDNA intermediate (by at least a factor of 6, calculated from the extent of total product formation as a function of input LigC3), while suppressing formation of the ligated 24-mer (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>C-Mn<sup>2+</sup> and 2A). This effect was evident in the presence of manganese or magnesium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C).</p><p>The quaternary structures of AtuLigC2 and AtuLigC3 were examined by zonal velocity sedimentation in 15&#x02013;30% glycerol gradients. Marker proteins catalase (native size 248&#x02009;kDa), BSA (66&#x02009;kDa) and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> (12&#x02009;kDa) were included as internal standards in the gradients. The ligase activity profiles for AtuLigC2 and AtuLigC3 comprised single peak components sedimenting between BSA and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> (Supplementary Figure S2), which paralleled the abundance of the AtuLigC2 and AtuLigC3 polypeptides (not shown). A plot of the <italic>S</italic> values of the three standards versus fraction number yielded a straight line. We calculated <italic>S</italic> values of 3.4 for AtuLigC2 and 3.4 for AtuLigC3 by interpolation to the internal standard curves. The results are consistent with a monomeric quaternary structure for AtuLigC2 and AtuLigC3. In summary, these experiments show that <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigC2 and LigC3 resemble <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> LigC in that they have feeble DNA nick-sealing activity in the presence of ATP.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigD paralogs</title><p>LigD1 and LigD2 are 771-aa and 884-aa polypeptides composed of a central ligase domain flanked by putative N-terminal phosphoesterase (PE) and C-terminal polymerase (POL) domains. The ligase domains include all of the canonical nucleotidyltransferase motifs (Supplementary Figure S3). We produced AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 in <italic>E. coli</italic> as His<sub>10</sub>-AtuLigC fusions and purified them from soluble extracts by nickel-agarose chromatography. SDS-PAGE revealed that the LigD1 and LigD2 preparations contained major polypeptides of 90 and 102&#x02009;kDa, corresponding to the respective His-tagged LigD proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 migrated slightly faster and slower, respectively, during SDS-PAGE than did <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD (840-aa; &#x0223c;97&#x02009;kDa by SDS-PAGE).</p><p>AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 catalyzed nick sealing in the absence of added ATP, with little accumulation of AppDNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). From the slopes of the titration curves, we estimated that ligase-AMP comprised 5 and 27% of the AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 preparations, respectively. ATP-independent nick sealing by AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 required a divalent cation cofactor, which could be manganese, magnesium or cobalt. Calcium, copper and zinc did not support activity (data not shown). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B shows that inclusion of ATP stimulated the manganese-dependent activity of AtuLigD1 by a factor of 8 (calculated from the extent of total product formation as a function of input LigD1), with relatively little trapping of the AppDNA intermediate. In contrast, when magnesium was the divalent cation, the enzyme was 6-fold less reactive overall (as judged by consumption of substrate) and AppDNA was the majority product (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B, Mg<sup>2+</sup> versus Mn<sup>2+</sup>). ATP stimulated the manganese-dependent reaction of AtuLigD2 with nicked DNA by a factor of 8, with AppDNA accumulating at lower enzyme concentrations and ligated 24-mer predominating at higher levels of input LigD2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C). ATP trapping of the AppDNA intermediate during the LigD2 reaction was more pronounced in the presence of magnesium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C).
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Nick-sealing activity of AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2. (<bold>A</bold>) Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing either 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5) (AtuLigD1) or 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0) (AtuLigD2), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 pmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled nicked 24-mer DNA substrate (shown at the top), and increasing amounts of AtuLigD1 (63, 125, 250, 500 and 1000&#x02009;ng) or AtuLigD2 (31, 63, 125, 250, 500&#x02009;ng) were incubated for 20&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C. (<bold>B</bold>) Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub> (left panel) or MgCl<sub>2</sub> (right panel), 250&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP, 1 pmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled nicked 24-mer DNA substrate, and increasing amounts of AtuLigD1 (63, 125, 250, 500, 1000&#x02009;ng) were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. (<bold>C</bold>) Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub> (left panel) or MgCl<sub>2</sub> (right panel), 250&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP, 1 pmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled nicked 24-mer DNA substrate, and increasing amounts of AtuLigD2 (31, 63, 125, 250, 500&#x02009;ng) were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. Enzyme was omitted from control reaction mixtures (lanes &#x02013;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f3"/></fig></p><p>AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 were sedimented in 15&#x02013;30% glycerol gradients with internal markers catalase, BSA and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> (Supplementary Figure S4). The nick-sealing activity profiles for AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 comprised single peaks that coincided with the AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 polypeptides. We calculated <italic>S</italic> values of 4.5 for AtuLigD1 and 5.5 for AtuLigD2 by interpolation to the internal standard curves. These results are consistent with monomeric quaternary structures for AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2. (The <italic>S</italic> value of 4.5 for AtuLigD1 is slightly lower than expected for a globular protein of 90&#x02009;kDa, suggesting that it might have an elongated shape.)</p></sec><sec><title>Activities of the POL domain of <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigD2</title><p>The primary structure of the C-terminal domain of AtuLigD2 from aa 569 to 884 is similar throughout its length to the POL domain of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD (aa 533&#x02013;840) (Figure S3). In contrast, the C-terminal module of AtuLigD1 is truncated by 63-aa compared to AtuLigD2 (Figure S3). To assess what activities, if any, are associated with the AtuLigD2 and AtuLigD1 POL domains, we produced AtuLigD2-(569&#x02013;884) and AtuLigD1-(536&#x02013;771) in <italic>E. coli</italic> as His<sub>10</sub> fusions and purified them from soluble extracts by Ni-agarose chromatography. SDS-PAGE showed that the preparations were highly enriched with respect to the recombinant D2 and D1 POL domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, left panel). The LigD2 POL domain was capable of template-directed DNA or RNA synthesis, as gauged by its ability to extend a primer-template composed of a 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer DNA strand annealed to a complementary 24-mer strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, right panel). In contrast, the LigD1 POL domain displayed no polymerase activity with rNTP or dNTP substrates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, right panel). A mixing experiment revealed that primer extension by LigD2 POL was unaffected by addition of an equal amount of LigD1 POL (not shown); thus the inactivity of the LigD1 POL protein was not caused by an inhibitor in the preparation. We surmise that the C-terminal truncation of AtuLigD1 compromises its POL function. Thus, AtuLigD2 and AtuLigD1 are not functionally equivalent.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Recombinant LigD2 and LigD1 POL domains. (<bold>A</bold>) Aliquots (7&#x02009;&#x000b5;g) of the Ni-agarose preparations of the POL domains of AtuLigD2 and AtuLigD1 were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. The Coomassie blue-stained gel is shown in the <italic>left</italic> panel. Polymerase reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M rNTPs or dNTPs as specified, 50&#x02009;nM 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer/24-mer DNA primer-template (depicted at bottom) and 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;g of LigD2 or LigD1 POL as specified were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. The products were analyzed by denaturing PAGE. An autoradiograph of the gel is shown in the right panel. POL was omitted from the control reaction in lane &#x02212;. (<bold>B</bold>) Glycerol gradient sedimentation was performed as described under Experimental Procedures. Aliquots (15&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) of the odd-numbered fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE (top panel). The catalase, BSA, LigD2 POL and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> polypeptides are indicated. Polymerase activity was gauged by incubating 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l reaction mixtures containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M rNTPs, 1 pmol 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer/24-mer DNA primer-template and 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of the indicated gradient fractions at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. PAGE analysis of the primer extension products is shown in the bottom panel. (<bold>C</bold>) Metal specificity. Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M rNTPs, 50&#x02009;nM 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer/24-mer DNA primer-template, 156&#x02009;nM LigD2 POL, and either no divalent cation (&#x02013;) or 5&#x02009;mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Cd<sup>2+</sup>, Co<sup>2+</sup>, Cu<sup>2+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>, Mn<sup>2+</sup> or Zn<sup>2+</sup> were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f4"/></fig></p><p>The native size of the active LigD2 POL domain was gauged by glycerol gradient sedimentation. The 38&#x02009;kDa LigD2 POL polypeptide sedimented as a discrete component (peaking in fraction 19) between the BSA and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> markers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B, top panel), coincident with the peak of the templated ribonucleotide addition activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B, bottom panel). An <italic>S</italic> value of 3.7 for LigD2 POL was calculated by interpolation to the internal standard curve. These results are consistent with a monomeric quaternary structure for LigD2 POL.</p><p>Templated ribonucleotide addition by the POL domain required a divalent cation cofactor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). Testing various metals at 5&#x02009;mM concentration showed that activity, expressed as the percent of the input primer that had been extended, was optimal with manganese (89% extended) or cobalt (80% extended). Whereas most of the products formed in manganese were elongated by one or two nucleotides, the cobalt-directed products comprised a ladder extending to the end of the template strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). Magnesium was less effective (43% of primer extended) and the reaction was limited to a single step of rNMP addition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). Cadmium and copper were weak activators of the polymerase; calcium and zinc were ineffective (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). Manganese, cobalt and magnesium displayed relative activities and product distributions similar to that seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C over a concentration range of 0.3&#x02013;10&#x02009;mM (not shown).</p><p>Further characterization of the POL activity is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>. When provided with manganese and a mixture of the four dNTPs or rNTPs (100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M of each nucleotide), increasing concentrations of input POL catalyzed progressive elongation of the 12-mer primer to yield a ladder of products 13&#x02013;18&#x02009;nt long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A, left panel). Very little of the primer was elongated to the end of the template strand, even under conditions of POL excess when all of the primer had been extended. The efficiency of the extension reaction was quantified as the percent of the input 12-mer primer strand that was elongated by at least one nucleotide. A plot of primer utilization versus input POL showed that ribonucleotide substrates were preferred over deoxynucleotides by a factor of 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A, right panel).
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Preferential utilization of ribonucleotides by LigD2 POL. (<bold>A</bold>) Enzyme titration. Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 nM 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer/24-mer DNA primer-template, 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M rNTPs or dNTPs as specified, and increasing amounts of LigD2 POL (62, 125, 250, 500 and 1000&#x02009;ng, from left to right in each titration series, corresponding to 78, 156, 312, 625 and 1250 nM POL) were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. PAGE analysis of the primer extension products is shown in the left panel. POL was omitted from the control reaction in lane &#x02013;. The fraction of input primer extended by at least one nucleotide is plotted as a function of input POL in the right panel. (<bold>B</bold>) Kinetics of primer extension. Reaction mixtures (220&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 nM 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer/24-mer DNA primer-template, 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M rNTPs or dNTPs as specified, and 1.25&#x02009;&#x000b5;M LigD2 POL were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C. Aliquots (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) were withdrawn at the times specified and quenched immediately with EDTA/formamide. PAGE analysis of the primer extension products is shown in the left panels. The fraction of input primer extended by at least one nucleotide is plotted as a function of time in the right panel. (<bold>C</bold>) NTP concentration dependence. Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 nM 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled 12-mer/24-mer DNA primer-template, 1.25&#x02009;&#x000b5;M LigD2 POL and rNTPs or dNTPs as specified were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f5"/></fig></p><p>A kinetic analysis of primer extension by excess POL in the presence of 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M rNTPs or dNTPs is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B. The first cycle of ribonucleotide addition was rapid, with nearly all of the 12-mer primer elongated to 13-mer (with some 14-mer) at 10 s, the earliest timepoint in the experiment. We estimated from the 10 s datum an apparent rate constant of &#x02265;0.21&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the first rNMP incorporation step. It was apparent that the second cycle of templated ribonucleotide addition was much slower, insofar as the 13-mer product formed within 10&#x02009;s was gradually converted to 14-mer or longer product over the subsequent 5&#x02009;min. By quantifying the flux through the 13-mer species (not shown), we estimated a rate constant of 0.016&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the second cycle of rNMP incorporation. The 13-fold rate decrement after the first cycle of ribonucleotide addition by AtuLigD2 POL agrees well with the findings for <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD POL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>), which becomes progressively less active with each ribonucleotide added at the 3&#x02032; primer terminus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The kinetics of dNMP incorporation by AtuLigD2 POL were much slower than extension with rNTPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). The first cycle of dNMP addition displayed a pseudo-first order pattern with an apparent rate constant of 0.0062&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Thus, by comparing the rate constants, LigD2 POL is at least 34-fold faster at incorporating a ribonucleotide than a deoxynucleotide during the first reaction cycle at a DNA primer end.</p><p>The effect of limiting the rNTP pool is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C (top panel), where we see that LigD2 POL was remarkably efficient at scavenging ribonucleotide substrate and adding it to the primer-template at stoichiometric ratios of rNTP to primer. For example, virtually all of the primer was elongated at least once during the 20-min reaction at a 3:1 ratio of rNTP to primer-template (156:50 nM). At limiting rNTP concentrations&#x02014;20 and 39 nM&#x02014;the yields of extended primer were 19 and 33 nM, respectively. LigD2 POL was &#x0223c;8-fold less effective at scavenging dNTPs at the same limiting concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C bottom panel).</p></sec><sec><title>3&#x02032; End-healing activities of the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigD1 and LigD2 PE domains</title><p><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD (PaeLigD) has a 3&#x02032;-ribonuclease/3&#x02032;-phosphatase activity, whereby it resects a short tract of 3&#x02032;-ribonucleotides on a primer-template substrate to the point at which the primer strand has a single 3&#x02032;-ribonucleotide remaining (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31 B32 B33">31&#x02013;33</xref>). The failure to digest beyond this point reflects a requirement for a 2&#x02032;-OH group on the penultimate nucleoside of the primer strand. The ribonucleotide resection activity resides within the 187-aa N-terminal PE domain and is the result of at least two component steps: (i) the 3&#x02032;-terminal nucleoside is first removed to yield a primer strand with a ribonucleoside 3&#x02032;-PO<sub>4</sub> terminus; (ii) the 3&#x02032;-PO<sub>4</sub> is hydrolyzed to a 3&#x02032;-OH. The 3&#x02032;-ribonuclease and 3&#x02032;-phosphatase activities are both dependent on manganese. The PaeLigD PE domain also catalyzes hydrolysis of the 3&#x02032;-PO<sub>4</sub> of an all-DNA primer-template substrate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>).</p><p>The primary structures of the N-terminal segments of AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 resemble that of the PaeLigD PE domain (Supplementary Figure S3), which has no apparent structural or mechanistic similarity to any previously characterized nucleases or 3&#x02032;-phosphatases. Extensive mutational analysis of the PaeLigD PE domain has identified an ensemble of side chain functional groups that are essential for phosphoesterase activity, which is conserved in the two <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigD proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). In order to probe whether the AtuLigD paralogs possess an end-healing function, we produced the N-terminal PE domains of AtuLigD1 (aa 1&#x02013;186) and AtuLigD2 (aa 1&#x02013;193) in <italic>E. coli</italic> as His<sub>10</sub> fusions and purified them from soluble bacterial lysates by Ni-agarose chromatography. SDS-PAGE analysis verified that the preparations were enriched to the same extent with respect to the LigD1 and LigD2 PE polypeptides, which migrated anomalously at &#x0223c;30&#x02009;kDa (predicted size 24&#x02009;kDa) and &#x0223c;33&#x02009;kDa (predicted size 25&#x02009;kDa), respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). This electrophoretic anomaly echoes the properties of the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> PE domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). We also produced and purified two mutated versions of each of the Atu PE domains, in which the conserved counterparts of essential PaeLigD residues His42 and His84 were substituted by alanine. The purities of the AtuLigD1 H35A and H77A PE proteins and the AtuLigD2 H40A and H82A PE mutants were comparable to the respective wild-type versions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>A).
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>End-healing activities of the AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 PE domains. (<bold>A</bold>) Aliquots (5&#x02009;&#x000b5;g) of the Ni-agarose preparations of the wild-type (WT) and mutated versions of the N-terminal PE domains of AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. The Coomassie blue-stained gel is shown. The positions and sizes (kDa) of marker polypeptides are indicated on the left. (<bold>B</bold>) Reaction mixtures (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 0.5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 50&#x02009;nM pmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D10R2 primer-template (shown at bottom, with ribonucleotides highlighted in shaded boxes), and 4&#x02009;&#x000b5;M WT or mutant PE domain as specified were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. The products were resolved by PAGE and visualized by autoradiography. The labeled species corresponding to the D10R2 substrate and the D10R1 end-product are indicated by arrowheads on the right. (<bold>C</bold>) Reaction mixtures (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 0.5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 50&#x02009;nM <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D11p primer-template (shown at bottom) and 4&#x02009;&#x000b5;M WT or mutant PE domain as specified were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min. The products were analyzed by PAGE and visualized by autoradiography. The labeled species corresponding to the D11p substrate and the D11<sub>OH</sub> product are indicated by arrowheads on the right. (<bold>D</bold>) Reaction mixtures (90&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 0.5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 100&#x02009;nM <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D10R2 primer-template and 4&#x02009;&#x000b5;M AtuLigD1 or AtuLigD2 PE as specified were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C. Aliquots (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) were withdrawn at the times specified above the lanes and quenched immediately with EDTA/formamide. The products were resolved by PAGE and visualized by autoradiography. The labeled species corresponding to the D10R2 substrate, the D10R1p intermediate and the D10R1 end-product are indicated by arrowheads on the right.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f6"/></fig></p><p>The PE proteins were reacted with a 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D10R2 primer-template composed of a 12-mer primer strand with two terminal ribonucleotides and a 24-mer DNA template strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). The wild-type AtuLigD PE domains converted virtually all of the input labeled strand to a more rapidly migrating end-product, D10R1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). This species migrated identically to the D10R1 product generated by the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD PE domain (not shown). A kinetic analysis of the ribonucleotide resection reaction in enzyme excess showed the transient appearance of small amounts of D10R1p at early times (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>D), suggesting that the Atu PE domains remove the terminal ribonucleotide in a two-step pathway similar to that described for the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD PE domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The 3&#x02032;-phosphomonoesterase activity of the AtuLigD PE domains was demonstrated directly by reaction with a 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D11p primer-template composed of a 3&#x02032;-phosphate-terminated 11-mer primer strand annealed to a 24-mer DNA strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). The wild-type AtuLigD PE domains converted the input D11p strand to a more slowly migrating 3&#x02032;-OH end-product, D11<sub>OH</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). The 3&#x02032;-ribonucleotide resection and polynucleotide 3&#x02032;-phosphatase activities of the AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 PE domains were abolished by each of the histidine-to-alanine mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B and C). These results verify that the 3&#x02032; ribonuclease and 3&#x02032; phosphomonoesterase activities are intrinsic to the AtuLigD PE domains and that they rely on the same essential histidines as the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> homolog.</p><p>The quaternary structures of the PE domains were examined by zonal velocity sedimentation in a 15&#x02013;30% glycerol gradient with marker proteins catalase, BSA and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> included as internal standards. After centrifugation, the polypeptide compositions of the odd-numbered gradient fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and aliquots of the fractions were assayed for shortening of the D10R2 primer-template. The LigD1 and LigD2 PE proteins sedimented as a discrete peaks between BSA and cytochrome <italic>c</italic>, coincident with the 3&#x02032; ribonuclease activity (not shown). We infer that the isolated PE domains are monomers.</p><p>The 3&#x02032; ribonucleotide resection activity of the AtuLigD PE domain was optimal at pH 5.5&#x02013;8.0 in 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate or Tris-HCl buffer (data not shown) and was strictly dependent on a divalent cation, preferably manganese or cobalt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). A manganese titration experiment showed that the 3&#x02032; ribonuclease activity was optimal at 0.2&#x02013;5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub> (not shown). Magnesium and calcium were ineffective at 0.5&#x02009;mM concentration. Cadmium, copper and zinc (0.5&#x02009;mM) were capable of sustaining progressively reduced activity that resulted in the formation of the initial D10R1p product, little of which was converted to the D10R1<sub>OH</sub> end-product in the presence of copper or zinc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>).
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Divalent cation specificity of the 3&#x02032;-ribonuclease activity of AtuLigD PE domains. Reaction mixtures (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0), 100&#x02009;nM <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D10R2 primer-template, 0.5&#x02009;mM divalent cation as specified, and either 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M AtuLigD1 PE (bottom panel) or 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M AtuLigD2 PE (top panel) were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f7"/></fig></p><p>The experiments in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref> probed the contribution of the 5&#x02032; single-strand tail of the primer-template to the ribonucleotide resection reactions. We annealed the labeled D10R2 primer to a series of incrementally shortened template strands to form substrates with 12-, 8- or 4-nt 5&#x02032; tails attached to identical 12-bp duplex segments, and a substrate consisting only of the 12-bp duplex with no single-strand tail. We examined the kinetics of the reaction of the AtuLigD1 PE domain with this set of primer-templates under conditions of enzyme excess (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>, top panel). As noted above, the labeled D10R2 strand of the 12-mer/24-mer substrate was converted to a 3&#x02032;-OH end-product, D10R1, with low levels of the 3&#x02032;-phosphorylated species, D10R1-p, appearing transiently at 0.5&#x02013;1&#x02009;min. The extent of substrate decay and the distribution of the reaction products were strongly affected by shortening of the 5&#x02032; tail (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>, top panel). The primer-template containing an 8-nt 5&#x02032; tail was consumed at 44% of the rate of the &#x02018;standard&#x02019; DNA with the 12-mer tail (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>, bottom left panel) and there was a clear delay in the conversion of the D10R1-p intermediate to the D10R1 end-product, i.e. the intermediate persisted for the entire time course and exceeded the level of the end-product for the first 5&#x02009;min of the reaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>, top panel). Further shortening of the tail to 4&#x02009;nt slowed the rate of substrate consumption to 7% of the standard primer-template (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>, bottom panel) and there was scant formation of the D10R1 end-product. The reaction rate on the blunt duplex was 4% of the rate on the standard primer-template. Similar effects of tail shortening on the rate of resection and the distribution of the D10R1-p and D10R1 products were observed for the AtuLigD2 PE domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>, middle and lower panels).
<fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Effect of the template strand 5&#x02032; tail on AtuLigD PE activity. Reaction mixtures (80&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-acetate (pH 6.0), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 0.5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 50&#x02009;nM <sup>32</sup>P-labeled D10R2 primer-templates with variable 5&#x02032; tails and 4&#x02009;&#x000b5;M AtuPE1 or AtuPE2 were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C. Aliquots (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) were withdrawn at the times specified and quenched immediately with EDTA/formamide. The products were resolved by PAGE. The structures of the primer-templates are depicted below the autoradiograms, with ribonucleotides highlighted in shaded boxes. The kinetic profiles of the reactions were quantified by scanning the gel. Phosphodiesterase activity, expressed as the fraction of radiolabeled material in the D10R1-p plus D10R1 products, is plotted as a function of time. The substrate symbols are as depicted below the autoradiograms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f8"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Ku stimulates repair of double-strand breaks by Atu ligases C2, C3, and D2</title><p>The DNA-binding protein Ku is critical for NHEJ-mediated repair of linear plasmid DNA in mycobacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Mycobacterial Ku interacts physically and functionally with mycobacterial LigD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17 B18 B19">17&#x02013;19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). In particular, Ku stimulates the joining of linear DNA fragments by mycobacterial LigD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). In light of the genetic evidence that LigC functions in a Ku-dependent NHEJ pathway <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>), it was of interest to query whether Ku might affect also the strand-sealing activity of LigC <italic>in vitro</italic>. The abundance of LigC and LigD enzymes in <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> affords a unique opportunity to address the Ku-ligase connections. However, the situation is complicated by the multiple Ku isoforms in the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> proteome. Mycobacteria specify a single Ku protein, which has a homodimeric quaternary structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Eukaryal Ku is a heterodimer of separately encoded subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). The homomeric and heteromeric association properties of the three <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> Ku polypeptides are not known and the combinatorial possibilities are daunting. Our initial efforts to produce and purify recombinant His-tagged versions of the individual AtuKu proteins were not fruitful, e.g. Ku1 and Ku2 were not expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic>. Consequently, we produced and purified the single Ku protein encoded by <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (PaeKu; locus tag PA2150; Genbank accession NC_002516). PaeKu was chosen as a stand-in for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> Ku in light of the shared domain organization and biochemical activities of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD and <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigD2. Analysis of the quaternary structure of recombinant PaeKu by zonal velocity sedimentation in a glycerol gradient revealed it to be a single discrete component that overlapped the &#x02018;heavy&#x02019; side of the BSA marker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>A). We surmise that PaeKu is a homodimer of the recombinant 35&#x02009;kDa Ku polypeptide.
<fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Ku stimulation of double-strand break repair by Atu ligases. (<bold>A</bold>) Homodimeric quaternary structure of Ku. Glycerol gradient sedimentation of PaeKu was performed as described under Experimental Procedures. Aliquots (15&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) of odd-numbered gradient fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. The catalase, BSA, Ku and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> polypeptides are indicated. (<bold>B</bold>) Plasmid end joining. Reaction mixtures (20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) containing 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.25&#x02009;mM ATP, 0.2&#x02009;&#x000b5;g BamHI-digested pUC19 DNA (120&#x02009;fmol plasmid; 240 fmol double-strand breaks), either AtuLigD2 (250&#x02009;ng), AtuLigC2 (75&#x02009;ng; 1.9&#x02009;pmol) or AtuLigC3 (125&#x02009;ng; 3.1&#x02009;pmol), and PaeKu as indicated were incubated for 2&#x02009;h at 37&#x000b0;C. The reactions were quenched by adjusting the mixtures to 0.2% SDS and 6&#x02009;mM EDTA. The products were resolved by electrophoresis through a 1% agarose gel in TBE containing 0.05% ethidium bromide. A photograph of the gel under UV illumination is shown. The positions and sizes (kbp) of linear duplex DNA markers (lane M) are indicated on the left. The products of ligation are linear concatemers. A closed monomer circle migrates ahead of the linear monomer; a nicked monomer circle migrates between the linear monomer and linear dimer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm145f9"/></fig></p><p>To approximate an NHEJ-like double-strand break repair scenario <italic>in vitro</italic>, we tested the ability of Atu ligases to join linear pUC19 plasmid DNA that had been digested with BamHI. The reaction mixtures contained &#x0223c;120&#x02009;fmol plasmid DNA, corresponding to 240&#x02009;fmol double-strand breaks. Whereas addition of a molar excess of AtuLigC2 (1.9&#x02009;pmol) or AtuLigC3 (3.1&#x02009;pmol) over the available DNA ends resulted in little end joining, the inclusion of Ku clearly stimulated end joining, as evinced by the appearance of a ladder of linear concatemers, comprising dimer, trimer, tetramer and pentamer products (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>B). The Ku-mediated stimulation of break repair by LigC2 and LigC3 was proportional to the amount of Ku added in the range of 30, 60 and 120&#x02009;ng, corresponding to 0.43, 0.86 and 1.7&#x02009;pmol of Ku homodimer. Ku by itself (120&#x02009;ng) had no strand-joining activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>B). The absence of monomer circles among the reaction products signifies that Ku promotes intermolecular repair events by LigC2 and LigC3. In contrast, reaction of T4 DNA ligase with the same linear DNA yielded a significant amount of monomer circle along with linear concatemers (not shown). Ku also strongly stimulated plasmid end joining by AtuLigD2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>B). The amount of LigD2 added (250&#x02009;ng) sufficed to join a small fraction of the input DNA, generating mostly linear dimer and trimer products. Supplementation with increasing amounts of Ku resulted in reaction of nearly all of the input DNA and its conversion to higher order concatamers (tetramer or greater) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>B). In contrast, Ku had no apparent effect on plasmid end joining by AtuLigD1 (data not shown). These experiments provide the first evidence that Ku directly affects the double-strand break repair activity of a LigC-type enzyme and they implicate LigD2, LigC2 and LigC3 as likely agents of Ku-dependent NHEJ in <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The menu of DNA ligases in the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> proteome is especially rich, owing to the proliferation of paralogs within the LigC and LigD clades, which is accompanied by an expansion of paralogs of Ku. The complexity of the bacterial NHEJ apparatus now ranges from the relatively simple state found in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (which has a single Ku, a single LigD and no LigC), to progressively more complex forms in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> (single Ku, single LigD, single LigC), <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> (single Ku, single LigD, two LigCs) and <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> (three Ku paralogs, two LigDs, three LigCs). Understanding the meaning (if any) of the larger complement of putative NHEJ ligases in <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> (and other plant-associated bacteria such as <italic>Mesorhizobium loti</italic> and <italic>Sinorhizobium meliloti</italic>) requires a systematic dissection of their biochemical properties, focused on the following questions: (i) Do the putative ligases really have strand-joining activity? (ii) What other catalytic functions are associated with the ligases, particularly the LigD paralogs? (iii) How do the paralogs compare biochemically to each other? (iv) How do they compare to putative orthologs from other species? (v) Are they affected by Ku?</p><p>The present study addressed these issues and thereby illuminates shared features within the LigC and LigD clades, as well as remarkable differences. The key findings are: (i) Not all putative ligases have demonstrable strand-joining activity, e.g. AtuLigC1; (ii) Atu ligases C2, C3, D1 and D2 are relatively feeble at sealing singly nicked DNA duplexes, a characteristic shared with mycobacterial LigC and LigD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>); (iii) AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 have an intrinsic 3&#x02032; end-healing function similar to that of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD; (iv) AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 are not functionally equivalent, because only LigD2 has an intrinsic polymerase activity; (v) AtuLigD2 POL prefers ribonucleotide substrates; (vi) The capacity of Atu LigC2, C3, and D2 to seal double-strand breaks <italic>in vitro</italic> (a model NHEJ-like reaction) is enhanced strongly by Ku.</p><p>The Ku stimulation of plasmid end joining by AtuLigC is significant, in that it provides the first biochemical support for the genetic evidence in mycobacteria of a Ku/LigC-driven pathway of NHEJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). It is remarkable that <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> LigC2 and LigC3 are stimulated by Ku derived from <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>, which does not have a LigC protein. We presume that Ku assists in approximating the duplex ends for sealing by the bacterial ligase, although the molecular details remain obscure. Clearly, the functional interaction of LigC and Ku extends across species lines and does not require ancillary structural modules flanking the core ligase domain. This differs from the LigD&#x02013;Ku interaction, where the POL domain is implicated in binding to Ku (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). If such an interaction is indeed critical for Ku function in the LigD-mediated NHEJ pathway, then it also appears to cross species lines, because we find that PaeKu stimulates sealing of broken plasmid ends by AtuLigD2 <italic>in vitro</italic>. The observation that PaeKu does not stimulate plasmid joining by AtuLigD1, which lacks the complete POL domain, provides additional support for the idea that Ku&#x02013;LigD interactions occur via POL. However, we do not exclude an alternative scenario in which AtuLigD1 interacts specifically with one of the AtuKu paralogs (e.g. AtuKu1, which is encoded in a putative operon adjacent to AtuLigD1). Ultimately, it will be of interest to test whether LigD and Ku proteins from different bacterial species can be exchanged <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p>The polymerase activity of LigD is a major contributor to the mutagenic character of bacterial NHEJ at blunt and 5&#x02032;-overhang DNA breaks <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Whereas the single LigD enzymes encoded by mycobacteria and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> have catalytically active POL domains, the situation is more complex in <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>. The domain order of AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2 (PE-LIG-POL) mimics that of PaeLigD, yet only AtuLigD2 has an intrinsic polymerase activity. The C-terminal POL domain of AtuLigD2 comprises a complete homolog of the PaeLigD POL domain, whereas the POL domain of AtuLigD1 is truncated at its C-terminus. The equivalent of the missing segment of AtuLigD1 POL constitutes the &#x02018;back&#x02019; surface of PaeLigD POL, away from the active site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). As PaeLigD POL exemplifies a minimized version of the archaeal-eukaryal polymerase-primase family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>), it is reasonable that the C-terminal deletion in AtuLigD1 results in loss of activity, most likely because the fold of the residual POL domain is compromised, notwithstanding that the domain contains most of the catalytic residues in the POL active site. The presence of a rump POL domain in AtuLigD1 suggests that LigD1 and LigD2 evolved by duplication of a single full-length ancestral LigD gene, followed by deletion of the C-terminal segment of the LigD1 POL module.</p><p>The salient feature of AtuLigD2 POL is its much higher rate of templated ribonucleotide addition at a DNA primer terminus compared to deoxyribonucleotide addition. This property is shared with PaeLigD POL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) and is likely to be relevant to NHEJ <italic>in vivo</italic>. NHEJ provides the means to repair double-strand breaks in the absence of a sister chromatid homolog, i.e. in quiescent cells that have a single copy of the bacterial genome. In the absence of ongoing DNA replication, dNTP pools are likely to be limiting because ribonucleotide reductase is cell-cycle regulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>); thus the shared capacity of LigD POL enzymes to efficiently scavenge and preferentially incorporate ribonucleotides could be advantageous for bacterial survival during quiescence, by providing a temporary &#x02018;ribo patch&#x02019; at the 3&#x02032;-OH side of the repair junction.</p><p>The present study underscores that the 3&#x02032; end-healing functions of the PE domain of bacterial LigD are conserved across species (e.g. <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> and <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>) and among LigD paralogs within a species (AtuLigD1 and AtuLigD2). The <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> PE domains each catalyze two phosphoesterase reactions: (i) a phosphodiesterase-type resection of a diribonucleotide end of a primer-template to leave a single ribonucleotide and (ii) a phosphomonoesterase reaction that removes a 3&#x02032;-PO<sub>4</sub> from either a terminal ribo or deoxyribonucleotide of a primer-template to leave a 3&#x02032;-OH. The phosphodiesterase activity of the AtuLigD PE domains is apparently limited to resecting an RNA 3&#x02032; terminus, insofar as we observe no 3&#x02032; nucleotide resection activity on an all-DNA primer-template and the resection reaction of the AtuLigD PE proteins halts once the primer has a single 3&#x02032; ribonucleoside. The ribonucleotide resection activity of the AtuLigD PE domains is strongly stimulated by the 5&#x02032; single-strand tail of the complementary DNA strand. These features are shared with the PaeLigD PE domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31 B32 B33">31&#x02013;33</xref>). In contrast, it has been reported that <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> LigD has an intrinsic 3&#x02032; exonuclease activity on DNA phosphodiesters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Although the observed DNA exonuclease of full-length MtuLigD was suppressed by a mutation in the PE segment of the protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>), it was surprising that no DNA exonuclease activity was detected for the isolated PE domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). We have purified the PE domain of MtuLigD and find that it performs a manganese-dependent 3&#x02032; ribonucleotide resection reaction on a 3&#x02032; diribonucleotide-containing primer-template and that it removes the 3&#x02032;-PO<sub>4</sub> from an all-DNA primer-template (Supplementary Figure S5). Thus, the PE domain of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> LigD has the activities ascribed to the homologous modules of <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> LigD. We surmise that 3&#x02032; ribonuclease and 3&#x02032; phosphatase reactions are the relevant repair functions of the PE domain that are conserved in all LigD proteins characterized to date.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm145_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="nar_gkm145_nar-00154-t-2007-File011.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="nar_gkm145_nar-00154-t-2007-File012.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="nar_gkm145_nar-00154-t-2007-File013.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="nar_gkm145_nar-00154-t-2007-File014.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="nar_gkm145_nar-00154-t-2007-File015.doc"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><p>This work was supported by NIH grant GM63611. SS is an American Cancer Society Research Professor. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by NIH grant GM63611.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA ligase: structure, mechanism, and function</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1974</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>790</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4377758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowater</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial DNA ligases</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11442824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e5;kansson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Timson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigley</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the adenylation domain of an NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent DNA ligase</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>1999</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10368271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent DNA ligase: modular architecture and functional implications</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>1129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10698952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gajiwala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural rearrangement accompanying NAD<sup>+</sup> synthesis within a bacterial DNA ligase crystal</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>2004</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1449</fpage><lpage>1459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15296738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastiva</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent DNA ligase (Rv3014c) from <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: crystal structure of the adenylylation domain and identification of novel inhibitors</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>30273</fpage><lpage>30281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15901723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sriskanda</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conserved residues in domain Ia are required for the reaction of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DNA ligase with NAD<sup>+</sup></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>9685</fpage><lpage>9700</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Gellert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics and function of DNA ligase in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1973</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4353284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konrad</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Modrich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and enzymatic characterization of a conditional lethal mutant of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K12 with a temperature-sensitive DNA ligase</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1973</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4353283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>UE</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivera</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillyard</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA ligase and the pyridine cycle in <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1989</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>2173</fpage><lpage>2180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2649488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The NAD-dependent ligase encoded by <italic>yerG</italic> is an essential gene of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>4642</fpage><lpage>4648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11095673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaczmarek</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaniewski</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gootz</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Danley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cloning and functional characterization of an NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent DNA ligase from <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2001</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>3016</fpage><lpage>3024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11325928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genes required for mycobacterial growth defined by high density mutagenesis</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12657046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of an ATP-dependent DNA ligase encoded by <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9060431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magnet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanistic and kinetic study of the ATP-dependent DNA ligase of <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic></article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2004</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>710</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14730975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongiorno</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and genetic analysis of the four DNA ligases of mycobacteria</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>20594</fpage><lpage>20606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14985346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongiorno</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephanou</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of nonhomologous end-joining in mycobacteria: a low fidelity repair system driven by Ku, ligase D and ligase C</article-title><source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15778718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kysela</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonkin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanlan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Della</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of a DNA nonhomologous end-joining complex in bacteria</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>1686</fpage><lpage>1689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12215643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Della</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmbos</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonkin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Topper</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitcher</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomkinson</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mycobacterial Ku and ligase proteins constitute a two-component NHEJ repair machine</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>306</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15499016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korycka-Machala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brzostek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozalska</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumijowska-Galewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dziedzic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowater</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dziadek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct DNA repair pathways involving RecA and nonhomologous end joining in <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic></article-title><source>FEBS Microbiol. Lett</source><year>2006</year><volume>258</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alwood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaipisuttikul</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haugen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Will</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive transposon mutant library of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>14339</fpage><lpage>14344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14617778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Setlow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Conlon</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Setlow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Losick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The forespore line of gene expression in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16497325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Setubal</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Monks</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitajima</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Okura</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome of the natural genetic engineer <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> C58</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>2317</fpage><lpage>2323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinkle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gattung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Qurollo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Askenazi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of the plant pathogen and biotechnology agent <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> C58</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>2323</fpage><lpage>2328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleuyard</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Daoudal-Cotterell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jallut</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ku80 plays a role in non-homologous recombinant but is not required for T-DNA integration in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2003</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12940949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Attikum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bundock</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Overmeer</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelvin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooykaas</surname><given-names>PJJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis AtLIG4</italic> gene is required for the repair of DNA damage, but not for the integration of <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> T-DNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>4247</fpage><lpage>4255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12853643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomkinson</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human DNA ligase I completely encircles and partially unwinds nicked DNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>432</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15565146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A primer-dependent polymerase function of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATP-dependent DNA ligase (LigD)</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandakumar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aniukwu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atomic structure and nonhomologous end-joining function of the polymerase component of bacterial DNA ligase D</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1711</fpage><lpage>1716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16446439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yakovleva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleotide misincorporation, 3'-mismatch extension, and responses to abasic sites and DNA adducts by the polymerase component of bacterial DNA ligase D</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>25026</fpage><lpage>25040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16816388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel 3&#x02032;-ribonuclease and 3&#x02032;-phosphatase activities of the bacterial non-homologous end-joining protein, DNA ligase D</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>25973</fpage><lpage>25981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15897197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential constituents of the 3&#x02032;-phosphoesterase domain of bacterial DNA ligase D, a nonhomologous end-joining enzyme</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>33707</fpage><lpage>33715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16046407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substrate specificity and structure-function analysis of the 3&#x02032;-phosphoesterase component of the bacterial NHEJ protein, DNA Ligase D</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>13873</fpage><lpage>13881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16540477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aniukwu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure and nonhomologous end joining function of the ligase domain of <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> DNA ligase D</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>13412</fpage><lpage>13423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitcher</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonkin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Domain structure of a NHEJ repair ligase from <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16023671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reexamining the role of the accessory plasmid pATC58 in the virulence of <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strains C58</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14551325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccinia DNA ligase: specificity, fidelity, and inhibition</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1995</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>16138</fpage><lpage>16147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8519771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sriskanda</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutational analysis of <italic>Chlorella</italic> virus DNA ligase: catalytic roles of domain I and motif VI</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>4618</fpage><lpage>4625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9753729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Corpina</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the Ku heterodimer bound to DNA and its implications for double-strand break repair</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>412</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11493912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Camara</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Klungs&#x000f8;yr</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Crooke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Skarstad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel regulatory mechanism couples deoxyribonucleotide synthesis and DNA replication in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16482221</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
