<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17355989</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1874648</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm068</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Computational Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bioinformatic prediction and experimental verification of Fur-regulated genes in the extreme acidophile <italic>Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quatrini</surname><given-names>Raquel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lefimil</surname><given-names>Claudia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Veloso</surname><given-names>Felipe A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pedroso</surname><given-names>Inti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>David S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jedlicki</surname><given-names>Eugenia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Center for Bioinformatics and Genome Biology, MIFAB, Life Science Foundation and Andr&#x000e9;s Bello University, Santiago, Chile and <sup>2</sup>ICBM, Faculty of Medicine, University of Chile, Santiago, Chile</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>56 2 237 3014</phone><fax>56 2 237 2259</fax><email>rquatrini@yahoo.com.ar</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2153</fpage><lpage>2166</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The <bold>&#x003b3;</bold>-proteobacterium <italic>Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> lives in extremely acidic conditions (pH 2) and, unlike most organisms, is confronted with an abundant supply of soluble iron. It is also unusual in that it oxidizes iron as an energy source. Consequently, it faces the challenging dual problems of (i) maintaining intracellular iron homeostasis when confronted with extremely high environmental loads of iron and (ii) of regulating the use of iron both as an energy source and as a metabolic micronutrient. A combined bioinformatic and experimental approach was undertaken to identify Fur regulatory sites in the genome of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> and to gain insight into the constitution of its Fur regulon. Fur regulatory targets associated with a variety of cellular functions including metal trafficking (e.g. <italic>feoPABC</italic>, <italic>tdr</italic>, <italic>tonBexbBD</italic>, <italic>copB</italic>, <italic>cdf</italic>), utilization (e.g. <italic>fdx</italic>, <italic>nif</italic>), transcriptional regulation (e.g. <italic>phoB</italic>, <italic>irr</italic>, <italic>iscR</italic>) and redox balance (<italic>grx</italic>, <italic>trx</italic>, <italic>gst</italic>) were identified. Selected predicted Fur regulatory sites were confirmed by FURTA, EMSA and <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription analyses. This study provides the first model for a Fur-binding site consensus sequence in an acidophilic iron-oxidizing microorganism and lays the foundation for future studies aimed at deepening our understanding of the regulatory networks that control iron uptake, homeostasis and oxidation in extreme acidophiles.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Iron availability is an environmental stimulus to which organisms respond by regulating the expression of many genes, termed the iron stimulon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). The iron stimulon includes clusters of genes under the control of a number of different transcriptional regulators of which Fur is the best characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Fur recognizes and binds specifically to a DNA sequence, known as the Fur box, that is typically located in proximity to the &#x02212;10 and/or &#x02212;35 &#x003c3;<sub>70</sub> promoter elements of target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Genes, whose expression is under the control of Fur, constitute the Fur regulon. To date, more than 90 genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), 87 in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) and 46 in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) are known to be regulated by Fur.</p><p>Although less data exists for other microorganisms, Fur typically binds target DNA that has recognizable sequence similarity to the <italic>E. coli</italic> Fur box consensus. For example, canonical Fur boxes have been described in <italic>Legionella pneumoniae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>), <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), <italic>Vibrio anguillarum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>), <italic>V. cholerae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) and <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) among others. There are a few exceptions where Fur-binding sites have been reported to exhibit an incomplete target DNA consensus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>).</p><p>Since Fur is a global regulator controlling a relatively common set of genes in different microorganisms, both the search for conserved target genes and for conserved Fur-binding sites have proved useful for the identification of genes belonging to the Fur regulon in a wide variety of bacteria. Several experimental strategies have been employed to find Fur regulated loci: <italic>in vivo</italic> FURTA assays in <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> and <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15 B16 B17 B18">15&#x02013;18</xref>), <italic>in vitro</italic> cycle-selection procedures in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) and more recently microarray transcriptional profiling in <italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic>, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>S. enterica</italic>, <italic>N. meningitidis</italic> and <italic>H. pylori</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19 B20 B21 B22">19&#x02013;22</xref>). Once Fur-binding sites have been recognized for common shared genes in genomes, the information can then be used to mount searches for Fur-binding sites associated with species-specific targets.</p><p>As the complete genome sequences of more microorganisms become available, the prediction of transcriptional regulatory DNA sites by computational analysis of sequence data, including phylogenetic footprinting, is quickly becoming an indispensable tool in biological research. Quantitative models based on information theory have been constructed for predicting the DNA recognition sequence for the OxyR, PurR, Lpr, Fis transcription factors, among others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23 B24 B25 B26">23&#x02013;26</xref>) and used to search for additional or new regulator target sequences. Consensus-building algorithms have also been employed to conduct comparative genomic analyses of the Lex regulon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) and the Fur regulons of <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>S. typhi</italic>, <italic>Y. pestis</italic> and <italic>V. cholerae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) and <italic>B. subtilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>).</p><p>We are interested in understanding how the bacterium <italic>Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> copes with iron uptake and homeostasis considering that it grows at acidic pHs in environmental situations where soluble iron is abundant ([FeIII]<sub>pH2</sub> = 0.1&#x02009;M) compared with its bioavailability in circum-neutrophilic aerobic conditions ([FeIII]<sub>pH7</sub> = 10<sup>&#x02212;18</sup> M). Another special feature of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> is its use of iron as an energy source that may make its requirement for iron particularly demanding given its abundant repertoire of iron-dependent respiratory enzymes. It also suggests that <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> must have developed mechanisms to coordinately regulate iron homeostasis and iron oxidation.</p><p>In this article, an <italic>in silico</italic> approach, fed with experimentally confirmed Fur boxes, has been used to identify candidate Fur-binding sites in the <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> genome. The identification of Fur boxes associated with several transporters, iron-containing proteins and miscellaneous functions, in addition to typical Fur targets that are involved in iron assimilation in other bacteria, provides the first insight into the nature of the Fur regulon in an acidophilic, iron oxidizing microorganism. A role for Fur in coordinating metal homeostasis responses, beyond iron uptake can be suggested. A first glimpse into how iron homeostasis and iron oxidation could be coordinated through the Fur-dependent repression of Fe(II)/Fe(III) uptake systems and de-repression/activation of Fe(II) oxidizing and Fe(III) uptake systems in response to iron availability is presented and a framework is suggested for future investigations into the biology of less well-studied Fur targets that could form part of the iron stimulon in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Weight-matrix-based Fur-binding site prediction</title><p>A set of 66 experimentally confirmed Fur boxes from <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>S. typhimurium</italic>, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> was used to generate an alignment matrix and a weight matrix by the information content method of Schneider (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) (Supplementary Data S1). The weight matrix was initially tested against known Fur-box-containing DNA segments from several microorganisms. The method consistently predicted the DNAse I protected and/or gel-shifted sites by Fur binding in each tested example (data not shown). The matrix was used to search the genome of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> using a 19-bp sliding window. Each window was scored for its degree of matching the Fur weight matrix and only those with scores higher than the lowest accepted <italic>E. coli</italic> Fur box were retained in the analysis. To further reduce the number of false positives, this initial pool of candidate Fur boxes was culled by including only those that: (i) were located &#x0003c;600&#x02009;nt from the proposed initiation of translation of the potential target gene and (ii) exhibited conservation of key nucleotides known to be protected by Fur binding in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Near-symmetric sites with high scores in both the forward and reverse direction were counted only once, and the higher of the two scores was retained.</p></sec><sec><title>Hidden Markov Model-based Fur binding site prediction</title><p>A group of experimentally validated Fur-binding sites from <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> derived from electrophoretic mobility shift assays (EMSA) was used to build HMM profiles and to search for additional sites in the genome of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. For this purpose, the Fur-binding promoters were aligned with ClustalW (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ebi.ac.uk/ClustalW">www.ebi.ac.uk/ClustalW</ext-link>) and an HMM was built from this alignment (Supplementary Data S1) using <italic>hmmb</italic> in the HMMER package 1.8.4 programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Subsequently, <italic>hmmls</italic> was used for finding multiple non-overlapping matching hits in an <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> intergenic sequence database constructed from the annotated genome sequence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.tigr.org">www.tigr.org</ext-link>). HMMER bit scores assigned to each candidate Fur box reflect whether the sequence is a better match to the profile model (positive score) or to the null model (negative score), the magnitude of which shows how well the sequence matches the HMM. Scores above log2 of the number of sequences in the target database are likely to be true functional Fur-binding sites. Our cutoff value was set on the basis of the worst scored training sequence at 9.00 bits. This strong search criteria is bound to overlook intrinsically weak binding sites (or sites significantly divergent to the ones tested experimentally herein which may not accurately reflect the statistical distribution of all true targets), but was chosen to reduce biases introduced by false positives.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA sequence Logos</title><p>Logos were generated using the web-based application available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://weblogo.berkeley.edu/logo.cgi">http://weblogo.berkeley.edu/logo.cgi</ext-link>. The height of each letter corresponds to its relative abundance at each position in bits.</p></sec><sec><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p>Bacterial strains and plasmids are described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. <italic>Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> ATCC23270 was grown in modified 9K basal salt media (0.1 g of (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 0.04 g of K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 0.4 g of MgSO<sub>4</sub>-7H<sub>2</sub>O per liter) containing 200&#x02009;mM FeSO<sub>4</sub>; adjusted to pH 1.6 with H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) at 30&#x000b0;C under aerobic conditions on a rotary shaker at 150&#x02009;rpm. <italic>E. coli</italic> was grown at 37&#x000b0;C in LB broth with the appropriate antibiotics: ampicillin (Amp: 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml), streptomycin (Sm: 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml) and/or kanamycin (Km: 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml) as indicated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strains</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relevant genotype</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference or source</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC23270</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type strain, genome sequenced by TIGR and Integrated Genomics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1717</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fhuF::lacZ</italic>, Sm<sup>r</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QC-1732</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC4468, F- &#x025b5;(<italic>lacZYA-argF</italic>)U169 <italic>rpsL &#x025b5;fur</italic>, Sm<sup>r</sup>, Km<sup>r</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Plasmids</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pUC-18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">plasmid vector, Amp<sup>r</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibco, BRL</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGEM-T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">plasmid vector, Amp<sup>r</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Promega</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pAFH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fur</italic> from <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> ATCC23270 expressed from pGEMT-Easy <italic>lacZ</italic> promoter, Amp<sup>r</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>General DNA techniques and cloning procedures</title><p><italic>Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> cultures, to be used for nucleic acid or protein purification, were centrifuged at 600&#x02009;g to remove solid sulfur or iron precipitates prior to cell harvest. The cell pellet was resuspended in 9&#x02009;K salt solution for further washing. Washed cells were collected by centrifugation at 10,000&#x02009;g for 10&#x02009;min.</p><p>DNA isolation and routine manipulations were carried out following standard protocols as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>) or by the manufacturers of the reagents. Plasmid DNA was prepared with the Wizard Plasmid Miniprep Kit (Promega) or the QIAprep Spin Mini-kit (Qiagen). Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) products were amplified with proofreading DNA polymerase Elongase (Invitrogen) and were purified from agarose gels with the QiaEx DNA purification kit (Qiagen). Oligonucleotide primers used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>. Each PCR reaction contained 10&#x02009;ng of template DNA, 0.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;M of required primers and 0.2&#x02009;mM of each deoxyribonucleotides in a volume of 25&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 1 &#x000d7; PCR buffer containing 1.5&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> (Invitrogen). PCR conditions were as follows: initial denaturing step at 95&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min followed by 28&#x02013;30 amplification cycles (denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;s, annealing at the appropriate temperature depending on the specific primer pairs for 30&#x02009;s and elongation at 72&#x000b0;C) and a final elongation step at 72&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min. DNA sequencing was carried out by Agencourt, Inc. (Beverley, MA, USA)
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Oligonucleotide primers used in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primers</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence (5&#x02032;&#x02013;3&#x02032;)</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vector</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pUC-1(2006971)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AACAGCTATGACCATC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pUC-2(2006972)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTTTTCCCAGTCACGAC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FeoP-1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAATTCCGTCATTACCGTCATGGCAAC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FeoP-2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGGATCCCCAGCGCAGATGATGAGCAC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GloA-1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACGCAAGCGGTAACAAAGC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GloA-2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACGGCAACAACGACACATC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fdx1-1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTATTGGGCAGACTGTTGCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fdx1-2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGATCACTGAGAGGCAGGAC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HppH-1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCAAGGCGACCTGGTATTCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HppH-2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCTTTCCTTTCTGTGGATGCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IscR-1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGTCAGTTTCATATCTGGTGC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IscR-2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCGTCAATAAGGGTGAGCATAC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PhoB-1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACTTCAGTAATTCACTGATC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PhoB-2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGCTGCCTTGCGGTATGG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CopB-1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAGGCTACCCAATGGGTAG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CopB-2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCAAGGCAGCAGTAGAAGC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AbcS4-1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGCAGTTTCAAAAAGCCTCTC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AbcS4-2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTGTTTCACGGGCTCTACTCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FeoP-3&#x02666;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GACCCCATCGCTAGTCATG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FeoP-4&#x02666;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAGCTCACTGTCGGCATG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GloA-3&#x02666;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACGCAAGCGGTAACAAAGC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GloA-4&#x02666;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCGGGAAACCGCATATCGG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CopB-3&#x02666;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCAAGGCAGCAGTAGAAGC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CopB-4&#x02666;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGCGGCATGGTTGTGACC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PhoB-3&#x02666;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACTTCAGTAATTCACTGATC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PhoB-4&#x02666;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAATCGGGCAGACCAGTCC</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>*Oligonucleotides used for amplification of EMSA probes; &#x02666;Oligonucleotides used for amplification of IVTA probes.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Fur titration assay (FURTA)</title><p>Fur titration assays was performed according to Stojiljkovic <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). A pUC-18-based randomly cloned genomic library from <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> (pGTF) containing <italic>Sau</italic>3AI DNA fragments (average weight of 0.5&#x02009;kb) was electroporated into <italic>E. coli</italic> H1717 (<italic>fur<sup>+</sup></italic>, <italic>fhuF::lacZ</italic>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). A total of 3.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> Amp<sup>r</sup> clones were recovered in selective MacConkey indicator plates containing 40&#x02009;&#x003bc;M FeSO<sub>4</sub>. The cloning vector pGEMT-Easy and the <italic>E. coli</italic> Fur box upstream of the <italic>fhuF</italic> gene cloned in the same vector (FB-FhuF1 + 2, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) were employed as negative and positive controls, respectively. Clones exhibiting red color in FeSO<sub>4</sub>-MacConkey plates after 12&#x02013;24&#x02009;h of incubation at 37&#x000b0;C were isolated and further re-streaked. DNA inserts of candidate clones were subsequently subjected to DNA sequencing. The recovered sequences were assessed for the presence of putative promoter elements and Fur box-like sequences using bioinformatics approaches described above. FURTA-positive clones were ranked for further analysis based on the following criteria: (i) presence of a predicted Fur-binding site in the insert; (ii) that the target gene is Fur-regulated in other bacteria and/or (iii) that the target gene is related to known genes involved in iron metabolism in other organisms.</p></sec><sec><title>Overexpression and purification of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur</title><p>The <italic>E. coli</italic> strain QC1732/pAFH carrying the recombinant plasmid pAFH expresses the <italic>fur</italic> regulator from <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> 23270 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). The 500&#x02009;ml cultures of this strain were grown in Luria-Bertani broth containing 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l of ampicillin and 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l of streptomycin to an optical density at 590&#x02009;nm of 0.8&#x02013;1.0. The cells were isolated by centrifugation and were resuspended in 50&#x02009;ml of buffer Tris-HCl 50&#x02009;mM pH 8.0 containing 5% glycerol, 1&#x02009;mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride and 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml of lysozyme. The cells were incubated to 4&#x000b0;C for one hour and sonicated, and the mixture was centrifuged at 25&#x02009;000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 15&#x02009;min. The soluble extract was applied to a DEAE-Sephacel (Pharmacia Biotech, Uppsala, Sweden) column with a 50-ml bed volume. The bound proteins were eluted with a 50&#x02013;500&#x02009;mM NaCl linear gradient, and 2-ml fractions were collected. The majority of Fur eluted between 150 and 200&#x02009;mM NaCl as determined by western blot analysis of fractions with anti-Fur antibody. Elution fractions containing Fur were pooled and applied to a chelating Sepharose (Pharmacia Biotech) column (5-ml bed volume) charged with ZnSO<sub>4</sub> 0.2&#x02009;M as recommended by the manufacturer. The bound proteins were eluted with 1M imidazole in 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 150&#x02009;mM NaCl and 0.5-ml fractions were collected. Fractions containing Fur were pooled and dialyzed at 4&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h in 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 1&#x02009;mM DTT, 25&#x02009;mM EDTA, 1&#x02009;h in 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 1&#x02009;mM DTT and finally overnight in 50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 1&#x02009;mM DTT, 30% glycerol, 0.1&#x02009;mM MnSO<sub>4</sub>. The protein fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE (15% gel) and either silver stained or western blotted. Polyclonal antibodies against <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur were obtained by immunizing white rabbits with 200&#x02009;&#x000b5;g of a Fur protein preparation following standard procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Electrophoretic mobility shift assays (EMSAs)</title><p>Probes (representing selected candidate Fur boxes) were obtained by PCR amplification using the pairs of oligonucleotides shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> and were end labeled with [&#x003b3;<sup>32</sup>P]-ATP using T4 polynucleotide kinase (Invitrogen). Unincorporated nucleotides were removed with Bio-Gel P10 Micro Bio-spin chromatography columns (BioRad). EMSA assays were performed as described by de Lorenzo <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) with the following modifications. A 300&#x02009;nM (or otherwise stated concentrations) of purified Fur protein form <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> obtained as described above was equilibrated in 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l final volume of gel mobility shift buffer (20&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 40&#x02009;mM KCl, 1&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1&#x02009;mM MnSO<sub>4</sub>, 1mM DTT, 0.1&#x02009;mg/ml bovine serum albumen, 5% (v/v) glycerol). The labeled probes (50&#x02013;75&#x02009;pM; 10,000&#x02009;c.p.m.) and non-specific competitor salmon sperm DNA (50&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l) were added, and the reactions incubated for 10&#x02009;min at 30&#x000b0;C. In supershift experiments, a 1:500 dilution of Fur-specific antiserum was added to the reaction and incubated for an additional 5&#x02009;min. A 50-fold excess of cold probe was used to challenge each of the labeled probes. Bound and unbound probes were separated by non-denaturing polyacrylamide (4% w/v) gel electrophoresis at 100&#x02009;V for 1&#x02009;h in Tris acetate buffer at 4&#x000b0;C. Retardation was assessed after exposure of the dried gel to Imaging Screen-K (Kodak) by scanning on a PhosphorImager (Molecular Imagen FX Pro Plus, BioRad). The image was captured and analyzed with Quantity One version 4.1.1 (BioRad). Purified Fur protein concentration to be used in EMSA assays (300&#x02009;nM) was determined after titrating the amount of protein that produced a shift of a non-specific probe corresponding to a low G + C PCR fragment spanning the multicloning region of pUC18 (amplified with primers shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>), which is 500&#x02009;nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>F&#x02014;lane 6).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription (IVTA)</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription assays were performed according to Friedman and O&#x02019;Brian (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>) with minor modifications. Promoter-containing template sequences (average size = 400 bp) were PCR-amplified using the primers specified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>. Templates (5&#x02013;7&#x02009;nM) were incubated for 10&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C with 300&#x02009;nM Fur protein from <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> (Fur<sub>AF</sub>) in IVTA buffer (20&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 40&#x02009;mM KCl, 10&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1&#x02009;mg/ml bovine serum albumin, 0.1&#x02009;mM MnSO<sub>4</sub>, 5&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol) in a final volume of 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;l. One unit of <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase (Amersham) was added to the reaction in the presence of 40 U of RNAse inhibitor (Fermentas) and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min, before adding 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of a preheated NTP mix (250&#x02009;&#x003bc;M ATP, CTP and GTP, 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;M UTP and 12.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;M of UTP-&#x003b1;P<sup>32</sup>) in IVTA buffer. Incubation at 37&#x000b0;C was carried out for 10&#x02009;min. Transcripts were resolved by polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (10%) under denaturing conditions (7&#x02009;M urea) in Tris borate EDTA electrophoresis buffer. Transcript sizes were determined using an RNA ladder (Invitrogen) labeled with (&#x003b3;<sup>32</sup>-P)-ATP using T4 polynucleotide kinase (Fermentas).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>Strategy for the identification of candidate Fur-binding sites in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic></title><p>In order to identify <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> genes directly targeted by the Fur regulator, a genome-wide search for conserved Fur boxes was carried out using the computational and experimental approach outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Pipeline for the computational and experimental steps used to identify candidate Fur-binding sites in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. Additional information and results can be found in Supplementary Data S1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm068f1"/></fig></p><p>The strategy involves the following steps:
<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>A Fur recognition weight matrix was derived from a pool of recognized Fur-binding sites of several bacteria as described in Methods (Supplementary Data S1A). This matrix was used to locate potential Fur-binding sites by computing the information content of each 19 base pair sequence of a sliding window passed over the complete genome of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. After reducing potential false positives, a set of 90 candidate sites (Supplementary Data S1B) was selected for further analysis.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A gene library of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> was transformed into the <italic>E. coli</italic> FURTA strain H1717 carrying a Fur regulated <italic>lacZ</italic> fusion as a reporter gene (<italic>fhuF::lacZ</italic>) in order to identify <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> sequences capable of sequestering <italic>E. coli</italic> Fur. After re-streaking positive candidates three times to fresh media, clones with reproducible LacZ+ phenotypes were sequenced and potential Fur-binding sites were identified using information theory (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>A set of candidate Fur-binding sequences derived from bioinformatic predictions (Information Theory) and <italic>in vivo</italic> isolated candidate Fur-regulated promoters (FURTA) were evaluated for <italic>in vitro</italic> binding of Fur from <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> (Fur<sub>AF</sub>) using the EMSA (Supplementary Data S1C).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The EMSA-validated sequences were used to construct a HMM profile for further screening of the <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> genome. This strategy aimed to set a more stringent search-criteria in order to locate potential &#x02018;species specific&#x02019; Fur-binding sites and to reduce the rate of false positives. The DNA sequences of binding sites with scores higher than the weakest experimentally confirmed Fur box are provided in Supplementary Data S1D.</p></list-item></list>
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Genes associated with HMM- or IT-predicted Fur boxes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prediction</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Validation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fur box</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score (bits)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distance to ATG (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene or Gene cluster</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotated function (TIGR)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIGR#</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">METHOD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FURTA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMSA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITVA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron acquisition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGTAATAAGACTCATTCGT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>feoP/feoABC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OprB family porin -Feo FeII uptake transporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0580</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTAATAAGACTCATTCGT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTAATATTAGTCATTAGT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S(36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAAACGGGAATCATTCTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mntH</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metal ion transporter, NRAMP family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE2920</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATAAACGGGAATCATTCTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAATATCGTTATCATCCTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tdrA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TonB-dependent receptor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0174</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TACTATCAGATTTATAATT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">521</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tdrB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TonB-dependent receptor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0173</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATATTATAGTTATTCTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>gloA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved globin domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1602</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGATATTATAGTTATTCTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATATCCAGAATTTTTATC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>abcP</italic>1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC iron(lll) dicitrate transport system permease, FecCD family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1594</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAAATGACAATTTTATGA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>exbBDtonB2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TonB Biopolymer transport system</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0827</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAAATTCATTCCCATTTTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tonB4</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TonB family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE2270</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAAAATAAAACTTGTGTTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tonB4</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TonB family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1114</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGAAATGAGAATCAAATCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>exbD4</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bipolymer transport ExbD protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0106</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron utilization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGAATTGTTAATTTGTCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hyp/fdx1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferredoxin (4Fe-4S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1138</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACAAAGAGAATCAATATC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fdx2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferredoxin (Fe-S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE2230</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAGAATCATATGCAATTTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nuoI</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADH-quinone oxidoreductase, I subunit-2(4Fe-4S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0482</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAAAACAATAATATATATT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">273</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>noxA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyridine nucleotide-disulfide oxidoreductase (Fe-S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1282</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGAAACCAGATCCATTTCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">583</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hemN</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O2-indep coproporphyrinogen III DH (4Fe-4S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE2891</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATATATGTAATTATTCTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hppH</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBH NiFe hydrogenase high potential iron-sulfur protein (4Fe-4S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE2333</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dsrK</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hup reductase (Fe-S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE3048</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATAACGCGTTTCGTCTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">434</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hdrC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterosulfide reductase subunit (4Fe-4S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0551</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCATTGGATAACAATTATC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nifV</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe-S cluster assembly accessory protein (Fe-S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1553</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGGAAGGATTGGCATATTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nifS</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase cofactor synthesis protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1547</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGAAATCGCATTTATCATC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fdx</italic>4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferredoxin (2Fe-2S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1543</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAAAATGGTATTCTTCTGC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nifX</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase cofactor processing protein (Fe-Mo)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1569</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAAAAAGCGTTTAATTTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hyp/hyp/fdx</italic>7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical in nitrogenase gene cluster</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1570</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted transporters <italic>ABC transport</italic>ers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATAATAATAGCTAGTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fatC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter, permease protein, putative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0990</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATAATAATAGCTAGTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>yvsF</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter, permease protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0989</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TATAATAAGTGTCATTATT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hyp/cvaA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0932</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATAATAAGTGTCATTATT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0932</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAAAATGACAATCGATACT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">410</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cvaA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CvaA colicin V exporter MFP family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0931 AFE0931</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGTTTGTATACTTATTATC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>abcA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transport protein, ATP-binding subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0803.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGTAATGGTAACTGTTCTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nikB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Di/oligopeptide/nickel permease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0119</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TACTGGTAACTATTTTTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>abcS4</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter, periplasmic SO4/MoFeIII-binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1586</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cation diffusion facilitator transporters</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TACTGGTAACTATTTTTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cdf1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDF family protein*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1588</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RND efflux transporter</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TACTGGTAACTATTTTTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rnd1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy metal RND efflux outer membrane protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1587</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAATTGTTAATTTGTCTA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hyp/omf/mfp/rnd2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein TIGR00481</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1140</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TATAGCGGTATTGCACTTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>omf/mfp/rnd3</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy metal RND efflux outer membrane protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1057</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MFS Transporters</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAATGAATAAGTTTTATT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">276</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>msfB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug resistance transporter, EmrB-QacA family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE2984</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;P-type ATPase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;IT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCAAATGATAAGCATCCTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>copA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copper-translocating P-type ATPase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1073</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAAATGATAAGCATCCTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0329</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAAACGATAATTTTATTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">244</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>copB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copper-translocating P-type ATPase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE2222</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATGATGGTAAATATTCAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">391</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hat1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma-membrane proton-efflux P-type ATPase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulators</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATAAGGGTGAGCATACGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>iscR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe-S cluster assembly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE2368</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATAACTATAACTAGTTTA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>irr</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulator Fur family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE1137</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAAATGACAATTTTATGA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>phoB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulator PhoB family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0827</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTTTGGTAATTATAAGC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>arsR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulator ArsR family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0734</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAAATAGTAAGTATATTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>marR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulator MarR family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0507</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HMM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCAAAAGTAATTATTTAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ntrC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sigma-54 dependent transcriptional regulator NtrC family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFE0505</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>FURTA, Fur titration assay (T, positive titration); EMSA, Electrophoretic mobility shift assay (S, positive shift); IVTA, <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription assay (R, transcriptional repression); IT, Information Theory; HMM, Hidden Markov Models.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>First, Fur boxes were identified upstream of conserved <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> genes whose orthologs encode Fur-regulated functions in other microorganisms. This set of genes not only provides interesting insights into the iron uptake strategies of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> but also strengthens the validity of the prediction pipeline. Second, through this genome-wide search, Fur regulatory targets were predicted that are associated with a variety of other cellular functions (metal uptake, utilization and efflux; phosphate utilization; transcriptional regulators and redox balance) providing the first model of the Fur-dependent iron regulon in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. Selected predicted targets were functionally evaluated for Fur binding <italic>in vitro</italic> through (i) gel shift assays (EMSA) and (ii) Fur-mediated metal-dependent control determined by <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription analysis in the presence of purified Fur from <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> and the metal co-repressor.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> candidate Fur-binding sites and associated genes</title><p>Genes associated with predicted Fur-binding sites were classified into five functional categories (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). The first two categories include several genes orthologous to well characterized iron and/or Fur-regulated genes from other bacteria, encoding iron acquisition and iron utilization functions, respectively. Most Fur regulons described to date overlap at the level of iron uptake and iron utilizing protein functions. The fact that these two gene categories are also well represented in the <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> candidate target gene list, attests to the efficacy of the prediction pipeline outlined above.</p><p>The following predicted gene function categories correspond to those listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>.</p><p><bold>Iron acquisition</bold> includes a predicted GTP-driven FeoB ferrous iron uptake transporter, one ortholog of the NRAMP family of proton-coupled FeII/MnII transporters known in bacteria as MntH and a number of genes predicted to be involved in the uptake of ferric iron by means of <underline>T</underline>onB <underline>d</underline>ependent outer membrane ferri-siderophores <underline>r</underline>eceptors (Tdr) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Among the latter Fur regulatory targets are two adjacent genes encoding TonB-dependent OMRs with probable affinity for catechol siderophores (<italic>tdr</italic> of the <italic>cirA</italic>-type), a 13 gene cluster encoding for all necessary siderophore mediated ferric iron uptake functions and four loci encoding TonB/ExbBD biopolymer transport proteins.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Predicted Fur-regulated gene clusters and associated predicted Fur boxes grouped into four main functional categories: iron acquisition, iron utilization, transporters and transcriptional regulators. Arrows representing each gene indicate direction of transcription and are not drawn to scale. The double-hashed line separating independent gene clusters indicates that they are not contiguous in the genome.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm068f2"/></fig></p><p><bold>Iron utilization functions</bold> contain several genes predicted to encode redox proteins and/or Fe&#x02013;S binding proteins, including electron transporting ferredoxins, oxido/reductases (NuoI, NoxA), heme biosynthesis coproporphyrinogen III dehydrogenase (HemN), a high potential iron protein (HppH) and a subuntit of the Hup reductase involved in hydrogenase maturation (DrsK-like), and several genes implicated in Fe&#x02013;S cluster assembly such as a cysteine desulfurase NifS, accessory protein NifV and an Fe&#x02013;Mo nitrogen fixation protein (NifX) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p><bold>Transporters</bold> were identified belonging to diverse functional families (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) including two distinct efflux permeases of the ATP-dependent family of transmembrane efflux pumps (secretion ABC). One of these systems consists of adjacent genes encoding, respectively, a protein with a permease motif characteristic of the FatC Fe(III) -anguibactin efflux permease of <italic>Bartonella quintana</italic> (CAF26500) and an uncharacterized permease similar to YvsF (CAB69806) from <italic>Bacillus cereus.</italic> The other permease transporter is similar to CvaB of <italic>E. coli</italic> (P22520), and forms part of a predicted operon encoding a microcin exporter system that has been shown to be iron regulated via a well conserved Fur box in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Shared organization and associated Fur box suggest a similar regulatory behavior in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. Two gene clusters encoding resistance-nodulation-cell division (RND) family efflux pumps and one cluster encoding for a translocase of the major facilitator superfamily (MSF) are preceded by Fur boxes in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. RND complexes typically transport cations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>) or a chemically diverse group of organic substances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>) from the cytoplasm across the periplasmic space to the outside of the cell, driven by proton motive force. Additionally, trans-envelope efflux pumps of the RND have been proposed to be involved in the secretion of iron siderophores under conditions of iron starvation in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>) and <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). Recently, several MSFs sharing the signature COG0477 of the EmrB/QacA subfamily of MFS have been implicated in the proton motive force-driven and iron-regulated transport of siderophores in a number of bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43 B44 B45 B46 B47 B48">43&#x02013;48</xref>). The gene context of RND-1 and the presence of Fur boxes in the promoters of both the RND-1 and the MSF gene clusters suggest that their expression is regulated by iron and by Fur in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> and suggests a role for these proteins in the secretion of xenosiderophores. In addition, a hybrid operon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) consisting of an unusual combination of transport components including an ABC solute-binding protein (AbcS4<italic>)</italic>, an RND-type outer membrane factor (Rnd1) similar to OprD and a cation diffusion facilitator (Cdf1), was found in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. The solute-binding protein shares 70% similarity to the sulfate/molybdate-binding protein ModA (COG0725) and weak similarity (&#x0003c;30%) to the ABC-type Fe(III)-binding protein AfuA (COG1840), while the CDF (pfam01545) carries a C-terminal signature (MTH1175) found in several uncharacterized proteins belonging to the Fe&#x02013;Mo cluster binding proteins. Since members of the CDF family are metal-specific pumps that serve as secondary filters for various divalent cations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48 B49 B50">48&#x02013;50</xref>), a role for Mo or Fe efflux facilitation can be envisioned. Finally, three predicted ATP dependent translocases of charged ions of the P-type ATPases superfamily were found to have upstream Fur boxes. These membrane pathways can either actively take up or extrude inorganic monovalent cations such as Cu(I)/Ag(I), divalent Zn(II)/Cd(II)/Pb(II) or H(I)/Na(I)/K(I) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). One of the <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> candidate Fur-regulated P-type ATPases potentially encodes a plasma-membrane proton-efflux transporter [EC 3.6.3.6], and the other two are predicted to be copper P-type ATPases (CPx-type; EC 3.6.1.3) with similarity, respectively, to the well-studied CopA (61% S to P32113) and CopB (68% S to P05425) copper homeostasis proteins in <italic>Enterococcus hirae</italic>.</p><p><bold>Transcriptional regulators</bold> were identified belonging to six different protein families: IscR, Irr, PhoB, NtrC, MarR and ArsR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Some of these regulators exhibit iron and/or Fur-dependent expression in other bacteria and therefore are reasonable targets for Fur control in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. For example, the IscR regulator of <italic>E. coli</italic> controls the negative feedback expression of a housekeeping Fe&#x02013;S assembly gene-cluster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>) and the Irr regulator of &#x003b1;-proteobacteria is known to control heme biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>). The PhoB-like transcriptional regulator in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> is the first gene of a predicted operon containing the three components of the TonB iron acquisition system known to be a Fur target in other organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>) and an acid phosphatase similar to AcpA of <italic>Burkholderia sp</italic>. The other three transcriptional regulators are located upstream (ArsR) or divergent to (NtrC and MarR) gene clusters encoding proteins that have predicted roles in redox balance maintenance (e.g. rhodanases, glutaredoxins, thiorredoxins, GST). The presence of these Fur boxes suggests the necessity to control intracellular iron-mediated effects on oxidative stress.</p><p>In addition, several genes that encode a variety of functions such as ribosomal proteins, transposase etc., or genes with unknown functions were identified with predicted Fur boxes. Their possible role in Fur-regulated activities remains to be addressed.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental validation of selected candidate Fur boxes</title><sec><title>Fur titration assays (FURTA)</title><p>Evidence for the capacity of Fur from <italic>E. coli</italic> to recognize and bind target DNA sequences in our model system was obtained by transforming a gene library of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> into the <italic>E. coli</italic> FURTA reporter strain H1717 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Clones with LacZ-positive phenotype were recovered and the plasmids purified for DNA sequencing. Isolated genome fragments were inspected bioinformatically for the presence of ORFs, promoter regions and Fur-binding sites. FURTA positive clones retained after filtering as likely Fur targets in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>.</p><p>Sequence analysis of FURTA-positive clones revealed sequences with genes and/or promoters known to be regulated by Fur in other organisms such as the ferrous iron transporters <italic>feoPABC</italic> and <italic>mntH</italic>, several ferri-siderophore transport components (<italic>tdr</italic>, <italic>tonB</italic>, <italic>abc</italic>) and a variety of proteins that use iron as a cofactor in the form of heme groups or Fe&#x02013;S clusters (<italic>fdx1</italic>, <italic>hemN</italic>, <italic>hppH</italic>, <italic>dsrK</italic>, <italic>hdrC</italic>, <italic>iscR</italic>). In addition, the majority of these sequences contained predictions for Fur boxes according to information theory screens, based on a heterologous Fur box weight matrix, and/or by HMM profile searches based on EMSA-validated <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur boxes. These experimental results provide evidence that (i) there are several genomic sequences in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> carrying Fur-binding site motifs, (ii) that at least a part of the population of Fur-binding sites present in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> are recognizable by the Fur protein of <italic>E. coli in vivo</italic> and (iii) that several of the Fur-binding sites found within these genomic fragments coincide with the bioinformatically predicited Fur boxes presented above (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Fur<sub>AF</sub> binding to candidate Fur boxes (EMSA)</title><p>Gel shift assays with purified regulatory proteins is a well recognized method to reveal putative DNA-binding sites in a DNA probe that represent direct targets for the concerned regulator. To evaluate the functionality of the predicted Fur boxes, we assayed the capacity of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> purified Fur protein to form Fur<sub>AF</sub>&#x02013;DNA complexes <italic>in vitro</italic> using the EMSA.</p><p>Fur<sub>AF</sub> was able to shift the promoter regions of the iron acquisition genes <italic>gloA</italic> and <italic>feoB</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). Probes encompassing the Fur box predicted upstream of the transporter genes <italic>copB</italic> and <italic>abcS4</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B), the transcriptional regulators <italic>iscR</italic> and <italic>phoB</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C) and the iron-containing protein encoding genes <italic>hppH</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D) and <italic>fdx1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>E) were bound and shifted <italic>in vitro</italic> by 300&#x02009;nM purified Fur<sub>AF</sub>. No Fur<sub>AF</sub>-dependent shift was achieved with the probe for the predicted <italic>copA</italic> Fur box, indicating that Fur<sub>AF</sub> is unable to bind the region under the conditions used or else that this Fur box prediction is a false positive.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>EMSAs of <sup>32</sup>P-labeled DNA fragments (probes) containing predicted Fur boxes and promoters of (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>gloA</italic> and <italic>feoP</italic>, (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>copB</italic> and <italic>abcS4</italic>, (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>iscR</italic> and <italic>phoB</italic>, (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>hppH</italic> and (<bold>E</bold>) <italic>fdx1</italic> in the presence of Fur<sub>AF</sub> (Fur), Fur<sub>AF</sub> plus anti-Fur serum (&#x003b1;-Fur) or cold probe (P*) as indicated. (<bold>F</bold>) EMSA of a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled probe containing no predicted Fur box and corresponding to a low G + C DNA fragment of pUC18 vector. 1 = probe DNA, (A&#x02013;D) 2 = shift with 300&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub>, 3 = supershift with anti-Fur antibody; (E) 2 = shift with 300&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub>, 3 = shift with 400&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub>, 4 = supershift, 5 = cold probe competition, 6 = absence of shift in the presence of the anti-Fur antibody alone. (F) absence of shift in the presence of: 2 = 100 nM Fur<sub>AF</sub>, 3 = 200&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub>, 4 = 300&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub>, 5 = 400&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub> and occurrence of shift in the presence of 6 = 500&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm068f3"/></fig></p><p>These reactions were demonstrated to be Fur specific by supershifting in the presence of anti-Fur antiserum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, A&#x02013;D lane 3; E lane 4). A complete loss of the shift was also observed when excess unlabeled DNA probe was used to compete out the labeled probe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, E lane 5). No effect on the migration of the labeled probes could be detected in the absence of purified Fur<sub>AF</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, A&#x02013;E lane 1) or in the presence of the antiserum alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, E lane 6). Purified Fur<sub>AF</sub> up to 400&#x02009;nM was unable to shift a non-specific probe (no Fur box prediction) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, F lanes 2&#x02013;5). At 500&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub> non-specific binding was observed to occur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, F lane 6). Therefore, an upper limit of 400&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub> was set for specific binding assays.</p><p>EMSA results confirm that DNA fragments containing the predicted Fur boxes for <italic>gloA</italic>, <italic>feoB</italic>, <italic>copB</italic>, <italic>abcS4</italic>, <italic>iscR</italic>, <italic>phoB</italic>, <italic>hppH</italic> and <italic>fdx1</italic> could be recognized by purified Fur<sub>AF</sub>
<italic>in vitro</italic> and can thus be considered as <italic>bona fide</italic> sites. An additional predicted Fur box associated with <italic>mntH</italic> has been previously validated by EMSA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Transcriptional repression of Fur-dependent promoters by Fur<sub>AF</sub> using in vitro transcription assays (IVTA)</title><p>To evaluate the effect of Fur<sub>AF</sub> binding on transcription expression, predicted EMSA Fur targets were analyzed by <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription in the presence of the metal co-repressor Mn(II) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription assays (IVTAS) of genes with predicted Fur boxes. (<bold>A</bold>) Scheme of each gene showing the sequence and relative position of the predicted Fur box with respect to cognate promoters. (<bold>B</bold>) IVTAs in the presence (+) or absence (&#x02212;) of 300&#x02009;nM Fur<sub>AF</sub> and 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M Mn(II). Primers used for IVTAs are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>. M = molecular standards in bps. Arrow heads indicate where a transcript is absent after the addition of Fur<sub>AF</sub> and Mn(II).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm068f4"/></fig></p><p>All Fur boxes evaluated overlap with predicted &#x02212;10 or &#x02212;35 elements of the corresponding promoters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). In the presence of 300 nM purified Fur<sub>AF</sub> protein, 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M Mn(II) and <italic>E. coli's</italic> RNA polymerase, disappearance of the expected transcripts for the iron transporter genes <italic>feoP</italic> and <italic>gloA</italic>, the copper transporter <italic>copB</italic> and the transcriptional regulator <italic>phoB</italic> is observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). These results indicate that <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> regulator is involved in a classical divalent metal dependent Fur-mediated repression of transcription of the genes directly linked to the tested promoters and, by implication, also of the genes clustered with them in predicted operons.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Fur-binding site consensus sequence and organization in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic></title><p>Candidate <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur-binding sites derived from both bioinformatic prediction routines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C and D) and from experimental validations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>E) were aligned and used to derive the corresponding logos. <italic>Acidithobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> HMM-predicted species-specific Fur boxes, and the nine targets bound <italic>in vitro</italic> by Fur<sub>AF</sub> (including previously validated <italic>mntH</italic>), are conserved with respect to the <italic>E. coli</italic> Fur box consensus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A) in 10&#x02013;12 out of 19 positions including those deemed critical for Fur binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>).
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>DNA sequence logos of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur-binding sites derived from several bioinformatic and experimental prediction strategies. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>E. coli</italic> Fur box consensus sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>), (<bold>B</bold>) Heterologous training set logo (66 Fur boxes, Supplementary Data S1A), (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> information-theory-based logo (90 Fur boxes, Supplementary Data S1B), (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> HMM-based logo (79 Fur boxes, Supplementary Data S1D), (<bold>E</bold>) <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur box logo derived for EMSA-validated genes (9 Fur boxes), (<bold>F</bold>) <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> consensus Fur-binding sequence. Boxed and blue letters represent bases that are protected by Fur DNA binding in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm068f5"/></fig></p><p>Each of the candidate <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur box sequences contains a conserved core region encompassing two contiguous imperfect repeats with additional bases present in a poorly conserved third repeat offset either to the right or left of the central hexamer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>F). Although the key residues known to interact with Fur are conserved between <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>, the latter Fur box consensus exhibits a less conserved third flanking hexamer suggesting either that a single dimer of Fur binds to the box or else that the architecture of the box in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> might alter the capacity of Fur to polymerize along the site.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>ADDITIONAL DISCUSSION</title><p>As part of an effort to understand iron management in the acidophilic iron-oxidizing bacterium <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>, a combined computational search and experimental analysis to identify Fur-regulated genes was undertaken (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). This approach is particularly important given the lack of amenable genetic systems to manipulate <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> that impair classical genetic approaches to study Fur regulation. However, experimental validation of candidate Fur boxes is also essential to overcome the limitations of bioinformatic approaches imposed by the reduced information content and considerable sequence variability of Fur boxes. However, once a predicted site has been demonstrated to be functional, then that site can be employed to generate a revised binding site weight matrix to be used in a new global search for the identification of stronger regulatory signatures. Such a pipeline has been successfully introduced in the work described herein.</p><p>Fur-control is a common feature of ferrous iron and ferri-siderophore transporting genes in other bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55 B56 B57 B58">55&#x02013;58</xref>). Thus, the occurrence of a functional Fur regulator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) and of several predicted specialized high-affinity systems for the acquisition of iron (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>) provided initial evidence that a Fur-dependent regulatory network was present in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. The strategy devised herein enabled the recognition of cognate Fur-binding sites upstream of these previously identified iron acquisition genes and also uncovered several novel Fur targets specific for <italic>A. ferrooxidans.</italic> This new evidence not only provides a better understanding of the Fur regulon and the iron homeostasis control mechanisms in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>, but also provides the first consensus Fur box in acidophilic iron-oxidizers.</p><p>Among the high affinity iron acquisition systems that constitute part of the <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur regulon, the following were identified herein: a FeoB Fe(II) transporter, a <italic>gloA</italic>-linked TonB-dependent Fe(III)-siderophore transporter and several additional Fe(III)-siderophore transport components. A well conserved Fur box was recognized upstream of a predicted <italic>feoPABC</italic> gene cluster (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) and was shown to bind Fur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>) and to overlap with its promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Divalent metal-Fur-dependent repression of <italic>feoP</italic> was similar to that observed in other bacteria where expression of the <italic>feo</italic> gene cluster has been shown to vary in accordance with ferrous iron bioavailability in a Fur-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60 B61 B62 B63">60&#x02013;63</xref>) under anaerobic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>) or acidic-microaerobic growth conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>). In addition, a high scoring Fur box associated with a <italic>gloA</italic>-linked ferri-siderophore transporter (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) was bound by Fur <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>) and Fur binding to this site down regulated transcription of the transporter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). This evidence shows that the <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> TonB-dependent iron uptake system is probably regulated in a classical iron and Fur dependent way and suggests that <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> is able to scavenge iron from the environment if necessary as has been described for well-studied neutrophilic bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>). This novel finding raises the question as to what these iron-scarce environmental conditions might be, given that it is generally considered that <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> inhabits principally iron-rich acidic environments. It might be that <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> needs to compete occasionally for Fe(III) with other microorganisms in iron-poor environments while using sulfur as its principal energy source or else that these TonB-regulated systems confer <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> with a special capacity to acquire Fe(III) when Fe(II) concentrations begin to drop due to its oxidation. This property, might in turn, render <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> more sensitive to the high Fe(III) concentrations that are generated after prolonged bio-oxidation of minerals in tank reactors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>). Both possibilities require exploration.</p><p>The occurrence of predicted Fur boxes upstream of a number of <italic>nif</italic> and <italic>hup</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>) suggests that Fur acts specifically in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> to modulate the use of iron as a cofactor by the FeMo nitrogenase and the NiFe hydrogenase. These results are in agreement with the evidence presented for <italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) and <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) showing (positive) Fur regulation of <italic>nifS</italic> and the hydrogenase-2 operon <italic>yybOA-G</italic>, respectively. Other Fur target genes, coding for redox active proteins that carry iron as Fe&#x02013;S clusters or heme groups (e.g. certain ferredoxins), provide evidence that Fur-dependent control of the expression of iron-containing proteins also constitutes part of the global iron homeostatic mechanism in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> as has been found in other microorganisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Interestingly, the transcriptional regulators Irr and IscR, that control heme biosynthesis and Fe&#x02013;S cluster assembly and/or repair respectively, also constitute part of the <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> Fur regulon. This finding suggests that Fur<sub>AF</sub>, in addition to controlling metaloprotein expression, could be indirectly adjusting cofactor production in response to changes in iron availability through coordinated control of specific secondary regulators.</p><p>In addition, the results presented herein are in agreement with reports in other microorganisms showing that Fur controls the expression of genes belonging to several functional classes besides iron transport and utilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Our global search of Fur boxes in the genome of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> yielded a substantial number of putative boxes that were associated with functions that are not <italic>a priori</italic> related to iron metabolism but which can be clearly related to metal homeostasis. Several of the Fur regulatory targets identified in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> are efflux transporters driven either by ATP or by protons, with specificities other than iron. As a strict acidophile <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> has to face the high concentrations of iron required for its energetic metabolism, but also it has to deal with the high concentrations of most other metals found in its environment, notably copper.</p><p>The most important metal recovered in industrial bioleaching operations is copper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>). Copper is bioleached as soluble copper sulfate from insoluble copper sulfides by acid and ferric iron. <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>, and other acidophilic iron oxidizers, contribute to the solubilization of copper by generating ferric iron and sulfuric acid as by-products of metabolism and in a typical bioleaching operation are confronted with soluble copper concentrations that may exceed 600 mM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>). Copper-adapted cell shows decreased Cu(II) accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>), suggesting that the Cu(II) is excluded from the cell possibly via an inducible efflux system. The Cu efflux P-type ATPase CopB and the Cus-like RND system identified herein could contribute to this task.</p><p>Physiologically, copper is an essential metal ion required as a cofactor for enzymes such as the copper-heme family of cytochrome c oxidases (that also carry Fe&#x02013;S clusters) and electron transporting blue copper proteins like rusticyanin (5% of the total soluble protein in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>). However, as with other redox active metals, use of copper in aerobes is inevitably accompanied by oxidative stress in the absence of tightly regulated homeostatic mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>). In this context, a coordinated homeostatic response to both iron and copper mediated by Fur would be beneficial both for energetic metabolism and for cell survival. Alternatively, Fur could be regulating the expression of the copper trafficking genes via metal-independent mechanisms, such as in response to acid shock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>). Two independent observations support this view: (i) studies in the acid tolerant <italic>Lactobacillus bulgaricus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>) and <italic>H. pylori</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>) have shown that acidification of the growth medium significantly induced the expression of <italic>cop</italic> orthologs by an unknown mechanism and (ii) a Fur box has been described for <italic>copA</italic> in <italic>H. pylori</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>).</p><p>Several of the Fur target genes identified in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>, are transcriptional regulators. Thus, many genes are probably controlled indirectly by Fur. This finding implies that Fur acts as a master regulator of iron-dependent gene expression in <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic>. An iron-responsive global regulator, like Fur, could aid in the control of metal transport functions that in general entail a risk for <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> by coordinating the expression of a variety of metal uptake and efflux systems when iron, and probably other metals are in excess, either directly or through a set of secondary regulators. Consistent with this suggestion is the evidence indicating that metal toxicity for <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> is dependent on the growth substrate; for example, cultures growing on Fe(II) rather than on thiosulfate are more metal resistant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>).</p><p>During chemolithoautotrophic growth, <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> oxidizes ferrous iron to ferric iron as an energy source. Therefore, iron uptake systems involved in the assimilation of iron for biosynthesis must be fine-tuned with iron utilizing proteins implicated in ferrous iron oxidation. In the initial stages of growth at pH 2, when ferrous iron is highly abundant, sensitive control of the expression levels of these systems by Fur is expected to allow a sufficient provision of iron for biosynthesis yet avoiding intracellular overloads that would cause severe oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>). Intracellular copper levels might be fine-tuned with intracellular iron level, through Fur-dependent balancing of the uptake and efflux of this metal. Such a coordinated response might ensure that both metals, needed as cofactors for many energy-metabolism proteins, are simultaneously available in appropriate concentrations. However, as iron levels increase above a certain &#x02018;repression-threshold,&#x02019; Fur might turn off high affinity Fe(II) uptake systems and copper transporters to escape oxidative threats. In addition, as growth proceeds and ferrous iron is oxidized to Fe(III), <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> might need to switch to the uptake of ferric iron. Alternatively, during growth of <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> via the oxidation of sulfur at higher pHs (3.5&#x02013;5.5), where iron availability might become limiting both as an energy source and as a nutrient, it is hypothesized that the ferrous iron oxidizing machinery will need to be turned off while ferric iron acquisition systems might be activated to scavenge for iron traces and efficiently compete with other microorganisms present in its niche. Under these conditions efficient intracellular removal of xenosiderophores might become necessary, either to efficiently recycle these high affinity chelators or for cell detoxification. Fur-dependent regulation, coupling the expression levels of all these systems driven by iron oxidation during <italic>A. ferrooxidans</italic> growth, is likely to be a key aspect for iron homeostasis and survival in this bacterium.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR online.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm068_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="nar_gkm068_nar-02876-t-2006-File008.xls"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>Work supported by Fondecyt 1050063, Fondecyt 11060164, DI-UNAB 25-04-R, DI-UNAB 34-06-R and a Microsoft sponsored research award. I.P. thanks the Fundaci&#x000f3;n Andes for a student scholarship. We gratefully acknowledge Alex Bateman, Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Cambridge, UK, for discussions and Emilio Garcia, Lawrence Livermore Lab, Berkeley, 50 USA, for sequencing some FURTA clones. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charge was provided by Andr&#x000e9;s Bello University.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baichoo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmann</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of the <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> Fur regulon and the iron starvation stimulon</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1613</fpage><lpage>1629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12354229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hantke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iron and metal regulation in bacteria</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11282473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escolar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opening the iron box: transcriptional metalloregulation by the Fur protein</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1999</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>6223</fpage><lpage>6229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10515908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Qui&#x000f1;ones</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul-Tehrani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Svistunenko</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global iron-dependent gene regulation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. A new mechanism for iron homeostasis</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>29478</fpage><lpage>29486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12746439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochsner</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilderman</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasil</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasil</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GeneChipR expression analysis of the iron starvation response in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: identification of novel pyoverdine biosynthesis genes</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12207696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinkey</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cianciotto</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and sequencing of the <italic>Legionella pneumoniae fur</italic> gene</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1994</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8200525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loong Chan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and transcription regulation of the ferric uptake regulatory gene of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> TGH9011</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1995</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7590316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochsner</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasil</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene repression by the ferric uptake regulator in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: cycle selection of iron-regulated genes</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>4409</fpage><lpage>4414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8633080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Angerer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Genco</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of Fur binding to operator sequences within the <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae fbpA</italic> promoter</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1996</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>5020</fpage><lpage>5023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8759870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosa</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the interaction between Fur and the iron transport promoter of the virulence plasmid in <italic>Vibrio anguillarum</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>33841</fpage><lpage>33847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9837975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watnick</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Butterton</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderwood</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The interaction of the <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> transcription factors, Fur and IrgB, with the overlapping promoters of two virulence genes, <italic>irgA</italic> and <italic>irgB</italic></article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1998</year><volume>209</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9524224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fetherston</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertolino</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>YbtP and YbtQ: two ABC transporters required for iron uptake in <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10231486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wexler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolade</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmings</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>AWB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fur is not the global regulator of iron uptake genes in <italic>Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>1357</fpage><lpage>1365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brian</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel DNA-binding site for the ferric uptake regulator (Fur) protein from <italic>Bradyrhizobium japonicum</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>38395</fpage><lpage>38401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12881516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stojiljkovic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumler</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hantke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fur regulon in gram-negative bacteria. Identification and characterization of new iron-regulated <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> genes by a Fur titration assay</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>236</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8107138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsolis</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumler</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojiljkovic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Heffron</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fur regulon of <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic>: identification of new iron-regulated genes</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1995</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>4628</fpage><lpage>4637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7642488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fassbinder</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van Vliet</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimmel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusters</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bereswill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of iron-regulated genes of <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> by a modified fur titration assay (FURTA-Hp)</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett</source><year>2000</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10713425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vassinova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozyrev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method for direct cloning of Fur regulated genes: identification of seven new Fur-regulated loci in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>3171</fpage><lpage>3182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11101675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Beliaev</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Giometti</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollaksen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Khare</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lies</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nealson</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional and proteomic analysis of a ferric uptake regulator (<italic>fur</italic>) mutant of <italic>Shewanella oneidensis</italic>: possible involvement of <italic>fur</italic> in energy metabolism, transcriptional regulation, and oxidative stress</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11823232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjarnason</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Southward</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Surette</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic profiling of iron-responsive genes in <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> Serovar <italic>Typhimurium</italic> by high-throughput screening of a random promoter library</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2003</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>4973</fpage><lpage>4982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12897017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grifantini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frigimelica</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Draghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartolini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rappuoli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Genco</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of iron-activated and repressed Fur-dependent genes by transcriptome analysis of <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic> group B</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>9542</fpage><lpage>9547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12883001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bereswill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Waidner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoof</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mader</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusters</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuipers</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Vliet</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional profiling of <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> Fur- and iron-regulated gene expression</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15699202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Doan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computation-directed identification of oxyR DNA binding sites in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2001</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>4571</fpage><lpage>4579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11443092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mironov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Roytberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computer analysis of transcription regulatory patterns in completely sequenced bacterial genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2981</fpage><lpage>2989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10390542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shultzaberger</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using sequence logos and information analysis of Lrp DNA binding sites to investigate discrepancies between natural selection and SELEX</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9889287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hengen</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartram</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Information analysis of Fis binding sites</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>4994</fpage><lpage>5002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erill</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Escribano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Campoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barb&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In silico analysis reveals substantial variability in the gene contents of the Gamma Proteobacteria LexA-regulon</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2225</fpage><lpage>2236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14630651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panina</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mironov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of Fur regulons in gamma-proteobacteria</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>5195</fpage><lpage>5206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11812853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baichoo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmann</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of DNA by Fur: a reinterpretation of the Fur box consensus sequence</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2002</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>5826</fpage><lpage>5832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12374814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Information content of individual genetic sequences</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9446751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neilands</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metal ion regulation of gene expression. Fur repressor-operator interaction at the promoter region of the aerobactin system of pColV-K30</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1988</year><volume>203</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3062182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escolar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Binding of the Fur (ferric uptake regulator) repressor of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to arrays of the GATAAT sequence</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9784364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HMMER 1.8 program: Hidden Markov models of proteins and DNA sequences</article-title><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Seattle</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Washington University School of Medicine</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hantke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection procedure for deregulated iron transport mutants (<italic>fur</italic>) in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K 12: fur not only affects iron metabolism</article-title><source>Mol. Gen. Genet</source><year>1987</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3323834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Touati</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tardat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Despied</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lethal oxidative damage and mutagenesis are generated by iron in delta Fur mutants of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: protective role of superoxide dismutase</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1995</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>2305</fpage><lpage>2314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7730258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quatrini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefimil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jedlicki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ferric iron uptake regulator (Fur) from the extreme acidophile <italic>Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>2005</fpage><lpage>2015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15942007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</source><year>1989</year><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the <italic>cvaA</italic> and <italic>cvi</italic> promoters of the colicin V export system: iron dependent transcription of <italic>cvaA</italic> is modulated by downstream sequences</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1998</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>1662</fpage><lpage>1672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9537361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Phung</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial heavy metal resistance: new surprises</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8905098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikaido</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple antibiotic resistance and efflux</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10066525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Neshat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple antibiotic resistance in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: evidence for involvement of an efflux operon</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1993</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>7363</fpage><lpage>7372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8226684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Neshat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and sequence analysis of an EnvCD homologue in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: regulation by iron and possible involvement in the secretion of the siderophore pyoverdine</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7968531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorsey</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolmasky</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosa</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Actis</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic organization of an <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> chromosomal region harbouring genes related to siderophore biosynthesis and transport</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>1227</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerinot</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FRD3, a member of the multidrug and toxin efflux family, controls iron deficiency responses in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1787</fpage><lpage>1799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12172022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Funahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinoda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of genes required for biosynthesis and transport of the siderophore vibrioferrin in <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2003</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>6938</fpage><lpage>6949</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14617658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Salicylate induces an antibiotic efflux pump in <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic> complex genomovar III (<italic>B. cenocepacia</italic>)</article-title><source>J. Clin. Invest</source><year>2004</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14755343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brickman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bordetella AlcS transporter functions in alcaligin siderophore export and is central to inducer sensing in positive regulation of alcaligin system gene expression</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>3650</fpage><lpage>3661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15901687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nies</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efflux-mediated heavy metal resistance in prokaryotes</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000fc;nberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wawer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tebo</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;ler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A large gene cluster encoding several magnetosome proteins is conserved in different species of magnetotactic bacteria</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>4573</fpage><lpage>4582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11571158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of two homologous yeast genes that encode mitochondrial iron transporters</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>28485</fpage><lpage>28493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9353309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Giel</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Patschkowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Luther</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruzicka</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beinert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IscR, an Fe-S cluster-containing transcription factor, represses expression of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> genes encoding Fe-S cluster assembly proteins</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>14895</fpage><lpage>14900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamza</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brian</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bacterial irr protein is required for coordination of heme biosynthesis with iron availability</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>21669</fpage><lpage>21674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9705301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Llagostera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez de Rozas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Badiola</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Pasteurella multocida exbB</italic>, <italic>exbD</italic> and <italic>tonB</italic> genes are physically linked but independently transcribed</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett</source><year>2002</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12044675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The interaction of the ferric uptake regulation protein with DNA</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun</source><year>1995</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>784</fpage><lpage>792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7626111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crosa</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signal transduction and transcriptional and posttranscriptional control of iron-regulated genes in bacteria</article-title><source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev</source><year>1997</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9293185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Occhino</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyckoff</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wrona</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> iron transport: haem transport genes are linked to one of two sets of <italic>tonB, exbB, exbD</italic> genes</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>1507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9781885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaisser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>tonB</italic> gene of <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic>: sequence, activity and partial complementation of <italic>Escherichia coli tonB</italic> mutants</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2777</fpage><lpage>2787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1838128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Postle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aerobic regulation of the <italic>Escherichia coli tonB</italic> gene by changes in iron availability and the <italic>fur</italic> locus</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1990</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>2287</fpage><lpage>2293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2139645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quatrini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jedlicki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic insights into the iron uptake mechanisms of the biomining microorganism <italic>Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic></article-title><source>J. Indust. Microbiol. Biotech</source><year>2005</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>614</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patzer</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hantke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual repression by Fe(2+)-Fur and Mn(2+)-MntR of the <italic>mntH</italic> gene, encoding an NRAMP-like Mn(2+) transporter in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2001</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>4806</fpage><lpage>4813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11466284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodionov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubchak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstruction of regulatory and metabolic pathways in metal-reducing-&#x003b4;-proteobacteria</article-title><source>Genome. Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R90</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15535866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kehres</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Janakiraman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Slauch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> Serovar <italic>Typhimurium mntH</italic> transcription by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, FeII, and MnII</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2002</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>3151</fpage><lpage>3158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hantke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hengge-Aronis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The art of keeping low and high iron concentrations in balance</article-title><source>Bacterial Stress Responses</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>ASM Press, Washington DC</publisher-name><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>288</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kammler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hantke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the ferrous iron uptake system of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1993</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>6212</fpage><lpage>6219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8407793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Velayudhan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McColm</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagshaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iron acquisition and virulence in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>: a major role for FeoB, a high-affinity ferrous iron transporter</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Qui&#x000f1;ones</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial iron homeostasis</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawlings</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tributsch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansford</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reasons why &#x0201c;<italic>Leptospirillum</italic>&#x0201d;-like species rather than <italic>Thiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> are the dominant iron-oxidizing bacteria in many commercial processes for the biooxidation of pyrite and related ores</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1999</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10206710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brierley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brierley</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioleaching review, part B. Progress in bioleaching: applications of microbial processes by the minerals industries</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14566430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Modak</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerez</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiertz</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of special strains of <italic>Thiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> for enhanced bioleaching of sulphide minerals</article-title><source>Biohydrometallurgical Processing</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Santiago</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Chile</publisher-name><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnin</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copper ion removal by <italic>Thiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> biomass</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>190</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teitzel</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Geddi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De Long</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirisits</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsek</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival and growth in the presence of elevated copper: transcriptional profiling of copper-stressed <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2006</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>7242</fpage><lpage>7256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17015663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Touati</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iron and oxidative stress in bacteria</article-title><source>Arch. Biochem. Biophys</source><year>2000</year><volume>373</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10620317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of fur in the acid tolerance response of <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> is physiologically and genetically separable from its role in iron acquisition</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1996</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>5683</fpage><lpage>5691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8824613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bijlsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Waidner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vliet</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hag</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bereswill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenbroucke-Grauls</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> homologue of the ferric uptake regulator is involved in acid resistance</article-title><source>Infect. Immun</source><year>2002</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11796589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudebbouze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Maguin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Guchte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of heavy-metal-transporting CPX-type ATPases during acid adaptation in <italic>Lactobacillus bulgaricus</italic></article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>7445</fpage><lpage>7454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16997986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sindici</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matrubutham</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gleeson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acid-induced gene expression in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>: study in genomic scale by microarray</article-title><source>Infect. Immun</source><year>2001</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1679</fpage><lpage>1686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11179343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Spohn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rappuoli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarlato</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of an operon of <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> that is involved in motility and stress adaptation</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1997</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>4676</fpage><lpage>4683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9244252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondratyeva</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Muntyan</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Karavaiko</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc- and arsenic-resistant strains of <italic>Thiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> have increased copy numbers of chromosomal resistance genes</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1995</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1157</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trevors</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Oddie</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Belliveau</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metal resistance in bacteria</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev</source><year>1985</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avoidance of iron toxicity through regulation of bacterial iron transport</article-title><source>Biol. Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9377472</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
