<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17478521</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1904298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm206</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sequences in <italic>attB</italic> that affect the ability of &#x003d5;C31 integrase to synapse and to activate DNA cleavage</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Milind</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Till</surname><given-names>Rob</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Margaret C. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Institute of Medical Sciences, University of Aberdeen, Foresterhill, Aberdeen AB25 2ZD and <sup>2</sup>Institute of Genetics, Queens Medical Centre, University of Nottingham, Nottingham NG7 2UH, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>01224 555739</phone>; Fax: <fax>01224 555844</fax>; Email: <email>Maggie.smith@abdn.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3407</fpage><lpage>3419</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Phage integrases are required for recombination of the phage genome with the host chromosome either to establish or exit from the lysogenic state. <bold>&#x003d5;</bold>C31 integrase is a member of the serine recombinase family of site-specific recombinases. In the absence of any accessory factors integrase is unidirectional, catalysing the integration reaction between the phage and host attachment sites, <italic>attP</italic> &#x000d7; <italic>attB</italic> to generate the hybrid sites, <italic>attL</italic> and <italic>attR</italic>. The basis for this directionality is due to selective synapsis of <italic>attP</italic> and <italic>attB</italic> sites. Here we show that mutations in <italic>attB</italic> can block the integration reaction at different stages. Mutations at positions distal to the crossover site inhibit recombination by destabilizing the synapse with <italic>attP</italic> without significantly affecting DNA-binding affinity. These data are consistent with the proposal that integrase adopts a specific conformation on binding to <italic>attB</italic> that permits synapsis with <italic>attP</italic>. Other <italic>attB</italic> mutants with changes close to the crossover site are able to form a stable synapse but cleavage of the substrates is prevented. These mutants indicate that there is a post-synaptic DNA recognition event that results in activation of DNA cleavage.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>&#x003d5;C31 integrase and several of its relatives are being widely used for precise engineering of complex genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3 B4 B5 B6 B7 B8">1&#x02013;8</xref>) and are emerging as promising new tools for gene therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9 B10 B11 B12 B13 B14 B15">9&#x02013;15</xref>). In addition to being highly portable &#x003d5;C31 integrase is, unlike other recombinases used for genome manipulation such as Cre and Flp, unidirectional (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). In nature phage integrases are required for recombination of the phage genome with the host chromosome either to establish or exit from the lysogenic state. For integration the host-encoded <italic>attB</italic> site undergoes a conservative and reciprocal recombination with the phage <italic>attP</italic> site to form the hybrid product sites, <italic>attL</italic> and <italic>attR</italic>. During induction into the lytic cycle, the phage genome excises and this reaction normally requires integrase and an accessory protein Xis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Phage-encoded integrases can belong to the tyrosine or the serine recombinase families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Both families of proteins act by binding to their cognate substrates and bringing the DNAs together in a synapse. Recombination is initiated by cleaving DNA strands, which undergo strand exchange to form recombinant products and these are then released (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). While the mechanism of phage &#x003bb; integrase, a tyrosine recombinase, is well understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>), the mechanism of action of integrases such as &#x003d5;C31 integrase that belong to the serine recombinase family, is less clear.</p><p>All serine recombinases have a conserved catalytic domain required for DNA cleavage and rejoining (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). The resolvase/invertases also have a small (&#x0223c;60 amino acids; aa) C-terminal DNA-binding domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). The serine integrases, some transposases and the staphylococcal cassette recombinases (Ccr proteins; required for the movement of methicillin resistance gene in MRSA) are so-called large serine recombinases as they have extensive C-terminal domains (&#x0223c;300&#x02013;500 aa in length; 20). Sequence alignments of these large serine recombinases indicate that they are an extremely diverse family. Experiments with &#x003d5;C31 integrase, mycobacteriophage Bxb1 integrase and TnpX transposase suggest that the recombination mechanism used by the large serine recombinases resembles that of the well-studied resolvase/invertases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26 B27 B28 B29 B30 B31 B32 B33">26&#x02013;33</xref>). DNA cleavage occurs at a 2&#x02009;bp crossover sequence to form a staggered break and a transient covalent phosphoserine bond between the recessed 5&#x02032; ends and the recombinase is formed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Strand exchange most likely occurs by rotation of two recombinase subunits bound to half sites relative to the other two subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34 B35 B36 B37">34&#x02013;37</xref>). Rejoining of the products is dependent on the complementarity of the DNA sequence at the staggered breaks; if there is a mismatch at this sequence, joining of the products is severely inhibited but iteration of strand exchange results in changes in the topology of the substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>).</p><p>Divergence from the resolvase paradigm by the serine integrases occurs in the nature of substrate recognition and the formation of the synapse. The pairs of recombination sites used by the serine integrases have different sequences; for example, the &#x003d5;C31 <italic>attP</italic> and <italic>attB</italic> sites share 39% sequence identity [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>)]. The recombination sites are generally short, &#x0223c;50&#x02009;bp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). The minimal sites for &#x003d5;C31 integrase have been defined as a 39&#x02009;bp <italic>attP</italic> site and a 34&#x02009;bp <italic>attB</italic> site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Under <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions &#x003d5;C31 integrase converts &#x0223c;80% of <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> to products in the absence of accessory proteins and there are no restrictions on the topology of the substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Moreover, in these <italic>in vitro</italic> reactions, &#x003d5;C31 integrase is catalytically inert on all other combinations of substrates including <italic>attL</italic> and <italic>attR</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Hatfull and colleagues have shown that Bxb1 integrase has similar properties and they have gone on to show that Bxb1 integrase binds to its substrates as a dimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). The synapse is therefore likely to contain a tetramer of integrase subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>&#x003d5;C31 <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> sites. (<bold>A</bold>) The double-stranded DNA sequences of the <italic>S. coelicolor attB</italic> site (green) and the <italic>attP</italic> site (blue) are shown. The crossover dinucleotides are shown in black. The colons connecting the two sequences indicate the positions of sequence identity between the aligned <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> sites. The grey shading indicates the positions where sequence conservation can be detected between the <italic>attB</italic> or <italic>attP</italic> sites and their pseudo-sites from <italic>Streptomyces</italic> or <italic>Mycobacteria</italic> (pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sites) or from human or mouse cell lines (pseudo-<italic>attP</italic> sites) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9 B41 B42 B43">41&#x02013;43</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Summary of mutation scanning in <italic>attB</italic>. The <italic>attB</italic> site is shown as a single-strand sequence where each base acts as point on the <italic>x</italic>-axis of a histogram. The <italic>y</italic>-axis shows the fold reduction in product made when mutations are introduced in <italic>attB</italic>. The positions are annotated according to the numbering shown. The activities of <italic>attB</italic> sites with double mutations at symmetrical positions (eg &#x02212;/+1, &#x02212;/+2, etc.) are shown in pink and the activities of mutants with single mutations are shown in black. The data for the summary graph were calculated from the estimated absolute activities shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and Supplementary Data, Figure S1. Beneath the <italic>attB</italic> sequence, three of the <italic>S. coelicolor</italic> pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sites [<italic>pseB1, pseB2</italic> and <italic>pseB3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>)] are shown for comparison with the wild-type <italic>attB</italic>. The four sites have been aligned and are shaded according to whether there is 100% identity (black background and white text) or 75% identity (grey background) between the sites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm206f1"/></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Recombination activities of <italic>attB</italic> mutant sites. Recombination activities are shown for the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site (<bold>A</bold>), mutant sites at position 2 (<bold>B</bold>), 6 (<bold>C</bold>), 12 (<bold>D</bold>), 15 (<bold>E</bold>), 16 (<bold>F</bold>) 18 (<bold>G</bold>). Panel <bold>H</bold> shows the activities of partially symmetrized <italic>attB</italic> sites that contain the right sequence between +12 and +18 changed to the same sequence as on the left (&#x02212;12 to &#x02212;18), 2L (+12 to +18) or vice versa, 2R (&#x02212;12 to &#x02212;18). Recombination assays were performed using the standard plasmid assay containing the plasmid indicated in each panel and pRT702 encoding <italic>attP</italic>. The concentrations of integrase used for each set of six reactions in panels A to C and E, F and H was 0, 441, 110, 55, 27 and 14&#x02009;nM. The concentrations of integrase used for each set of six reactions in panels D and G was 0, 351, 87, 43, 21 and 10&#x02009;nM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm206f2"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>List of mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites and their activity compared to the wild-type <italic>attB</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkm206i2.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p><sup>a</sup>Concentration of integrase required to observe recombinants in a 0.8% TBE gel stained with ethidium bromide. Two concentrations (350&#x02013;87 or 55&#x02013;27&#x02009;nM) are given when the level of recombination obtained at the lower concentration is much less than that obtained with 14&#x02009;nM integrase with wild-type <italic>attB.</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>A major focus in our lab has been to understand why &#x003d5;C31 integrase can only recombine <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP in vitro</italic>. We have shown previously that integrase cannot synapse pairs of recombination sites other than <italic>attP</italic> with <italic>attB</italic> indicating that the formation of the synapse is the major block to excision <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). We and others have proposed that integrase adopts specific conformations when bound to <italic>attP</italic> and <italic>attB</italic> sites that enable the formation of a synapse, but when bound to <italic>attL</italic> and <italic>attR</italic> disable or destabilize the synapse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). In this model, the interactions between integrase and <italic>attP</italic> and <italic>attB</italic> are central to the formation of the synaptic interface. Some clues as to the preferred sequences of <italic>attP</italic> and <italic>attB</italic> have been obtained previously through studies that have characterized the substrates used by integrase when one of the cognate sites is not present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). Pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sites in the bacterial host, <italic>Streptomyces coelicolor</italic> and other actinomycetes show a strong preference for certain bases [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>)]. Similarly, pseudo-<italic>attP</italic> sites have been characterized in mammalian genomes and these also show base specific preferences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Many of the bases that are conserved in the pseudo-<italic>attP</italic> and pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sites are also conserved between <italic>attP</italic> and <italic>attB</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>To examine the integrase&#x02013;<italic>attB</italic> interaction in more detail, the minimal <italic>attB</italic> site was subjected to mutagenesis and the activities of the mutants assayed in recombination and binding assays. Recombination defective <italic>attB</italic> mutants that could still bind to integrase with affinities not dissimilar to the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site were found to be blocked either at synapsis or at DNA cleavage. The most likely explanation is that there are two separate recognition events that occur between integrase and the <italic>attB</italic> site. The first event results in a protein&#x02013;protein interface that enables synapsis and the second post-synapsis event results in activation of DNA cleavage.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Bacterial strains and plasmids</title><p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains DH5<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> and DS941 were used as general cloning hosts and were grown in LB or 2xYT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). <italic>E. coli</italic> transformation, plasmid preparations and DNA manipulation were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>).</p><p>Plasmids pRT600 and pRT700 were constructed previously by insertion of annealed oligonucleotides RM1/RM2 containing <italic>attB</italic> (51&#x02009;bp) and RM3/RM4 <italic>attP</italic> (50&#x02009;bp) sites inserted into pGEM7 cut with EcoRI and Csp45I (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). For this work, the <italic>attP</italic> site from pRT700 was excised with BamHI and EcoRI and inserted into BamHI and EcoRI cut pSP72 to form pRT702. Plasmids containing mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites at all positions except for &#x02212;/+3, &#x02212;/+8 and &#x02212;/+12 were constructed as for pRT600; annealed oligonucleotides (see Supplementary Data, Table S1) were inserted into pGEM7 cut with EcoRI and Csp45I. Plasmids containing mutations at &#x02212;/+3, &#x02212;/+8 and &#x02212;/+12 were constructed differently; PCR amplification using primers containing a randomized base at positions 3, 8 or 12 (Supplementary Data, Table S2) resulted in fragments that could be inserted into pGEM7 and these were then sequenced to determine the nature of the mutations. To create the double mutants with mutations at symmetrical positions, fragments containing the two single mutations were spliced together using the unique StyI site in the centre of the <italic>attB</italic> site. All the plasmids containing the mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites were subjected to confirmation by sequencing.</p></sec><sec><title>Recombination assays</title><p>Standard recombination assays between two attachment sites located on two separate plasmids were performed as described previously. Plasmids (100&#x02009;ng each) containing <italic>attB</italic> (or the mutant <italic>attB</italic>s) and <italic>attP</italic> were mixed with 18&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of recombination buffer (10&#x02009;mM Tris pH 7.5, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA pH 8, 100&#x02009;mM NaCl, 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 5&#x02009;mM spermidine, 4.5% glycerol and 0.5&#x02009;mg/ml bovine serum albumin) and &#x003d5;C31 integrase was added to the recombination reaction to final concentrations 0, 441, 110, 55, 27 or 14&#x02009;nM unless otherwise stated. Reactions were incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h unless otherwise stated and terminated by incubation at 65&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min. After addition of an equal volume of 2&#x000d7; restriction buffer (20&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 7.9, 100&#x02009;mM NaCl, 20&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2&#x02009;mM DTT) the plasmids were treated with HindIII restriction endonuclease (37&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;h) and the fragments were separated by electrophoresis through 0.8% agarose gels in 1&#x000d7; TBE buffer (100&#x02009;V). HindIII linearizes the substrates containing <italic>attB</italic> (or mutant <italic>attBs)</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> to give DNA molecules of 3035 and 2491&#x02009;bp, respectively. The recombination product is a cointegrate of the two substrate plasmids and is cut by HindIII into two fragments; 5435&#x02009;bp containing <italic>attL</italic> and 91&#x02009;bp containing <italic>attR</italic>. Only the <italic>attL</italic> fragment is detected routinely after electrophoresis.</p><p>Recombination reactions were also performed using a plasmid encoding the <italic>attP</italic> site, pRT702, and annealed oligonucleotides containing the <italic>attB</italic> sequence or its mutant derivatives (the &#x02018;oligo-plasmid&#x02019; assay; see Table S2 in the Supplementary Data for the sequences of the oligos) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). pRT702 (100&#x02009;ng) was mixed with 4.5&#x02009;ng of annealed oligonucleotides encoding a mutant <italic>attB</italic> site and 18&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of recombination buffer. &#x003d5;C31 integrase (1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l) was added to give final concentrations as described above (i.e. 0, 441, 110, 55, 27 and 14&#x02009;nM) and the reactions were incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h. The recombination reactions were terminated by heat inactivating the samples at 65&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min and the products of recombination were analysed on 0.8% agarose gels in 1&#x000d7; TBE buffer (100&#x02009;V). The products of recombination were identified as linear DNAs (2546&#x02009;bp).</p></sec><sec><title>DNA binding and radioactive recombination assays</title><p>DNA affinity and synapse assays were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). DNA fragments for radioactive labelling were prepared by digestion of pRT600 (encoding wt <italic>attB</italic>), pRT700 (encoding <italic>attP</italic>), or plasmids containing cloned annealed oligonucleotide pairs encoding mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites with HindIII and XhoI restriction enzymes. The 72&#x02009;bp fragments containing the <italic>att</italic> sites were separated on 4% agarose gel (Nusieve agarose) and then purified using gel extraction columns (QIAGEN) as per the manufacturer's protocol. The concentration of the purified fragment was determined on 4% agarose gels following which the fragments were end-labelled using DNA polymerase I large (Klenow) fragment in the presence of [<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02212;<sup>32</sup>P]dCTP (as described previously in Sambrook <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>)). Unless otherwise stated, binding affinity assays were performed with 1.0&#x02009;ng labelled probe in binding buffer (20&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA, 50&#x02009;mM KCl, 5% glycerol), 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g sonicated salmon sperm DNA and integrase added to final concentrations of 0, 351, 87, 43, 21 and 10&#x02009;nM. Reactions with no integrase contained 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g BSA. Reactions were incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min prior to electrophoresis following which the reaction mix were separated on 5% non denaturing 0.5&#x000d7; TBE polyacrylamide gels in 0.5&#x000d7; TBE running buffer (200&#x02009;V, 5&#x02009;W for 2&#x02009;h).</p><p>For radioactive recombination assays, unlabelled &#x02018;partner&#x02019; fragments prepared by PCR amplification of pRT600 and pRT700 with SP6 and T7 primers containing either <italic>attP</italic> (193&#x02009;bp) or wt or mutant <italic>attBs</italic> (194&#x02009;bp) were added to the radiolabelled attachment site in the presence of integrase. Complexes containing either the uncleaved synapse, the cleaved intermediates with integrase bound covalently to the <italic>att</italic> sites, and integrase bound to the labelled substrate and products were observed by non-denaturing PAGE as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). These assays were performed using 1.5&#x02009;ng of labelled probe (72&#x02009;bp), 20&#x02009;ng of the unlabelled fragment containing a &#x02018;partner&#x02019; attachment site and 66&#x02009;nM integrase in binding buffer. Unless otherwise stated, all reactions were incubated for a period of 2&#x02009;h at 30&#x000b0;C prior to electrophoresis on 5% non-denaturing polyacrylamide gels (200V, 5W for 2&#x02009;h).</p><p>To detect the cleavage of the DNA fragments by integrase, reactions were set up as for the radioactive recombination assays but after incubation at 30&#x000b0;C, reactions were heat inactivated (72&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min) then incubated with 1&#x003bc;l of subtilisin A (Sigma 0.1&#x02009;mg/ml in 1&#x000d7; binding buffer) for 15&#x02009;min at 30&#x000b0;C. Subtilisin was inactivated (72&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min) and the reactions were loaded onto a 0.5&#x000d7; TBE, 5% non-denaturing polyacrylamide gel.</p><p>After electrophoresis gels were dried and exposed to a phosphorimager screen (Fuji) for 16&#x02009;h and then scanned (Fuji FLA3200 phosphorimager). Quantification of radioactivity was performed using the AIDA software (Raytest, Straubenhardt, Germany).</p></sec><sec><title>Purification of integrase</title><p>Wild-type &#x003d5;C31 and S12A integrase were purified as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Integrase concentration was assayed using a method based on the dye-binding procedure of Bradford (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>) employing the BioRad protein assay solution, and bovine serum albumin as a standard.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Identification of defective mutations in <italic>attB</italic></title><p>The minimal <italic>attB</italic> site, according to Groth <italic>et al</italic>., (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) is 34&#x02009;bp with the crossover 5&#x02032;TT (abbreviated to XO) at the centre (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Footprinting confirmed that integrase binds either side of the crossover site in all the attachment sites and, as integrase is a dimer in solution it probably binds as a dimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Moreover, we have shown that integrase binds to <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> in a functionally symmetrical manner. Thus in order to maximize any phenotype arising from mutations in <italic>attB</italic> we generated a set of doubly mutated sites with base pair changes at symmetrical positions with respect to the crossover sequence. To aid in the description of the positions of mutations, the base pairs in the minimal <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> sites were annotated with either a negative number when they lie to the left of the crossover dinucleotide sequence (5&#x02032;TT) i.e. B or P arm to use the &#x003bb; terminology) or positive when it lies to the right of the crossover (B&#x02032; or P&#x02032; arm); the numbers count upwards as the position extends away from the crossover (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Thus mutations in a double mutant involving the two base pairs adjacent to the crossover is at &#x02212;/+1 and mutations at the next position moving outwards are at &#x02212;/+2, etc. Mutations were chosen that would introduce sequence symmetry at the desired position. Thus each double mutant was designed to contain one of the four bases, A, T, C or G, at position <italic>&#x02013;x</italic> on the B arm and at <italic>+x</italic> on the B&#x02032; arm its complement, T, A, G or C, respectively, was inserted. The choice of mutation was made on the basis that the introduced bases had to be different from those present in both arms of <italic>attB</italic> and preferably also different to those seen in the pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). For example, position 15 is a T in the B arm and a C in the B&#x02032; arm and the pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sites have a G in the B arm and a C or A in the B&#x02032; arm. T-15C:C+15G and the T-15A:C+15T contain changes at &#x02212;/+15 on the B and the B&#x02032; arm to base pairs that are different from both the wt and the pseudo-site sequences and should be functionally the same mutation in both arms. For most positions at least two mutant forms were made but for some sites (positions 4, 7, 16) only one option was available. Other positions where only a single mutant form was made are at 14, 17 and 18.</p><p>Except for mutations at positions &#x02212;/+3, &#x02212;/+8 and &#x02212;/+12 the activities of the double substituted <italic>attB</italic> sites was first assayed using annealed oligonucleotides. Oligonucleotides containing the double substitutions were purified by PAGE, annealed and used in an oligo-plasmid recombination assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). In this assay, a supercoiled plasmid containing <italic>attP</italic> was mixed with the oligonucleotide containing <italic>attB</italic> or one of the mutant forms and various concentrations of integrase. The extent of linearization of the <italic>attP</italic> plasmid indicated the extent of recombination and this was assayed after separation of the DNA in an agarose gel. A control reaction using the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site was performed in every assay so that the activities could be compared under identical conditions. The lowest integrase concentration at which recombination could be observed was scored (Figure S1 and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Many of the mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites showed little or only 2-fold change in activity compared to the wild-type site. These sites were changed at &#x02212;/+1, &#x02212;/+4, &#x02212;/+5, &#x02212;/+7, &#x02212;/+10, &#x02212;/+11 and &#x02212;/+13 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The remaining mutants showed defective or partially defective activity ranging from 4-fold less active than wild type to apparently inactive. Oligos encoding sites C-2G:G+2C, C-2A:G+2T, G-6A:C+6T, (G-6T:C+6A, G-9T:C+9A, G-9A:C-9T, G-9C:C-9G, T-15C:C+15G, G-16T:G+15A and G-18C:A+18G were cloned into pGEM7 (Promega) so that the activities of the mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites could be verified by a standard recombination assay using both <italic>att</italic> sites residing on plasmids. Only one of the mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites that was partially defective (at position &#x02212;/+14) was not represented in the cloned mutant <italic>attB</italic> site collection; this site was instead subjected to single site substitutions (see later). T-15A:C+15T was not cloned as a plasmid containing another mutant at &#x02212;/+15 (T-15C:C+15G) with the same activity was quickly obtained. A plasmid encoding G-6C:C+6G was not obtained due to technical difficulties. Plasmids containing mutations in C-3T:G+3A, C-3G:G+3C, C-3A:G+3T, G-8T:C+8A, G-8C:G+8C, C-12A:G+12T and C-12T:G+12A were obtained by PCR mutagenesis as described in the Material and Methods section. The relative activities of the double substitution mutants were estimated compared to a standard reaction with wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). As for the oligo-plasmid assay the activity of each mutant site was scored as the concentration of integrase required to observe recombinants in an agarose gel stained with ethidium bromide (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The relative activities compared to the wild-type site are summarized graphically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>Three of the mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites were very defective for recombination and these contained substitutions at &#x02212;/+2, &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16. In all cases no recombination was observed in either the oligo-plasmid or the standard assay using these double substituted <italic>attB</italic> sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and Figure S1). Recombination was just detectable with <italic>attB</italic> containing substituted &#x02212;/+18 in the plasmid assay with 351&#x02009;nM integrase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). The low activity of the &#x02212;/+18 double mutant was surprising given that this position is outside the minimal <italic>attB</italic> site defined previously by Groth <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). The nature of the mutations made small differences to activity in only a few mutants. The &#x02212;/+12 mutant containing the double transversion C-12A:G+12T was only just active with 87&#x02009;nM integrase while the &#x02212;/+12 mutant containing the transitions C-12T:G+12A was active with 43&#x02009;nM integrase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). The G-6T:C+6A transversions had similar activity to wild-type <italic>attB</italic> but another &#x02212;/+6 mutant, containing transitions (G-6A:C+6T) was 2-to 4-fold less active than <italic>attB</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p>All of the mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites described in this section that were cloned into plasmids were used to test whether they would recombine with <italic>attL, attR</italic> or <italic>attB</italic> but no activity was detected in any case. Thus none of these mutant sites had any detectable gain-of-function.</p></sec><sec><title>The sequence on the left side of <italic>attB</italic> has a greater role in <italic>attB</italic> function than the right side</title><p>The effects of mutations at positions &#x02212;/+2, &#x02212;/+14, &#x02212;/+15, &#x02212;/+16 and &#x02212;/+18 were studied further. Oligonucleotides were synthesized that had single mutations at either the <italic>&#x02212;x</italic> position in the B arm or in the <italic>+x</italic> position in the B&#x02032; arm. Recombination was performed with the oligo-plasmid assay and with the standard recombination assay using the sites cloned into pGEM7. The <italic>attB</italic> sites containing the single mutations C-2G and G+2C regained much of the activity of the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site suggesting that a correct interaction on one or other side of the crossover at this position is sufficient for recombination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Similarly the single mutation at &#x02013;18 or +18 also regained some activity compared to wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (Figure S1). Single mutations at the 15 and 16 positions behaved differently. Mutants at &#x02013;15 or &#x02013;16 had much greater effects on recombination than the mutants at +15 or +16. The single mutations C+15G and G+16A regained some activity compared to the double mutants T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A whereas the single mutants at T-15C and G-16T did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). A similar difference, but less so, was also observed at position 14 where the left B arm was more sensitive to mutation than the right B&#x02032; arm (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). To test this further we experimented with partially symmetrical sites. The B arm of <italic>attB</italic> that included the region from &#x02013;12 to &#x02013;18 was replaced with the +12 to +18 sequence from the B&#x02032; side [2R (&#x02212;12 to &#x02212;18)] and vice versa, [2L (+12 to +18)]. The 2L (+12 to +18) <italic>attB</italic> site was as active as the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site whereas the 2R (&#x02212;12 to &#x02212;18) site was inactive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). These data indicate that the sequence in the left arm of <italic>attB</italic> plays a major role in <italic>attB</italic> function and its loss removes all activity. A mutant <italic>attB</italic> site RL, with the straight swap of the B arm sequence between &#x02212;12 and &#x02212;18 with the B&#x02032; arm sequence at +12 to +18 was inactive (Figure S1) indicating that whatever positive role the &#x02212;12 to &#x02212;18 sequence plays in <italic>attB</italic> function, it is not acting independently of other sequences in the <italic>attB</italic> site.</p></sec><sec><title>Mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites have little or no reduction in affinity for integrase</title><p>This mutational analysis of <italic>attB</italic> showed that double mutations at three positions &#x02212;/+2, &#x02212;/+15 &#x02212;/+16 and the single mutants at &#x02013;15 and &#x02013;16 were particularly defective for recombination.</p><p>We have shown previously that it is possible to assay several intermediate steps in recombination i.e. DNA binding, formation of the synapse and cleavage of the DNA to form the covalent intermediate in which integrase is covalently bound to its cleaved substrate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). The mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites were used first in affinity assays with integrase. As seen previously integrase bound to the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site with an affinity of &#x0223c;60&#x02009;nM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Most of the mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites bound with a similar affinity to the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site including the severely recombination defective sites C-2A:G+2T and G-16T:G+16A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The mutant T-15C:C+15G had a slightly lower affinity for integrase (&#x0223c;128&#x02009;nM) but this loss of affinity was abolished in the single mutant at &#x02212;15 (T-15C) which was still defective in recombination (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Differences in binding affinities by integrase for mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites C-2A:G+2T, G-16T:G+16A, T-15C and G-16T cannot therefore account for the defectiveness of these sites in recombination. Mutations involving position 18 from the crossover dinucleotide showed an &#x0223c;3-fold lower affinity for integrase than wild-type <italic>attB</italic> which could contribute to the observed decrease in recombination activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). It seems likely that <italic>attB</italic> sites with mutations at &#x02212;/+2, &#x02212;/+15, &#x02212;/+16 were blocked elsewhere in the recombination pathway.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Binding affinities by integrase for the wild-type and mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites. Integrase was incubated with radiolabelled wild type (panel <bold>A</bold>) and mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites (panels <bold>B&#x02013;F</bold>). In each panel, the phosphorimage shows the complexes obtained with increasing integrase concentrations and, below, the quantitative analysis of the% bound versus the concentration of integrase. Only the &#x02212;/+15 mutant (T-15C:C+15G) and the &#x02212;/+18 mutant (G-18C:A+18G) sites showed reduced binding affinities for integrase under the conditions used. A summary of the integrase concentrations required for 50% binding of the different <italic>attB</italic> mutants is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm206f3"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Apparent binding affinities by integrase for mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>attB</italic> Site; position of mutation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nature of mutation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean integrase concentration for 50% binding &#x000b1; SD<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2"><sup>a</sup></xref> (nM)</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.3 &#x000b1; 12.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/+2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-2A:G+2T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7 &#x000b1; 16.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-2G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.7 &#x000b1; 3.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G+2C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.3 &#x000b1; 6.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/+15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-15C:C+15G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.7 &#x000b1; 24.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-15C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3 &#x000b1; 5.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C+15G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.7 &#x000b1; 5.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/+16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-16T:G+16A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.3 &#x000b1; 12.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-16T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.0 &#x000b1; 5.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G+16A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.3 &#x000b1; 6.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/+18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-18C:A+18G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189.7 &#x000b1; 30.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-18C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">194.7 &#x000b1; 17.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+18G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.3 &#x000b1; 19.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partially symmetrical site</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2L(+12 - +18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7 &#x000b1; 5.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2"><p><sup>a</sup>Means and SDs were calculated from the integrase concentrations required for 50% binding from three separate binding experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Cleavage by integrase of <italic>attB</italic> sites with mutations at <bold>&#x02212;</bold>/<bold>+</bold>2 is severely inhibited</title><p>The formation of both the cleaved covalent intermediate and the synapse can be observed in a recombination assay using a radiolabelled <italic>attB</italic> or <italic>attP</italic> site, a cold partner <italic>att</italic> site and integrase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). These assays are performed in a buffer that is sub-optimal for recombination (binding buffer) that enriches for synaptic complexes and the cleaved covalent complex compared with standard recombination conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). <italic>attP</italic> was labelled with [&#x003b1;&#x02212;<sup>32</sup>P] dCTP, mixed with cold wild-type or mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites and integrase and run in a non-denaturing PAGE gel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, left panel). Compared to wild-type <italic>attB</italic>, sites with &#x02212;/+2 changes (C-2G:G+2C and C-2A:G+2T) showed an accumulation of synapse with almost undetectable cleaved covalent complex or product formed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, left panel). Treatment of the recombination intermediates with the protease, subtilisin showed a small amount of cleaved probe with C-2G:G+2C but this was undetectable with C-2A:G+2T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). Subtilisin treatment of reactions containing wild-type <italic>attB</italic> clearly revealed the two recombination products <italic>attL</italic> and <italic>attR</italic> but these were not visible with C-2A:G+2T and barely visible with C-2G:G+2C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). As seen in the recombination assay reverting one of the two mutations in C-2G:G+2C back to the wild-type sequence was sufficient to regain activity similar to the wild type <italic>attB</italic> site (C-2G or G+2C in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, left panel). The catalytically inactive integrase mutant (S12A) was able to bind to C-2G:G+2C, C-2A:G+2T, C-2G and G+2C normally to form a synaptic complex indistinguishable from the wild type <italic>attB</italic> site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, right panel). Experiments in which the labelled probes were <italic>attB</italic> or the &#x02212;/+2 mutant derivatives and unlabelled <italic>attP</italic> was used to supershift the complexes showed similar results, i.e. very little cleavage of the &#x02212;/+2 mutant <italic>attB</italic> was observed (Supplementary Data&#x02014;Figure S2). These data indicate that <italic>attB</italic> sites with a double substitution at &#x02212;/+ 2 are able to generate a stable synapse but are severely defective in cleavage of the substrates.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Synapse assays with wild-type and mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites. Panel (<bold>A</bold>) Radiolabelled <italic>attP</italic> was incubated with wild-type (left panel) or the catalytically inactive integrase, S12A, (right panel) and a cold partner fragment containing wild-type <italic>attB (</italic>wt) or the indicated mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites. The arrows show the positions of the synapse containing the radiolabelled substrate, the cold partner fragment and integrase (Int:synapse <italic>attP/B</italic>), the covalently linked cleaved substrate (Int:cleaved <italic>attP/B</italic>), the shifted and free products (Int:<italic>attL/R</italic> and <italic>attL/R</italic>, respectively) and the positions of the <italic>attP</italic> bound only to integrase (two complexes labelled Int:<italic>attP</italic>) or free (<italic>attP</italic>). Panel (<bold>B</bold>) The protease subtilisin was used to reveal the extent of cleavage of <italic>attB</italic> sites and the products formed during the synapse assay. Arrows show the positions of the products, <italic>attL</italic> and <italic>attR</italic>, the radiolabelled substrate and <italic>attB</italic>. The smear of radioactivity migrating faster than the free probe results from subtilisin treated cleaved covalently linked complexes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm206f4"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>The stability of the synapse is reduced in <italic>attB</italic> sites with mutations at <bold>&#x02212;</bold>/<bold>+</bold>15, <bold>&#x02212;</bold>/<bold>+</bold>16, <bold>&#x02212;</bold>15 and <bold>&#x02212;</bold>16</title><p>The <italic>attB</italic> sites with mutations at &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16 that were defective in the standard recombination assay did not appear to be defective in the radioactive assay to detect intermediates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, left panel). The amounts of cleaved covalent intermediate and shifted <italic>attL</italic>/<italic>attR</italic> products were indistinguishable from the reaction with the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, left panel). The only observable difference was in the amount of synapse, which was reduced in the reactions with the most defective sites i.e. T-15C:C+15G, T-15G, G-16T:G+16A and G-16T and the appearance of some free product. These differences were also observed when the <italic>attB</italic> sites were labelled and incubated with integrase and cold <italic>attP</italic> (Supplementary Data&#x02014;Figure S2). When the S12A catalytically inactive integrase mutant was used, there was a small reduction in accumulation of the synaptic complex with T-15C:C+15G, T-15G, G-16T:G+16A and G-16T compared with wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, right panel).</p><p>The inconsistency whereby mutants T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A were inactive in the recombination assay but active in the assay for intermediates was addressed. As the standard recombination assay is performed over 1&#x02009;h and the synapse assay is over 2&#x02009;h, time courses were performed for each assay. In the standard recombination assay, products were observed in 2 and 3&#x02009;h with mutants T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). Using the more sensitive radioactive assay, cleaved substrates, T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A, and their recombinant products started to appear at 30&#x02009;min of incubation and accumulated further over the next 30&#x02009;min whereas with the wild-type <italic>attB</italic>, most of the substrate had been converted to intermediates or products at 15&#x02009;min. Even after 60&#x02009;min, less <italic>attP</italic> in the presence of T-15C:C+15G or G-16T:G+16A was converted to product compared to <italic>attP</italic> in the presence of wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). Thus both the mutants T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A could undergo recombination but the reaction is considerably slower than that for the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> site. As there is a consistently reduced level of synaptic complex observed with these mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites, it is likely that changes in <italic>attB</italic> at &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16 both result in an unstable synapse that explains the slow rate of recombination.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>The rate of recombination with mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A is greatly reduced. Panel (<bold>A</bold>) shows the appearance of products from recombination assays using T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A as substrates after prolonged incubation. Plasmids encoding the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (wt) or the indicated <italic>attB</italic> mutants were incubated with pRT702 (<italic>attP</italic>) for 1, 2 or 3&#x02009;h at 30&#x000b0;C and then the products analysed by restriction and agarose gel electrophoresis. After 2 and 3&#x02009;h some product (<italic>attL</italic>) is visible in the lanes containing the &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16 mutations. Panel (<bold>B</bold>) shows the time-dependent appearance of recombination intermediates when wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (wt) was used compared to C-2A:G+2T, T-15C:C+15G or G-16T:G+16A. The &#x02212;/+2 mutant site rapidly forms a synapse (Int:synapse <italic>attP/B</italic>) and thereafter the reaction is blocked. The &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16 <italic>attB</italic> sites slowly accumulated the cleaved intermediate (Int:cleaved <italic>attP/B</italic>) and some shifted product complexes (Int:<italic>attL/R</italic>). The remaining complexes on the gel are as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm206f5"/></fig></p><p>We reasoned that altered recombination conditions might partially suppress the defect in T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A by stabilizing the putative protein&#x02013;protein interface. Recombination was observed when the NaCl concentration was increased to 500&#x02009;mM or 1&#x02009;M in recombination buffer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). However, increasing the concentration of NaCl did not increase the amount of synaptic complex observed with these mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). Indeed at 1&#x02009;M NaCl there was a reduction in the level of synapse observed with the mutants at &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16 and a slight reduction in the affinity for the <italic>attB</italic> site by integrase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">C</xref>).
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>High NaCl concentrations can partially suppress the recombination defective phenoytpe of the mutations. Panel (<bold>A</bold>) shows the appearance of products from recombination assays using T-15C:C+15G, G-16T:G+16A, G-16T and T-15C as substrates after incubation in either 500&#x02009;mM or 1&#x02009;M NaCl. Plasmids encoding the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (wt), or the above mutants were incubated with pRT702 (<italic>attP</italic>) in recombination buffer adjusted to 100&#x02009;mM, 500&#x02009;mM or 1&#x02009;M NaCl. After digesting with HindIII the DNA was separated in an agarose gel. The appearance of the 5435&#x02009;bp fragment encoding <italic>attL</italic> is indicative of recombination. Panel (<bold>B</bold>) shows the synapse assays using the wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (wt), C-2A:G+2T, T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A under different NaCl conditions with wild type (left panel) or S12A integrase (right panel) with labelled <italic>attP</italic>. The complexes are annotated as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>. &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16 mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites accumulated both the cleaved complex (Int:cleaved <italic>attP/B</italic>), the shifted products (Int:<italic>attL/R</italic>) and released some free product (<italic>attL/R</italic>) with 500&#x02009;mM and 1&#x02009;M NaCl with the wild-type integrase. The synapse however as indicated using the S12A integrase did not become more abundant in high NaCl buffer, if anything it reduced. Panel (<bold>C</bold>) shows that the binding affinity of <italic>attB</italic> sites for integrase in the presence of different NaCl concentrations. Radiolabelled <italic>attB</italic> sites were incubated in binding buffer containing 50&#x02009;mM, 500&#x02009;mM or 1&#x02009;M NaCl. Integrase was added at 66 nM. The shifted <italic>attB</italic> complexes are indicated by arrows. Only at 1&#x02009;M NaCl, there was a slight increase in the free DNA for all four <italic>attB</italic> sites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm206f6"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The interactions between &#x003d5;C31 integrase and its attachment sites are critical in determining the directionality of recombination. <italic>In vitro</italic> integrase only recombines <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> to form the hybrid products, <italic>attL</italic> and <italic>attR</italic>. We have shown previously that, <italic>in vitro</italic>, integrase selectively brings <italic>attP</italic> and <italic>attB</italic> together to form the synapse and no other combination of sites forms a stable synapse under these conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). These observations have led to the proposal that integrase adopts specific conformations when bound to <italic>attP</italic> or <italic>attB</italic> that permit formation of the protein:protein interface required for stable synapsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Here we showed that mutations in <italic>attB</italic> can significantly affect the ability of integrase to form a stable synapse or to cleave the substrates. These perturbations in the reaction are likely to be due to the absence of important interactions between integrase and <italic>attB</italic> and could be indicative of &#x02018;non-permissive&#x02019; conformations of integrase that block recombination at these different stages.</p><p>The mutations at &#x02212;/+2 in <italic>attB</italic> showed a failure to cleave the DNA but these substrates could still form a stable synapse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4 F5 F6">Figures 4&#x02013;6</xref>). These data show clearly that there is a post-synaptic activation step required for recombination by &#x003d5;C31 integrase. This activation step depends on an interaction that has been disrupted in the <italic>attB</italic> &#x02212;/+2 mutants, C-2G:G+2C or C-2A:G+2T. The nature of the interaction is not known but could be a specific base-pair contact or a DNA conformation that is recognized. The block in DNA cleavage occurred in both the mutant <italic>attB</italic> sites themselves and in the wild-type <italic>attP</italic> sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4 F5 F6">Figures 4&#x02013;6</xref> and Figure S2). This behaviour is consistent with concerted DNA cleavage in the reaction with wild-type recombination sites. Possibly the block in cleavage in reactions containing the &#x02212;/+2 mutant sites could be due to failure to undergo a conformational change in the whole synaptic complex which would normally lead to cleavage. Alternatively the DNA conformation of the mutant sites prevents the catalytic sites gaining access to the scissile phosphate. As reversion of just one of the bases from the double mutant back to the wild type was sufficient to regain most of the <italic>attB</italic> activity it would seem that activation only requires a &#x02018;correct&#x02019; interaction at one half-site of <italic>attB</italic>.</p><p>The mutants T-15C:C+15G and G-16T:G+16A were able to recombine but at a slow rate compared to wild-type <italic>attB</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). There was a consistent reduction in the amount of synapse observed during recombination with these mutants suggesting that the synaptic complex was unstable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Raising the concentration of NaCl partially suppressed the defect in recombination with the &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16 mutants but it is not clear which step was affected by NaCl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). The stability of the synapse did not increase in the presence of a higher concentration of NaCl, if anything the binding affinity and the level of synapse was reduced at 1&#x02009;M NaCl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). Despite this, suppression was still observed suggesting that high NaCl activates or stabilizes an event later in the recombination pathway. The single point mutants at &#x02013;15 and &#x02013;16 were sufficient to severely affect recombination while mutations at +15 or +16 had a lesser effect (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4 F5 F6">4&#x02013;6</xref>). Thus the single mutations at positions &#x02013;15 and &#x02013;16 accounted for most of the defect in the &#x02212;/+15 and &#x02212;/+16 double mutants. These data argue that there could be a specific interaction between the B arm and integrase that contributes significantly to the activity of the <italic>attB</italic> site. The partial symmetrization of the <italic>attB</italic> sites (with either the sequence from the B arm [2L (+12 to +18)] or with that from the B&#x02032; arm [2R (&#x02212;12 to &#x02212;18)]; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, panel H) showed that the B arm was indeed more active than the B&#x02032; arm. However, it is known from previous work that the <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> sites act with integrase in a functionally symmetrical manner as integrase does not control the relative orientation of the sites when they come together at synapsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Thus the interactions by each subunit of integrase bound to each arm of <italic>attB</italic> are not independent of each other and we propose that a specific integrase conformation that results from the &#x02013;15, &#x02212;16 interactions in the B arm is communicated through both subunits.</p><p>These conclusions can be combined with information from other large serine recombinases and the resolvases to generate a model that focuses on substrate recognition and formation of the synapse by integrase (adapted from that published previously for Bxb1 integrase, 26; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). In the resolvases, the DNA is contacted in the minor groove in the centre of each binding site and through specific contacts in the major groove towards the outer flank of the site via the C-terminal DNA binding domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). The geometry of DNA-binding is such that the C-terminal domain of resolvase extends around the DNA and contacts on the opposite side of the DNA to the catalytic serine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). As in Bxb1 and TnpX, &#x003d5;C31 integrase has a proteolytically sensitive site between the N and C terminal domains (K152, unpublished data)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>). Moreover, the C-terminal domains of Bxb1 and TnpX have been shown previously to be capable of binding specifically to DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>). Thus we propose that the C-terminal domains interact with the outer flanks of the <italic>att</italic> sites, that these interactions determine the conformations of integrase bound to each site and therefore whether they are compatible for synapsis. In <italic>attB</italic> this information is &#x02018;read&#x02019; at least in part from &#x02013;15 and &#x02013;16 where disruption of this interaction disables the ability of integrase to form a stable synapse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4 F5 F6">Figures 4&#x02013;6</xref>). The model predicts that there is communication between the putative DNA-binding motifs in the C-terminal domain and the regions of integrase that generate the protein-protein interface for synapsis. We currently envisage this communication as an allosteric switch mediated by conformational changes. In &#x003b3;&#x003b4; resolvase, the synaptic interface is located at the DNA distal surface of the catalytic domain and it is likely that the serine integrases use the equivalent of this interface for synapsis, although it is possible that the C-terminal domain may also have a role in synapsis. After synapsis an activation step is required for DNA cleavage and in <italic>attB</italic> this depends on the base pairs at position &#x02212;/+2. In <italic>attB</italic> only one of the &#x02212;/+2 bases needs to be wild type for activity and this can be either on the B or B&#x02032; arm. Given the proximity of &#x02212;/+2 to the scissile phosphate, position 2 is more likely to interact with the catalytic domain than with the C-terminal domain. As in resolvase there may be significant conformation changes that occur with activation of recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>).
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Model for the mechanism of integrase. The integrase subunits are shown with a small N-terminal (catalytic) domain through which the subunits may dimerize (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>) and a large C-terminal domain that we propose recognizes the sequences in the outer flanks of the recombination sites. These recognition events, specifically &#x02212;15 and &#x02212;16 (annotated as blue bars) in <italic>attB</italic>, lead to an &#x02018;induced fit&#x02019; or stabilization of a specific conformation of integrase that enables synapsis with integrase bound to <italic>attP</italic>. Different conformations of integrase bound to either <italic>attB</italic> or <italic>attP</italic> are shown as different colours. The synaptic interface via the N-terminal catalytic domains is indicated based on the resolvase precedent; there is no evidence to indicate that the C-terminal domains could also participate in a synaptic interface. Mutations at positions &#x02212;15 or &#x02212;16 (such as in T-15C:C+15G, G-16T:G+16A), T-15C or G-16T do not induce the conformation of integrase that can form a stable synapse with <italic>attP</italic> so the rate of reaction decreases (thin arrow). Mutations at &#x02212;/+2 in <italic>attB</italic> (red bars) are severely inhibited in cleavage but are capable of forming a stable synapse. These mutants indicate that the formation of the synaptic complex is followed by a well-defined activation step that results in concerted DNA cleavage. After strand exchange integrase is bound to the hybrid sites and adopts a conformation that cannot synapse <italic>attL</italic> and <italic>attR</italic>. The putative tetrameric complex rapidly dissociates to binary complexes containing integrase and either <italic>attL</italic> or <italic>attR</italic>. See text for more details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm206f7"/></fig></p><p>The data presented here provides a source of information that could be used for the design of alternative <italic>attB</italic> sites for genome engineering using &#x003d5;C31 integrase. Indeed we have already used this information to create a non-methylatable <italic>attB</italic> site for use in vertebrate cell lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). In this site, <italic>attB</italic><sup>m</sup>, the CpG steps have been replaced with bases that we have shown here were neutral with respect to recombination activity. It is noteworthy that the positions in <italic>attB</italic> that are critical for recombination other than position 2 i.e. positions 15, 16 were not highlighted as being particularly preferred in the pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). However all of the pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sequences have either the wild-type C at &#x02212;2 or a wild-type G at +2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). It is also noticeable that the regions where there are most identities between <italic>attB</italic> and <italic>attP</italic> are not particularly sensitive to mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). A plausible explanation for both these observations is that the 24&#x02009;bp of <italic>att</italic> site DNA from about position 11 to the crossover site is a core sequence that integrase binds to specifically. We propose that the role of positions 15 and 16 in <italic>attB</italic> revealed by this study is to greatly enhance the efficiency of the reaction and effectively discriminate between the pseudo-sites and the cognate <italic>attB</italic> site. It is envisaged that this data and a similar analysis with <italic>attP</italic> will enable an understanding of the optimal sequences to target for continued application of &#x003d5;C31 integrase.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We are grateful for comments on this manuscript from Paul Rowley and Paul Hoskisson. M.G was funded by a scholarship from the University of Aberdeen. This work was funded by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council, UK. Funding to pay the open access publication charges for this article was provided by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council, UK.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-specific transformation of Drosophila via &#x003d5;C31 integrase-mediated cassette exchange</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>777</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16547094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwenk</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuter-Luks</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Faust</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced efficiency through nuclear localization signal fusion on phage &#x003d5;C31-integrase: activity comparison with Cre and FLPe recombinase in mammalian cells</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2299</fpage><lpage>2306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belteki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gertsenstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ow</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-specific cassette exchange and germline transmission with mouse ES cells expressing &#x003d5;C31 integrase</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12563279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dafhnis-Calas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iterative <italic>in vivo</italic> assembly of large and complex transgenes by combining the activities of &#x003d5;C31 integrase and Cre recombinase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>e189</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16361264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>KMalik</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phage &#x003d5;C31 integrase: a new tool in plastid genome engineering</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dafhnis-Calas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brookfield</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rearranging the centromere of the human Y chromosome with &#x003d5;C31 integrase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>6101</fpage><lpage>6113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16246911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomason</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Calendar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ow</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene insertion and replacement in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> mediated by the <italic>Streptomyces</italic> bacteriophage &#x003d5;C31 site-specific recombination system</article-title><source>Mol. Gen. Genom</source><year>2001</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1038</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nkrumah</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhle</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfull</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Fidock</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient site-specific integration in <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> chromosomes mediated by mycobacteriophage Bxb1 integrase</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16862136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thyagarajan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-specific genomic integration in mammalian cells mediated by phage &#x003d5;C31 integrase</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3926</fpage><lpage>3934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11359900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groth</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thyagarajan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phage integrase directs efficient site-specific integration in human cells</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>5995</fpage><lpage>6000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10801973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalberg</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Meuse</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-specific genomic integration produces therapeutic Factor IX levels in mice</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1124</fpage><lpage>1128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12379870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Held</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Finegold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grompe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo correction of murine hereditary tyrosinemia type I by &#x003d5;C31 integrase-mediated gene delivery</article-title><source>Mol. Ther</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15727936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Portlock</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Keravala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term increase in mVEGF164 in mouse hindlimb muscle mediated by phage &#x003d5;C31 integrase after nonviral DNA delivery</article-title><source>Hum. Gene Ther</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16942446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keravala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Portlock</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitrant</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x003d5;C31 integrase mediates integration in cultured synovial cells and enhances gene expression in rabbit joints</article-title><source>J. Gene Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1008</fpage><lpage>1017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16779871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarrahian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of plasmid-mediated gene therapy for muscular dystrophy by directed plasmid integration</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> site-specific integration of bacteriophage DNA catalyzed by a recombinase of the resolvase/invertase family</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>5505</fpage><lpage>5510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9576912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfull</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The orientation of mycobacteriophage Bxb1 integration is solely dependent on the central dinucleotide of <italic>attP</italic> and <italic>attB</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14636570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azaro</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Landy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Craigie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gellert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambowitz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mobile DNA II</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Washington D.C.</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>148</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasil</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfull</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of phage Bxb1 excision by a novel recombination directionality factor</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e186</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16719562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity in the serine recombinases</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Craigie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gellert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambowitz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mobile DNA II</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Radman-Livaja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Filman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Landy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A structural basis for allosteric control of DNA recombination by lambda integrase</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>435</volume><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15973401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radman-Livaja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Landy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA arms do the legwork to ensure the directionality of lambda site-specific recombination</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16368232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grindley</surname><given-names>NDF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Craigie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gellert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambowitz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mobile DNA II</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>302</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal-structure of the site-specific recombinase gamma-delta resolvase complexed with a 34bp cleavage site</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7628011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pannunzio</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfull</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synapsis in phage Bxb1 integration: selection mechanism for the correct pair of recombination sites</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>349</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15890199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCA</given-names></name><name><surname>Till</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Soultanas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synapsis and DNA cleavage in &#x003d5;C31 integrase-mediated site-specific recombination</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2607</fpage><lpage>2617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCA</given-names></name><name><surname>Till</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Switching the polarity of a bacteriophage integration system</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1719</fpage><lpage>1728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15009897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of directionality in the site-specific recombination system of the Streptomyces phage &#x003d5;C31</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucet</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tynan</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiarezza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossjohn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyras</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rood</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two distinct regions of the large serine recombinase TnpX are required for DNA binding and biological function</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16629663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crellin</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rood</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The resolvase/invertase domain of the site-specific recombinase TnpX is functional and recognizes a target sequence that resembles the junction of the circular form of the <italic>Clostridium perfringens</italic> transposon Tn4451</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1997</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>5148</fpage><lpage>5156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9260958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullany</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The large resolvase TndX is required and sufficient for integration and excision of derivatives of the novel conjugative transposon Tn5397</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>6577</fpage><lpage>6583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11073898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Craigie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gellert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambowitz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mobile DNA II</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>271</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamtekar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkis</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grindley</surname><given-names>NDF</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of a synaptic gammadelta resolvase tetramer covalently linked to two cleaved DNAs</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>1210</fpage><lpage>1215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15994378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nollmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Byron</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of the Tn3 resolvase-crossover site synaptic complex</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15469828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boocock</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherratt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalysis by site-specific recombinases</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>432</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1337225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamtekar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cocco</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenwieser</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Boocock</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Grindley</surname><given-names>NDF</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implications of structures of synaptic tetramers of gamma delta resolvase for the mechanism of recombination</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>10642</fpage><lpage>10647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16807292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Grindley</surname><given-names>NDF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfull</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Boocock</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resolvase-catalyzed reactions between sites differing in the central dinucleotide of subsite-I</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1991</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>3541</fpage><lpage>3548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1655422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhstoss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the integration function of the streptomycete bacteriophage &#x003d5;c31</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>222</volume><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1762157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breuner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brondsted</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resolvase-like recombination performed by the TP901-1 integrase</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2001</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>2051</fpage><lpage>2063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11495984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Combes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Till</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The streptomyces genome contains multiple pseudo-<italic>attB</italic> sites for the (&#x003d5;)C31-encoded site-specific recombination system</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2002</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>5746</fpage><lpage>5752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12270833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chalberg</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Portlock</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thyagarajan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillman</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoelters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integration specificity of phage &#x003d5;C31 integrase in the human genome</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>357</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16414067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new site-specific integration system for mycobacteria</article-title><source>Tuberculosis (Edinb)</source><year>2005</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16256438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edn</article-title><source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</source><year>2001</year><edition>3rd edn</edition><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem</source><year>1976</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucet</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tynan</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossjohn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyras</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rood</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the structural and functional domains of the large serine recombinase TnpX from Clostridium perfringens</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>2503</fpage><lpage>2511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15542858</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
