<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14981095</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1615912</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200309152</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200309152</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Epiblast cells that express MyoD recruit pluripotent cells to the skeletal muscle lineage</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gerhart</surname><given-names>Jacquelyn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Neely</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>Jordanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wallon</surname><given-names>Margaretha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>George-Weinstein</surname><given-names>Mindy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Department of Anatomy, Philadelphia College of Osteopathic Medicine, Philadelphia, PA 19131</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Lankenau Institute for Medical Research, Wynnewood, PA 19096</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Mindy George-Weinstein, Department of Anatomy, Philadelphia College of Osteopathic Medicine, 4170 City Ave., Philadelphia, PA 19131. Tel.: (215) 871-6541. Fax: (215) 871-6540. email: <email>mindyw@pcom.edu</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>164</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Embryonic stem cells are derived from the epiblast. A subpopulation of epiblast cells expresses MyoD mRNA and the G8 antigen in vivo. G8 positive (G8<sup>pos</sup>) and G8 negative (G8<sup>neg</sup>) populations were isolated by magnetic cell sorting. Nearly all G8<sup>pos</sup> cells switched from E- to N-cadherin and differentiated into skeletal muscle in culture. G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were impaired in their ability to switch cadherins and few formed skeletal muscle. Medium conditioned by G8<sup>pos</sup> cells stimulated skeletal myogenesis and N-cadherin synthesis in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. The effect of conditioned medium from G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures was inhibited by bone morphogenetic protein (BMP) 4. Treatment of G8<sup>neg</sup> cells with a soluble form of the BMP receptor-IA or Noggin promoted N-cadherin synthesis and skeletal myogenesis. These results demonstrate that MyoD-positive epiblast cells recruit pluripotent cells to the skeletal muscle lineage. The mechanism of recruitment involves blocking the BMP signaling pathway.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>embryonic stem cells; skeletal myogenesis; bone morphogenetic protein; noggin; cadherins</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>J. Perlman's present address is Western University of the Health Sciences, Chino Hills, CA 91709.</p></fn><fn><p>D. Beckmann's present address is Duke University, Durham, NC 27708.</p></fn><fn><p>Abbreviations used in this paper: BMP, bone morphogenetic protein; DMEM, Dulbecco's minimal essential medium; ES cell, embryonic stem cell; G8<sup>pos</sup>, G8 positive; G8<sup>neg</sup>, G8 negative; HGF/SF, hepatocyte growth factor/scatter factor; MyoD<sup>pos</sup>, MyoD positive; N-cadherin<sup>pos</sup>, N-cadherin positive.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Embryonic stem cells (ES cells) are pluripotent cells derived from the epiblast (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 2001</xref>). Defining the molecular mechanisms involved in regulating the pathways of differentiation of these pluripotent cells is critical for understanding tissue formation in the embryo and for using stem cells to repair damaged tissues in the adult. Various methods have been devised to promote mammalian ES cell differentiation including culturing them as three-dimensional aggregates, plating them on different extracellular matrices at high or low density, and supplementing the medium with growth factors (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">O'Shea, 2001</xref>).</p><p>We use an in vitro system comprised of epiblast cells from the chick embryo to dissect the steps involved in commitment and differentiation. Chick epiblast cells differentiate when cultured at high density in medium that lacks exogenous growth factors (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996a</xref>). Although some neurons, notochord, and cardiac muscle cells emerge under these conditions, the preferred pathway of differentiation is skeletal myogenesis (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996a</xref>).</p><p>The precise factors that direct the majority of chick epiblast cells to the skeletal muscle lineage in vitro are unknown; however, a change in the expression of cell&#x02013;cell adhesion molecules appears to be required for terminal stages of differentiation. Cultured epiblast cells recapitulate the switch in expression from E- to N-cadherin that occurs in vivo when they enter the primitive streak and mesoderm (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Edelman et al., 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Hatta and Takeichi, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>). Although both E- and N-cadherin support the synthesis of the skeletal muscle specific transcription factor MyoD (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Holt et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>), adhesions via N-cadherin are necessary for the accumulation of sarcomeric proteins (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>Alterations in cell adhesion also accompany skeletal myogenesis in vivo. Muscle differentiation is initiated in the embryonic somites, structures that form as a result of compaction and epithelialization of mesoderm cells (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Christ and Ordahl, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Pourquie, 2001</xref>). Members of the Wnt family produced in the neural tube and presomitic mesoderm, and sonic hedgehog released from the notochord, promote the expression of members of the MyoD family and the onset of differentiation in somites (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Pownall et al., 2002</xref>). Wnts may play a dual role in regulating myogenesis in somites because they enhance the stability of &#x003b2;-catenin, a protein that serves as both a transcription factor and a link between cadherins and the actin cytoskeleton (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Gumbiner, 2000</xref>). Somite cells from N-cadherin null mice are able to undergo myogenesis; however, they appear to express another cadherin (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Radice et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>Although skeletal myogenesis is regulated by factors in the environment of somites, MyoD mRNA is present in a small number of cells in the epiblast before somite formation (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Gerhart et al., 2000</xref>). The following experiments were designed to explore the significance of this early expression of MyoD in the epiblast and the potential of these cells to regulate the fate of pluripotent cells. These experiments demonstrate that epiblast cells expressing MyoD mRNA in vivo differentiate into skeletal muscle in vitro. The MyoD positive (MyoD<sup>pos</sup>) cells promote the expression of N-cadherin in pluripotent cells and their recruitment to the skeletal muscle lineage. The recruitment process involves blocking the bone morphogenetic protein (BMP) signaling pathway.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Myogenesis in cultures of G8 positive (G8<sup>pos</sup>) and G8 negative (G8<sup>neg</sup>) epiblast cells</title><p>The epiblast of the chick embryo is an epithelium that expresses E-cadherin and gives rise to all three germ layers (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Edelman et al., 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bellairs, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Hatta and Takeichi, 1986</xref>). A subpopulation of these cells expresses MyoD mRNA (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Gerhart et al., 2000</xref>). When epiblasts are isolated from the mesoderm and hypoblast, dissociated, and cultured in serum-free medium on a substrate of gelatin and fibronectin, most cells switch from expression of E- to N-cadherin and differentiate into skeletal muscle (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996a</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). To understand the role of epiblast cells that express MyoD mRNA in these processes, MyoD<sup>pos</sup> and MyoD-negative populations were isolated and cultured separately. The ability to purify living epiblast cells with MyoD is based on the expression of an as yet unidentified cell surface antigen that is recognized by the G8 mAb. In fetal organs, the G8 mAb selectively binds to cells that express MyoD mRNA (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gerhart et al., 2001</xref>). This is also the case for stages 3&#x02013;5 epiblasts (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
A).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Characteristics of G8</bold>
<sup>po</sup>
<bold><sup>s</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> epiblast cells in vivo and in vitro.</bold> The stage 4 embryo was labeled with the G8 mAb and a secondary antibody conjugated with Alexa 488, followed by in situ hybridization with Cy3 labeled dendrimers containing a recognition sequence for MyoD mRNA. (A) Nuclei were stained with bis-benzamide (blue). Cells coexpressed the G8 antigen (green) and MyoD mRNA (red). The G8<sup>pos</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> populations were isolated from stages 3 to 5 epiblasts. After 5 d in culture, cells were stained with antibodies to the skeletal muscle specific 12101 antigen, cardiac muscle specific troponin T (CTpn), neurofilament associated antigen (Nf), and type II collagen (Col). G8<sup>pos</sup> cells differentiated into skeletal muscle when plated at high (B) or low density (C). Some G8<sup>neg</sup> cells differentiated into cardiac muscle (D), neurons (E), and chondroblasts (F). G8<sup>neg</sup> cells formed skeletal muscle when grown in conditioned medium from G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures (G). Noggin (H) and soluble BMP receptor-IA (I) also stimulated skeletal myogenesis in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. Bar, 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200309152f1"/></fig><p>Magnetic sorting of epiblast cells resulted in the isolation of the G8<sup>pos</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> populations, each with a purity of &#x0003e;97%, as determined by labeling with a fluorescent secondary antibody directly after sorting. After 5 d in culture, nearly all of the G8<sup>pos</sup> cells contained MyoD protein and differentiated into skeletal muscle (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref> and <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B). By contrast, only a small percentage of cells in the G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures synthesized detectable levels of MyoD protein and 12101, a skeletal muscle specific marker for differentiation (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Kitner and Brockes, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). The number of cells that stained with MF20, a mAb that recognizes sarcomeric myosin in both skeletal and cardiac muscle (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bader et al., 1982</xref>), was also reduced in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures; however, this population was larger than that expressing 12101 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). The significance of this finding is addressed in the next section.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table I.</label><caption><title>Skeletal myogenesis in unsorted, G8<sup>pos</sup>, G8<sup>neg</sup>, and epiblast cultures</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom"/><th colspan="3" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Percent positive
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">MyoD</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">12101</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">Myosin</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Unsorted</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">82 &#x000b1; 10 (10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">67 &#x000b1; 8 (31)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">80 &#x000b1; 12 (16)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>pos</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">98 &#x000b1; 3 (5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">95 &#x000b1; 6 (16)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">94 &#x000b1; 4 (7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>neg</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">7 &#x000b1; 4 (21)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">4 &#x000b1; 4 (26)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">33 &#x000b1; 9 (16)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Stages 3&#x02013;5 epiblast cells were labeled with the G8 mAb, separated into G8<sup>pos</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> populations by magnetic cell sorting, and cultured for 5 d. Unsorted cells were also plated. Cells were labeled with mAbs to MyoD, the skeletal muscle specific 12101 antigen, or sarcomeric myosin heavy chain present in both skeletal and cardiac muscle. Percent positive = (No. of fluorescent cells &#x000f7; total cells) &#x000d7; 100. Values are the mean &#x000b1; SD. The number of cultures scored is indicated in parentheses. A minimum of 200 cells was scored per culture. Nearly all cells in G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures differentiated into skeletal muscle, whereas few cells formed skeletal muscle in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. The higher percentage of myosin positive cells compared with 12101 positive cells reflects the presence of cardiomyocytes (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>After 2 wk in culture the percentage of G8<sup>neg</sup> cells with 12101 remained low (3% &#x000b1; 2, <italic>n</italic> = 6). Therefore, in the absence of cells that express MyoD (and the G8 antigen) in vivo, most epiblast cells do not differentiate into skeletal muscle in vitro. When G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were recombined with G8<sup>pos</sup> cells, the percentage of differentiated skeletal muscle was similar to that found in unsorted cultures (62% &#x000b1; 6, <italic>n</italic> = 4). This indicates that the cell sorting procedure did not impair the innate ability of the G8<sup>neg</sup> population to undergo skeletal myogenesis and demonstrates the validity of using unsorted cells as controls in subsequent experiments.</p></sec><sec><title>Differentiation of nonskeletal muscle cell types in epiblast cultures</title><p>The ability of epiblast cells to differentiate into nonskeletal muscle cell types in the absence of the MyoD/G8<sup>pos</sup> cells was investigated with cell type&#x02013;specific antibodies. Although the majority of cells in unsorted cultures formed skeletal muscle, some chondroblasts, cardiac muscle cells, and neurons began to emerge after the first day in culture (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996a</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Tables I</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">II</xref>). The sum of the percentages of these four cell types equaled &#x0003e;90%, indicating that in unsorted cultures few undifferentiated cells or those of other lineages were present by the fifth day in culture.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table II.</label><caption><title>Differentiation of epiblast cells into chondroblasts, neurons, and cardiac muscle</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">
<hr/>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Chondroblasts
<hr/>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Neurons
<hr/>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Cardiac muscle
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Unsorted</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"> &#x0003c;1 (8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">4 &#x000b1; 1 (10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">22 &#x000b1; 10 (9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>pos</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">ND</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">ND</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">1 &#x000b1; 1 (7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>neg</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"> &#x0003c;1 (7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">5 &#x000b1; 3 (6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">50 &#x000b1; 7 (7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Epiblast cells were sorted into G8<sup>pos</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> populations and cultured for 5 d. Cells were stained with the CIICI mAb to type II collagen (chondroblasts), 3A10 mAb to neurofilament-associated protein (neurons), and an mAb to cardiac muscle&#x02013;specific troponin T (cardiac muscle). Percent = (No. of fluorescent cells &#x000f7; total cells) &#x000d7; 100. Values are the mean &#x000b1; SD. The number of cultures scored is indicated in parentheses. A minimum of 200 cells was scored per culture. The percentage of cardiomyocytes was higher in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures than in unsorted cultures which contain G8<sup>pos</sup> cells (P &#x02264; 0.025).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Sorted cells also were examined for markers of other lineages (Table II; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, D&#x02013;F). The number of chondroblasts and neurons were similar in unsorted and G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures, suggesting that enhanced recruitment of cells to the chondrogenic and neurogenic lineages did not occur in the absence of the G8<sup>pos</sup> cells. The percentage of cells labeled with the cardiac troponin T antibody was similar to that of the MF20/sarcomeric myosin&#x02013;positive population (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Tables I</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">II</xref>). Therefore, most muscle cells in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures were cardiomyocytes and not skeletal muscle. The percentage of cardiomyocytes in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures was larger than that in unsorted cultures (P &#x02264; 0.025). However, all three populations combined accounted for only 55% of the cells in these cultures suggesting that nearly half of the cells in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures were not recruited to the chondrogenic, cardiomyogenic, or neurogenic lineage even in the absence of G8<sup>pos</sup> cells. This may reflect suboptimal culture conditions for the differentiation of these cell types and/or the absence or ineffectiveness of cells capable of recruiting pluripotent cells to these lineages.</p></sec><sec><title>The effect of medium conditioned by G8<sup>pos</sup> cells on G8<sup>neg</sup> cells</title><p>The effects of the G8<sup>pos</sup> cells on G8<sup>neg</sup> cells in mixed cultures were at least partially mediated by soluble factors because transfer of conditioned medium from 48-h G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures stimulated skeletal myogenesis in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table III</xref> and <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> G). Medium from unsorted 48-h cultures had a slight stimulatory effect on muscle differentiation in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. When conditioned medium from G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures was added to G8<sup>neg</sup> cells plated at low density, only a small percentage of cells not in contact with other cells synthesized detectable levels of the 12101 antigen (10 &#x000b1; 4, <italic>n</italic> = 4). Therefore, cell&#x02013;cell contacts facilitate the effect of conditioned medium on differentiation. By contrast, most G8<sup>pos</sup> cells plated at low density were stained with the 12101 mAb (92% &#x000b1; 2, <italic>n</italic> = 5; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> C). This demonstrates that the differentiation of epiblast cells expressing MyoD mRNA before removal from the embryo is independent of direct cell&#x02013;cell interactions.</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table III.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Differentiation of G8</bold>
<sup>neg</sup>
<bold>cells in the presence of medium conditioned by G8</bold>
<sup>pos</sup>
<bold>cells, Noggin, BMP-4, and soluble BMP receptor</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">Percent skeletal muscle</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Untreated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2 &#x000b1; 2 (22)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>neg</sup>-conditioned medium</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2 &#x000b1; 1 (4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Unsorted conditioned medium</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">6 &#x000b1; 2 (5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">49 &#x000b1; 12 (18)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Noggin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">50 &#x000b1; 9 (10)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium + BMP-4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2 &#x000b1; 2 (10)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Soluble BMP receptor-IA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">69 &#x000b1; 9 (8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">HGF/SF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">6 &#x000b1; 2 (4)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Medium conditioned for 48 h by unsorted, G8<sup>pos</sup>, or G8<sup>neg</sup> cells was added to 48-h G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. 50 ng/ml Noggin, 80 ng/ml of soluble BMP receptor-IA, and 25 ng/ml HGF/SF also were added to 48-h G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. 40 ng/ml BMP-4 was added to G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures in G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium. Cells were stained with the 12101 mAb on the fifth day in culture. Percent skeletal muscle = (No. of fluorescent cells &#x000f7; total cells) &#x000d7; 100. Values are the mean &#x000b1; SD. The number of cultures scored is indicated in parentheses. A minimum of 200 cells was scored per culture. Medium from G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures, Noggin, and soluble BMP receptor-IA stimulated myogenesis in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. BMP-4 blocked the stimulatory effect of G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Effects of noggin, BMP-4, and soluble BMP receptor-IA on the differentiation of <italic>G8</italic>
<sup>neg</sup> cells</title><p>In an attempt to identify the factors produced by G8<sup>pos</sup> cells that stimulated myogenesis in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures, conditioned medium was analyzed by silver staining. Bands of similar molecular weight were present in G8<sup>pos</sup>- and G8<sup>neg</sup>-conditioned media indicating that the factors were present in amounts below the level of detection by this method. A second approach was taken to identify the factors that involved addition of growth factors to G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures.</p><p>We had shown previously that treatment of epiblast cells from pregastrulating embryos with hepatocyte growth factor/scatter factor (HGF/SF) resulted in a moderate increase in muscle differentiation (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">DeLuca et al., 1999</xref>). G8<sup>neg</sup> cells from gastrulating embryos did not form skeletal muscle in response to HGF/SF, Wnt-1 (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1998</xref>), or Wnt-3A; however, they did respond to Noggin (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table III</xref> and <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> H). A dose response experiment revealed that 50 ng of human recombinant Noggin per milliliter of medium produced maximal stimulation of myogenesis.</p><p>Because Noggin is an inhibitor of BMPs (for review see <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Balemans and Van Hul, 2002</xref>), and BMP-4 is a regulator of myogenesis in the somites (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Pourquie et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dietrich et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Sela-Donenfeld and Kalcheim, 2002</xref>), BMP-4 was added to G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium at the time of its addition to G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. BMP-4 blocked the stimulatory effect of G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium on myogenesis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table III</xref>). Maximal inhibition was produced with a dose of 40 ng/ml.</p><p>Further evidence for involvement of BMPs in the inhibition of G8<sup>neg</sup> differentiation is that a soluble form of the BMP receptor-IA, a known competitor of the endogenous receptor for ligand binding, stimulated myogenesis in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table III</xref> and <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> I). The optimal dose for this effect was 80 ng/ml. These results suggest that BMP signaling represses myogenesis in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures and G8<sup>pos</sup> cells produce a BMP antagonist.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression of cadherins in G8<sup>pos</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> epiblast cultures</title><p>Previous experiments demonstrated that epiblast cells switch from E- to N-cadherin as they ingress through the primitive streak (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Edelman et al., 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Hatta and Takeichi, 1986</xref>; unpublished data), and down-regulation of E-cadherin and adhesion via N-cadherin are required for epiblast cells to form skeletal muscle in vitro (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>). 3 h after plating, most G8<sup>pos</sup> cells continued to express E-cadherin (67 &#x000b1; 17, <italic>n</italic> = 5); however, some were synthesizing N-cadherin (21 &#x000b1; 11, <italic>n</italic> = 5). After 24 h in culture, most G8<sup>pos</sup> were stained with antibodies to both N-cadherin (70 &#x000b1; 19, <italic>n</italic> = 6) and E-cadherin (74 &#x000b1; 12, <italic>n</italic> = 6). By the fifth day, most cells in G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures expressed N-cadherin, but not E-cadherin (Table IV; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, A and B</xref>)
.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Immunofluorescence localization of cadherins and</bold> &#x003b2;<bold>-catenin in G8</bold>
<sup>po</sup>
<bold><sup>s</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures.</bold> G8<sup>pos</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were isolated from stages 3 to 5 epiblasts, cultured for 5 d, and double labeled with antibodies to N- and E-cadherin (A&#x02013;D), or single labeled with antibodies to cadherin 11 and &#x003b2;-catenin. Most G8<sup>pos</sup> cells expressed N- but not E-cadherin (A and B). G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures contained cells with E- but not N-cadherin (C and D). G8<sup>neg</sup> cells stained with antibodies to &#x003b2;-catenin (E) and cadherin 11 (F). Bar, 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200309152f2"/></fig><p>G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were impaired in their ability to switch from E- to N-cadherin (Table IV; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, C and D</xref>). Although there was some variability of cadherin expression in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures between experiments, the percentage of N-cadherin positive (N-cadherin<sup>pos</sup>) cells was significantly smaller (P &#x02264; 0.0005) and the E-cadherin positive population significantly larger (P &#x02264; 0.005) than that observed in unsorted and G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures. Some cells in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures expressed neither N- nor E-cadherin (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table IV</xref>); however, &#x003b2;-catenin was localized to the membrane of all cells and most cells expressed cadherin 11 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, E and F</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table IV.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Expression of cadherins in cultures of unsorted, G8</bold>
<sup>pos</sup>
<bold>, and G8</bold>
<sup>neg</sup>
<bold>epiblast cells</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="bottom"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">% total<break/>with<break/>N-cad</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">N-cad<sup>pos</sup>
<break/>without<break/>E-cad</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">% total<break/>with<break/>E-cad</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">E-cad<sup>pos</sup>
<break/>without<break/>N-cad</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">% total<break/>with N-cad<break/>and E-cad</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">% total<break/>without<break/>N-or E-cad</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Unsorted</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">87 &#x000b1; 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">83 &#x000b1; 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">15 &#x000b1; 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">11 &#x000b1; 6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">5 &#x000b1; 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">2 &#x000b1; 5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic> = 8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>pos</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">87 &#x000b1; 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">85 &#x000b1; 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">14 &#x000b1; 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">12 &#x000b1; 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">1 &#x000b1; 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">1 &#x000b1; 1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic> = 7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>neg</sup> cells</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">45 &#x000b1; 23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">34 &#x000b1; 25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">39 &#x000b1; 21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">29 &#x000b1; 26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">10 &#x000b1; 8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">26 &#x000b1; 30</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic> = 16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>neg</sup> cells with unsorted CM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">45 &#x000b1; 9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">95 &#x000b1; 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">56 &#x000b1; 10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">96 &#x000b1; 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">2 &#x000b1; 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic> = 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">G8<sup>pos</sup> CM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">65 &#x000b1; 8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">94 &#x000b1; 7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">39 &#x000b1; 10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">92 &#x000b1; 11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">4 &#x000b1; 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic> = 6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Noggin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">63 &#x000b1; 13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">98 &#x000b1; 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">35 &#x000b1; 15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">98 &#x000b1; 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">1 &#x000b1; 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">2 &#x000b1; 2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic> = 6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Sol. BMP receptor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">62 &#x000b1; 7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">98 &#x000b1; 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">37 &#x000b1; 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">97 &#x000b1; 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">1 &#x000b1; 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">2 &#x000b1; 2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
<italic>n</italic> = 7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Stages 3&#x02013;5 epiblast cells were labeled with the G8 mAb, separated by magnetic cell sorting, and cultured for 5 d in DMEM/F12 medium. G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were also cultured in conditioned medium (CM) by unsorted or G8<sup>pos</sup> cells, or DMEM/F12 containing 50 ng/ml Noggin or 80 ng/ml soluble BMP receptor-IA. Cells were double labeled with a rabbit polyclonal antibody to N-cadherin and a mouse mAb to E-cadherin, and species-specific fluorescent secondary antibodies. Percentage of total cells = (No. of cells with N-cadherin, E-cadherin, both cadherins, or neither cadherin &#x000f7; total cells) &#x000d7; 100. N-Cadherin<sup>pos</sup> without E-cadherin = (No. of N-cadherin<sup>pos</sup> cells without E-cadherin &#x000f7; No. of cells with N-cadherin) &#x000d7; 100. E-Cadherin<sup>pos</sup> without N-cadherin = (No. E-cadherin<sup>pos</sup> cells without N-cadherin &#x000f7; No. of cells with E-cadherin) &#x000d7; 100. Values are the mean &#x000b1; SD. The number of cultures scored is indicated in parentheses. A minimum of 200 cells was scored per culture. Most cells in G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures expressed N- but not E-cadherin. Cadherin switching was reduced in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. Conditioned medium from G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures, Noggin, and soluble BMP receptor-IA stimulated N-cadherin expression in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The percentage of MyoD<sup>pos</sup> cells in unsorted cultures was similar to the number of cells expressing N- but not E-cadherin (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Tables I</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">IV</xref>). This was not the case in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures where the percentages of cells with MyoD and the 12101 antigen were smaller than the N-cadherin<sup>pos</sup>/E-cadherin negative population (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Tables I</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">IV</xref>). Therefore, a switch in expression of cadherins alone does not promote myogenesis. However, when G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were cultured in medium conditioned by G8<sup>pos</sup> cells or treated with Noggin or soluble BMP receptor-IA, the increase in muscle differentiation was accompanied by an increase in the percentage of cells with N-cadherin and a decrease in the population of cells expressing both cadherins (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Tables III</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">IV</xref>). These results suggest that G8<sup>pos</sup> cells produce an antagonist of the BMP pathway that promotes the expression of N-cadherin while stimulating skeletal myogenesis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The epiblast is a pluripotent tissue that gives rise to the three germ layers of the embryo (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bellairs, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">O'Shea, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 2001</xref>). Undifferentiated cells that express MyoD mRNA are embedded within the epiblast epithelium (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Gerhart et al., 2000</xref>). This study revealed that these MyoD<sup>pos</sup> cells form skeletal muscle when removed from the embryo, differentiate in the absence of cell&#x02013;cell contacts, promote a switch in the expression of E- to N-cadherin in pluripotent cells, and recruit them to the skeletal muscle lineage. These findings enhance our knowledge of the behavior of epiblast cells in vitro and have important implications for understanding the regulation of ES cell fate.</p><p>Skeletal myogenesis is the preferred pathway of differentiation when the entire population of chick epiblast cells is grown in vitro (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996a</xref>). This phenomenon is dependent on several factors including separating the epiblast from the mesoderm, disrupting cell&#x02013;cell contacts within the epithelium, plating cells on a substrate of denatured collagen and fibronectin to promote their attachment and survival, and culturing them in serum-free medium (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996a</xref>). In addition, most unsorted epiblast cells must be plated at high density in order to differentiate (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996b</xref>). This reflects a requirement for cadherin-mediated adhesions to support the synthesis of MyoD and sarcomeric myosin (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>). Our conclusion from these earlier experiments was that the emergence of skeletal muscle as the dominant phenotype in epiblast cultures was the result of a &#x0201c;community effect&#x0201d; (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gurdon, 1988</xref>) in which equivalent cells were induced to differentiate along the same pathway (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996a</xref>). In these cultures, the community effect was mediated by cell&#x02013;cell adhesions via N-cadherin (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>We have now determined the epiblast is a heterogeneous tissue comprised of both pluripotent cells and those that are biased, and possibly committed, to differentiate into skeletal muscle. Furthermore, it would seem that the single most important factor for the widespread induction of skeletal myogenesis in epiblast cultures is the release of factors from cells that are preprogrammed to form skeletal muscle within the embryo. Despite the fact that the culture conditions overwhelmingly support skeletal myogenesis, most pluripotent cells cannot form skeletal muscle in the absence of epiblast cells that express MyoD mRNA and the G8 antigen in vivo.</p><p>The MyoD<sup>pos</sup>/G8<sup>pos</sup> epiblast cells also affect cadherin expression. In unsorted and G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures, most cells down-regulated E-cadherin and up-regulated N-cadherin during skeletal muscle differentiation. In addition, previous experiments with unsorted epiblast cells revealed that both E- and N-cadherin supported MyoD protein synthesis; however, only those cells with N-cadherin but not E-cadherin differentiated (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>). The G8<sup>neg</sup> cells differed from unsorted and G8<sup>pos</sup> cells in three ways. First, G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were impaired in their ability to switch cadherins. Second, neither cadherin appeared to support the synthesis of MyoD protein in more than a minor population of G8<sup>neg</sup> cells. Finally, the percentage of differentiated skeletal muscle cells was significantly less than the percentage of N-cadherin<sup>pos</sup>/E-cadherin negative cells. The lack of skeletal myogenesis could reflect, in part, reduced homotypic N-cadherin&#x02013;mediated adhesions due to the presence of cells that continued to express E-cadherin alone or both cadherins.</p><p>The precise factors produced by MyoD<sup>pos</sup>/G8<sup>pos</sup> cells that stimulate myogenesis and N-cadherin expressions remain to be identified; however, the effect of the G8<sup>pos</sup> cells appears to involve antagonism of the BMP signaling pathway. Noggin, an inhibitor of BMPs-4, -6, and -7, and growth and differentiation factor-5 (for review see <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Balemans and Van Hul, 2002</xref>), stimulated N-cadherin synthesis and skeletal myogenesis when added to G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. Furthermore, BMP-4 blocked the stimulatory effect of G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium, and a soluble form of BMP receptor-IA known to compete with the endogenous receptor for ligand binding, increased muscle differentiation in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures in the absence of G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium. Releasing the G8<sup>neg</sup> cells from the inhibitory effects of BMPs may be sufficient to trigger myogenesis, although it is possible that these cells produce stimulatory factors that are also required for skeletal muscle differentiation.</p><p>These experiments provide additional evidence that skeletal myogenesis is the preferred pathway of chick epiblast cells under these culture conditions. They also complement experiments of the regulation of muscle differentiation in the somite. Expression of Noggin in the presomitic and somitic mesoderm releases cells from BMP-mediated repression of MyoD and Myf5 activation (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Pourquie et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Hirsinger et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Marcelle et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dietrich et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Reshef et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Amthor et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Sela-Donenfeld and Kalcheim, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Linker et al., 2003</xref>). Noggin is also involved in the down-regulation of E-cadherin during epithelial bud formation in combination with Wnt3a (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Jamora et al., 2003</xref>). At this time it is unclear whether G8<sup>pos</sup> cells directly affect cadherin synthesis, or if the expression of N-cadherin follows the recruitment of G8<sup>neg</sup> cells to the skeletal muscle lineage.</p><p>The results of our cell sorting experiments support the theory proposed decades ago by Holtzer and colleagues (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Holtzer et al., 1983</xref>) that founder cells for the myogenic lineage exist in the early embryo (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 1989</xref>). Testing the role of these cells in vivo could be accomplished by ablating the MyoD population at early times in development. There are several possible outcomes of this type of experiment including a complete or partial disruption of muscle differentiation, or no effect due to a stimulation of myogenic transcription factor expression in other cells. Molecules downstream in the sonic hedgehog pathway can directly regulate the promoter of the MyoD family member, myf5 (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Gustafsson et al., 2002</xref>), suggesting that signaling from the notochord may compensate for the loss of MyoD<sup>pos</sup> epiblast cells. Alternatively, release of factors from the original population of MyoD expressing cells could prime surrounding pluripotent cells to respond to molecules produced by the notochord and neural tube. In this regard, a subpopulation of cells within the presomitic mesoderm secretes Wnt5b which stimulates MyoD expression (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Linker et al., 2003</xref>). It is possible that the Wnt5b producing mesoderm cells are derived from cells that express MyoD within the epiblast.</p><p>Apart from any role that the MyoD<sup>pos</sup> epiblast cells may play in regulating muscle differentiation in vivo, their ability to recruit pluripotent cells to the myogenic lineage in vitro has important implications in the field of stem cell biology. We suggested previously that implanting a mixture of committed and pluripotent stem cells into diseased tissues might facilitate regeneration (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gerhart et al., 2001</xref>). Our results now suggest that exposure of stem cells to committed precursors or the factors they produce before implantation may preprogram them to follow the desired pathway in vivo. <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Asakura et al. (2002)</xref> demonstrated that neonatal myoblasts can induce stem cells derived from adult muscle to undergo skeletal myogenesis; however, the rate of conversion of these stem cells to the muscle lineage was low (&#x0223c;4%). Furthermore, conditioned medium from the neonatal myoblast cultures did not stimulate the stem cells to differentiate. This suggests that stem cells from adult muscle are more resistant to conversion to the myogenic lineage than pluripotent epiblast cells and/or neonatal myoblasts are less effective recruiters than MyoD<sup>pos</sup> epiblast cells. A third possibility is that the culture conditions for the neonatal myoblasts and adult stem cells were less permissive for the recruitment process than the epiblast culture system. Modifications in the method for pretreating adult stem cells with committed cells may enhance the extent of their conversion to the myogenic lineage and their regenerative potential in vivo.</p><p>An equally important consideration for the use of stem cells therapeutically is the role of the community effect in facilitating differentiation (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gurdon, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cossu et al., 1995</xref>). The molecular mechanism for the community effect involves cadherin-mediated adhesion (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Holt et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>). Although the G8<sup>pos</sup> cells release soluble factors that stimulate skeletal myogenesis in G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures, the factors are more effective when G8<sup>neg</sup> cells are plated at high density. Ensuring that the appropriate cadherin is expressed in the stem cell population may be a critical component of a strategy to regenerate skeletal muscle and other tissues.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Double labeling of embryos with 3DNA<sup>TM</sup> dendrimers and the G8 antibody</title><p>Previous experiments revealed that MyoD mRNA and the G8 antigen are expressed in the same cells in fetal organs (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gerhart et al., 2001</xref>). To test whether G8 is a marker for embryonic cells expressing MyoD, double labeling was performed with the G8 mAb and Cy3-labeled 3DNA<sup>TM</sup> dendrimers (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 1998</xref>; Genisphere, Inc.), having a cDNA sequence for MyoD mRNA ligated to their outer arms as described previously (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gerhart et al., 2001</xref>). The antisense oligonucleotide 5&#x02032;-TTCTCAAGAGCAAATACTCACCATTTGGTGATTCCGTGTAGTAGCTGCTG-3&#x02032; was derived from chicken MyoD (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Dechesne et al., 1994</xref>). The antibody was applied to living stages 3&#x02013;5 (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hamburger and Hamilton, 1951</xref>) White Leghorn chick embryos (CBT Farms; B&#x00026;E Farms), followed by fixation in 2% formaldehyde and incubation in a goat anti&#x02013;mouse IgM secondary antibody conjugated with Alexa 488 (Molecular Probes). After permeabilizing cells with Triton X-100 and pepsin, in situ hybridization with Cy3-labeled dendrimers was performed and nuclei were counterstained with bis-benzamide (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Gerhart et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Embryos were observed with an epifluorescence microscope (model Eclipse E800; Nikon, purchased from Optical Apparatus). Photomicrographs were produced with the Evolution QE video camera (Media Cybernetics) and Image-Pro Plus image analysis software (Phase 3 Imaging Systems).</p></sec><sec><title>Magnetic cell sorting</title><p>Epiblasts were isolated from stages 3 to 5 embryos and dissociated in 0.25% trypsin-EDTA (Invitrogen) at 37&#x000b0;C for 10 min (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1996a</xref>). Cells were centrifuged and resuspended in Dulbecco's minimal essential medium (DMEM) containing 5% FBS, 5% horse serum, 100 U of penicillin and streptomycin (Invitrogen Corp.), and 5% chick embryo extract (Myo medium). The G8 mAb was added to the cell suspension at a concentration of 2 &#x003bc;g/ml. After incubation at 37&#x000b0;C for 45 min, cells were centrifuged and resuspended in 80 &#x003bc;l PBS. 20 &#x003bc;l of rat anti&#x02013;mouse IgM microbeads (Miltenyi Biotec) were added for 15 min at RT. Cells were centrifuged, resuspended in 500 &#x003bc;l PBS, and added to the MiniMACS column attached to the magnetic sorting separation unit (Miltenyi Biotec). G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were eluted by rinsing the column with PBS. The column was then removed from the separation unit and the G8<sup>pos</sup> cells eluted in PBS with gentle plunging. The purity of the sorts was determined by labeling an aliquot of the positive and negative populations with a fluorescent secondary antibody, and calculating the percentage of the total cells that was fluorescent. G8<sup>pos</sup> and G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were centrifuged, resuspended in Myo medium, and placed in culture.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of epiblast cell cultures</title><p>Sorted and unsorted epiblast cells were cultured under conditions shown previously to promote myogenesis (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1994</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">1996a</xref>). 20,000 cells in 15 &#x003bc;l Myo medium were plated in the center of 35-mm tissue culture dishes coated with gelatin and human serum fibronectin (Invitrogen). After the cells had attached to the dish (90 min), they were flooded with 1 ml serum and hormone-free DMEM/F12 medium (Invitrogen). Low density cultures were prepared by plating 40,000 cells in 1 ml of Myo medium over the entire surface of a coated 35-mm dish. 90 min after plating, the medium was replaced with DMEM/F12.</p><p>G8<sup>neg</sup> cells were treated with conditioned medium by removing their medium after 48 h in culture and replacing it with 48-h medium obtained from G8<sup>pos</sup>, other G8<sup>neg</sup>, or unsorted cultures. The medium was centrifuged to remove cells before its addition to the G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures. Medium in 48-h G8<sup>neg</sup> cultures was replaced with 1 ml DMEM/F12 medium containing recombinant human Noggin (PeproTech), soluble BMP receptor-IA/Fc chimeric protein, HGF/SF, or 1 ml G8<sup>pos</sup>-conditioned medium containing recombinant human BMP-4 (all purchased from Sigma-Aldrich).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunofluorescence localization</title><p>Cells were fixed in 2% formaldehyde, permeabilized with 0.5% Triton X-100, and labeled with primary and fluorescent secondary antibodies as described previously (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1994</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">1996a</xref>). Labeling with antibodies to the cadherins required fixation in methanol. The skeletal muscle specific 12101 mAb (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Kitner and Brockes, 1984</xref>), MF20 mAb to sarcomeric myosin heavy chain (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bader et al., 1982</xref>), mAb to LCAM/E-cadherin (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Gallin et al., 1983</xref>), CIIC1 mAb to type II collagen (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Holmdahl et al., 1986</xref>), and 3A10 mAb to neurofilament associated antigen (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Furley et al., 1990</xref>) were obtained from the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank. The AB-1 mAb to cardiac muscle specific troponin T (Neomarkers) stained cardiomyocytes in vivo but did not bind skeletal muscle cells in fetal pectoralis muscle cultures or G8<sup>pos</sup> cultures (Table IV; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> E). The mAb 5B2H5 to cadherin 11 was purchased from Zymed Laboratories. A rabbit polyclonal antiserum to N-cadherin was generated as described previously (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>). Secondary antibodies were affinity purified, goat anti&#x02013;mouse F(ab')2 fragments conjugated with rhodamine or Cy3 (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories), and goat anti&#x02013;rabbit IgG conjugated with Cy2 (CHEMICON International, Inc.). Cells that had been prelabeled with the G8 IgM mAb before being placed in culture were later stained with IgG primary mAbs and a goat anti&#x02013;mouse IgG secondary antibody conjugated with rhodamine (CHEMICON International, Inc.). Nuclei were counterstained with bis-benzamide. The anti-IgG secondary antibody did not recognize the G8 IgM mAb.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr. Kenneth Chepenik, Noah May, and Kathleen Zazzali for critically reading the manuscript and Dr. Marina D'Angelo for insightful discussions. mAbs were obtained from the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank (University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA).</p><p>These studies were supported by the National Institutes of Health (HD043157 to M. George-Weinstein, GM61702 to K.A. Knudsen).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Amthor, H., B. Christ, and K. Patel. <year>1999</year>. A molecular mechanism enabling continuous embryonic muscle growth-a balance between proliferation and differentiation. <source>Development.</source>
<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>1041</fpage>&#x02013;1053.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9927604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Asakura, A., P. Seale, A. Girgis-Gabardo, and M.A. Rudnicki. <year>2002</year>. Myogenic specification of side population cells in skeletal muscle. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>159</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;134.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12379804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bader, D., T. Masaki, and D.A. Fischman. <year>1982</year>. Immunochemical analysis of myosin heavy chain during avian myogenesis in vivo and in vitro. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>763</fpage>&#x02013;770.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6185504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Balemans, W., and W. Van Hul. <year>2002</year>. Extracellular regulation of BMP signaling in vertebrates: a cocktail of modulators. <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>250</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;250.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bellairs, R. <year>1986</year>. The primitive streak. <source>Anat. Embryol.</source>
<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;14.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3518538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Choi, J., T. Schultheiss, M. Lu, F. Wachtler, N. Kuruc, W.W. Franke, and D. Bader. D.A. Fischman. and H. Holtzer. 1989. Founder cells for the cardiac and skeletal myogenic lineages. Cellular and Molecular Biology of Muscle Development. L. Kedes and F.E. Stockdale, editors. Alan R. Liss Inc., New York. 27&#x02013;36.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Christ, B., and C.P. Ordahl. 1995. Early stages of chick somite development. <italic>Anat. Embryol</italic>. (Berl). 191:381&#x02013;396.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cossu, G., R. Kelly, S. Di Donna, E. Vivarelli, and M. Buckingham. <year>1995</year>. Myoblast differentiation during mammalian somitogenesis is dependent upon a community effect. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>2254</fpage>&#x02013;2258.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7892257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dechesne, C.A., Q. Wei, J. Eldridge, L. Gannoun-Zaki, P. Millasseau, L. Bougueleret, D. Caterina, and B.M. Paterson. <year>1994</year>. E-box and MEF-2-independent muscle-specific expression, positive autoregulation, and cross-activation of the chicken MyoD (CMD1) promoter reveal an indirect regulatory pathway. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>5474</fpage>&#x02013;5486.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8035824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dietrich, S., F.R. Schubert, C. Healy, P.T. Sharpe, and A. Lumsden. <year>1998</year>. Specification of the hypaxial musculature. <source>Development.</source>
<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>2235</fpage>&#x02013;2249.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9584123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">DeLuca, S.M., J. Gerhart, E. Cochran, E. Simak, J. Blitz, M. Mattiacci-Paessler, K. Knudsen, and M. George-Weinstein. <year>1999</year>. Hepatocyte growth factor/scatter factor promotes a switch from E- to N-cadherin in chick embryo epiblast cells. <source>Exp. Cell Res.</source>
<volume>251</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;15.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10438566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Edelman, G.M., W.J. Gallin, A. Delouvee, B.A. Cunningham, and J.P. Thiery. <year>1983</year>. Early epochal maps of two different cell adhesion molecules. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>4384</fpage>&#x02013;4388.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6576344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Furley, A.J., S.B. Morton, D. Manalo, D. Karagogeos, J. Dodd, and T.M. Jessell. <year>1990</year>. The axonal glycoprotein TAG-1 is an immunoglobulin superfamily member with neurite outgrowth-promoting activity. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;170.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2317872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gallin, W.J., G.M. Edelman, and B.A. Cunningham. <year>1983</year>. Characterization of L-CAM, a major cell adhesion molecule from embryonic liver cells. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>1038</fpage>&#x02013;1042.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6573655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">George-Weinstein, M., J. Gerhart, F. Foti, and J.W. Lash. <year>1994</year>. Maturation of myogenic and chondrogenic cells in the presomitic mesoderm of the chick embryo. <source>Exp. Cell Res.</source>
<volume>211</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;274.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8143772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">George-Weinstein, M., J. Gerhart, R. Reed, J. Flynn, B. Callihan, M. Mattiacci, C. Miehle, G. Foti, J.W. Lash, and H. Weintraub. <year>1996</year>a. Skeletal myogenesis: the preferred pathway of chick embryo epiblast cells in vitro. <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>173</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;291.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8575629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">George-Weinstein, M., J. Gerhart, R. Reed, A. Steinberg, M. Mattiacci, H. Weintraub, and K. Knudsen. <year>1996</year>b. Intrinsic and extrinsic regulation of the development of myogenic precursors in the chick embryo. <source>Basic Appl. Myol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;430.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">George-Weinstein, M., J. Gerhart, J. Blitz, E. Simak, and K.A. Knudsen. <year>1997</year>. N-cadherin promotes the commitment and differentiation of skeletal muscle precursor cells. <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;24.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9169046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">George-Weinstein, M., J. Dare, J. Gerhart, A.M.C. Brown, A. Redfield, H. Brown, and K.A. Knudsen. <year>1998</year> Unexpected effects of Wnt-1 on the differentiation and adhesion of myogenic cells. <source>Basic Appl. Myol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;314.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gerhart, J., M. Baytion, S. DeLuca, R. Getts, C. Lopez, R. Niewenhuis, T. Nilsen, S. Olex, H. Weintraub, and M. George-Weinstein. <year>2000</year>. DNA dendrimers localize MyoD mRNA in presomitic tissues of the chick embryo. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>825</fpage>&#x02013;833.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10811824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gerhart, J., B. Bast, C. Neely, S. Iem, P. Amegbe, R. Niewenhuis, S. Miklasz, P.F. Cheng, and M. George-Weinstein. <year>2001</year>. MyoD-positive myoblasts are present in mature fetal organs lacking skeletal muscle. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;391.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11684706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gumbiner, B.M. <year>2000</year>. Regulation of cadherin adhesive activity. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;404.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10662767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gurdon, J.B. <year>1988</year>. A community effect in animal development. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>336</volume>:<fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;774.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3205305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gustafsson, M.K., H. Pan, D.F. Pinney, Y. Liu, A. Lewandowski, D.J. Epstein, and C.P. Emerson, Jr. <year>2002</year>. Myf5 is a direct target of long-range Shh signaling and Gli regulation for muscle specification. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;126.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11782449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hamburger, V., and H.L. Hamilton. <year>1951</year> A series of normal stages in development of the chick embryo. <source>J. Morphol.</source>
<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;92.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24539719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hatta, K., and M. Takeichi. <year>1986</year>. Expression of N-cadherin adhesion molecules associated with early morphogenetic events in chick development. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>320</volume>:<fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;449.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3515198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hirsinger, E., D. Duprez, C. Jouve, P. Malapert, J. Cooke, and O. Pourquie. <year>1997</year>. Noggin acts downstream of Wnt and Sonic Hedgehog to antagonize BMP4 in avian somite patterning. <source>Development.</source>
<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>4605</fpage>&#x02013;4614.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9409677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Holmdahl, R., K. Rubin, L. Klareskog, E. Larsson, and H. Wigzell. <year>1986</year>. Characterization of the antibody response in mice with type II collagen-induced arthritis using monoclonal anti-type II collagen antibodies. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source>
<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>400</fpage>&#x02013;410.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2421741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Holt, C.E., P. Lemaire, and J.B. Gurdon. <year>1994</year>. Cadherin-mediated cell interactions are necessary for the activation of MyoD in <italic>Xenopus</italic> mesoderm. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>10844</fpage>&#x02013;10848.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7971972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Holtzer, H., J. Biehl, R. Payette, J. Sasse, M. Pacifici, and S. Holtzer. 1983. Cell diversification: differing roles of cell lineages and cell-cell interactions. Limb Development and Regeneration. Part B. P.F. Goetinck and J.A. MacCabe, editors. Alan R. Liss Inc., New York. 271&#x02013;283.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jamora, C., R. DasGupta, P. Kocieniewski, and E. Fuchs. <year>2003</year>. Links between signal transduction, transcription and adhesion in epithelial bud development. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>422</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;322. (published erratum in <italic>Nature</italic>. 2003. 424:974)
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12646922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kitner, C.R., and J.P. Brockes. <year>1984</year>. Monoclonal antibodies identify blastemal cells derived from dedifferentiating muscle in newt limb regeneration. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>308</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;69.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6366572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Linker, C., C. Lesbros, M. Stark, and C. Marcelle. <year>2003</year>. Intrinsic signals regulate the initial steps of myogenesis in vertebrates. <source>Development.</source>
<volume>130</volume>:<fpage>4797</fpage>&#x02013;4807.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12917295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marcelle, C., M.R. Stark, and M. Bronner-Fraser. <year>1997</year>. Coordinate actions of BMPs, Shh and Noggin mediate patterning of the dorsal somite. <source>Development.</source>
<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>3955</fpage>&#x02013;3963.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9374393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">O'Shea, K.S. <year>2001</year>. Directed differentiation of embryonic stem cells: genetic and epigenetic methods. <source>Wound Repair Regen.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;459.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11896987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pourquie, O., C.M. Fan, M. Coltey, E. Hirsinger, Y. Watanabe, C. Breant, P. Francis-West, P. Brickell, M. Tessier-Lavigne, and N.M. Le Douarin. <year>1996</year>. Lateral and axial signals involved in avian somite patterning: a role for BMP4. <source>Cell</source>. <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;471.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8608600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pourquie, O. <year>2001</year>. Vertebrate somitogenesis. <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;350.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11687492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pownall, M.E., M.K. Gustafsson, and C.P. Emerson. <year>2002</year>. Myogenic regulatory factors and the specification of muscle progenitors in vertebrate embryos. <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>747</fpage>&#x02013;783.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Radice, G.L., H. Rayburn, H. Matsunami, K.A. Knudsen, M. Takeichi, and R.O. Hynes. <year>1997</year>. Developmental defects in mouse embryos lacking N-cadherin. <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;78.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9015265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reshef, R., M. Maroto, and A.B. Lassar. <year>1998</year>. Regulation of dorsal somatic cell fates: BMPs and Noggin control the timing and pattern of myogenic regulator expression. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>290</fpage>&#x02013;303.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sela-Donenfeld, D., and C. Kalcheim. <year>2002</year>. Localized BMP4-noggin interactions generate the dynamic patterning of noggin expression in the somite. <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>246</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;328.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12051818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smith, A.G. <year>2001</year>. Embryo-derived stem cells: Of mice and men. <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;462.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11687496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang, J., M. Jiang, T.W. Nilsen, and R.C. Getts. <year>1998</year> Dendritic nucleic acid probes for DNA biosensors. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>8281</fpage>&#x02013;8282.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
