<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098930</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1669770</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl880</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>ApiDB: integrated resources for the apicomplexan bioinformatics resource center</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aurrecoechea</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heiges</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Haiming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Zhiming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>Steve</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>Philippa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>Eileen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>Christian J.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>David S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kissinger</surname><given-names>Jessica C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Center for Tropical and Emerging Global Diseases</institution><addr-line>Athens GA, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Computer Science, University of Georgia</institution><addr-line>Athens GA, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Genetics, Center for Bioinformatics</institution><addr-line>423 Guardian Dr, Philadelphia, PA, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Penn Genomics Institute, University of Pennsylvania</institution><addr-line>Philadelphia, PA, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Genetics, University of Georgia</institution><addr-line>Athens GA, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 706 542 6562; Fax: +1 706 542 3582; Email: <email>jkissing@uga.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D427</fpage><lpage>D430</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2006 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>ApiDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ApiDB.org"/>) represents a unified entry point for the NIH-funded Apicomplexan Bioinformatics Resource Center (BRC) that integrates numerous database resources and multiple data types. The phylum Apicomplexa comprises numerous veterinary and medically important parasitic protozoa including human pathogenic species of the genera <italic>Cryptosporidium, Plasmodium</italic> and <italic>Toxoplasma</italic>. ApiDB serves not only as a database in its own right, but as a single web-based point of entry that unifies access to three major existing individual organism databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="PlasmoDB.org"/>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ToxoDB.org"/> and CryptoDB.org), and integrates these databases with data available from additional sources. Through the ApiDB site, users may pose queries and search all available apicomplexan data and tools, or they may visit individual component organism databases.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The phylum Apicomplexa comprises numerous veterinary and medically important parasitic protozoa including human pathogenic species of the genera <italic>Cryptosporidium, Plasmodium</italic> and <italic>Toxoplasma</italic>. Multiple species of <italic>Plasmodium</italic> are capable of causing malaria in humans, a leading cause of morbidity and mortality in developing countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>). <italic>Cryptosporidium</italic> causes a severe and chronic diarrheal disease that may be life threatening in immunocompromised patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>). <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infections, although typically asymptomatic in healthy individuals, may lead to congenital birth defects and encephalitis in HIV/AIDS patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>). Human infections with <italic>T.gondii</italic> may be acquired from food or soil contamination and infections with <italic>Cryptosporidium parvum</italic> from soil and water contamination. Due to the potential threat to public health from intentional dispersal into the population, <italic>T.gondii</italic> and <italic>C.parvum</italic> are listed as Category B Biodefense Pathogens by the National Institutes of Health.</p><p>The research communities for <italic>Cryptosporidium, Plasmodium</italic> and <italic>Toxoplasma</italic> have benefited from the bioinformatics resources provided by the distinct online genome databases CryptoDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>), PlasmoDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>) and ToxoDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>), respectively (See supplementary material). Because of the phylogenetic relationship of these human pathogens, (all are included in the phylum Apicomplexa, along with the prominent animal pathogens, <italic>Babesia, Theileria</italic> and <italic>Eimeria</italic>) comparative genomic and proteomic studies across these species is critical for expediting discovery of therapeutic targets, increasing understanding of parasite biology and enhancing other areas of research on the biology of these organisms. However, the researcher's ability to perform comparative studies utilizing multiple data sources has been tempered by the difficulty of managing and collating the data from the existing disparate resource databases. Here we describe the online apicomplexan Bioinformatics Resource Center (BRC), ApiDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ApiDB.org"/>), which has been established to provide researchers centralized, integrated access to experimental and computational data, as well as tools to facilitate comparative research.</p><p>ApiDB integrates the existing CryptoDB, ToxoDB and PlasmoDB component resources. Database integration is accomplished via a combination of federation and link integration technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). Link integration allows researchers to begin their query with one data source and then follow hypertext links to related information in other data sources. Database federation is achieved by decomposing distributed queries into component queries and executing these queries in the source databases, delivering the results into a uniform format. It leaves the information in its source databases but builds an environment around the databases that makes them all seem part of one large system. In ApiDB 2.0 the federation has been implemented using Oracle DbLink technology. In order to handle heterogeneous data sources in the future we are studying other federation approaches, such as Java Database Connectivity (JDBC) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/javase/technologies/database.jsp"/>) and Web Services (WS) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/2002/ws/"/>).</p><p>ApiDB serves as a web portal for cross-species comparison. Genome data from other apicomplexan parasites are also integrated. In its current release, ApiDB 2.0 offers an initial set of queries that enable gene searches of the three component databases by a variety of criteria such as text keywords, Enzyme Commission (EC) number Gene Ontology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>) assignments, and Pfam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>) terms. In addition, ApiDB offers tools to BLAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>) all public apicomplexan data, access to the multi-species gene orthology database OrthoMCL DB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>) and access to KEGG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>) metabolic pathway maps with &#x02018;painted&#x02019; comparative highlights of apicomplexan and human enzymes.</p></sec><sec><title>FUNCTIONALITY OF CURRENT RELEASE</title><p>ApiDB 2.0 was released in April 2006. The datasets available in ApiDB include the component databases (CryptoDB, PlasmoDB and ToxoDB), apicomplexan genomic sequences for other species (<italic>Theileria annulata</italic> and <italic>Theileria parva</italic>) obtained from the NCBI Genbank (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>) and GeneDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>), a collection of clustered apicomplexan ESTs including: <italic>Eimeria, Gregarina, Neospora, Sarcocystis</italic> and <italic>Theileria</italic> called ApiDoTS [a newer version of ApiEST-DB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>)] and unclustered ESTs from the NCBI Genbank division, dbEST.</p><p>The ApiDB web interface shares its architecture and &#x02018;look and feel&#x02019; with the component sites (CryptoDB, PlasmoDB and ToxoDB). The user can interact with four areas on the main page: the sidebar, a tools section, a query section and a menu bar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). The sidebar gives the user access to apicomplexan community resources, from our project's most recent news to PubCrawler (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>) and external resources, as well as information on the annual ApiDB training workshop (See supplementary material). The tools section provides access to a BLAST search of Apicomplexa genomic, EST and gene model sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>) and to OrthoMCL DB and KEGG maps with apicomplexan and human enzymes highlighted. The query section provides queries for gene and protein features that span CryptoDB, PlasmoDB and ToxoDB and may include searches of all or a subset of the component species genomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Finally, the menu bar appears on every page and gives access to the user's query history and the information on the datasets used in the database.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Database Functionality (<bold>A</bold>) Searches are initiated via tools or queries provided on the web site's front page. (<bold>B</bold>) Query forms allow user-defined refinement for the queries, e.g. which species would you like to search? Descriptions and help are provided for the queries. (<bold>C</bold>) Query searches return a table with results from the component databases sites. The result summary states the number of records found at each site (circled). Individual results are linked to a detailed record page at its component database site. (<bold>D</bold>) The BLAST tool integrates searches of all publicly available apicomplexan genomic data, including species not hosted by a component database. (<bold>E</bold>) Query results can be downloaded in a customized tab-delimited file.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl880f1"/></fig><p>ApiDB's query architecture provides a set of pages where users can easily execute and manage queries. On the front page, six federated queries are currently available that span the component databases: search genes by gene ID, by annotated keyword in product description (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>), by Pfam domain, by EC number, by GO term, and by BLAST similarity. Upon query selection, the user is presented with a question page where they can refine their search (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). When the query is executed, a summary page offers the number of hits for each organism and the list of genes that meet the requirements (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). Hyperlinks connect the user to the gene page in the component sites. Gene pages, acquired from the appropriate component database provide a detailed view of annotation and analysis for the given gene record in the database. For a detailed description of the gene record page we refer to the component databases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>).</p><p>The query history page, linked in the menu bar, permits users to track their searches and combine them into more complex queries across data types, e.g. find all genes in <italic>Cryptosporidium, Plasmodium</italic> and <italic>Toxoplasma</italic> that have a signal peptide and no transmembrane domains. Summaries of the number of hits for each organism are provided when queries are executed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). As in the component sites, the web interface includes a mechanism to allow users to readily download the sequences and other attributes associated with their query result set (e.g. gene name, product description, coordinates, length) in a versatile tab-delimited file (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1E</xref>) that can be viewed in the spreadsheet programs, or, if only sequences are desired, may be downloaded in Fasta format. Examples of inquiries that can be performed on ApiDB are located in the supplementary material.</p></sec><sec><title>FUTURE DIRECTIONS</title><p>ApiDB will be guided in large part by input from the user communities of ApiDB, the component databases and the objectives of the BRCs. An annual workshop on the usage of apicomplexan database resources is not only a valuable opportunity for users to obtain hands-on instruction, but it also provides a forum for feedback used to further drive development of this site. As the autonomous component databases evolve with new data and features, ApiDB will respond to integrate these elements as appropriate. As data from phylogenetically related species becomes increasingly available, e.g. ciliates and <italic>Perkinsus</italic>, and perhaps, some day a dinoflagellate, orthologous genes will be determined and links will be provided, via orthology to these resources when possible.</p><p>The ApiDB website currently excludes queries of datasets not found in all three component databases. For example, PlasmoDB contains microarray-based gene expression data whereas CryptoDB and ToxoDB presently do not. We will investigate permitting the querying of a subset of the component databases through ApiDB. Feature enhancements that will be available by early 2007 include persistent history to allow users to save their search results and corresponding results and a &#x02018;sort&#x02019; tool to allow users to sort the results they obtain from individual queries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>) by species, gene ID or feature description.</p><p>Combinations of existing tools, pre-formed queries and query history can be leveraged in powerful ways to mine the apicomplexan data but do not lend themselves well to high-throughput explorations. To facilitate large-scale database utilization, we will be providing programmatic access to our facilities through the use of standard web service technologies. Modular web service tasks will serve as building blocks for creating a user-defined workflow. As a single example, linking a series of tasks would enable a researcher with a collection of putative gene regulatory motifs to perform a bulk series of BLAST searches of chromosomal sequences, extract hit coordinates from the report, then query for gene models downstream of each hit. As our web services capabilities expand, we will use them to permit workflows that include ClustalW (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>) for multiple sequence alignments. Web services may also be used to collaborate with additional databases, including other BRCs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://BRC-central.org"/>), to offer users integrated access to additional pathogen data.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The ApiDB project is co-administered by David S. Roos, Christian J. Stoeckert Jr and Jessica C. Kissinger. We thank our database development collaborators: Aaron J. Mackey, Bindu Gajria, Thomas Gan, Jerric Gao, John Iodice and the entire development team for the component database sites. This project has been funded in whole or in part with Federal funds from the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Department of Health and Human Services, under Contract No. HHSN266200400037C. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by National Institute of Allergy and Infectious 215 Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Department of Health and Human Services, under Contract No. HHSN26620040 0037C.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement.</italic> None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lop&#x000e9;z-Antu&#x000f1;ano</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmunis</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Parasitic Protozoa</source><year>1993</year><volume>Vol. 5</volume><publisher-loc>San Deigo, CA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press Inc.</publisher-name><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>265</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fayer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cryptosporidium and Cryptosporidiosis</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press Inc.</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Toxoplasmosis of Animals and Man.</source><year>1988</year><publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press Inc.</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heiges</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aurrecoechea</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaluskar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>C.-Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CryptoDB: a <italic>Cryptosporidium</italic> bioinformatics resource update</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D419</fpage><lpage>D422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunk</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraunholz</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gajria</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kissinger</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Labo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PlasmoDB: the <italic>Plasmodium</italic> genome resource. A database integrating experimental and computational data</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kissinger</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gajria</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>I.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ToxoDB: accessing the <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> genome</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrating biological databases</article-title><source>Nature Rev. Genet.</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12728276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolinski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwight</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eppig</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</article-title><source>Nature Genet.</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Pfam protein families database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrthoMCL-DB: querying a comprehensive multi-species collection of ortholog groups</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D363</fpage><lpage>D368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki-Kinoshita</surname><given-names>K.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From genomics to chemical genomics: new developments in KEGG</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D354</fpage><lpage>D357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karsch-Mizrachi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GenBank</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hertz-Fowler</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aslett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerhornou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tivey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berriman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GeneDB: a resource for prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>D339</fpage><lpage>D343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinney</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ApiEST-DB: analyzing clustered EST data of the apicomplexan parasites</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>D326</fpage><lpage>D328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hokamp</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PubCrawler: keeping up comfortably with PubMed and GenBank</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>W16</fpage><lpage>W19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple sequence alignment with ClustalX</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source><year>1998</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9810230</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
