<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17251198</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1807955</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl1100</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Deletion of a trypanosome telomere leads to loss of silencing and progressive loss of terminal DNA in the absence of cell cycle arrest</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>Lucy</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alsford</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, Keppel Street, London, WC1E 7HT, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>(020) 7927 2352</phone>; Fax: <fax>(020) 7636 8739</fax>; E-mail: <email>david.horn@lshtm.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>880</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Eukaryotic chromosomes are capped with telomeres which allow complete chromosome replication and prevent the ends from being recognized by the repair machinery. The African trypanosome, <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic>, is a protozoan parasite where antigenic variation requires reversible silencing of a repository of telomere-adjacent variant surface glycoprotein (<italic>VSG</italic>) genes. We have investigated the role of the telomere adjacent to a repressed <italic>VSG</italic>. In cells lacking telomerase, the rate of telomere-repeat loss appeared to be inversely proportional to telomere length. We therefore constructed strains in which a single telomere could be immediately removed by conditional I-<italic>Sce</italic>I meganuclease cleavage. Following telomere deletion, cells maintain and segregate the damaged chromosome without repairing it. These cells continue to proliferate at the normal rate but progressively lose terminal DNA at the broken end. Although sirtuin-dependent repression is lost along with the telomere, <italic>VSG</italic>-silencing is preserved. The results provide direct evidence for telomere-dependent repression but suggest a telomere-independent mode of <italic>VSG</italic>-silencing. They also indicate the absence of a telomere-loss checkpoint in <italic>T. brucei</italic>.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Telomeres are nucleoprotein complexes that form protective caps at the natural DNA double strand breaks (DSBs) found at chromosome ends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). Telomere loss or DSBs elsewhere in the genome are potent DNA damage response (DDR) stimuli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). In proliferating cells, even a single DSB triggers a DDR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). The classical DDR involves cell-cycle arrest and repair and ensures the maintenance of genome integrity. G<sub>2</sub>/M arrest can last for the length of several cell cycles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) and, if damage is extensive and/or not repaired, can be followed by senescence or apoptosis. Consequently, if DDR pathways are defective, DSBs can have profound consequences including chromosome rearrangement and oncogenesis. Telomeres also influence sister chromosome separation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) and recruit a histone deacetylase, sirtuin complex that represses the expression of adjacent genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Thus, telomeres protect chromosome ends, influence chromosome dynamics, repress local gene expression and mask the DNA end from damage surveillance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>).</p><p>In the mammalian host bloodstream, <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic>, the African trypanosome, escapes the immune response through mono-telomeric expression and reversible silencing of variant surface glycoprotein (<italic>VSG</italic>) genes. Antigenic variation can occur via rare epigenetic switching to alternative telomeric expression sites (ESs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Unusually, RNA polymerase I, a polymerase generally confined to ribosomal RNA genes in eukarya, transcribes the active <italic>VSG</italic> towards a telomere. A typical ES is polycistronic with the promoter &#x0223c;50&#x02009;kbp from the telomere-adjacent <italic>VSG</italic> which produces approximately 10% of total cellular protein. <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> telomeres repress RNA polymerase I transcription within a few thousand base pairs of the telomere in a sirtuin-dependent manner but ES silencing is sirtuin-independent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>).</p><p>In total, there are probably more than 200 telomeres in <italic>T. brucei</italic>; the majority cap the minichromosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). The specialized reverse-transcriptase known as telomerase extends <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomeres by adding T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub> repeats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). Human chromosome ends are protected by a six subunit complex known as shelterin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) and an apparent homologue of one of the subunits, TRF2, has been characterized in <italic>T. brucei</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). t-loops are another feature shared by human and <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomeres (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Unlike the situation in many organisms however, there is no rigorous telomere length monitoring in <italic>T. brucei</italic>. Telomerase-dependent extension is minimally 6&#x02009;bp/population doubling (PD) but is increased by transcription at the chromosome end (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), a feature that may only affect the single active ES telomere in bloodstream form cells. Growth and occasional deletions are responsible for highly variable telomere lengths ranging from less than one to more than 15&#x02009;kbp in each cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>).</p><p>Telomeres play key roles in regulating virulence gene expression and recombination in a range of pathogens and are thought to play important roles in <italic>T. brucei</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). We established tetracycline-inducible I-<italic>Sce</italic>I expression and used this system to delete a specific <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomere. The resulting cells allowed us to explore the role of the telomere in gene expression and in protecting the chromosome end from nucleolytic degradation and the DDR. We show that telomeric DNA represses the expression of adjacent genes and protects terminal DNA from degradation. Telomeres do not appear to be required for <italic>VSG</italic> silencing however and, remarkably, <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomere deletion does not trigger a DDR.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title><italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> growth and manipulation</title><p>All bloodstream form cells were derived from Lister 427 MITat1.2 (clone 221a) and grown in HMI-11. Cells were transformed with linear DNA constructs as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Drug selection was applied as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) and cell density was determined using a haemocytometer. Tetracycline (Tet) was from Sigma and was removed from the medium by washing the cells twice in HMI-11. To estimate <italic>VSG221</italic> reactivation frequency, VSGX-expressing cells were pre-grown in Tet (1 &#x000b5;g/ml) for 24&#x02009;h and then 1.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells were distributed into each well of a 24-well plate in medium containing Tet and puromycin (5&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml). Wells were inspected for growth after 6 days and positive cultures were examined for VSG221 expression.</p></sec><sec><title>Plasmid constructs</title><p>pHD1313 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>) was used to introduce the tetracycline-repressor (<italic>TetR:BLE</italic>) into <italic>T. brucei</italic>. pESP<sup>i</sup><italic>PAC</italic> and pESP<sup>i</sup><italic>RFP:PAC</italic> were used to introduce a Tet operator (<italic>TetO</italic>) followed by a <italic>PAC</italic> gene or an <italic>RFP:PAC</italic> fusion downstream of the <italic>VSG221</italic> ES promoter respectively. The upstream and downstream targeting fragments in these two constructs were amplified by PCR from pRK8(+) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) using the VTet5U (GATC<italic>GAGCTC</italic>GCATTTACAACTGATGCTATA), VTOp3U (GATC<italic>GGATCC</italic>ACT<underline>CTATCA</underline>T<underline>TGATAG</underline>GGTGaGTCTGATATCCTAGATTTC) primer pair and from BAC TBH25N7 (22, Acc:AL671259) using the VTet5D (GATC<italic>GGGCCC</italic>GGTGTGGCGGACGTCTCG), VTet3D (GATC<italic>GGTACC</italic>GGCTGGATCAATTCCTGCAG) primer pair, respectively. The VTOp3U primer encodes the <italic>TetO</italic> sequence (underlined) and the &#x02018;a&#x02019; represents the transcription start site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Relevant restriction sites encoded by the primers are in italics. The fragments were cloned either side of a <italic>PAC</italic> gene flanked by <italic>T. brucei</italic> mRNA processing signals. The <italic>RFP:PAC</italic> fusion was assembled by ligating <italic>RFP</italic> and <italic>PAC</italic> genes PCR amplified using the RFP5Fu (GATC<italic>AAGCTT</italic>atgGTGCGCTCCTCCAAG), RFP3Fu (GATC<italic>GCGGCCGC</italic>ACAGGAACAGGTGGTGGCG) primer pair with pDsRed1-C1 (Clontech) and the PAC5Fu (GATC<italic>GCGGCCGC</italic>ACCGAGTACAAGCCCACG), TUBIR3Fu (GATC<italic>GGGCCC</italic>CCCCTCGACT) primer pair respectively. The <italic>RFP</italic> start codon is indicated in lower-case. <italic>BLA</italic> and <italic>HYG</italic> constructs were used to disrupt the telomerase gene (GeneDB ID: Tb11.01.1950) generating homozygous <italic>telomerase</italic><sup>&#x025b5;222-954</sup> null strains (see 10). The I-<italic>Sce</italic>I cleavage site was added to the telomere-mediated fragmentation construct, pTMF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), by annealing the SceF (GGCC<italic>TAGGGATAACAGGGTAAT</italic>) and SceR (GGCC<italic>ATTACCCTGTTATCCCTA</italic>) primers and ligating the product to <italic>Not</italic>I-digested pTMF. The I-<italic>Sce</italic>I ORF was amplified by PCR from pSCM525 using the SceNLS (GATC<italic>AAGCTT</italic>atg<underline>CCAAAGAAGAAGCGAAAGGTA</underline> &#x02013; I-<italic>Sce</italic>I codons 2&#x02013;9) and Sce3 (GATC<italic>GGATCC</italic>tta - I-<italic>Sce</italic>I codons 231&#x02013;237) primers such that an SV40 nuclear localization signal (PKKKRKV, codons underlined) was encoded at the <italic>N</italic>-terminus. Start and stop codons are indicated in lower-case. The recombinant I-<italic>Sce</italic>I gene was ligated to a construct for Tet-on inducible expression from a <italic>RRNA</italic> promoter. This vector is used to integrate the expression cassette at <italic>T. brucei RRNA</italic> loci in cells expressing TetR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). <italic>BLA</italic> and <italic>HYG</italic> constructs were used to disrupt the <italic>SIR2rp1</italic> gene (GeneDB ID: Tb927.7.1690) generating homozygous <italic>sir2rp1</italic><sup>&#x025b5;1-285</sup> null strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>DNA and RNA analysis</title><p>Southern and northern analyses were carried out according to standard protocols. Telomere healing locations were mapped using genomic DNA from <italic>T. brucei</italic> clones that survived <italic>PAC</italic> selection (0.2&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml puromycin) after I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction; <italic>PAC</italic> at a repressed ES was sufficient to confer resistance to this concentration of puromycin. Briefly, the 221B (GGCGTTACCAAGCTTGTTGA) and Tel2 (ACCCTA)<sub>5</sub> primers were used to amplify the healed end by PCR and the 221Uxho primer (N<sub>10</sub>TTTCCCCCCTCAAATTTCCCC) was used for sequencing.</p></sec><sec><title>Protein analysis</title><p>Western blotting and fluorescence microscopy were carried out using standard protocols as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Briefly, extracts of total cell protein were separated on SDS-polyacrylamide gels and stained with coomassie blue (Sigma) or subjected to western blotting using rabbit-&#x003b1;VSG221 and an ECL kit (Amersham). For immunofluorescence analysis, cells were labelled using rabbit &#x003b1;NPT-II (Europa Bioproducts) primary antibody and fluorescein-conjugated goat-&#x003b1;rabbit secondary antibody (Pierce). Cells were mounted in Vectashield (Vector Laboratories) containing 4,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) and images were captured using an Eclipse E600 microscope with digital camera (Nikon) and Metamorph software.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Derivation of isogenic strains with active and repressed <italic>VSG</italic> expression sites</title><p>Approximately twenty telomeric loci are occupied by similar polycistronic <italic>VSG</italic> expression sites (ESs) in <italic>T. brucei</italic>. In bloodstream form cells, all but one are reversibly repressed and the frequency of switching is very low, typically &#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>/PD (1 PD &#x0223c;7.5&#x02009;h). For most studies, we use cells expressing <italic>VSG221</italic>, a single copy <italic>VSG</italic> gene on chromosome VIa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). To facilitate studies on this well characterized ES in its repressed state, we expressed the tetracycline repressor (TetR) and, in the presence of Tet, inserted a Tet operator (see 24) adjacent to the <italic>VSG221</italic> ES promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). TetR-binding in this position is expected to interfere with ES transcription. The resulting cells continued to express <italic>VSG221</italic> in the presence of Tet but only cells that switched to an alternative <italic>VSG</italic> expression site survived when Tet was removed from the growth medium (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). This is explained by the blockage of <italic>VSG221</italic> ES transcription that occurs when TetR binds <italic>TetO</italic> and because <italic>VSG</italic> expression is essential for viability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). <italic>VSG221</italic> was reversibly repressed in the switched clones and, under permissive conditions (+Tet), yielded five puromycin resistant clones from 3.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> cells (equivalent to &#x0003c;2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>/PD). All four puromycin resistant clones tested had also reactivated VSG221 and one of these clones is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B. Thus, the approach allowed the generation of isogenic strains with active and repressed <italic>VSG221</italic> ESs with unique markers at each end, <italic>PAC</italic> adjacent to the promoter and <italic>VSG221</italic> adjacent to the telomere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). In the experiments described below, the <italic>VSG221</italic>-associated telomere was manipulated in &#x02018;221-repressed&#x02019; strains while &#x02018;221-active&#x02019; strains served as controls when assessing loss of repression.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Inactivating the <italic>VSG221</italic> ES. <bold>(A)</bold> The <italic>VSG221</italic> ES was rendered tetracycline (Tet)-dependent by expressing the Tet-repressor and inserting a Tet-operator immediately downstream of the ES promoter. <italic>PAC</italic>, puromycin <italic>N-</italic>acetylase. <bold>(B)</bold> VSG analysis. western blotting indicates that the modified <italic>VSG221</italic> ES is active in the presence of Tet (1&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml, on). Following Tet removal, cloned survivors were found to have switched to an alternative <italic>VSG(X)</italic> ES (off). <italic>VSG221</italic> could be reactivated (on<sup>2</sup>) in the presence of Tet and puromycin (see Materials and Methods) indicating that repression is reversible. Arrowheads indicate bands representing the abundant VSGs in the coomassie-stained gel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1100f1"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Short telomeres shrink at a diminished rate in telomerase null mutants</title><p>To explore the role of telomeric repeats at a repressed ES we began by engineering a short telomere in telomerase null mutants, where terminal DNA is lost at a rate of &#x0223c;4&#x02009;bp/PD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). To establish these short and shrinking telomeres we disrupted one allele of telomerase, used a telomere-mediated fragmentation (pTMF) construct to seed a telomere with 33 T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub> repeats at the repressed <italic>VSG221</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A) and then disrupted the second allele of telomerase. The TMF construct also integrates an <italic>NPT</italic> reporter adjacent to the telomere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). The reporter is subject to position effect repression but generates sufficient antibiotic resistance to allow recombinant clone selection. Clones 1 and 2, generated by this approach, initially had <italic>VSG221</italic>-associated T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub>-repeat tracts of &#x0223c;800&#x02009;bp and &#x0223c;1.2&#x02009;kbp respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). If the rate of DNA loss remained constant at &#x0223c;4&#x02009;bp/PD, we calculated that clone 1 repeats would be completely lost following 200 PDs (&#x0223c;60 days). We monitored telomere length using a Southern blot assay over a 40-day period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). Repeat loss in clone 2 was only marginally lower than expected but clone 1 lost only &#x0223c;300&#x02009;bp, consistent with an average rate of &#x0003c;2.5&#x02009;bp/PD. The results suggest that the rate of DNA loss may be inversely proportional to telomere-length. This rate of DNA loss is too slow to be explained by the inability of the conventional DNA replication machinery to fully replicate chromosome termini and indicates a telomerase-independent, possibly replication-slippage mechanism for telomeric DNA replication. These findings are entirely consistent with a recent report of telomerase-independent stabilization of short <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomeres (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Telomere-proximal <italic>NPT</italic> reporter repression was maintained in these telomerase null cells with short and shrinking telomeres (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C).
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Telomerase is not required for <italic>VSG</italic>-associated repression. <bold>(A)</bold> A telomere-mediated fragmentation construct, pTMF was used to insert a reporter gene (<italic>NPT</italic>, neomycin phosphotransferase) driven by a <italic>RRNA</italic> promoter (<italic>P<sub>RRNA</sub></italic>) 5&#x02009;kbp from a <italic>de novo</italic> telomere at a repressed ES in telomerase heterozygotes. Transformation using this vector results in deletion of the native telomere and formation of a new telomere by elongation of a (T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub>)<sub>33</sub> &#x02018;seed&#x02019;. <bold>(B)</bold> Following disruption of the second allele of telomerase, Southern blotting indicates the rate of telomere-repeat loss in the telomerase null strains. DNA extracted at ten-day intervals was digested with <italic>Hpa</italic>I, an enzyme that cleaves immediately upstream of <italic>NPT</italic> and 5.1&#x02009;kbp from the telomere, non-telomere junction (asterisk). The arrowheads indicate the expected size if DNA were lost at 4&#x02009;bp/PD. <bold>(C)</bold> Immunofluorescence analysis indicates that the <italic>NPT</italic> reporter remains repressed when adjacent to a short, shrinking telomere. NPT signals are green; blue, DAPI-stained DNA. Scale bar, 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1100f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Telomere cleavage with I-<italic>Sce</italic>I</title><p>Our attempts at complete telomere removal using telomerase disruption were complicated by the diminished rate of DNA loss at a short telomere. We therefore decided to use a different approach involving complete and immediate <italic>in vivo</italic> telomere removal. I-<italic>Sce</italic>I is a site specific double strand homing endonuclease encoded by a mitochondrial group I intron of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). The sequence recognized and cleaved by the enzyme is 18&#x02009;bp in length and is expected to appear only once in every 6.87 &#x000d7; 10<sup>10</sup>&#x02009;bp. This exceeds the size of the <italic>T. brucei</italic> genome by &#x0003e;2000-fold. We introduced an I-<italic>Sce</italic>I cleavage site at the telomere &#x02013; non-telomere junction in the pTMF construct (see asterisk in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). Specific I-<italic>Sce</italic>I cleavage of this construct was verified <italic>in vitro</italic> (data not shown) using recombinant I-<italic>Sce</italic>I (New England BioLabs) and the DNA was targeted to the repressed <italic>VSG221</italic> telomere. The I-<italic>Sce</italic>I ORF was then fused to an SV40 nuclear localization signal and cloned in a Tet-on inducible expression construct (see Materials and Methods). This construct was targeted to a transcriptionally silent locus in cells with the engineered I-<italic>Sce</italic>I site.</p><p>To determine whether I-<italic>Sce</italic>I would cleave the repressed <italic>VSG221</italic>-associated telomere, genomic DNA samples were prepared at a number of time points up to 72&#x02009;h following induced I-<italic>Sce</italic>I expression. The samples were digested with <italic>Hpa</italic>I, which generates a terminal fragment encompassing the <italic>NPT</italic> gene. Southern blotting using an <italic>NPT</italic> probe revealed the expected terminal fragment at <bold>&#x0223c;</bold>7&#x02009;kbp which was diminished in intensity over the time-course of the experiment concomitant with the appearance of the expected 5.1&#x02009;kbp cleavage product (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Significant I-<italic>Sce</italic>I cleavage had occurred only 3&#x02009;h after induction. Importantly, phosphorimager analysis indicated almost complete (&#x0003e;95%) cleavage 24&#x02009;h after induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>B) showing that I-<italic>Sce</italic>I expression was tightly regulated. Thus, I-<italic>Sce</italic>I accesses and specifically cleaves <italic>in vivo</italic> chromatin templates in <italic>T. brucei</italic>. Using inducible I-<italic>Sce</italic>I, endonuclease activity can be rapidly delivered to the entire population of cells in a synchronous manner.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Induction of I-<italic>Sce</italic>I expression results in specific telomere cleavage. Strains with a Tet-inducible copy of I-<italic>Sce</italic>I and a unique I-<italic>Sce</italic>I cleavage site adjacent to the <italic>VSG221</italic> telomere were grown in Tet (1&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml) for three days. DNA samples extracted at various intervals were digested with <italic>Hpa</italic>I (top panel; EtBr, ethidium bromide stain) and analysed by Southern blotting. The map to the left indicates the expected 7&#x02009;kbp terminal fragment and the 5.1&#x02009;kbp, I-<italic>Sce</italic>I cleaved product. The phosphorimager scans to the right (0, 6 and 48&#x02009;h) further illustrate the presence of the expected fragments. Blots hybridized with a control (GeneDB ID: Tb927.7.1690) probe indicate specific cleavage at the I-<italic>Sce</italic>I site. The growth curve below the blots indicates no significant impact on cell growth during the time-course of the experiment. Error bars: one standard deviation. <italic>n</italic> = 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1100f3"/></fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>A damaged chromosome is maintained but loses terminal DNA. Cells with Tet-inducible I-<italic>Sce</italic>I and a unique I-<italic>Sce</italic>I cleavage site adjacent to the <italic>VSG221</italic> telomere were grown in Tet (1&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml) for up to one week. DNA samples extracted at various intervals were digested with <italic>Pst</italic>I (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>C</bold>) or <italic>Hpa</italic>I (top panel in <bold>C</bold>) and analysed by Southern blotting. Data for the plots shown in <bold>B</bold> and <bold>D</bold> were derived by phosphorimager analysis of the blots in Figures 3 and 4A, and 4C respectively. The maps to the left indicate the location of relevant probes and the I-<italic>Sce</italic>I site. <bold>(A)</bold> Location of a T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub>-repeat-like tract is indicated by an open box. <bold>(B)</bold> Inset, VSG analysis in switched cells. Labels and clone derivation as in Figure 1B. Coo, coomassie-stained gel. Arrow, NPT band, not seen in &#x02018;off&#x02019; or &#x02018;on<sup>2</sup>&#x02019; cells. <bold>(C)</bold> Arrowhead indicates 5.1&#x02009;kbp cleavage-product. The chromosome II (GeneDB ID: Tb927.2.2190) and chromosome VI control probes (GeneDB ID: Tb927.6.910) were sequentially hybridized. <bold>(D)</bold> Error bars: one standard deviation. <italic>n</italic> = 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1100f4"/></fig></p><p>A DNA double-strand break (DSB) triggers cell cycle arrest and DNA repair in other cell-types (reviewed in 3). Despite DSBs in &#x0003e;95% of cells, we detected no significant impact on cell growth during the time-course of this experiment which spanned &#x0223c;10 PD or&#x02009;&#x0003e;1000-fold increase in cell number (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Indeed, we saw no evidence for cell cycle arrest or delay following telomere deletion in several independent strains (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>A minority of cells heal the broken chromosome following telomere deletion</title><p>Chromosome healing at a cleaved telomere is very efficient in mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) and terminal G-rich or T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub>-repeat-like sequences can serve as substrates for <italic>de novo</italic> telomere seeding in <italic>T. brucei</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). In addition, telomere-repeat-like sequences adjacent to DSBs act as &#x02018;anti-checkpoints&#x02019; in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> by seeding <italic>de novo</italic> telomeres in the absence of a conventional DNA damage response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>).</p><p>To determine the fate of terminal sequences following telomere deletion, we carried out further Southern analysis with the same samples used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, but now using a restriction enzyme that generates discrete <italic>NPT</italic> and <italic>VSG221</italic> fragments (indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). More than 95% of the <italic>NPT</italic> signal and &#x0223c;90% of the <italic>VSG221</italic> signal is lost after 48&#x02009;h under inducing conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B). Almost complete loss of the <italic>NPT</italic> signal and persistence of a residual and undiminished <italic>VSG221</italic> signal between 48 and 72&#x02009;h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B) suggests significant healing between the <italic>NPT</italic> and <italic>VSG221</italic> genes. The only T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub>-like tract in the <italic>VSG221</italic> ES, that might be expected to serve as a substrate for <italic>de novo</italic> telomere seeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), lies between the <italic>NPT</italic> and <italic>VSG221</italic> genes (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and accession number AJ271641, nt 211&#x02013;322; 46&#x02009;bp of T<sub>1-2</sub>AG<sub>1-6</sub> followed by 10.5 degenerate repeats; T<sub>2</sub>AG G/A G/A/C, 106&#x02009;bp in total). Several independent healing events were mapped (data not shown, see Materials and Methods) and were all found to occur within this tract indicating that the T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub>-like sequence serves as a substrate for <italic>de novo</italic> telomere seeding in &#x0223c;10% of cells. <italic>VSG221</italic> remained reversibly repressed in these &#x02018;healed&#x02019; clones as demonstrated by the emergence of puromycin-resistant cells that also reactivated <italic>VSG221</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B inset). Consistent with loss of the terminal DNA segment, the NPT band is not detected in these reactivated, &#x02018;on<sup>2</sup>&#x02019; cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Progressive loss of sub-telomeric sequences following telomere deletion</title><p>The results described above indicate that only approximately 10% of cells heal the chromosome end between the <italic>NPT</italic> and <italic>VSG221</italic> sequences. Thus, telomere deletion leads to the loss of <italic>NPT</italic> and <italic>VSG221</italic> DNA in the majority of cells. From the data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, we noted that the 5.1&#x02009;kbp terminal fragment from which the telomere had been cleaved became relatively less intense by 12&#x02009;h and also the presence of a &#x02018;smear&#x02019; of smaller <italic>NPT</italic> fragments. This suggested that, rather than being repaired, the DNA may be degraded from the cleaved end by native exonuclease(s). The data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B indicates that telomere deletion is indeed followed by diminishing <italic>NPT</italic> signal which is then followed by diminishing <italic>VSG221</italic> signal. Twelve hours after I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction, for example, &#x0223c;90% of the cells have a cleaved telomere, &#x0223c;50% of cells have lost the <italic>NPT</italic> gene and &#x0223c;20% have lost the <italic>VSG221</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). The relative rates of loss of the <italic>NPT</italic> and <italic>VSG221</italic> signals indicate that DNA is progressively degraded from the DSB. The interval between approximately 50% telomere cleavage (data derived from blot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>) and 50% diminished signals for the <italic>NPT</italic> gene located at 4&#x02009;kbp from the cleavage site is &#x0223c;5&#x02009;h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). Although variable within the population, this roughly translates to a rate of DNA loss at a broken end of 100&#x02009;bp every 7.5&#x02009;min or 6&#x02009;kbp/PD.</p><p>Polycistronic <italic>VSG</italic> ESs extend &#x0223c;50&#x02009;kbp from the promoter to the telomere (see 29) and we predict a length of &#x0223c;65&#x02009;kbp for the <italic>VSG221</italic> expression site following addition of the <italic>NPT</italic> and <italic>PAC</italic> cassettes (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). To facilitate expression monitoring at both ends of the <italic>VSG221</italic> ES (see below), we replaced the promoter-adjacent <italic>PAC</italic> gene (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A) with a red fluorescent protein (<italic>RFP:</italic>)<italic>PAC</italic> fusion gene. Using two independent clones with reversibly repressed <italic>RFP:PAC</italic> and <italic>VSG221</italic> genes, we asked whether progressive DNA loss continues through the ES towards the core of the chromosome following telomere deletion. Both clones were monitored for one week after I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction, equivalent to &#x0003e;20&#x02009;PD or &#x0003e;10<sup>6</sup>-fold increase in cell number. Southern blots showed specific and inducible telomere cleavage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C, top panel). The <italic>VSG221</italic> ES is on chromosome VIa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) and signals for genes within the core of chromosomes VI and II were stable during the course of this analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). <italic>VSG221</italic> and <italic>RFP:PAC</italic> analysis indicated loss of the <italic>VSG221</italic> signal prior to the <italic>RFP:PAC</italic> signal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C and D) and DNA loss consistent with a rate of &#x0223c;6&#x02009;kbp/PD (see above). The analysis confirms that terminally deleted <italic>T. brucei</italic> chromosomes are replicated and segregated without being repaired.</p></sec><sec><title>Telomere deletion leads to loss of sirtuin-dependent repression without ES de-repression</title><p>In bloodstream-form <italic>T. brucei</italic>, ectopic promoters adjacent to telomeres are subject to sirtuin-dependent repression while a sirtuin-independent mechanism maintains <italic>VSG</italic> ES silencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). The <italic>NPT</italic> signal in the <italic>sir2rp1</italic> null strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C) confirmed sirtuin-dependent repression of the current <italic>NPT</italic> reporter but phosphorimager analysis revealed only 5% NPT mRNA in <italic>SIR2rp1</italic>-null mutants relative to the active ES reflecting the quantitatively more significant, sirtuin-independent mode of <italic>VSG</italic> ES silencing.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>The effect of telomere deletion on local gene expression. (<bold>A</bold>) The schematic map of the <italic>VSG221</italic> ES illustrates the reporter genes and the mean extent of DNA loss at different time points following I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction (based on DNA loss at 6&#x02009;kbp/PD). Reporter expression was assessed following I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induced (+Tet) telomere deletion. The <italic>VSG221</italic> ES is permissive for activation under these conditions (see Figure 1). (<bold>B</bold>) Immunofluorescence (NPT, VSG221) and fluorescence (RFP) analysis reveals transient, non-synchronous loss of telomeric silencing (NPT) but otherwise maintained ES repression (VSG221, RFP). Numbers indicate hours following I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction. NPT and VSG signals are green; RFP signals are red; blue, DAPI-stained DNA. Scale bar, 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;m. (<bold>C</bold>) Northern (left-hand side) and western (right-hand side) blot analysis. Numbers indicate hours following I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction. mRNA expression was also analysed in <italic>sir2rp1</italic> null mutants and in cells with an active <italic>VSG221</italic> ES (on). For northern analysis, tubulin (<italic>TUB</italic>) is used as a loading control and for western analysis, an equivalent coomassie (Coo) stained gel is shown as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1100f5"/></fig></p><p>Replication and segregation of a chromosome lacking a telomere provided an opportunity to directly test the impact of the telomere (and potentially other associated factors) on local gene expression. We estimated the mean DNA loss over time following I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction and this is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A. Then, using individual cell, (immuno)fluorescence analysis, we looked for de-repression over a three-day time-course. This analysis revealed transient and non-synchronous de-repression of <italic>NPT</italic> at 6 and 9&#x02009;h but no de-repression of <italic>VSG221</italic> and no de-repression of <italic>RFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B, the fields shown are representative of the population and the results were confirmed with an independent clone). Transient de-repression of <italic>NPT</italic> is consistent with the fact that it is adjacent to a &#x02018;broken&#x02019; end for only a short time before being lost itself (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). These results suggest that the sirtuin effect spreads from within telomeric repeats and that telomere deletion leads to loss of sirtuin-dependent repression. Since transcription from the ES promoter remains repressed following telomere deletion, the results also suggest the absence of any additional repressive effect spreading from the telomere. In fact, despite the longer time frame between telomere deletion and <italic>RFP</italic> loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A), <italic>RFP</italic> de-repression is not seen at any point during progressive loss of ES sequences. This suggests that the <italic>VSG</italic> and associated sequences are also not required for maintained ES silencing.</p><p>Maintained silencing of <italic>RFP</italic> and <italic>VSG221</italic> was confirmed by northern blotting with RNA extracted at a number of time points following I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C). Although the low-abundance <italic>NPT</italic> mRNA is not detected by northern blot following I-<italic>Sce</italic>I induction, we were able to confirm NPT de-repression by western blot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C). The results are consistent with sirtuin-dependent telomeric gene silencing but suggest that ES silencing is sirtuin and telomere-independent.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>We removed a <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomere <italic>in vivo</italic> to explore its role in gene repression and in protecting the chromosome end from endonucleolytic degradation and the DDR. Initially, we demonstrated terminal DNA loss at &#x0003c;2.5&#x02009;bp/PD in telomerase null strains, consistent with a recent report showing that short <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomeres are stabilized in a telomerase-independent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Telomere removal was then achieved using meganuclease cleavage, and subsequent experiments using unique sub-terminal reporters indicated telomere-dependent gene-repression and telomere-dependent protection of adjacent DNA from rapid degradation. Telomere deletion has little impact on <italic>VSG</italic> ES silencing however and, surprisingly, does not trigger a DDR in <italic>T. brucei</italic>.</p><p>Telomeres provide substrates for telomerase and are essential for maintaining chromosome stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). Whereas <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomerase null strains lose telomeric DNA at a rate of &#x0223c;4&#x02009;bp/PD or less, a broken chromosome end progressively loses terminal DNA at a rate averaging 6000&#x02009;bp/PD. This &#x0003e;1000-fold higher rate of DNA-loss at an uncapped chromosome end illustrates the protective effect of T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub> repeats, even in the absence of telomerase. The data reveal nucleolytic activity that is normally excluded from the chromosome end, likely due to the formation of t-loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>) stabilized by telomere-associated factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Loss of these structures exposes substrates for nucleolytic degradation.</p><p>The two major pathways of DNA repair are non-homologous end-joining (NHEJ) and homologous recombination (HR). Single-celled organisms rely more heavily on HR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) and, in haploid yeast, sub-telomeric DSB-repair more commonly involves HR while NHEJ efficiency correlates with distance from the chromosome end (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Trypanosomatid genome sequence analysis revealed components of most repair pathways and also a number of NHEJ components although H2AX is notably absent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Many DNA repair factors are associated with telomeres (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) and this also appears to be the case in <italic>T. brucei</italic> where the Ku70/80 heterodimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>) and a sirtuin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) have been shown to influence telomere extension and silencing respectively. <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> cells lacking RAD51 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), Mre11 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) or the sirtuin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) do not display delay in progression through the cell cycle but they are all more sensitive to DNA damage induced by ionizing radiation or radiomimetic drugs.</p><p>In striking contrast to the situation in most other eukaryotes, a terminally truncated and un-repaired <italic>T. brucei</italic> chromosome is maintained and segregated with no significant impact on growth. In other proliferating cells, DSBs induce a DDR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). In <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, for example, chromosome ends with either few or no telomeric repeats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), and even a DSB in a dispensable plasmid, trigger cell-cycle arrest and DNA repair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). Some cells do recover but go on to lose the affected chromosome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). Similarly, only fused or repaired chromosomes are recovered when a DSB is introduced near a telomere in mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). The absence of a conventional telomere checkpoint and consequent failure to repair a truncated chromosome may eventually lead to chromosome loss and cell death. Although a large body of evidence suggests that telomere loss elicits the same response as a DSB elsewhere in the genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>), it has been proposed that the telomere checkpoint is distinct from the DNA damage checkpoint in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). In addition, terminally truncated telomeres can be protected in a sequence-independent manner in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). Thus, I-<italic>Sce</italic>I-cleaved <italic>T. brucei</italic> telomeres may recruit or retain factors that protect the terminus from the DDR. It will be important to introduce DSBs elsewhere in the <italic>T. brucei</italic> genome to assess how the DDR machinery responds to damage elsewhere.</p><p>Our data show that, before being lost, a reporter 5&#x02009;kbp from the deleted telomere is de-repressed and this provides direct evidence for telomere-dependent gene repression in <italic>T. brucei</italic>. We show that this same reporter is subject to sirtuin-dependent silencing. In <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, telomeric silencing is dependent upon recruitment of a histone deacetylase, sirtuin-complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) and we speculate that it is the sirtuin effect that is lost along with the telomere in <italic>T. brucei</italic>. Our results suggest however that <italic>VSG</italic> ES silencing, which relies upon transcription attenuation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>), is not only sirtuin-independent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) but is also telomere-independent. Thus, telomeric repression and ES silencing appear to be mechanistically distinct.</p><p>Although telomeres are not required to maintain ES silencing, they do repress genes in the vicinity of the <italic>VSG</italic> so that they may act in a cooperative manner to fully silence the large <italic>VSG</italic> repertoire. This includes the monocistronic, &#x02018;metacyclic&#x02019; <italic>VSG</italic> ESs that are transcribed from promoters in close proximity to the telomere during the first week of a mammalian infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). In addition, we cannot rule out a role for the telomere in establishment of ES silencing since telomere deletion may not reverse telomere-mediated DNA or chromatin modification, for example. The telomere may also play a role in active ES transcription and/or recombination.</p><p><italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> telomeres protect chromosome ends from degradation and repress local gene expression but appear to have little impact on ES silencing or chromosome segregation and fail to trigger a DDR when deleted. Using meganuclease manipulation, it should now be possible to examine the consequences that follow active ES deletion and the introduction of DSBs at non-telomeric loci.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Bernard Dujon (Pasteur Institute, Paris) for the I-<italic>Sce</italic>I plasmid, pSCM525, Gloria Rudenko (Oxford, UK) for the BAC (TBH25N7) and John Kelly (LSHTM) for critical reading of the manuscript. This work was supported by a Research Career Development Fellowship to DH (052323) and a Project Grant (069909), both from The Wellcome Trust.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandell</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakian</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of a yeast telomere: arrest, recovery, and chromosome loss</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1993</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8242745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>d'Adda di Fagagna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional links between telomeres and proteins of the DNA-damage response</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1781</fpage><lpage>1799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surviving the Breakup: The DNA damage checkpoint</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Genet</source><year>2006</year><comment>In press: doi:10.1146/annurev.genet.1140.051206.105231.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Umezu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Saccharomyces</italic> Ku70, mre11/rad50 and RPA proteins regulate adaptation to G<sub>2</sub>/M arrest after DNA damage</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9708741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dynek</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resolution of sister telomere association is required for progression through mitosis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>304</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15064417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grunstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast heterochromatin: regulation of its assembly and inheritance by histones</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9590166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundblad</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telomere identity crisis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2522</fpage><lpage>2525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16264188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The central roles of telomeres and subtelomeres in antigenic variation in African trypanosomes</article-title><source>Chromosome Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16132817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alsford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Isamah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sirtuin in the African trypanosome is involved in both DNA repair and telomeric gene silencing but is not required for antigenic variation</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><comment>In press, doi:10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05553.x.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repression of polymerase I-mediated gene expression at <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> telomeres</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16311518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dreesen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telomere structure and shortening in telomerase-deficient <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>4536</fpage><lpage>4543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16091631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Lange</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shelterin: the protein complex that shapes and safeguards human telomeres</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2100</fpage><lpage>2110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trypanosome telomeres are protected by a homologue of mammalian TRF2</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>5011</fpage><lpage>5021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15923618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munoz-Jordan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lange</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>t-loops at trypanosome telomeres</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dreesen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telomerase-independent stabilization of short telomeres in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>4911</fpage><lpage>4919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16782879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telomere maintenance and length regulation in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2332</fpage><lpage>2339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10811624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginger</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why are parasite contingency genes often associated with telomeres?</article-title><source>Int. J. Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12547344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic manipulation indicates that ARD1 is an essential N-acetyltransferase in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Biochem. Parasitol</source><year>2000</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alsford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tagging a <italic>T. brucei RRNA</italic> locus improves stable transfection efficiency and circumvents inducible expression position effects</article-title><source>Mol. Biochem. Parasitol</source><year>2005</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16182389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alibu</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A doubly inducible system for RNA interference and rapid RNAi plasmid construction in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Biochem. Parasitol</source><year>2005</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15610821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zomerdijk</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouellette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>ten Asbroek</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieft</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bommer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The promoter for a variant surface glycoprotein gene expression site in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2791</fpage><lpage>2801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1697265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berriman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheader</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bringaud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Isobe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Corton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The architecture of variant surface glycoprotein gene expression sites in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Biochem. Parasitol</source><year>2002</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12106867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melville</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Leech</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular karyotype of the megabase chromosomes of <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> stock 427</article-title><source>Mol. Biochem. Parasitol</source><year>2000</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Saenger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis of gene regulation by the tetracycline inducible Tet repressor-operator system</article-title><source>Nat. Struct. Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10700280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheader</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Minchin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gull</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudenko</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variant surface glycoprotein RNA interference triggers a precytokinesis cell cycle arrest in African trypanosomes</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>8716</fpage><lpage>8721</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15937117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colleaux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Auriol</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Galibert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dujon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition and cleavage site of the intron-encoded omega transposase</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1988</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>6022</fpage><lpage>6026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2842757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprung</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murnane</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosome healing in mouse embryonic stem cells</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>6781</fpage><lpage>6786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10359789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michelson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A telomeric repeat sequence adjacent to a DNA double-stranded break produces an anticheckpoint</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2546</fpage><lpage>2559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16230525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitcheson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Byles</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickstead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudenko</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of the repertoire of <italic>VSG</italic> expression site containing telomeres of <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> 427 using transformation-associated recombination in yeast</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2319</fpage><lpage>2329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Krejci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Komen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehorn</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rad51 recombinase and recombination mediators</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>42729</fpage><lpage>42732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12912992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ricchetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dujon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairhead</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distance from the chromosome end determines the efficiency of double strand break repair in subtelomeres of haploid yeast</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12729759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Sayed</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Myler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartholomeu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghedin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Worthey</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Delcher</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Blandin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome sequence of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>, etiologic agent of Chagas disease</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16020725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginger</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Browitt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ku is important for telomere maintenance, but not for differential expression of telomeric <italic>VSG</italic> genes, in African trypanosomes</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>21269</fpage><lpage>21277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11919193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreesen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telomere length regulation and transcriptional silencing in KU80-deficient <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>6575</fpage><lpage>6584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15602000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for RAD51 and homologous recombination in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> antigenic variation</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2875</fpage><lpage>2888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10557214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Proudfoot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct roles for two RAD51-related genes in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> antigenic variation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>6906</fpage><lpage>6919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16326865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Browitt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of Mre11 does not affect <italic>VSG</italic> gene duplication mediated by homologous recombination in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>26185</fpage><lpage>26193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> MRE11 is non-essential but influences growth, homologous recombination and DNA double-strand break repair</article-title><source>Mol. Biochem. Parasitol</source><year>2002</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12467970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>d'Adda di Fagagna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reaper</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clay-Farrace</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiegler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Zglinicki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saretzki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A DNA damage checkpoint response in telomere-initiated senescence</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>426</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14608368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Resnick</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lethality induced by a single site-specific double-strand break in a dispensable yeast plasmid</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1993</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>5613</fpage><lpage>5617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8516308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprung</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouladi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricoul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Murnane</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosome instability as a result of double-strand breaks near telomeres in mouse embryonic stem cells</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4836</fpage><lpage>4850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Glowczewski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEC3, MEC1, and DDC2 are essential components of a telomere checkpoint pathway required for cell cycle arrest during senescence in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2626</fpage><lpage>2638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12181334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oikemus</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Queiroz-Machado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunkel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodsky</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic telomere protection by <italic>Drosophila</italic> DNA damage response pathways</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>71</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanhamme</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Poelvoorde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pays</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tebabi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Xong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pays</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential RNA elongation controls the variant surface glycoprotein gene expression sites of <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10792720</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
