<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14707119</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1887729</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20030851</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20030851</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Definitive Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bone Marrow Allograft Rejection Mediated by a Novel Murine NK Receptor, NKG2I</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>Junzo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wakao</surname><given-names>Hiroshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishizuka</surname><given-names>Yuko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Taka-aki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamaoki</surname><given-names>Masaru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>Ken-ichiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koseki</surname><given-names>Haruhiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>Toshinori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>Masaru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Department of Molecular Immunology, Graduate School of Medicine, Chiba University, Chiba City, Chiba 260-8670, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Department of Medical Immunology, Graduate School of Medicine, Chiba University, Chiba City, Chiba 260-8670, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>Institute of Physical and Chemical Research, Research Center for Allergy and Immunology, Yokohama City, Kanagawa 230-0045, Japan</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>Department of Diagnostics, YAMASA Corporation, Choshi, Chiba 288-0056, Japan</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>PRESTO, Japan Science and Technology Corporation, Saitama 332-0012, Japan</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Masaru Taniguchi, Dept. of Molecular Immunology, Graduate School of Medicine, Chiba University, 1-8-1 Inohana, Chuoku, Chiba City, Chiba 260-8670, Japan. Phone: 81-43-226-2184; Fax: 81-43-227-1498; email: <email>taniguti@med.m.chiba-u.ac.jp</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>199</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Natural killer (NK) cells mediate bone marrow allograft rejection. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying such a rejection remain elusive. In previous analyses, it has been shown that NK cells recognize allogeneic target cells through Ly-49s and CD94/NKG2 heterodimers. Here, we describe identification and characterization of a novel murine NK receptor, NKG2I, belonging to the NKG2 family. NKG2I, which was composed of 226 amino acids, showed &#x0223c;40% homology to the murine NKG2D and CD94 in the C-type lectin domain. Flow cytometric analysis with anti-NKG2I monoclonal antibody (mAb) revealed that expression of NKG2I was largely confined to NK and NKT cells, but was not seen in T cells. Furthermore, anti-NKG2I mAb inhibited NK cell&#x02013;mediated cytotoxicity, whereas cross-linking of NKG2I enhanced interleukin 2&#x02013; and interleukin 12&#x02013;dependent interferon-&#x003b3; production. Similarly, the injection of anti-NKG2I mAb before the allogeneic bone marrow transfer in vivo impinged on the function of NKG2I, resulting in the enhanced colony formation in the spleen. NKG2I is a novel activating receptor mediating recognition and rejection of allogeneic target cells.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>C-type lectin family</kwd><kwd>NK cells</kwd><kwd>activating receptor</kwd><kwd>IFN-&#x003b3;</kwd><kwd>NKT cells</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>The online version of this article includes supplemental material.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>NK cells act as a first line of defense in innate immunity and also mediate rejection of allogeneic target cells, such as BM allografts (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). NK cell function is exquisitely controlled by the orchestration of signals from stimulatory and inhibitory NK receptors, which recognize MHC class I&#x02013;related molecules on target cells (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). NK receptors have been categorized into three groups based on their structural and sequence homology. The first is the killer cell inhibitory receptors, belonging to the Ig superfamily, which are expressed in humans but not in rodents (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The second group is the C-type lectinlike Ly-49 receptors present solely in rodents (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The third is the lectinlike homo- and heterodimer receptors, consisting of CD94 and a member of NKG2 family; they are observed both in humans and in rodents (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Killer cell inhibitory receptors and Ly-49s recognize classical MHC class I molecules, whereas NKG2 family receptors bind nonclassical MHC class I molecules (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p><p>Regarding the role of NK receptors in NK cell&#x02013;mediated allorejection, involvement of the NK receptors, such as CD94 and Ly-49, has been reported. Blocking the function of CD94 with anti-CD94 mAb enhances the in vitro cytotoxicity of C57BL/6 NK cells against BALB/c Con A lymphoblast target cells (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), implying that CD94, most likely together with NKG2A, may recognize the Qa-1 on the target cells. In addition, anti&#x02013;Ly-49D mAb treatment results in eradication of a Ly-49D<sup>+</sup> subset in lethally irradiated C57BL/6 mice that, in turn, abrogates the ability to reject H-2D<sup>d</sup> BM graft (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). In the present paper, we report identification and characterization of a novel murine NKG2 family receptor, NKG2I. We show that NKG2I acts as an activating receptor and mediates allorecognition and subsequent cytotoxic activity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals.</title><p>C57BL/6, BALB/c, C3H/HeN, ICR nu/nu mice, and Fisher rats were obtained from Charles River Laboratories. DBA/2Cr, AKR/N, (BALB/c &#x000d7; C57BL/6) F1, and 129/svJ mice were obtained from SLC and Jackson Laboratory, respectively. All experiments were performed in accordance with our institutional guidelines.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of NKG2I through the Library Subtraction.</title><p>PCR-Select cDNA subtraction kit (CLONTECH Laboratories, Inc.) was used to generate a library enriched for genes expressed in NKT cells over T cells. In brief, T cells were purified from the spleen of J&#x003b1;281 knockout mice (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), and NKT cells were purified by FACSVantage&#x02122; cell sorter (Becton Dickinson) with &#x003b1;-galactosylceramide/CD1-d tetramer staining from the spleen of C57BL/6 mice. Purity of sorted cells was estimated to be &#x0003e;98%. In subtraction, T cell cDNA was used as a tester, whereas that of NKT cells was used as a driver. After subtraction, 1,000 clones were sequenced and analyzed by virtual Northern blot analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Generation of Anti-NKG2I Monoclonal Antibodies.</title><p>Fisher rats were injected with a fusion protein consisting of the extracellular portion of NKG2I and the Fc region of the human immunoglobulin. Spleen cells were fused to the SP2/O-Ag14 fusion partner. Hybridoma supernatants were screened for the staining ability of NKG2I-transfected COS7 cells by flow cytometric analysis. Five clones were established as follows: 3G7 (IgG1/&#x003ba;), 5C6 (IgG1/&#x003ba;), 7E8 (IgG2a/&#x003ba;), 9D5 (IgG2a/&#x003ba;), and 9F2 (IgG2a/&#x003ba;). The mAbs were purified from ascites with protein G&#x02013;Sepharose 4B and conjugated with biotin, FITC, and Cy5 with commercial kits.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibodies and cDNA.</title><p>Anti-NKG2D antibody, murine CD94, NKG2C, E, D, DAP12, and DAP10 cDNA were provided by D.H. Raulet (University of California, Berkeley, Berkeley, CA). All other antibodies were obtained from BD Biosciences.</p></sec><sec><title>NK Cell Preparation and Stimulation by Anti-NKG2I mAb.</title><p>Splenic NK cells were enriched with anti-DX5 Ab using the AutoMACS&#x02122; (Miltenyi Biotec). For stimulation experiments, NK cells were further purified as NK1.1<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells to &#x0003e;90% by depleting CD4<sup>+</sup>, CD8<sup>+</sup>, CD3<sup>+</sup>, Gr-1<sup>+</sup>, Ter-119<sup>+</sup>, and CD19<sup>+</sup> cells. NK cells (10<sup>5</sup> cells/well) were incubated for 24 h with or without IL-2 and IL-12 in 96-well plates precoated with 10 &#x003bc;g/ml of mAb, and the concentration of IFN-&#x003b3; was measured by ELISA.</p></sec><sec><title>Cytotoxic Assay against Con A Lymphoblasts.</title><p>Con A lymphoblasts were generated by stimulation of spleen cells with 2 &#x003bc;g/ml Con A (Sigma-Aldrich) for 48 h. Cytotoxic activities of IL-2&#x02013;expanded NK cells (cultured for 1 wk) against Con A lymphoblasts were measured by a standard <sup>51</sup>Cr release assay. The specific lysis was calculated as follows: percent-specific lysis = <sup>51</sup>Cr cpm [(experimental release &#x02212; spontaneous release)/(maximum release &#x02212; spontaneous release)] &#x000d7; 100.</p></sec><sec><title>Biochemistry.</title><p>IL-2&#x02013;expanded NK cells were surface labeled with <sup>125</sup>I (Amersham Biosciences) using lactoperoxidase and lysed with buffer (1% NP-40, 50 mM Tris, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, and the protease inhibitor cocktail). The cell lysates were incubated with the 7E8-coated protein G&#x02013;Sepharose 4 FF (Amersham Biosciences) and washed extensively. The samples were separated on an SDS-PAGE, and bands were visualized using the Bio Image Analyser (model BAS2500; Fuji Film).</p></sec><sec><title>Assay for BM Engraftment.</title><p>Recipient C57BL/6 or (BALB/c &#x000d7; C57BL/6) F1 mice irradiated at 9.5 Gy were received intravenously with BALB/c or C57BL/6 BM cells. Spleen was removed and fixed with the Bouin's fixative on day 8, and the colony number was counted.</p></sec><sec><title>GenBank Accession No.</title><p>The NKG2I sequence has been deposited in GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ under accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF306663">AF306663</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>Online Supplemental Material.</title><p>Table S1 summarizes the results of cDNA subtraction (NKT vs. T cells), and Figs. S1 and S2 show the control experiments using anti&#x02013;asialo GM1 and anti-NKG2I. Online supplemental material is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20030851/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20030851/DC1</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>A Novel NK Receptor Belonging to NKG2 Family.</title><p>NKG2I was originally identified as a gene expressed preferentially in NKT cells over T cells by subtractive hybridization. Analysis of subtracted cDNA revealed that NK receptors, such as NKG2A/B, NKRP1-C, and NKG2D, were preferentially expressed in NKT cells (Table S1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20030851/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20030851/DC1</ext-link>). A novel clone, preferentially expressed in NK and NKT cells, showed an extensive homology to the NK receptors and was subjected to further analysis (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> A).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Preferential expression of NKG2I in NK and NKT cells over T cells. NKG2I expression was assessed by RT-PCR. &#x003b2;-actin serves as input cDNA control. Threefold serial dilution of cDNA was used.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20030851f1"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Characterization of NKG2I. (A) Alignment of the murine NKG2 family NK receptors and human CD94. The amino acid sequences of the murine NKG2 family receptors and human CD94 are aligned using the ClustalW algorithm. Highly conserved residues are displayed in the dark shaded boxes and depicted as consensus amino acids below the alignment. Similar amino acids are shown in light shaded boxes and are indicated with dots. The dotted line indicates the predicted transmembrane region using the TMpred program in EMBnet (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org">http://www.ch.embnet.org</ext-link>). The squares indicate the putative ligand-binding site based on the crystal structure of the human CD94. The arrowheads show the hydrophobic residues responsible for dimerization. The closed circles indicate the cysteins involved in inter- and/or intramolecular disulfide bonding. The asterisks exhibit the positively charged amino acids in the cytoplasmic domain. (B) Genomic map of the murine NK gene complex. The map is presented schematically based on the mouse genome sequence from the National Center for Biotechnology Information. The relative location of the NKG2I is indicated by the arrow.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20030851f2"/></fig><p>Putative proteins deduced from the nucleotide sequence consisted of 226 amino acids with four structural domains as follows: cytoplasmic (1-68), transmembrane (69-93), stalk (94-109), and C-type lectin domain (CTLD; 110-226) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A). Sequence comparison indicated that NKG2I was a novel NK receptor belonging to the NKG2 family. In fact, the CTLD within NKG2I showed &#x0223c;40% homology to that of murine NKG2D and CD94. Moreover, the residues in NKG2I, which may be engaged in disulfide bond formation (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A, closed circles) and in receptor dimerization (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A, closed circles and arrowheads), are readily inferred from the crystal structures of CD94 and NKG2D (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). These data suggest that the CTLD in NKG2I possesses a higher order structure similar to CD94 and NKG2D. Nevertheless, NKG2I lacks any signaling motifs and positively charged amino acids in its putative transmembrane region, which are required for association with adaptor molecules such as Fc&#x0025b;RI&#x003b3;, CD3&#x003b6;, DAP10, and DAP12 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A; references <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>Ligands for other members of the murine NKG2 receptors are MHC class I&#x02013;related molecules as follows: Qa-1 for CD94/NKG2 heterodimers (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) and Raes, H60, and MULT1 for NKG2D homodimers (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). As NKG2I exhibits little similarity in a putative ligand binding domain to other NK receptors (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A, squares), it may recognize ligands distinct from those aforementioned (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). An abundance of positively charged amino acids in the cytoplasmic domain of NKG2I points to the possibility that it may associate with novel adaptors responsible for signal transduction (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A, asterisks).</p><p>DNA sequence analysis of NKG2I in the National Center for Biotechnology Information mouse genome database revealed that NKG2I maps adjacent to the CD94/NKG2 gene cluster and between CD69 and CD94 in NK receptor gene complex on murine chromosome 6 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B). Curiously, no human orthologue of NKG2I was found, suggesting that this receptor may be unique to rodents.</p></sec><sec><title>Characterization of NKG2I by the mAbs.</title><p>To characterize NKG2I, we established several mAbs specific for NKG2I (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> A). These mAbs stained NKG2I-transfected COS7 cells specifically, and did not cross react with CD94, NKG2A/C/E, or NKG2D molecules (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> A). Staining with 3G7 mAb revealed that most NK (NK1.1<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) cells in the spleen (84%), BM (74%), and liver (77%) expressed NKG2I (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B). NKG2I was also expressed on a subset of NKT (NK1.1<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup>) cells, the expression levels of which varied significantly among tissues (ranging from 13 to 54%), but was barely detected on T (NK1.1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup>) cells (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Characterization of anti-NKG2I monoclonal antibodies. (A) Establishment of the mAbs against NKG2I. COS7 cells were transiently transfected with mock, NKG2I, murine CD94, NKG2A/C with CD94, NKG2E with DAP12, and NKG2D with DAP10 cDNA expression vector. Cells were harvested 48 h later and incubated with the biotin-conjugated 3G7, 5C6, 7E8, 9D5, 9F2, or control rat IgG, followed by staining with the FITC-streptavidin (thick histogram). For CD94, NKG2A/C/E, and NKG2D transfectants, cells were incubated with the biotin-conjugated anti-CD94 mAb or with the anti-NKG2A/C/E or anti-NKG2D mAb as positive control (P, thick histogram). Background staining is shown as thin histograms. (B) Expression of NKG2I in the various lymphoid subsets. Spleen, liver mononuclear cells, thymocytes, and BM cells from C57BL/6 mice were stained with the FITC&#x02013;anti-NKG2I (3G7), PE-NK1.1, and Cy5&#x02013;anti-CD3. The expression of NKG2I in the gated lymphoid subsets for NK (NK1.1<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>&#x02212;</sup>), NKT (NK1.1<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup>), or T (NK1.1<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup>) cells is shown as histogram (thick lines) overlaid with the background staining (thin lines). The percentage of NKG2I<sup>+</sup> cells in each lymphoid subset is shown. (C) Expression of the NKG2I, CD94, and NKG2A/C/E in the various strains of mice. Spleen cells from the different mouse strains were stained with PE-DX5 together with biotin&#x02013;anti-NKG2I (3G7), anti-CD94, or anti-NKG2A/C/E mAb followed by FITC-streptavidin. Percentage of cells in each subset is shown. (D) NKG2I exists as a dimer with the disulfide bond. C57BL/6 NK cells expanded with IL-2 were surface labeled with <sup>125</sup>I and immunoprecipitated with the anti-NKG2I mAb (7E8) or rat IgG2a. Immunoprecipitated proteins were separated on an SDS-PAGE under nonreducing (in the absence of 2-mercaptoethanol [&#x02212;2ME]) or reducing (in the presence of 2-mercaptoethanol [+2ME]) conditions, and visualized with BAS2500.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20030851f3"/></fig><p>Because the expression of NKG2 varies depending on mouse strains (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), we examined whether this is also the case for NKG2I. Flow cytometric analysis showed that NKG2I as well as CD94 and NKG2A/C/E expressions were found regardless of strains (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> C, C57BL/6, BALB/c, C3H/HeN, DBA/2Cr, AKR/N, and 129/svJ). However, the expression level of NKG2I differed among the strains, implying the &#x0201c;calibration&#x0201d; of this receptor (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Moreover, the cDNA sequence for NKG2I from these strains revealed that they encoded an identical amino acid, suggesting that NKG2I is an invariant molecule on NK cells and exhibits an expression profile distinct from that of Ly-49s, which carry allelic polymorphisms (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p><p>Biochemical analysis with <sup>125</sup>I-labeled NK cells followed by immunoprecipitation with anti-NKG2I mAb (7E8) revealed that NKG2I migrated predominantly as a &#x0223c;96-kD protein under nonreducing conditions, whereas a prominent &#x0223c;48-kD band emerged under reducing conditions on an SDS-PAGE (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> D, arrowheads). This suggests that NKG2I forms homo- or heterodimer-like other NKG2 family members (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Because its predicted molecular weight is 26,265, it is conceivable that NKG2I is covalently modified, though its precise nature has yet to be examined.</p></sec><sec><title>NKG2I Acts as an Activating Receptor in Allorejection.</title><p>Given that NKG2I is expressed predominantly in NK cells (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B) and that CD94, which is quite similar to NKG2I, is implicated in recognition of allogeneic target cells (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), we hypothesized that NKG2I also plays a role in NK cell&#x02013;mediated allorecognition and subsequent cytotoxic activity. Because activating signals elicited from NK receptors often lead to cytokine production and/or activation of cytotoxicity (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), the function of NKG2I was assessed by measuring IFN-&#x003b3; production (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A). Cross-linking of NKG2I with 3G7 mAb led to induction of IFN-&#x003b3; in the presence of either IL-2 or IL-12 in a cytokine dose-dependent manner and their synergistic effects were observed (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A, right). These results indicate that NKG2I cross-linking enhances the extent of IL-2&#x02013; and IL-12&#x02013;elicited signaling leading to IFN-&#x003b3; production. Thus, NKG2I may serve as an activating NK receptor.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>NKG2I functions as an activating NK receptor in allograft rejection. (A) IFN-&#x003b3; production upon cross-linking of NKG2I in NK cells. NK cells from C57BL/6 spleen were incubated in the presence of IL-2, IL-12, or IL-2/IL-12 in the plate immobilized with 3G7 or rat IgG1. Control experiments were done without any antibody. The concentrations of IFN-&#x003b3; in the culture supernatant are shown. Data are indicated as mean &#x000b1; SD from three independent experiments. (B) 3G7 mAb inhibits the cytotoxicity of NK cells against the allogeneic target cells. The cytolytic activity of C57BL/6 NK cells expanded with IL-2 was determined in the presence of 10 &#x003bc;g/ml of 3G7 mAb or control rat IgG1. Control experiments were done without any antibody. Con A lymphoblasts prepared from BALB/c (left) or C57BL/6 (right) mice were used as target cells. Data are shown as mean &#x000b1; SD from three independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 6/experiment). *, P &#x0003c; 0.05 as compared 3G7 mAb versus rat IgG1 at the indicated E/T ratio. (C) Blocking the NKG2I function compromises rejection of the allogeneic BM cell transplantation. Responder C57BL/6 or (BALB/c &#x000d7; C57BL/6) F1 mice were treated with 100 &#x003bc;g of 3G7 mAb or rat IgG before BM transplantation with 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells (for C57BL/6 recipients) or 0.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells (for F1 recipients) from BALB/c or C57BL/6, and received the same amount of each of the Abs on days 3 and 6. The number of colonies in the spleen of the recipient mice (<italic>n</italic> = 5) was counted 8 d after BM transfer. The error bars represent the standard deviation, and representative data from three independent experiments are shown. (D) Blocking the function of NKG2I does not interfere with the expression of other NK receptors. The effect of 3G7 mAb on the expression of other NK receptors relevant to the allorejection was evaluated by flow cytometric analysis on NK cells. C57BL/6 mice were left untreated (top) or treated with 100 &#x003bc;g/body of 3G7 (bottom) for 1 h. NK (NK1.1<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) cells were stained with the biotin&#x02013;anti-NKG2I (7E8), biotin&#x02013;anti-CD94, biotin&#x02013;anti-NKG2A/C/E, biotin&#x02013;anti-Ly49A, biotin&#x02013;anti-Ly49C/I, or FITC&#x02013;anti-Ly49D, respectively. Biotin-conjugated Ab was visualized with FITC-streptavidin. Expression of each NK receptor is shown as histogram (thick lines) overlaid with background staining (thin lines).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20030851f4"/></fig><p>We explored the function of NKG2I through an in vitro cytolytic assay with 3G7 mAb (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B). C57BL/6 NK cells lysed allogeneic BALB/c but not syngeneic C57BL/6 Con A lymphoblast target cells (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B). In contrast, treatment of C57BL/6 NK cells with 3G7 mAb inhibited cytolytic activity against BALB/c target cells significantly, whereas control Ab showed little effect (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B, left).</p><p>Allogeneic BM cell transplantation experiments further confirmed these results (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C). BALB/c BM cells administrated into lethally irradiated C57BL/6 mice (BALB/c into C57BL/6) were rejected in a manner dependent on NK cells, and no colony derived from the transplanted cells appeared in the spleen of recipient mice as reported (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C, left; reference <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In contrast, administration of 3G7 mAb but not the control anti&#x02013;rat IgG Ab into the recipient C57BL/6 mice before BALB/c BM transfer suppressed the rejection of BALB/c BM grafts and resulted in a significant number of colony formations in the spleen (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C, left). Similarly, (BALB/c &#x000d7; C57BL/6) F1 mice as a recipient, whose T cells are tolerant to the parent BALB/c, showed significantly impaired rejection of BALB/c BM cells (BALB/c into F1) in the presence of 3G7 mAb (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C, middle). In contrast, no effects were observed in the syngeneic BM transplantation (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C, right, C57BL/6 into C57BL/6). These results indicate that NKG2I on NK cells recognizes putative ligands present on allogeneic BM cells and induces signals leading to the rejection of allografts.</p><p>It should be mentioned that administration of anti-NK1.1, anti&#x02013;asialo GM1, or anti&#x02013;Ly-49D mAb also abrogated the rejection of allogeneic BM grafts (Fig. S1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20030851/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20030851/DC1</ext-link>), but these effects were primarily due to the depletion of NK cells expressing these molecules (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). On the other hand, 3G7 mAb treatment did not change the number of NK cells in vivo (Fig. S2, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20030851/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20030851/DC1</ext-link>). More importantly, 3G7 mAb treatment did not alter the expression of other NK receptors, such as CD94, NKG2A/C/E, Ly-49A, Ly-49C/I, and Ly-49D, under the conditions that NKG2I expression was rapidly down-regulated in vivo (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> D). These results suggest that allogeneic recognition and subsequent activation of NK cells leading to cytotoxic activity against allogeneic BM cells is attributed to NKG2I but not to modulation of other NK receptor expression.</p><p>In summary, we have identified and characterized a novel activating NK receptor that plays a crucial role in allograft rejection. Identification of the cognate ligands and elucidation of the signaling pathway of NKG2I will shed light on mechanisms underlying allogeneic recognition and rejection.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Dr. D.H. Raulet for CD94, NKG2C, E, D, DAP12, and DAP10 cDNA and anti-NKG2D mAb; Ms. H. Tanabe for preparation; and Mr. R. Triendl and Ms. N.M. Maeshima for critical reading.</p><p>This work was supported by grants from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan as follows: C13218016 (to T. Nakayama), A13307011 (to M. Taniguchi), B14370107 (to T. Nakayama), and C12670293 (to T. Nakayama). This work was also supported by the Special Coordination Funds for Promoting Science and Technology (to T. Nakayama); the Program for Promotion of Fundamental Studies in Health Sciences of the Organization for Pharmaceutical Safety and Research of the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare (to M. Taniguchi); and by the Human Frontier Science Program Research grant RG00168/2000-M206 (to M. Taniguchi). J. Koike is recipient of a Research Fellowships of the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science for Young Scientists (0000147313).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Murphy, W.J., V. Kumar, and M. Bennett. <year>1987</year>. Rejection of bone marrow allografts by mice with severe combined immune deficiency (SCID). Evidence that natural killer cells can mediate the specificity of marrow graft rejection. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>165</volume>:<fpage>1212</fpage>&#x02013;1217.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3549961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Trinchieri, G. <year>1989</year>. Biology of natural killer cells. <source>Adv. Immunol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;376.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2683611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lanier, L.L. <year>1998</year>. NK cell receptors. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;393.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9597134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yokoyama, W.M. <year>1998</year>. Natural killer cell receptors. <source>Curr. Opin. Immunol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>&#x02013;305.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9638366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Colonna, M. <year>1997</year>. Specificity and function of immunoglobulin superfamily NK cell inhibitory and stimulatory receptors. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source>
<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;133.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9059888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Moretta, A., R. Biassoni, C. Bottino, D. Pende, M. Vitale, A. Poggi, M.C. Mingari, and L. Moretta. <year>1997</year>. Major histocompatibility complex class I-specific receptors on human natural killer and T lymphocytes. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source>
<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;117.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9059886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Raulet, D.H., W. Held, I. Correa, J.R. Dorfman, M.F. Wu, and L. Corral. <year>1997</year>. Specificity, tolerance and developmental regulation of natural killer cells defined by expression of class I-specific Ly49 receptors. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source>
<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;52.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9059881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Houchins, J.P., T. Yabe, C. McSherry, and F.H. Bach. <year>1991</year>. DNA sequence analysis of NKG2, a family of related cDNA clones encoding type II integral membrane proteins on human natural killer cells. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>173</volume>:<fpage>1017</fpage>&#x02013;1020.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2007850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vance, R.E., D.M. Tanamachi, T. Hanke, and D.H. Raulet. <year>1997</year>. Cloning of a mouse homolog of CD94 extends the family of C-type lectins on murine natural killer cells. <source>Eur. J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>3236</fpage>&#x02013;3241.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9464811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Glienke, J., Y. Sobanov, C. Brostjan, C. Steffens, C. Nguyen, H. Lehrach, E. Hofer, and F. Francis. <year>1998</year>. The genomic organization of NKG2C, E, F, and D receptor genes in the human natural killer gene complex. <source>Immunogenetics.</source>
<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;173.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9683661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Anderson, S.K., J.R. Ortaldo, and D.W. McVicar. <year>2001</year>. The ever-expanding Ly49 gene family: repertoire and signaling. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source>
<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;89.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11513154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cerwenka, A., and L.L. Lanier. <year>2001</year>. Ligands for natural killer cell receptors: redundancy or specificity. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source>
<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>&#x02013;169.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11513137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vilches, C., and P. Parham. <year>2002</year>. KIR: diverse, rapidly evolving receptors of innate and adaptive immunity. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;251.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Toyama-Sorimachi, N., Y. Taguchi, H. Yagita, F. Kitamura, A. Kawasaki, S. Koyasu, and H. Karasuyama. <year>2001</year>. Mouse CD94 participates in Qa-1-mediated self recognition by NK cells and delivers inhibitory signals independent of Ly-49. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>166</volume>:<fpage>3771</fpage>&#x02013;3779.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Raziuddin, A., D.L. Longo, L. Mason, J.R. Ortaldo, M. Bennett, and W.J. Murphy. <year>1998</year>. Differential effects of the rejection of bone marrow allografts by the depletion of activating versus inhibiting Ly-49 natural killer cell subsets. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;94.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9551959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cui, J., T. Shin, T. Kawano, H. Sato, E. Kondo, I. Toura, Y. Kaneko, H. Koseki, M. Kanno, and M. Taniguchi. <year>1997</year>. Requirement for Valpha14 NKT cells in IL-12-mediated rejection of tumors. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>1623</fpage>&#x02013;1626.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9374462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Boyington, J.C., A.N. Riaz, A. Patamawenu, J.E. Coligan, A.G. Brooks, and P.D. Sun. <year>1999</year>. Structure of CD94 reveals a novel C-type lectin fold: implications for the NK cell-associated CD94/NKG2 receptors. <source>Immunity.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;82.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10023772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wolan, D.W., L. Teyton, M.G. Rudolph, B. Villmow, S. Bauer, D.H. Busch, and I.A. Wilson. <year>2001</year>. Crystal structure of the murine NK cell-activating receptor NKG2D at 1.95 A. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;254.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11224525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Moretta, A., C. Bottino, M. Vitale, D. Pende, C. Cantoni, M.C. Mingari, R. Biassoni, and L. Moretta. <year>2001</year>. Activating receptors and coreceptors involved in human natural killer cell-mediated cytolysis. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;223.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11244035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lanier, L.L. <year>2001</year>. On guard&#x02013;activating NK cell receptors. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;27.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11135574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vance, R.E., J.R. Kraft, J.D. Altman, P.E. Jensen, and D.H. Raulet. <year>1998</year>. Mouse CD94/NKG2A is a natural killer cell receptor for the nonclassical major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class I molecule Qa-1(b). <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>1841</fpage>&#x02013;1848.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9815261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vance, R.E., A.M. Jamieson, and D.H. Raulet. <year>1999</year>. Recognition of the class Ib molecule Qa-1(b) by putative activating receptors CD94/NKG2C and CD94/NKG2E on mouse natural killer cells. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>1801</fpage>&#x02013;1812.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Diefenbach, A., A.M. Jamieson, S.D. Liu, N. Shastri, and D.H. Raulet. <year>2000</year>. Ligands for the murine NKG2D receptor: expression by tumor cells and activation of NK cells and macrophages. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;126.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11248803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cerwenka, A., A.B. Bakker, T. McClanahan, J. Wagner, J. Wu, J.H. Phillips, and L.L. Lanier. <year>2000</year>. Retinoic acid early inducible genes define a ligand family for the activating NKG2D receptor in mice. <source>Immunity.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;727.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10894171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carayannopoulos, L.N., O.V. Naidenko, D.H. Fremont, and W.M. Yokoyama. <year>2002</year>. Cutting edge: murine UL16-binding protein-like transcript 1: a newly described transcript encoding a high-affinity ligand for murine NKG2D. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>169</volume>:<fpage>4079</fpage>&#x02013;4083.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12370332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Olsson-Alheim, M.Y., M. Salcedo, H.G. Ljunggren, K. Karre, and C.L. Sentman. <year>1997</year>. NK cell receptor calibration: effects of MHC class I induction on killing by Ly49Ahigh and Ly49Alow NK cells. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>159</volume>:<fpage>3189</fpage>&#x02013;3194.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9317116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ortaldo, J.R., A.T. Mason, R. Winkler-Pickett, A. Raziuddin, W.J. Murphy, and L.H. Mason. <year>1999</year>. Ly-49 receptor expression and functional analysis in multiple mouse strains. <source>J. Leukoc. Biol.</source>
<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>512</fpage>&#x02013;520.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10496323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bakker, A.B., J. Wu, J.H. Phillips, and L.L. Lanier. <year>2000</year>. NK cell activation: distinct stimulatory pathways counterbalancing inhibitory signals. <source>Hum. Immunol.</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;27.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10658974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tiberghien, P., D.L. Longo, J.W. Wine, W.G. Alvord, and C.W. Reynolds. <year>1990</year>. Anti-asialo GM1 antiserum treatment of lethally irradiated recipients before bone marrow transplantation: evidence that recipient natural killer depletion enhances survival, engraftment, and hematopoietic recovery. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>1419</fpage>&#x02013;1430.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2207317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
