<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1874644</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm157</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of the role of Aurora B on the chromosomal targeting of condensin I</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>Ai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>Akiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katano</surname><given-names>Miyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>Koichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>Shigeyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>Junn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hanaoka</surname><given-names>Fumio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>Keiji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Graduate School of Life and Environmental Sciences, University of Tsukuba, Tsukuba Science City, Ibaraki 305-8572, Japan, <sup>2</sup>Cellular Physiology Laboratory, Discovery Research Institute, RIKEN and SORST, Japan Science and Technology Agency, 2-1 Hirosawa, Wako, Saitama 351-0198, Japan, <sup>3</sup>Department of Biophysics and Biochemistry, Graduate School of Science, University of Tokyo, 7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113-0033, Japan, <sup>4</sup>RIKEN Genomic Sciences Center, 1-7-22, Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi, Yokohama 230-0045, Japan, <sup>5</sup>Department of Biochemistry II, Nagoya University Graduate School of Medicine, Showa-ku, Nagoya, Japan and <sup>6</sup>Graduate School of Frontier Biosciences, Osaka University, 1-3 Yamada-oka, Suita, Osaka 565-0871, Japan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+81-29-853-6632</phone><fax>+81-29-853-4605</fax><email>kekimura@sakura.cc.tsukuba.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2403</fpage><lpage>2412</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>During mitosis, chromosome condensation takes place, which entails the conversion of interphase chromatin into compacted mitotic chromosomes. Condensin I is a five-subunit protein complex that plays a central role in this process. Condensin I is targeted to chromosomes in a mitosis-specific manner, which is regulated by phosphorylation by mitotic kinases. Phosphorylation of histone H3&#x02009;at serine 10 (Ser10) occurs during mitosis and its physiological role is a longstanding question. We examined the function of Aurora B, a kinase that phosphorylates Ser10, in the chromosomal binding of condensin I and mitotic chromosome condensation, using an <italic>in vitro</italic> system derived from <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract. Aurora B depletion from a mitotic egg extract resulted in the loss of H3 phosphorylation, accompanied with a 50% reduction of chromosomal targeting of condensin I. Alternatively, a portion of condensin I was bound to sperm chromatin, and chromosome-like structures were assembled when okadaic acid (OA) was supplemented in an interphase extract that lacks Cdc2 activity. However, chromosomal targeting of condensin I was abolished when Aurora B was depleted from the OA-treated interphase extract. From these results, it is suggested that Aurora B-dependent and Cdc2-independent pathways of the chromosomal targeting of condensin I are present.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>At the onset of mitosis, dispersed chromatin in the interphase nucleus is resolved and packaged into physically separate compact structures, called mitotic chromosomes. This step, mitotic chromosome condensation, is a prerequisite for the accurate segregation of chromosomes, the failure of which is considered to lead to aneuploidy, cancer and cell death. Despite its importance, the molecular mechanism underlying dynamic changes of the higher order chromosome structure is poorly understood for a long time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>).</p><p>However, considerable progress has been made in the identification of proteins implicated in this process, using yeast genetics or an <italic>in vitro</italic> system derived from <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract. For example, topoisomerase II and condensin(s) have been identified as essential factors required for mitotic chromosome condensation. Topoisomerase II is an enzyme that catalyzes the strand passage of double-stranded DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>), and its activity is required for the proper condensation of mitotic chromosomes, as demonstrated by yeast genetics and the <italic>Xenopus in vitro</italic> system. Condensin(s) plays a more direct role in mitotic chromosome condensation, and also in the maintenance of its structure. About a decade ago, 13S condensin (now referred to as condensin I) was identified using a <italic>Xenopus</italic> system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Condensin I is composed of two structural maintenance of chromosomes (SMC), SMC4/CAP-C and SMC2/CAP-E subunits and three other non-SMC (CAP-D2, -G and -H) subunits, all of which are conserved widely in eukaryotes, ranging from yeast to humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6 B7 B8 B9">6&#x02013;9</xref>). Condensin I, purified from either <italic>Xenopus</italic> mitotic egg extract or mitotic HeLa cells, possesses activity to induce positive superhelical tension in double-stranded DNA in an ATP-hydrolysis-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10 B11 B12">10&#x02013;12</xref>). This activity is stimulated by mitosis-specific phosphorylation and reduced by CK2-mediated interphase phosphorylation, which suggests that it may be a physiologically relevant activity required for mitotic chromosome condensation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). More recently, a second condensin complex, condensin II, which possesses the same set of SMC subunits as condensin I but contains a different set of non-SMC subunits (CAP-D3, -G2 and -H2), was identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). The two complexes show distinct distributions on the mitotic chromosome axis and have distinct functions during mitotic chromosome condensation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>).</p><p>All eukaryotic chromosomes condensed during mitosis, and two mitotic kinases are implicated in the establishment and maintenance of chromosomes in a condensed state by regulating condensin complexes. One pathway is mediated by the master mitotic kinase, Cdc2. In <italic>Xenopus</italic> or humans, biochemical activity and the chromosomal association of condensin are stimulated by Cdc2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). In fission yeast, the phosphorylation of SMC4 by Cdc2 is required for nuclear localization of the condensin holo complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). The other pathway is thought to require Aurora B kinase (Ipl1 in budding yeast); however, the role of Aurora B in the regulation of condensin has been less characterized. Aurora kinases are serine/threonine protein kinases that play critical roles in many aspects of cell division, including the centrosome cycle, spindle assembly, chromosome condensation, the spindle checkpoint and cytokinesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). In mammals, at least three Auroras (A, B and C) are present and they share similar structures, but differ in their expression patterns, subcellular localization and substrates. Among them, Aurora B phosphorylates histone H3&#x02009;at its serine 10 (Ser10) residue during mitosis, which may be related to mitotic chromosome condensation. Aurora B forms a tight complex with inner centromere protein (INCENP) and survivin, and more recently, a fourth subunit of Aurora B complex was identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). It is also reported that Aurora C phosphorylates Ser 10 of nucleosomal H3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>).</p><p>Formerly, Aurora B was believed to be implicated in the chromosomal localization of condensin I and mitotic chromosome condensation. Inhibition of Aurora B function results in the loss of H3 phosphorylation and the recruitment of condensin I to chromatin in <italic>S. pombe</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). Depletion of Aurora B by RNA interference (RNAi) blocks mitotic chromosome condensation and the targeting of condensin in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) and <italic>C. elegans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>); however, this notion is now challenged. For example, condensin I was normally targeted to mitotic chromosomes in the Aurora B-depleted <italic>Xenopus</italic> mitotic egg extract, in which Ser10 phosphorylation was almost abolished (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Thus, different results were obtained among different species and different experimental systems, and the exact role of Aurora B in mitotic chromosome structures remains to be determined.</p><p>In this study, we focused on the regulation of the more abundant form of condensin, condensin I, by Aurora B, using cell-free extracts derived from <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs. Chromosomal targeting of condensin I was decreased to about 50% by the depletion of Aurora B from mitotic <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract. A substantial amount of condensin I was targeted to sperm chromatin in the okadaic acid (OA)-treated interphase extract that lacks Cdc2 activity, accompanied by H3 phosphorylation. Furthermore, partial chromosome condensation was introduced into the OA-treated interphase extract. The OA-dependent chromosomal targeting of condensin I, and H3 phosphorylation were almost abolished by the depletion of Aurora B from the extracts. Taken together, we conclude that a subpopulation of condensin I is bound to chromosomes in an Aurora B-dependent manner.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Antibodies</title><p>Rabbit antisera were raised against synthetic peptides corresponding to the carboxy-terminal sequences of <italic>Xenopus</italic> Aurora A (KNSQLKKKDEPLPGAQ), Aurora B (SRRVLPPVYQSTQSK), INCENP (SNRHHLAVGYGLKY) and Cdc2 (KSSLPDNQIRN). An amino-terminal cysteine was added to each peptide for sulfhydryl coupling. Conjugation of the peptides to keyhole limpet hemocyanin and affinity purification of antibodies was performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Affinity-purified antibodies were diluted to a concentration of 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml, and used for immunoblotting. Two micrograms of each antibody were used for immunoprecipitation from 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p><p>An antibody that recognizes the phosphorylated form of histone H3&#x02009;at Ser10 (purchased from Cell Signaling, Danvers, MA, USA) was diluted 1:1000 and used for immunoblotting.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts</title><p>Mitotic and interphase high-speed supernatants were prepared as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), and was used throughout the study. In some experiments, OA was supplemented into the interphase extract.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunodepletion</title><p>For immunodepletion of Aurora A from <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of affinity-purified anti-Aurora A antibody was incubated with 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of Protein A-Sepharose beads for 1&#x02009;h. To deplete Aurora B, a mixture containing 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of anti-Aurora B and 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of anti-INCENP was used. For Cdc2 depletion, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of anti-Cdc2 was used. After washing the antibody-coupled beads with XBE2 [10&#x02009;mM K-Hepes (pH 7.7), 100&#x02009;mM KCl, 2&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1&#x02009;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 5&#x02009;mM K-EGTA (pH 7.7) and 1.7% sucrose], 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts supplemented with the ATP-regenerating system (1&#x02009;mM Mg-ATP, 10&#x02009;mM creatine phosphate and 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml creatine kinase) were mixed, and incubated on a rotating wheel at 4&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h. The supernatants were recovered and then incubated with a fresh batch of the same beads. After incubating for 1&#x02009;h, the supernatant was recovered and used as a depleted extract.</p></sec><sec><title>Biochemical analysis of chromatin or chromosomes assembled <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>Sperm nuclei (5000&#x02009;nuclei/&#x003bc;l) were incubated with high-speed supernatant supplemented with the ATP-regenerating system at 22&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;h. Samples were placed on ice for 10&#x02009;min, and chromatin was isolated by centrifugation through a 30% sucrose cushion in XBE2&#x02009;at 10,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 15&#x02009;min. The chromatin fraction was subjected to SDS-PAGE followed by Coomassie staining or immunoblotting. In some experiments, the amounts of chromosome-bound condensin subunits in each extract were quantitated using the LAS 1000 imaging system (Fujifilm, Allendale, NJ, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunofluorescence staining</title><p>Immunofluorescence staining of chromatin or chromosomes assembled in the extracts was performed as described with minor modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). For fixation, 1% paraformaldehyde was used rather than 2%. For the detection of condensin I, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml affinity-purified anti-XCAP-H antibody was used.</p></sec><sec><title>Purification of <italic>Xenopus</italic> condensin I</title><p><italic>Xenopus</italic> condensin I was purified from mitotic, interphase or 4&#x02009;&#x003bc;M OA-supplemented interphase egg extracts using the anti-XCAP-G antibody coupled to protein A-Sepharose beads, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Depletion of Aurora B from mitotic extract results in the reduction of chromosomal association of condensin I</title><p>Aurora is a family of serine/threonine protein kinases that regulates many aspects during cell division. Among them, Aurora B, which phosphorylates nucleosomal Ser10 during mitosis, has long been believed to be correlated with mitotic chromosome condensation and segregation; however, different results are obtained depending on the experimental systems. To re-evaluate the exact roles of Aurora B in chromosome condensation and chromosomal targeting of condensin complex, we used an <italic>in vitro</italic> system derived from <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract. There are two types of the <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts; one is a high-speed supernatant in which chromosomes are assembled without preceding DNA replication, the other is a low-speed supernatant that allows one complete round of DNA replication before entry into mitosis. Chromatin assembly using the latter extracts may reflect more physiological process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>); however, we used a high-speed supernatant throughout this study because it is more simple system for analyzing the chromosomal loading of condensin I.</p><p>We immunodepleted Aurora B, Aurora A and Cdc2 from mitotic egg extracts, and examined Ser10 phosphorylation, chromosomal targeting of condensin I, and chromosome structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The immunodepletion efficiency of each kinase was estimated to be more than 94% by quantitative immunoblotting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). First, the phosphorylation level of histone H3&#x02009;at Ser10 residue was examined. Aurora A depletion barely affected the phosphorylation of Ser10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B, lanes 11&#x02013;13). When Aurora B was depleted from mitotic extract, the phosphorylation level of Ser10 of the chromatin-bound H3 was greatly reduced to that in the interphase extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B, lower, lanes 8&#x02013;10), while Aurora B depletion had little impact on the phosphorylation of Ser10 of H3 in the extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B, upper, lanes 8&#x02013;10). These results demonstrate that Aurora B is the major kinase phosphorylating Ser10 of nucleosomal H3, while other kinase(s) are also able to phosphorylate the soluble form of H3&#x02009;at Ser10 in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract. Cdc2 depletion resulted in a loss of Ser10 phosphorylation of chromatin-bound and soluble forms of H3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B, lanes 14&#x02013;16), suggesting that Ser10 phosphorylation during mitosis is downstream of Cdc2. Next, we tested the chromosomal targeting of condensin I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C). Sperm chromatin was incubated with each extract, isolated through a sucrose cushion, and the chromatin-associated condensin I was analyzed by immunoblotting using XCAP-E and XCAP-G. Condensin I was bound to sperm chromatin in a mitosis-specific manner, and the association was almost abolished by Cdc2 depletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C, lanes 14&#x02013;16). Aurora B depletion resulted in an approx. 50% reduction of chromosomal targeting of condensin I subunits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C, lanes 8&#x02013;10). On the other hand, the chromosomal targeting of condensin I was barely affected by mock depletion or Aurora-A depletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C, lanes, 5&#x02013;7 and 11&#x02013;13). Alternatively, chromatin-associated proteins were analyzed by Coomassie blue staining (Supplementary Figure 1A), and the intensity of the bands of XCAP-C, -E and -G was quantitated using the Las 1000 imaging system (Fujifilm) (Supplementary Figure 1B). This experiment also indicates that Aurora B depletion resulted in an about 50% reduction of chromosomal targeting of condensin subunits (Supplementary Figure 1B, lanes 1, 7 and 11). However, it is questionable that the 50% reduction of chromosomal association of condensin I in the Aurora B-depleted extract is a direct effect of the loss of Aurora B. For example, it is possible that Aurora B-depletion results in the reduction of Cdc2 activity in the Aurora B-depleted mitotic extract, which may lead to decreasing the amount of chromosome-associated condensin I. To address the criticism, we compared the Cdc2 kinase activity between control and Aurora B depleted-mitotic egg extract by MPM2 blotting. But, no significant difference was observed (data not shown).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Effect of Aurora-B depletion on condensin I binding to chromosomes. (<bold>A</bold>) Mitotic extracts were depleted with control IgG (lane 7), anti-Aurora B (lane 8), anti-Aurora A (lane 9) and anti-Cdc2 (lane 10). Two microliter aliquots of each extract were analyzed by immunoblotting with the indicated antibodies. To estimate the efficiency of depletion, 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lane 1) of interphase extract, 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lane 2), 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lane 3), 0.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lane 4), 0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lane 5) and 0.12&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lane 6) of mitotic extract were loaded in parallel (lanes 7&#x02013;10). <bold>(B)</bold> Sperm nuclei were incubated with interphase extract (lane 1), mitotic extract (lanes 2&#x02013;4), mock-depleted mitotic extract (lanes 5&#x02013;7), Aurora B-depleted mitotic extract (lanes 8&#x02013;10), Aurora A-depleted mitotic extract (lanes 11&#x02013;13), or Cdc2-depleted mitotic extract (lanes 14&#x02013;16). Assembled chromatin and chromosomes were isolated through a sucrose cushion, and 12.5% (lanes 2, 5, 8, 11 and 14), 25% (lanes 3, 6, 9, 12 and 15) and 50% (lanes 1, 4, 7, 10, 13 and 16) were separated by SDS-PAGE, and then detected by immunoblotting using anti-phospho H3 antibody (chromatin-bound; lower). To test the phosphorylation level in the extracts, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lanes 2, 5, 8, 11 and 14), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lanes 3, 6, 9, 12 and 15) and 4&#x02009;&#x003bc;l (lanes 1, 4, 7, 10, 13 and 16) of the extracts were immunoblotted with anti-phospho H3 antibody (in extract; upper). <bold>(C)</bold> Chromatin-bound proteins were prepared the same as (<bold>B</bold>), and were separated by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted by anti-XCAP-E (upper) or anti-XCAP-G antibodies (lower). <bold>(D)</bold> Sperm chromatin was incubated in interphase (a), mitotic (b), mock-depleted mitotic (c), Aurora B-depleted mitotic (d), Aurora A-depleted mitotic (e) or Cdc2-depleted mitotic (f) extracts at 22&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;h, fixed, and then stained with Hoechst.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm157f1"/></fig></p><p>The assembled structures were then fixed and stained with Hoechst to test the effect of the depletion of each kinase on chromosome condensation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>D). Sperm chromatin was converted into a condensed chromosome-like structure in a mitotic extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>Db), but no condensation occurred in the interphase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>Da) or Cdc2-depleted mitotic extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>Df). When Aurora B was depleted from mitotic extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>Dd), the chromosome structure was almost indistinguishable from undepleted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>Db) or mock-depleted mitotic extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>DC). These results indicate that chromosome condensation is dependent on Cdc2, but occurs in the Aurora B-depleted mitotic extract, in which the chromosomal association of condensin I is reduced and Ser10 phosphorylation is abolished.</p></sec><sec><title>OA treatment of interphase extract results in the partial chromosome association of condensin I</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> has shown that some populations of chromosomal targeting of condensin I were regulated by Aurora B; therefore, we next tested whether condensin I is able to target to chromosomes in the absence of Cdc2, when downstream kinases, such as Aurora B, are activated. It is known that the addition of OA, an inhibitor of type 1 and type 2A phosphatases, into interphase extracts promotes the activation of downstream mitotic kinases in the absence of Cdc2 activity. We therefore supplemented OA into the interphase egg extract and examined its effects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). The phosphorylation of chromatin-associated H3&#x02009;at Ser10 in the OA-treated interphase extract reached a similar level to that in the mitotic extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). This result is consistent with the previous report, in which RNAi depletion of Glc7/PP1 resulted in the phosphorylation of Ser10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Under this condition, a portion of condensin I subunits was targeted to the assembled chromatin: about 12.5% as much condensin I was associated with chromatin as in the mitotic extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). Next, we examined the chromatin structure by Hoechst staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C, upper). When OA was supplemented into the interphase extract, sperm chromatin was converted into partially condensed individual chromatin fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C), which are completely different from the round-shaped chromatin sphere in the interphase extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>Cb). However, the chromatin fibers assembled in the OA-treated interphase extract were thinner and much more fragile than chromosomes assembled in a mitotic extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>Ca). We also investigated the localization of condensin I by immunostaining using anti-XCAP-H antibody, because it is reported that condensin is bound to the specific regions of chromatin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C, middle lower), such as rDNA and centromere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>), was regulated by Aurora B; however, only weak staining signal was observed on the chromosome-like structure assembled in the interphase extract supplemented with OA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>Cf). Moreover, no specific region was intensively stained even when the signal was enhanced by long exposure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>Ch).
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Stimulation of chromosomal binding of condensin I by OA in interphase extracts. <bold>(A)</bold> Sperm nuclei were incubated with mitotic extract (lanes 1&#x02013;3), interphase extract (lanes 4&#x02013;6), interphase extract supplemented with 1.2 (lanes 7&#x02013;9), 3.6 (lanes 10&#x02013;12) or 12&#x02009;&#x003bc;M (lanes 13&#x02013;15) of OA at 22&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;h. Chromatin-bound proteins were dissolved with SDS-PAGE sample buffer, and 12.5 (lanes 1, 4, 7, 10 and 13), 25 (lanes 2, 5, 8, 11 and 14) and 50% (lanes 3, 6, 9, 12 and 15) of each sample were separated by SDS&#x02013;PAGE, and immunoblotted with anti-phospho H3. <bold>(B)</bold> Samples were prepared as described in (A), and 6.25% (lane 1), 12.5% (lanes 2, 4, 7, 10 and 13), 25% (lanes 3, 5, 8, 11 and 14) and 50% (lanes 6, 9, 12 and 15) of samples were blotted using anti-XCAP-E (upper), and anti-XCAP-G (lower) antibodies. <bold>(C)</bold> Sperm chromatin was assembled in the mitotic extract (a, d), interphase extract (b, e, g), and interphase extract supplemented with 3.6&#x02009;&#x003bc;M OA (c, f, h). Samples were fixed and stained with Hoechst (a, b, c; first low), and anti-XCAP-H antibody (d, e, f; second low, short exposure: g, h; third low, long exposure). Bar, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (<bold>D</bold>) Sperm chromatin was assembled in the mitotic extract (a, c, e) or interphase extract supplemented with 3.6&#x02009;&#x003bc;M OA (b, d, f). After assembly, the reaction mixtures were supplemented with the indicated extra concentration of KCl at 22&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min, fixed, and stained with Hoechst. Bar, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm157f2"/></fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Requirement of condensin in OA-dependent partial chromosome condensation in the interphase extract. <bold>(A)</bold> Mitotic (lanes 1&#x02013;2) and interphase (lanes 3&#x02013;4) extracts were mock-depleted (lanes 1 and 3) or depleted with a mixture of affinity-purified condensin antibodies (lanes 2 and 4). Equal volumes of these extracts were subjected to SDS-PAGE, blotted, and detected using the indicated antibodies. <bold>(B)</bold> Sperm chromatin was incubated with mock-depleted mitotic extract (lanes 1&#x02013;4), condensin-depleted mitotic extract (lane 5), mock-depleted interphase extract (lane 6), mock-depleted interphase extract supplemented with OA (lane 7), condensin-depleted interphase extract (lane 8) or condensin-depleted interphase extract supplemented with OA (lane 9) at 22&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;h. The assembled structures were isolated, and 25 (lane 1), 12.5 (lane 2), 6.3 (lane 3), 3.1 (lane 4) and 100% (lanes 5&#x02013;9) were analyzed by immunoblotting with the indicated antibodies. <bold>(C)</bold> Sperm chromatin was incubated with mitotic extract (a), condensin-depleted mitotic extract (b), mock-depleted interphase extract (c), mock-depleted interphase extract with OA (d), condensin-depleted interphase extract (e), or condensin-depleted interphase extract with OA (f) at 22&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;h. After incubation, assembled chromatin structures were fixed and stained with Hoechst. Bar, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm157f3"/></fig></p><p>Then, to compare the structural integrity of the chromosomes assembled in the OA-supplemented interphase extract with that assembled in the mitotic extract, the assembled structures were treated with buffers containing increasing concentrations of KCl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>D). Salt treatment of the chromosomes assembled in the mitotic extract resulted in a more extended and loosened structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>Dd and g); however, the structures of individual chromosome axes were still observed even when treated with buffer containing extra 300&#x02009;mM KCl. On the other hand, the chromosome-like structures assembled in the OA-treated interphase extract were fragile and easily broken by salt treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>De and h), indicating that they were qualitatively distinct from rigid chromosomes assembled in the mitotic extract.</p><p>The next question is whether partial chromosome condensation in the OA-supplemented interphase extract requires condensin I: it is possible that other factors activated by OA were implicated in chromosome condensation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). To test this possibility, OA was supplemented into condensin I-depleted <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts, and the chromatin structure was fixed and stained with Hoechst (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). The efficiency of immunodepletion was examined by immunoblotting using anti-XCAP-E, and -G antibodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). Next, we examined the amount of chromatin associated condensin I. Condensin I was absent from chromatin fraction assembled in the condensin I-depleted extract with OA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B, lane 9), in contrast to substantial amount of condensin I was attached to chromosomes assembled in the OA-treated interphase extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B, lane 7). Interestingly, chromosome condensation did not take place in the condensin I-depleted extract when OA was supplemented into the extract; only thin chromatin fibers were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>Cf). Thus, it is likely that OA-dependent chromosome condensation depends on condensin I.</p></sec><sec><title>Aurora B is the kinase implicated in the partial association of condensin I and chromosome condensation</title><p>Many kinases are activated by the addition of OA in the absence of Cdc2. Therefore, the next issue is to identify the kinase(s) that induces Ser10 phosphorylation, partial chromosome association of condensin I, and partial chromosome condensation in the OA-treated interphase extract. It is also possible that residual Cdc2/cyclin B in the interphase extract may be activated by this treatment, thereby causing these events. To address these questions, OA is supplemented into the interphase extract that had been depleted of Aurora B, Aurora A or Cdc2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). The efficiency of immunodepletion was determined by quantitative immunoblotting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). When OA was supplemented into Aurora A- or Cdc2-depleted interphase extracts, Ser10 phosphorylation and chromatin association of condensin I subunits were indistinguishable from those in the undepleted extract supplemented with OA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B, lanes 6, 8 and 9). Moreover, Aurora A or Cdc2 depletion did not interfere with the partial condensation of sperm chromatin in the presence of OA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>CC, e and f). On the other hand, Ser10 phosphorylation and chromatin association of condensin I were almost abolished in the OA-treated interphase extract that had been depleted of Aurora B (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B, lane 7). Furthermore, the chromatin structure assembled in this extract was round (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>Cd), similar to that assembled in the interphase extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>Cb). From these results, it is strongly suggested that Aurora B is the corresponding kinase that brings about Ser10 phosphorylation, chromatin binding of condensin I and partial condensation of sperm chromatin.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Requirement of Aurora B in the Cdc2-independent chromosomal targeting of condensin I. <bold>(A)</bold> Interphase extract was depleted with anti-Aurora B (lane 7), anti-Aurora A (lane 8) or anti-Cdc2 antibodies (lane 9). As a standard, 100% (lane 1) of mitotic extract, 100% (lane 2), 50% (lane 3), 25% (lane 4), 12.5% (lane 5) and 6.25% (lane 6) of interphase extract were loaded in parallel. Efficiency of immunodepletion was measured by quantitative immunoblotting using the antibodies indicated. <bold>(B)</bold> Sperm nuclei were incubated with mitotic extract (lanes 1&#x02013;4), or interphase extract (lane 5), OA-treated interphase extract (lane 6), OA-treated interphase extract depleted of Aurora B (lane 7), OA-treated interphase extract depleted of Aurora A (lane 8), and OA-treated interphase extract depleted of Cdc2 (lane 9). Chromatin or chromosomes were isolated, and 100% (lanes 1, 5&#x02013;9), 50% (lane 2), 25% (lane 3) and 12.5% (lane 4) of the samples were blotted by anti-phospho-H3 antibody (upper), anti-XCAP-C (middle) or anti-XCAP-E (lower) antibodies. In the case of blotting with anti-condensin subunit antibodies, a lower amount of samples was used as a standard, namely, 25% (lane 1), 12.5% (lane 2), 6.3% (lane 3) and 3.1% (lane 4). <bold>(C)</bold> Sperm chromatin was incubated with mitotic extract (a), interphase extract (b), OA-treated interphase extract (c), OA-treated interphase extract depleted of Aurora B (d), OA-treated interphase extract depleted of Aurora A (e) and OA-treated interphase extract depleted of Cdc2 (f). Samples were fixed and stained with Hoechst.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm157f4"/></fig></p><p>Finally, we examined the supercoiling activity of condensin I in the OA-treated interphase extract because chromosome-like structures assembled in the extract were very fragile and totally differ from chromosomes assembled in the mitotic extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Condensin I purified from the OA-treated interphase extract has low or undetectable supercoiling activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>, upper, lanes 10&#x02013;13), which was effectively the same as that of the inactive interphase condensin I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>, upper, lanes 6&#x02013;9). DNA-binding activity of condensin I was almost constant under all conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>, lower).
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Effect of OA on the supercoiling activity of condensin I. Condensin I was affinity-purified from mitotic (lanes 2&#x02013;5), interphase (lanes 6&#x02013;9), or OA-treated interphase extract (lanes 10&#x02013;13) and standard supercoiling (upper) and DNA binding assays (lower) were performed; r, relaxed circular DNA; s, positively supercoiled DNA; arrow, free DNA; asterisk, DNA bound to condensin I. The approximate molar ratios of condensin I to DNA were 15:1 (lanes 2, 6 and 10), 30:1 (lanes 3, 7 and 11), 60:1 (lanes 4, 8 and 12) and 120:1 (lanes 5, 9 and 13). Condensin I was omitted from lane 1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm157f5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Aurora B is the serine/threonine protein kinase that regulates many processes during cell division, such as chromosome condensation and cohesion, bipolar chromosome attachment, spindle checkpoint and cytokinesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Aurora B phosphorylates histone H3&#x02009;at Ser10, which has long been noted to be correlated with mitosis, both spatially and temporally. Ser 10 phosphorylation during mitosis is conserved in a wide range of eukaryotes, and is believed to be closely associated with the progression of mitosis, including chromosome condensation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>); however, recent studies have revealed that the relationship between Aurora B and chromosome condensation, or Ser10 phosphorylation and chromosome condensation is controversial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we extensively analyzed the role of Aurora B during mitosis on chromosome condensation using a <italic>Xenopus in vitro</italic> system. We showed that Aurora B depletion from <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract did not affect the mitotic chromosome structure in the absence of Ser10 phosphorylation, consistent with previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). In contrast, the amount of condensin I associated with chromosomes decreased to 50% of that in the undepleted extract, by the depletion of Aurora B from mitotic egg extract. Furthermore, a substantial amount of condensin I (about 12.5% of mitotic level) was targeted to chromatin assembled in the interphase extract supplemented with OA, a PP1 and PP2A phosphatase inhibitor, followed by Ser10 phosphorylation. Significantly, the OA-dependent partial chromosomal association of condensin I was abolished by the depletion of Aurora B from the extract. From these results, we conclude that the OA-dependent chromosomal targeting of condensin I is Aurora B-dependent. It is reported that condensin binding to the centromere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>) or rDNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) was mediated by Aurora B/Ipl1; however, we did not find the specific staining signal of condensin I as detected by immunofluorescence study using XCAP-H antibody, when the interphase extract was treated with OA. Thus, the activation of Aurora B may be a prerequisite but is not sufficient for condensin I targeting to these chromatin regions. In fact, chromosomal binding of condensin I in the Aurora B-depleted mitotic extract, which contains Cdc2 in the absence of Aurora B, was 50%, and that in the OA-treated interphase extract, in which Aurora B was activated in the absence of Cdc2, was about 12.5%, compared to that in the mitotic extract, in which both Cdc2 and Aurora B were active. From these results, it is suggested that about 50% of the chromosomal targeting of condensin I is Cdc2-dependent, 12.5% of that is Aurora B-dependent, while the other 37.5% requires both Cdc2 and Aurora B. Our preliminary experiment showed that Aurora B depletion from mitotic extract resulted in the reduction of chromosome associated condensin II (data not shown); thus, the chromosomal targeting of condensin II might be also regulated by Aurora B. The regulation of the condensin II recruitment to chromosomes is an object of our next interest.</p><p>We considered three possibilities for the partial chromosomal targeting of condensin I induced by Aurora B. One is that Ser10 phosphorylation of nucleosomal H3 by Aurora B is implicated during the process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). Phosphorylated Ser10 of H3 may act as a direct receptor for condensin I binding; for example, it is reported that condensin I is colocalized with phosphorylated H3 during the early stage of chromosome condensation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Very recently, it was proposed that H3 phosphorylation is required for the dissociation of HP1 during mitosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>); therefore, it is possible that the local decondensation induced by HP1 dissociation could help condensin I to access chromatin DNA. The second possibility is that chromosomal Aurora B may act as a direct ligand for condensin I binding, or Aurora B could work as condensin I cargo to the chromosomes; however, we have not yet detected the interaction of condensin I and Aurora B. The third possibility is that Aurora B phosphorylates condensin I and phosphorylation may be involved in condensin I binding to chromosomes. Aurora B is able to phosphorylate condensin I <italic>in vitro</italic>. (data not shown). Alternatively, Aurora B may phosphorylate some proteins that induce the chromosomal targeting of condensin I, or Aurora B may inactivate inhibitors that prevent the chromosomal targeting of condensin I.</p><p>The next question is why chromosomes were normally condensed in the Aurora B-depleted mitotic extract, despite the amount of condensin I attached to chromosomes being reduced. We consider that discrepancy results from a large stockpile of protein components, which constitute the chromosome structure, such as condensin I in the <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract; therefore, the 50% reduction of chromosomal condensin I may not affect apparent chromosome condensation. In fact, mitotic chromosomes were assembled normally in the mitotic extract that was depleted of 75% of condensin I (data not shown). It is possible that the consequence of Aurora B depletion differs depending on the species, and the developmental stage may come from differences in the concentration of condensin I in the cells.</p><p>It is also noted that all of our experiments were performed using a high-speed supernatant, in which no DNA replication occurs, just to focus on the mechanism of the chromosomal association of condensin I. The use of a low-speed supernatant, as described by Cuvier and Hirano, may reflect the more physiological process for chromosome condensation because it allows one round of replication before mitosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). It was reported that chromosomal targeting of condensin I and chromosome condensation took place in a low-speed supernatant that was depleted of Aurora B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) as well as in a high-speed supernatant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). Precise analysis of the effect of Aurora B depletion on the amount of chromosome bound condensin I in a low-speed supernatant is the next interest of our work.</p><p>Finally, we considered two possibilities for OA-dependent partial chromosome condensation in the interphase extract: one is that condensin I bound to sperm chromatin drives chromosome condensation, and the other is that factors other than condensin I are implicated in condensation. It is reported that the putative factor, RCA, is able to compact chromosome structures without condensin, and is inactivated by PP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>), which supports the latter model. But the former model is likely to account for the OA-dependent partial chromosome condensation in this experimental system because chromosome condensation was abolished when condensin I was depleted from OA-treated interphase extract. However, the chromosome-like structures assembled in the OA-treated interphase extract are very fragile and easily collapsed in the presence of high salt. It is noted that the supercoiling activity of condensin I purified from the extract was very weak, indistinguishable from that purified from the interphase extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Thus, chromosome-like structures may be assembled in the absence of supercoiling activity of condensin I; however, the supercoiling activity of condensin I is required to give structural integrity to the assembled chromosomes. Alternatively, we cannot exclude the possibility that the amount of condensin I associated with chromosomes in the OA-treated interphase extract are too small to make rigid structures.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm157_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"
xlink:href="nar_gkm157_nar-00147-c-2007-File007.tif"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>This work was supported by grants from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan, and from the Solution Oriented Research for Science and Technology (SORST) from the Japan Science and Technology Agency. This work was also supported by the Bioarchitect II Research Project of RIKEN. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by grants from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Sciences and Technology of Japan.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belmont</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitotic chromosome scaffold structure: new approaches to an old controversy</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>15855</fpage><lpage>15857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12461163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koshland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Strunnikov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitotic chromosome condensation</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8970729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA topoisomerases</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>1996</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8811192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Condensins, chromosome condensation protein complexes containing XCAP-C, XCAP-E and a Xenopus homolog of the Drosophila Barren protein</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9160743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A heterodimeric coiled-coil protein required for mitotic chromosome condensation in vitro</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7954811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagstrom</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Condensin and cohesin: more than chromosome compactor and glue</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12838344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosome cohesion, condensation, and separation</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Condensins: organizing and segregating the genome</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>R265</fpage><lpage>R275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15823530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasmyth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Haering</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure and function of SMC and kleisin complexes</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>2005</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15952899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATP-dependent positive supercoiling of DNA by 13S condensin: a biochemical implication for chromosome condensation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9288743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rybenkov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Crisona</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cozzarelli</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>13S condensin actively reconfigures DNA by introducing global positive writhe: implications for chromosome condensation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10428035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanaoka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell cycle-dependent phosphorylation, nuclear localization, and activation of human condensin</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>4551</fpage><lpage>4559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14607834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation and activation of 13S condensin by Cdc2 in vitro</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9774278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanaoka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Negative regulation of condensin I by CK2-mediated phosphorylation</article-title><source>EMBO. J.</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>5339</fpage><lpage>5348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17066080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Losada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuwald</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential contributions of condensin I and condensin II to mitotic chromosome architecture in vertebrate cells</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14532007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeong</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hombauer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mudrak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mechtler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Loregger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of a subunit of a novel Kleisin-beta/SMC complex as a potential substrate of protein phosphatase 2A</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2058</fpage><lpage>2064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14653995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerlich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Condensin I stabilizes chromosomes mechanically through a dynamic interaction in live cells</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16488867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerlich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct functions of condensin I and II in mitotic chromosome assembly</article-title><source>J. Cell Sci.</source><year>2004</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>6435</fpage><lpage>6445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuasa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomonaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohmae</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Takio</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fission yeast condensin complex: essential roles of non-SMC subunits for condensation and Cdc2 phosphorylation of Cut3/SMC4</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2271</fpage><lpage>2283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10485849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Earnshaw</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cellular geography of aurora kinases</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>842</fpage><lpage>854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14625535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meraldi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aurora kinases link chromosome segregation and cell division to cancer susceptibility</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15108802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gassmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henzing</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruchaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerloff</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Earnshaw</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Borealin: a novel chromosomal passenger required for stability of the bipolar mitotic spindle</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15249581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sampath</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leismann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Salic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozniakovski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Funabiki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chromosomal passenger complex is required for chromatin-induced microtubule stabilization and spindle assembly</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15260989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakashita</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuzaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanaoka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct association with inner centromere protein (INCENP) activates the novel chromosomal passenger protein, Aurora-C</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>47201</fpage><lpage>47211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15316025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsusaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Goshima</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatebe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bir1/Cut17 moving from chromosome to spindle upon the loss of cohesion is required for condensation, spindle elongation and repair</article-title><source>Genes Cells</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11554922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagan</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S. pombe aurora kinase/survivin is required for chromosome condensation and the spindle checkpoint attachment response</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drosophila aurora B kinase is required for histone H3 phosphorylation and condensin recruitment during chromosome condensation and to organize the central spindle during cytokinesis</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11266459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaitna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasierbek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jantsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Loidl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Glotzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The aurora B kinase AIR-2 regulates kinetochores during mitosis and is required for separation of homologous Chromosomes during meiosis</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagstrom</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cozzarelli</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C. elegans condensin promotes mitotic chromosome architecture, centromere organization, and sister chromatid segregation during mitosis and meiosis</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11914278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacCallum</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Losada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ISWI remodeling complexes in Xenopus egg extracts: identification as major chromosomal components that are regulated by INCENP-aurora B</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11809820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Losada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cohesin release is required for sister chromatid resolution, but not for condensin-mediated compaction, at the onset of mitosis</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3004</fpage><lpage>3016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12464631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawin</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wordeman</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for kinesin-related proteins in the mitotic apparatus using peptide antibodies</article-title><source>J. Cell Sci.</source><year>1992</year><volume>101</volume><issue>Pt 2</issue><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1629247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Losada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of Xenopus SMC protein complexes required for sister chromatid cohesion</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1986</fpage><lpage>1997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9649503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Losada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokochi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of SA/Scc3p subunits in the Xenopus and human cohesin complexes</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuvier</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role of topoisomerase II in linking DNA replication to chromosome condensation</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12604590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatchell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Grushcow</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brame</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mitotic phosphorylation of histone H3 is governed by Ipl1/aurora kinase and Glc7/PP1 phosphatase in budding yeast and nematodes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10975519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial and temporal regulation of Condensins I and II in mitotic chromosome assembly in human cells</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>3296</fpage><lpage>3308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15146063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo requirements for rDNA chromosome condensation reveal two cell-cycle-regulated pathways for mitotic chromosome folding</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14701879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vagnarelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinkle-Mulcahy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamond</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Earnshaw</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Condensin and Repo-Man-PP1 co-operate in the regulation of chromosome architecture during mitosis</article-title><source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16998479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone H3 phosphorylation and cell division</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>3021</fpage><lpage>3027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11420717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmiesing</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregson</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokomori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A human condensin complex containing hCAP-C-hCAP-E and CNAP1, a homolog of Xenopus XCAP-D2, colocalizes with phosphorylated histone H3 during the early stage of mitotic chromosome condensation</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>6996</fpage><lpage>7006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10958694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischle</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dormann</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueberheide</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabanowitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Funabiki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Allis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of HP1-chromatin binding by histone H3 methylation and phosphorylation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>438</volume><fpage>1116</fpage><lpage>1122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16222246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipp</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone H3 serine 10 phosphorylation by Aurora B causes HP1 dissociation from heterochromatin</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>438</volume><fpage>1176</fpage><lpage>1180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16222244</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
