<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17478520</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1904262</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm210</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chemistry</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>On the stability of peptide nucleic acid duplexes in the presence of organic solvents</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>Anjana</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>Peter E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Copenhagen, The Panum Institute, Blegdamsvej 3c, DK-2200 Copenhagen N, Denmark</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+45 35 327762</phone>; Fax: <fax>+45 35 396042</fax>; Email: <email>pen@imbg.ku.dk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3367</fpage><lpage>3374</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Nucleic acid double helices are stabilized by hydrogen bonding and stacking forces (a combination of hydrophobic, dispersive and electrostatic forces) of the base pairs in the helix. One would predict the hydrogen bonding contributions to increase and the stacking contributions to decrease as the water activity in the medium decreases. Study of nucleobase paired duplexes in the absence of water and ultimately in pure aprotic, non-polar organic solvents is not possible with natural phosphodiester nucleic acids due to the ionic phosphate groups and the associated cations, but could be possible with non-ionic nucleic acid analogues or mimics such as peptide nucleic acids. We now report that peptide nucleic acid (PNA) (in contrast to DNA) duplexes show almost unaffected stability in up to 70% dimethylformamide (DMF) or dioxane, and extrapolation of the data to conditions of 100% organic solvents indicates only minor (or no) destabilization of the PNA duplexes. Our data indicate that stacking forces contribute little if at all to the duplex stability under these conditions. The differences in behaviour between the PNA and the DNA duplexes are attributed to the differences in hydration and counter ion release rather than to the differences in nucleobase interaction. These results support the possibility of having stable nucleobase paired double helices in organic solvents.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Nucleic acid double helices are stabilized by hydrogen bonding and stacking forces (a combination of hydrophobic, dispersive and electrostatic forces) of the base pairs in the helix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3 B4 B5">1&#x02013;5</xref>). The most recent data suggest that stacking interactions are the more important for DNA duplex stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). Indeed these results suggest that while hydrogen bonding in GC base pairs are stabilizing the helix, hydrogen bonding in AT base pairs are slightly destabilizing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). One would predict the hydrogen bonding contributions to increase and the stacking contributions to decrease as the water activity in the medium decreases. Therefore, it could be of great interest both from a structural and thermodynamic as well as from a functional point of view to study nucleobase paired duplexes in the absence of water and ultimately in pure aprotic, non-polar organic solvents.</p><p>This is not possible with natural phosphodiester nucleic acids due to the ionic phosphate groups and the associated cations, but could be possible with uncharged nucleic acid analogues or mimics such as methylphosphonates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), phosphotriesters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), morpholino derivatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) and peptide nucleic acids (PNAs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). PNAs are DNA pseudopeptide mimics capable of forming DNA-like Watson&#x02013;Crick base-pair double helices with sequence complementary DNA, RNA and PNA oligomers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13 B14 B15 B16 B17 B18">13&#x02013;18</xref>). As the aminoethyl glycine backbone of PNA is charge neutral, no counter ions are required for stabilizing PNA&#x000b7;PNA duplexes, and consequently such duplexes may more conveniently be studied in organic solvents.</p><p>Results from a previous study has given preliminary indications that PNA&#x02013;PNA duplexes are much less affected by the presence of organic co-solvent (50% DMF) than DNA&#x02013;DNA duplexes, correlating well with the lack of measurable changes in hydration or counter ion binding upon PNA duplex formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). However, this observation warrants further exploration. We now report that PNA (in contrast to DNA) duplexes show almost unaffected stability in 70% dimethylformamide (DMF) or dioxane, and extrapolation of the data to conditions of 100% organic solvents indicates only a little (or no) destabilization of the PNA duplexes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>PNAs</title><p>PNA1, PNA2, PNA3, PNA4 and PNA5 were synthesized using solid phase Boc chemistry, purified by HPLC and characterized by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). PNA concentrations were determined spectrophotometrically at 65&#x000b0;C using molar extinction coefficients: &#x003b5;<sub>260</sub> of adenine = 15&#x02009;400&#x02009;M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003b5;<sub>260</sub> of guanine = 11&#x02009;700&#x02009;M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003b5;<sub>260</sub> of thymine = 8800&#x02009;M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and &#x003b5;<sub>260</sub> of cytosine = 7400&#x02009;M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Chemicals and DNAs</title><p>All chemical reagents used were of analytical grade except for dimethylformamide (DMF) and dioxane, which were spectroscopic grade from Sigma-Aldrich, Munich, Germany. The DNA oligonucleotides were purchased from DNA Technology, Aarhus, Denmark, and used without further purification.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample preparation</title><p>Main stock solutions of PNAs and DNAs were prepared by dissolution in deionized, double distilled water. Experimental samples were made by diluting from the corresponding main stock solutions in 10&#x02009;mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.2) containing 100&#x02009;mM NaCl and 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA.</p><p>Equimolar mixtures (1:1 stoichiometry in single strands) of the PNA or DNA and its complementary strand were dissolved in the buffer mentioned above with desired amount of organic co-solvents. The duplex formation was assured by heating to 90&#x000b0;C and then cooling slowly to room temperature to allow proper annealing. No sign of aggregation or decreased solubility of the PNAs at up to 70% of organic co-solvents was observed.</p></sec><sec><title>UV-melting experiments</title><p>The thermal melting experiments were performed on a Cary 300 Bio UV-visible spectrophotometer (Varian, Cary, NC, USA) connected to a temperature controller. Thermal melting profiles were obtained using heating&#x02013;cooling cycles in the range of &#x02212;3 to 95&#x000b0;C. The melting temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>) was determined from the peak of the first derivative of the heating curve. Cuvettes of 1.0&#x02009;cm path length and 1.0&#x02009;ml volume were used for all experiments.</p><p>Thermal melting curves at &#x0003e;50% of DMF or dioxane start to lose the upper baseline and show severe disturbances partly because of high absorbance of DMF at the wavelength required for the experiments. Therefore, thermodynamic data at &#x0003e;50% of DMF could not be obtained. However, it was possible to obtain <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> values at 60 and 70% of DMF or dioxane.</p></sec><sec><title>Thermodynamics</title><p>The thermodynamic parameters viz enthalpy change (&#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sup>0</sup>), entropy change (&#x00394;<italic>S</italic><sup>0</sup>), and Gibbs&#x02019; free energy change (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup>) were evaluated using the &#x02018;hyperchromicity method&#x02019; (curve fitting) and/or the concentration method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>The hyperchromicity method</title><p>The hyperchromicity method utilizes alpha curve and van't Hoff plots (ln <italic>K<sub>T</sub></italic> versus <italic>T</italic>&#x02009;<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) according to the following definitions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>): The fraction (&#x003b1;<sub>T</sub>) of single strands that remained hybridized in the duplex at a particular temperature <italic>T</italic> in Kelvin is represented as
<disp-formula id="M1"><label>1</label><graphic xlink:href="gkm210m1"/></disp-formula>
where, <italic>A</italic><sub>d</sub> is the absorbance of the duplex in fully hybridized condition, <italic>A</italic><sub>s</sub> is the absorbance of the single strands in fully denatured condition and <italic>A</italic><sub>s</sub> is absorbance at a particular point on the thermal melting curve at temperature <italic>T</italic>.</p><p>For non-self-complementary sequences forming <italic>n</italic>-mer structures, the general equilibrium constant equation at a particular temperature <italic>T</italic> can be expressed as:
<disp-formula id="M2"><label>2</label><graphic xlink:href="gkm210m2"/></disp-formula>
where, <italic>c</italic><sub>ts</sub> represents the total concentration of strands and <italic>n</italic> is the molecularity of the complex. Assuming a two-state model, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M2">2</xref>) reduces to
<disp-formula id="M3"><label>3</label><graphic xlink:href="gkm210m3"/></disp-formula></p><p>The van't Hoff plot ln <italic>K</italic><sub>T</sub> versus <italic>T</italic>&#x02009;<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> is a straight line represented by
<disp-formula id="M4"><label>4</label><graphic xlink:href="gkm210m4"/></disp-formula></p><p>Hence, &#x00394;<italic>H</italic>&#x02009;<sup>0</sup> can be obtained from the slope and &#x00394;<italic>S</italic>&#x02009;<sup>0</sup> can be obtained from the <italic>Y</italic>-intercept of the van't Hoff plot. &#x00394;<italic>G</italic>&#x02009;<sup>0</sup> at a particular temperature <italic>T</italic> in Kelvin can be calculated from
<disp-formula id="M5"><label>5</label><graphic xlink:href="gkm210m5"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>R</italic> is the universal gas constant which is equal to 1.986&#x02009;cal/mol K.</p></sec><sec><title>The concentration method</title><p>The concentration method utilizes a plot of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkm210i1.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>versus ln <italic>c</italic><sub>ts</sub>, where <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> is the thermal melting temperature of the duplex and <italic>c</italic><sub>ts</sub> is the total strand concentration of PNA or DNA.</p><p>Since <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> is defined by the temperature where &#x003b1; = 0.5 for a two state transition, combining Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M3">3</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M4">4</xref>) yields:
<disp-formula id="M6"><label>6</label><graphic xlink:href="gkm210m6"/></disp-formula></p><p>Thus, the thermodynamic parameters can be extracted from a linear fit to a plot of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkm210i1.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> versus ln <italic>c</italic><sub>ts</sub> according to Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M6">6</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), where &#x00394;<italic>H</italic>&#x02009;<sup>0</sup> is obtained from the slope of the linear fit and &#x00394;<italic>S</italic>&#x02009;<sup>0</sup> from the <italic>Y</italic>-intercept.</p><p>The values of the thermodynamic parameters calculated by this method are thus independent of strand concentration, which is not the case with the hyperchromicity method described above.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>PNA and DNA duplexes</title><p>In order to elucidate the properties of PNA duplexes as compared to those of iso-sequential DNA duplexes at reduced water activity, we have studied the effect of organic co-solvents on the thermal stability and thermodynamics of PNA&#x000b7;PNA, PNA&#x000b7;DNA and DNA&#x000b7;DNA duplexes of &#x02018;random&#x02019;, mixed base-sequence (Table S1). We chose DMF (dielectric constant of DMF is 36.7) and dioxane (dielectric constant of dioxane is 2.2) as organic co-solvents, as these are aprotic and are not hydrogen bond donors but still sufficiently polar to retain solubility of the PNA&#x000b7;DNA complexes even above 50% organic solvent.</p><p>The thermal stability of these duplexes and the corresponding thermodynamic parameters [evaluated using both the concentration method (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkm210i1.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> versus ln&#x02009;<italic>c</italic><sub>ts</sub> plot) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) and the hyperchromicity (curve fitting) method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>)] in aqueous medium with increasing amount of DMF (extrapolated to 100% DMF) are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tables 1</xref> and S2. Representative thermal melting curves are shown in Figures S1 and S2. It is important to note that thermal denaturation curves showed essentially unperturbed monophasic behaviour up to 50% organic co-solvent. The extrapolation was performed on the basis of the linear plots of the thermal stability (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>) and Gibbs&#x02019; free energy changes (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup>) as a function of increasing amount of DMF in the medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A and B). Because of insufficient thermal stability of the DNA1&#x000b7;DNA2 duplex in &#x0003e;30% DMF, we also designed a longer DNA&#x000b7;DNA duplex (DNA3&#x000b7;DNA4), that has thermal stability in aqueous solution similar to that of the PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2 duplex (data in Tables 1 and S3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A and B, representative thermal curves in Figure S3). While the organic solvent-dependent changes in &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> of all these duplexes show a very good correlation with the corresponding <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>, &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sup>0</sup> and &#x00394;<italic>S</italic><sup>0</sup> values were not significantly affected within experimental error (Tables S2&#x02013;S4). The extraction of thermodynamic parameters derived from thermal melting method requires that no change in heat capacity occurs in the duplex single-strand equilibrium. For the present systems we have found only minor changes. The values of specific heat capacity change (enthalpic) at constant pressure (&#x025b5;<italic>C<sub>p</sub></italic>) were 2.0&#x02009;kcal/mol.K for PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2, 1.4&#x02009;kcal/mol.K for PNA1&#x000b7;DNA2, 1.9&#x02009;kcal/mol.K for PNA2&#x000b7;DNA1 and 1.8&#x02009;kcal/mol.K for DNA1&#x000b7;DNA2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Plots of (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> and (<bold>B</bold>) &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> of PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2 (<italic>solid diamond</italic>), PNA1&#x000b7;DNA2 (<italic>solid square</italic>), DNA1&#x000b7;DNA2 (<italic>open square</italic>) and DNA3&#x000b7;DNA4 (<italic>solid triangle</italic>) as a function of the amount of DMF in the medium. (<bold>C</bold>) Plots of <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2 (<italic>open triangle</italic>) and DNA3&#x000b7;DNA4 (<italic>open square</italic>), as a function of the amount of formamide in the medium, compared to that of PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2 (dashed line) and DNA3&#x000b7;DNA4 (dotted line), as a function of the amount of DMF in the medium (DMF data taken from Figure 1A). The aqueous buffer was 10&#x02009;mM phosphate buffer containing 100&#x02009;mM NaCl and 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA, pH 7.2 &#x000b1; 0.01 (data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tables 1</xref>, S2&#x02013;S5).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm210f1"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Thermal stability and thermodynamic parameters of PNA and DNA duplexes<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duplex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMF<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2"><sup>b</sup></xref> (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> (&#x000b0;C)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>c,</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF4"><sup>d</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkm210i2.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (kcal/mol)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF4"><sup>d,</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF5"><sup>e</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;&#x00394;G<sup>0</sup>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF6"><sup>f</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.2 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16.6 &#x000b1; 0.5 (&#x02212;17.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15.4 &#x000b1; 0.5 (&#x02212;16.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.2 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;14.3 &#x000b1; 0.4 (&#x02212;15.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.3 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;14.5 &#x000b1; 0.8 (&#x02212;15.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.4 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;14.4 &#x000b1; 0.5 (&#x02212;15.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.3 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;13.6 &#x000b1; 0.7 (&#x02212;15.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0 &#x000b1; 0.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF7"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>h</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1 &#x000b1; 0.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF7"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>h</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>i</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA1&#x000b7;DNA2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.2 &#x000b1; 0.7 (&#x02212;7.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.2 &#x000b1; 1.2 (&#x02212;6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.7 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.9 &#x000b1; 0.8 (&#x02212;4.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF10"><sup>j</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.7 &#x000b1; 0.5 (&#x02212;3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>i</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;22.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA3&#x000b7;DNA4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.0 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16.4 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.1 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;14.3 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.2 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12.8 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.3 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9.3 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.1 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>i</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNA1&#x000b7;DNA2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10.3 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9.5 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9.0 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.3 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.7 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.1 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.7 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><sup>i</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p><sup>a</sup>PNA and DNA sequences: H-GTA GAT CAC T-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub> (PNA1); H-AGT GAT CTA C-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub> (PNA2); 5&#x02032;-GTA GAT CAC T-3&#x02032; (DNA1); 5&#x02032;-AGT GAT CTA C-3&#x02032; (DNA2); 5&#x02032;-AGT GAT CTA CGG TGG ACG GTC C-3&#x02032; (DNA3); 5&#x02032;-GGA CCG TCC ACC GTA GAT CAC T-3&#x02032; (DNA4).</p></fn><fn id="TF2"><p><sup>b</sup>Vol% in 10&#x02009;mM phosphate buffer containing 100&#x02009;mM NaCl and 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA, pH 7.2 &#x000b1; 0.01.</p></fn><fn id="TF3"><p><sup>c</sup>Duplex concentrations of 5.0&#x02009;&#x003bc;M in strands were used (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> plots are in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>A, S4A and S5A).</p></fn><fn id="TF4"><p><sup>d</sup>Standard deviations are based on five independent measurements.</p></fn><fn id="TF5"><p><sup>e</sup>Evaluated from the hyperchromicity (curve fitting) method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) at 37&#x000b0;C (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup><sub>37</sub> plots are in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>B, S4B and S5B). Values obtained from the concentration method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M6">Equation 6</xref>) are shown in paratheses (full details of these data are in Supplementary Data).</p></fn><fn id="TF6"><p><sup>f</sup>&#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> = &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup><sub>37</sub> (DMF) &#x02212; &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup><sub>37</sub> (aqueous). Calculated only with the values obtained from the hyperchromicity method.</p></fn><fn id="TF7"><p><sup>g</sup>These data have poorer accuracy due to upper baseline irregularities.</p></fn><fn id="TF8"><p><sup>h</sup>Data could not be evaluated because of bad thermal curves.</p></fn><fn id="TF9"><p><sup>i</sup>Data were obtained from manual extrapolation of the linear plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A and B.</p></fn><fn id="TF10"><p><sup>j</sup>Data obtained at higher than 30% of DMF were not reliable because of too low values of <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>It is clearly evident that the presence of DMF has a much smaller effect on the thermal stability and free energy of the PNA&#x000b7;PNA duplex than on the DNA&#x000b7;DNA duplex, whereas the effect on the PNA&#x000b7;DNA duplex is intermediate. The plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A and B show a linear dependence of both <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> and &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> on the DMF concentration. The change in thermal stabilities as a function of the amount of DMF in the medium did not deviate within experimental error from linearity up to 70% of DMF, thereby supporting a hypothetical approximation beyond 70% of DMF (and an extrapolation of the data to 100% DMF) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A and B, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). These results strongly indicate that PNA&#x000b7;PNA duplexes in contrast to DNA&#x000b7;DNA (and PNA&#x000b7;DNA) duplexes will have appreciable stability even in the absence of water. Naturally, we cannot exclude that non-linearity might occur at very low water contents.</p><p>Analogous studies of PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2, PNA1&#x000b7;DNA2 and DNA3&#x000b7;DNA4 in dioxane show that, despite the significant difference between the dielectric constants of these solvents, there is no significant difference between the effects of DMF and dioxane on <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> and &#x025b5;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> (Tables S3 and S4, representative thermal curves in Figures S2 and S3, plots in Figures S4 and S5).</p></sec><sec><title>PNA and DNA duplexes in formamide</title><p>In order to compare the effect of aprotic solvent (DMF and dioxane, where the destabilization of the duplex is assumed to be predominantly caused by dehydration (and perhaps change in dielectrics) with that of a hydrogen-bond donor (and breaking) solvent, we studied the thermal and thermodynamic properties of PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2 and DNA3&#x000b7;DNA4 in formamide (dielectric constant of formamide is 109), which is a well-established nucleic acid denaturant (Table S5, representative thermal curves in Figure S6, plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>C, S7 and S8). In formamide, the destabilization is caused by a combined effect of H-bond disruption and dehydration. Notably, the destabilizing effect of formamide is almost as pronounced for the PNA duplex as for the DNA duplex. The slopes of the linear plots of <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2 and DNA3&#x000b7;DNA4 as a function of increasing amount of DMF in the medium are &#x02212;0.17 (without taking the values at 60 and 70% into account) and &#x02212;0.77, respectively, whereas, those values in formamide are &#x02212;0.40 and &#x02212;0.61, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C). On the other hand, the decrease in <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> is paralleled by the increases in both &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> and &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sup>0</sup>. Thus in stark contrast to the effects of DMF and dioxane, formamide has comparable effects on PNA and DNA duplex stabilities.</p></sec><sec><title>Self-complementary PNA and DNA hairpins</title><p>Additionally, we examined the effect of organic co-solvent on the stability of self-complementary (foldback) PNA hairpins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Unfolding of hairpin PNAs, H-AGAG-(eg1)<sub>3</sub>-CTCT-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub> (PNA3) and H-ACAG-(eg1)<sub>3</sub>-CTGT-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub> (PNA4) also showed little change in <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> and &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> with increasing amount of DMF or dioxane in the medium (Tables S6 and S7, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>A, B and S9). In fact, the hairpins were slightly stabilized in dioxane (Table S7 and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B), and in this case the stabilization appears to be enthalpic (Table S7). Similar studies with an analogous DNA hairpin (DNA5: 5&#x02032;-AGAGTTTTCTCT-3&#x02032;) in DMF and dioxane as a control showed a dramatic thermal destabilization by both co-solvents (Tables S8 and S9, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>C, D and S10).
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Plots of <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of self-complementary (hairpin) PNAs PNA3 (<italic>solid inverted triangle</italic>) and PNA4 (<italic>solid circle</italic>) as a function of the amount of (<bold>A</bold>) DMF and (<bold>B</bold>) dioxane in the medium. Plots of <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of hairpin DNA control DNA5 as a function of the amount of (<bold>C</bold>) DMF (<italic>open triangle</italic>) and (<bold>D</bold>) dioxane (<italic>open square</italic>) in the medium. The aqueous buffer was 10&#x02009;mM phosphate buffer containing 100&#x02009;mM NaCl and 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA, pH 7.2 &#x000b1; 0.01 (PNA3: H-AGAG-(eg1)<sub>3</sub>-CTCT-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub>, PNA4: H-ACAG-(eg1)<sub>3</sub>-CTGT-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub>, DNA5: 5&#x02032;-AGA GTT TTC TCT-3&#x02032;) (data in Tables S6&#x02013;S9).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm210f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>PNA duplex with an endstacked tricyclic thymine</title><p>In order to evaluate the effect of removal of water from the medium (by increasing DMF content) on base stacking forces more directly, we studied the effect of DMF on the behaviour of a PNA duplex (PNA5&#x000b7;PNA6) containing a tricyclic thymine analogue (benzo[<italic>b</italic>]-1,8-naphthyridin-2(1<italic>H</italic>)-one, designated as tT) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) attached at the end of one strand, thereby stabilizing the duplex predominantly (or entirely) by end-stacking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). It is evident that, DMF preferentially destabilizes the PNA5&#x000b7;PNA6 duplex (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> slope is &#x02212;0.24) compared to the control PNA6&#x000b7;PNA7 duplex (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> slope is &#x02212;0.15) (Table S10, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3</xref> and S11). Most interestingly, the stabilization of the duplex contributed by the tT base is completely lost at 70% DMF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>), clearly indicating a dramatic reduction of the contribution of stacking interactions to duplex stability under these conditions (decrease in thermal stability of PNA5&#x000b7;PNA6&#x02009;at 70% DMF with respect to 0% DMF, &#x00394;<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> = 18.8, whereas, that of the control duplex PNA6&#x000b7;PNA7 is only 10.7).
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Plots of <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of PNA5 &#x000b7; PNA6 (<italic>open inverted triangle</italic>) containing tricyclic thymine (tT) and its control PNA6 &#x000b7; PNA7 (<italic>open circle</italic>), as a function of the amount of DMF in the medium (data in Table S10). The aqueous buffer was 10&#x02009;mM phosphate buffer containing 100&#x02009;mM NaCl and 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA, pH 7.2 &#x000b1; 0.01 (PNA5: H-tT-GTA GAT CAC T-NH<sub>2</sub>, PNA6: H-AGT GAT CTA C-NH<sub>2</sub>, PNA7: H-GTA GAT CAC T-NH<sub>2</sub>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm210f3"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Mismatched duplexes</title><p>Sequence discrimination is critically dependent on hydrogen bonding recognition, but base-pair mismatches may also change the geometry of the helix and thus influence stacking interactions. For instance, X-ray crystallography and NMR studies have revealed that G&#x000b7;T and T&#x000b7;T mismatches in DNA likely form wobble base pairs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23 B24 B25 B26 B27 B28 B29 B30">23&#x02013;30</xref>). The homopurine A&#x000b7;A mismatch in DNA involves one hydrogen bond between the amino group of one adenine and the nitrogen N1 of the opposite adenine, whereas, the mispaired T&#x000b7;T bases in DNA involve two imino-carbonyl hydrogen bonds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23 B24 B25 B26 B27 B28 B29 B30">23&#x02013;30</xref>). A C&#x000b7;T mismatch is the most unstable in DNA and makes one regular H-bond involving carbonyl groups along with one weak H-bond bridged by a water molecule at neutral pH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23 B24 B25 B26 B27 B28 B29 B30">23&#x02013;30</xref>). Effects of mispairs are rather localized and the duplex retains a global B-form conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23 B24 B25 B26 B27 B28 B29 B30">23&#x02013;30</xref>). As hydration and stacking forces could be more important factors for mismatch stabilization, removal of water may preferentially destabilize these.</p><p>However, surprisingly we find that the relative effects of DMF on the stability of single base mismatched (T&#x000b7;T, A&#x000b7;A and C&#x000b7;T) duplexes of PNA8 (H-AGT GTT CTA C-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub>), PNA9 (H-GTA GAA CAC T-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub>) and PNA10 (H-GTA GCT CAC T-Lys-NH<sub>2</sub>) with PNA1 and PNA2 are not distinguishable within experimental error from that observed with the corresponding fully matched PNA duplexes (The <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> slope of the fully matched PNA1&#x000b7;PNA2 is &#x02212;0.17, of T&#x000b7;T mismatched PNA1&#x000b7;PNA8 is &#x02212;0.13, of A&#x000b7;A mismatched PNA2&#x000b7;PNA9 is &#x02212;0.08, and of C&#x000b7;T mismatched PNA2&#x000b7;PNA10 is &#x02212;0.12) (Tables 1 and S11, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, S12 and S13). These results suggest that, in these base pair mismatched duplexes, hydrogen bonding and stacking interactions are equally compromised or that the mismatched base pair contributes only very little to the overall duplex stability.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Thermal stabilities of T&#x000b7;T, A&#x000b7;A and C&#x000b7;T mismatched PNA duplexes in DMF (data in Table S11). Plots of (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> (<italic>solid diamond</italic>) and (<bold>B</bold>) &#x025b5;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> (<italic>open diamond</italic>) of PNA1&#x000b7;PNA8 as a function of the amount of DMF in the medium. Plots of (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> (<italic>solid triangle</italic>) and (<bold>D</bold>) &#x025b5;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> (<italic>open triangle</italic>) of PNA2&#x000b7;PNA9 as a function of the amount of DMF in the medium. Plots of (<bold>E</bold>) <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> (<italic>solid square</italic>) and (<bold>F</bold>)&#x025b5;<italic>G</italic><sup>0</sup> (<italic>open square</italic>) of PNA2&#x000b7;PNA10 as a function of the amount of DMF in the medium. The aqueous buffer was 10&#x02009;mM phosphate buffer containing 100&#x02009;mM NaCl and 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA, pH 7.2 &#x000b1; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm210f4"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSIONS AND CONCLUSIONS</title><p>The relative insensitivity of PNA duplexes to the reduced water content is consistent with our previous observations showing that in contrast to the case of DNA&#x000b7;DNA (and to a lesser extent PNA&#x000b7;DNA duplexes), no change in hydration occurs upon duplex formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) and no change in counter ion binding is observed either (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).</p><p>Thus the effect of organic solvents on PNA duplex stability may be ascribed to changes in base-pair hydrogen bonding and stacking forces of the base pairs. Stacking forces have contributions from hydrophobic, dispersion and dipole electrostatic forces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31 B32 B33">31&#x02013;33</xref>), and therefore both hydrogen bonding as well as stacking interactions are affected by the dielectric constant of the solvent. However, we observe no correlation between PNA duplex stability and solvent dielectric constant. Water, formamide, DMF and dioxane have dielectric constants of 78, 109, 37 and 2.2, respectively, and in particular the comparable effect of dioxane and DMF strongly argue against a simple dependence of the dielectric constant. On the other hand, it is clear that the contribution of hydrogen bonding to PNA duplex stability should significantly increase when the dielectric constant and especially the hydrogen bonding donor/acceptor activity of the solvent decreases. (It should be kept in mind that the hydrogen bond stabilization results as the difference between nucleobase hydrogen bonding to solvent versus base pairing.) Furthermore, our results very clearly show that the stabilizing effect of end stacking decreases upon addition of DMF to the solvent. Indeed, the end-stacking effect using a tricyclic thymine analogue is absent already at 70% DMF. This thymine analogue in essence contains an additional phenyl ring compared to thymine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>), and therefore the stacking interactions of the tricyclic thymine are expected to contain a relatively larger hydrophobic contribution than natural nucleobase pairs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Thus a similar effect on the natural nucleobases is expected to occur at higher DMF (lower water) content. Nonetheless, our results strongly support the contention that relative helix stabilizing contribution of base-pair hydrogen bonding and base stacking will be shifting towards hydrogen bonding as the water content of the medium (as well as the dielectric constant) decreases. In this context, we note that for the PNA hairpins an increased stability is indicated with increasing concentration of the low dielectric constant solvent dioxane (in contrast to DMF).</p><p>It is well established that formamide and urea destabilize DNA and RNA duplexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>), and in agreement with the present data, the effect of DMF and dioxane (at 10&#x02009;mol%) on RNA duplex stability was found to be comparable to that of formamide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). However, also in case of RNA, no direct correlation between the duplex stabilizing effect and the solvent dielectric constant was apparent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Indeed, from our data comparing the effects of formamide and DMF on PNA duplex stability, we would argue that the effects of organic solvents on DNA and RNA duplexes is to a larger extent due to hydration (solvation) and counterion effects, whereas the effects on PNA duplexes more directly reflect changes in hydrogen bonding and stacking contributions to helix stability. Thus more systematic studies on the different behaviour of PNA versus DNA duplexes could possibly shed light on these relative contributions to nucleobase (including DNA) helix stability.</p><p>Interestingly, the data (Tables S2 and S3) could hint that the decreased stability of the DNA duplexes upon removal of water appears to be primarily entropic rather than enthalpic, though the data are not conclusive. This would be compatible with the differences in behaviour between the PNA and the DNA duplexes (as mentioned above) being caused by the differences in hydration and counter ion release rather than via nucleobase interaction. Thus, these results can be of great significance in understanding nucleobase pairing systems, and it will be of great interest to learn whether other non-ionic DNA analogues such as methylphosphonates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), phosphotriester (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) and morpholino (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) derivatives behave similarly.</p><p>The possibility of having stable nucleobase paired double helices in organic solvents has several implications. First of all, we note that it should be possible to reach the goal of finding PNA duplexes that are freely soluble in non-polar organic solvents by chemically modifying the PNA backbone, for instance using hydrophobic amino acids in place of glycine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">36</xref>). Studying the behaviour of these in the absence of water could provide valuable information about fundamental properties of nucleobase double helices. Furthermore, PNA duplexes spanning lipid membranes could be envisaged as a means for mediating electron transport over the membrane. Sequence-dependent electron transport (or hole migration) through DNA duplexes is now well established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36 B37 B38 B39 B40">37&#x02013;41</xref>), and although electron transport involving PNA still require more extensive studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">43</xref>) this should be worthwhile pursuing. Finally, entirely new dimensions would be added to the emerging technique of &#x02018;DNA sequence&#x02019; directed organic synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">44</xref>). Thus novel avenues of exploiting nucleobase recognition systems can be enabled by transferring these to non-aqueous environments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary data are available at NAR Online.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm210_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="nar_gkm210_1.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><p>This work is supported by the European Commission in the 6th framework PACE project, contract no. 002035. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by the European Commission.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Crick</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetical implications of the structure of deoxyribonucleic acid</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1953</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>964</fpage><lpage>967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13063483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saenger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><source>Principles of Nucleic acid Structure</source><year>1988</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrogen bonding, base stacking, and steric effects in DNA replication</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struct</source><year>2001</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11340050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oostenbrink</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>van Gunsteren</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient calculation of many stacking and pairing free energies in DNA from a few molecular dynamics simulations</article-title><source>Chemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4340</fpage><lpage>4348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15880545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundaralingam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponnuswamy</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability of DNA duplexes with Watson&#x02013;Crick base pairs: a predicted model</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2004</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>16467</fpage><lpage>16476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15610041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Protozanove</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakovchuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank-Kamenetskii</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stacked-unstacked equilibrium at the nick site of DNA</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>342</volume><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yakovchuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Protozanove</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank-Kamenetskii</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Base-stacking and base-pairing contributions into thermal stability of the DNA double helix</article-title><source>Nucleic. Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16449200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ts&#x02019;o</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonionic nucleic acid analogues. Synthesis and characterization of dideoxyribonucleoside methylphosphonates</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1979</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>5134</fpage><lpage>5143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">497173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tosquellas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dell'Aquila</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Morvan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasseur</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Imbach</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pro-oligonucleotide approach: solid phase synthesis and preliminary evaluation of model pro-dodecathymidylates</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2069</fpage><lpage>2074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9547261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summerton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morpholino antisense oligomers: the case for an RNase H-independent structural type</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>1999</year><volume>1489</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10807004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Egholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchardt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence-selective recognition of DNA by strand displacement with a thymine-substituted polyamide</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1991</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>1500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1962210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peptide nucleic acid. A molecule with two identities</article-title><source>Acc. Chem. Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>630</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchardt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Freier</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Driver</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PNA hybridizes to complementary oligonucleotides obeying the Watson&#x02013;Crick hydrogen-bonding rules</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1993</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7692304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchardt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Egholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nord&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA-like double helix formed by peptide nucleic acid</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1994</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8139692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d8;rum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nord&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics for hybridization of peptide nucleic acids (PNA) with DNA and RNA studied with the BIAcore technique</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1997</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>5072</fpage><lpage>5077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9125529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Veal</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR solution structure of a peptide nucleic acid complexed with RNA</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7519361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of a peptide nucleic acid-DNA duplex</article-title><source>Nature Struct. Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8612069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kastrup</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of a peptide nucleic acid (PNA) duplex at 1.7&#x02009;A resolution</article-title><source>Nature Struct. Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9033585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unique properties of purine/pyrimidine asymmetric PNA.DNA duplexes: differential stabilization of PNA.DNA duplexes by purines in the PNA strand</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>2006</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1329</fpage><lpage>1337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16326919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gildea</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Egholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchardt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Solid-phase synthesis of peptide nucleic acids</article-title><source>J. Pept. Sci</source><year>1995</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9222994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peyret</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Seneviratne</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allawi</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>SantaLucia</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Nearest-neighbor thermodynamics and NMR of DNA sequences with internal A.A, C.C, G.G, and T.T mismatches</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>3468</fpage><lpage>3477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10090733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eldrup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Haaima</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kastrup</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>1,8-Naphthyridin-2(1<italic>H</italic>)-ones&#x02014;novel bicyclic and tricyclic analogues of thymine in peptide nucleic acids (PNAs)</article-title><source>Eur. J. Org. Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1781</fpage><lpage>1790</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Eckstein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>DMJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>In Nucleic acid and Molecular Biology</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Germann</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalisch</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Varnum</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Sande</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR spectroscopic and enzymatic studies of DNA hairpins containing mismatches in the EcoRI recognition site</article-title><source>Biochem. Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9923708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allawi</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>SantaLucia</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Thermodynamics of internal C.T mismatches in DNA</article-title><source>Nucleic. Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2694</fpage><lpage>2701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9592156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulard</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cognet</surname><given-names>JAH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazakerley</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure as a function of pH of two central mismatches, C.T and C.C, in the 29 to 39&#x02009;K-ras gene sequence, by nuclear magnetic resonance and molecular dynamics</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9159474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nemecek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepanek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Turpin</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Raman study of potential &#x02018;antisense&#x02019; drugs: nonamer oligonucleotide duplexes with a central mismatch as a model system for the binding selectivity evaluation</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>2004</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15137107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kneale</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabinovich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennard</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure of guanosine-thymidine mismatches in B-DNA at 2.5-A resolution</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1987</year><volume>262</volume><fpage>9962</fpage><lpage>9970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3611072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wartell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The thermal stability of DNA fragments with tandem mismatches at a d(CXYG).d(CY&#x02032;X&#x02032;G) site</article-title><source>Nucleic. Acids Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8604314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gervais</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cognet</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bret</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazakerley</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of two mismatches A.A and T.T in the K-ras gene context by nuclear magnetic resonance and molecular dynamics</article-title><source>Eur. J. Biochem</source><year>1995</year><volume>228</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7705340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guckian</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>RX-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheils</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahmassebi</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors contributing to aromatic stacking in water: Evaluation in the context of DNA</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2000</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>2213</fpage><lpage>2222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20865137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A series of nonpolar thymidine analogs of increasing size: DNA base pairing and stacking properties</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>2048</fpage><lpage>2053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15760186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solvent effects on the stability of A<sub>7</sub>U<sub>7</sub>p</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1985</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2086</fpage><lpage>2094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4016102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Renaturation kinetics and thermal stability of DNA in aqueous solutions of formamide and urea</article-title><source>Nucleic. Acids Res</source><year>1977</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>3537</fpage><lpage>3555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">928068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Delcourt</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermodynamic effects of formamide on DNA stability</article-title><source>Nucleic. Acids Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2095</fpage><lpage>2103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8668541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000fc;schl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sforza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haaima</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peptide nucleic acids (PNAs) with a functional backbone</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>4707</fpage><lpage>4710</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><source>In Long-Range Charge Transfer in DNA I-II</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-range DNA charge transport</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>6475</fpage><lpage>6483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12919006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schonenberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrical conduction through DNA molecules</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>398</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10201370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiebig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiemann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zewail</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Femtosecond direct observation of charge transfer between bases in DNA</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>14052</fpage><lpage>14055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11106376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustyn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence dependence of charge transport through DNA domains</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2005</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>17445</fpage><lpage>17452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16332096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Frydenlund</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Orum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Batz</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peptide nucleic acid-DNA duplexes: long range hole migration from an internally linked anthraquinone</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>12320</fpage><lpage>12325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9356447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohno</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of electron transfer in DNA by peptide nucleic acids (PNA)</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Symp. Ser</source><year>2000</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12903255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gertner</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Grubina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyon</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA-templated organic synthesis and selection of a library of macrocycles</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>305</volume><fpage>1601</fpage><lpage>1605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319493</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
