<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCB</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16260498</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1934410</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200506082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200506082</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in vivo prevents dark, spontaneous activity of <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elia</surname><given-names>Natalie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Frechter</surname><given-names>Shahar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gedi</surname><given-names>Yinon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Minke</surname><given-names>Baruch</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Selinger</surname><given-names>Zvi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Department of Biological Chemistry, K&#x000fc;hne Minerva Center for Studies of Visual Transduction, Institute of Life Sciences, The Hebrew University, Givat Ram, Jerusalem 91904, Israel</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Department of Physiology, K&#x000fc;hne Minerva Center for Studies of Visual Transduction, Institute of Life Sciences, The Hebrew University, Givat Ram, Jerusalem 91904, Israel</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Correspondence to Zvi Selinger: <email>selinger@vms.huji.ac.il</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>171</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> photoreceptor cells are capable of detecting single photons. This utmost sensitivity is critically dependent on the maintenance of an exceedingly low, dark, spontaneous activity of photoreceptor cells. However, the underlying mechanisms of this hallmark of phototransduction are not fully understood. An analysis of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> visual heterotrimeric (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;) Gq protein revealed that wild-type <italic>Drosophila</italic> flies have about a twofold excess of G&#x003b2; over G&#x003b1; subunits of the visual Gq protein. Studies of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> mutants in which the excess of G&#x003b2; was genetically eliminated showed dramatic dark, spontaneous activity of the photoreceptor cells, whereas concurrent genetic reduction of the G&#x003b1; subunit, which restored the excess of G&#x003b2;, abolished this effect. These results indicate that an excess of G&#x003b2; over G&#x003b1; is a strategy used in vivo for the suppression of spontaneous activity, thereby yielding a high signal to noise ratio, which is characteristic of the photoreceptor light response. This mechanism could be relevant to the regulation of G protein signaling in general.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>N. Elia and S. Frechter contributed equally to this paper.</p></fn><fn><p>Abbreviations used in this paper: ERG, electroretinogram; GDP, guanosine diphosphate.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Many signaling systems use heterotrimeric (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;) G proteins to relay signals from heptahelical receptors to downstream effectors. To accomplish signal transduction, G proteins act as conformational sensors of a guanine nucleotide, which is bound to the &#x003b1; subunit. G proteins that are charged with guanosine diphosphate (GDP) are in the inactive state, where the &#x003b1; and the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits are associated with each other. Receptor activation accelerates the exchange of bound GDP for free GTP (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Cassel and Selinger, 1978</xref>) followed by the dissociation of active G&#x003b1;-GTP from &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits. Hydrolysis of the bound GTP by a GTPase reaction brings the G&#x003b1; subunit back to the inactive state (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Cassel et al., 1977</xref>), which is characterized by tightly bound GDP and a reassociation with the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex. To ensure specificity, high effective concentrations, and speed of interaction, the G protein signaling components are usually attached to the membrane domain as peripheral membrane proteins.</p><p>Membrane attachment of heterotrimeric G proteins has been extensively investigated, and the effect of lipid modification on membrane localization has been addressed by several studies (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Wedegaertner, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Resh, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Manning, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kosloff et al., 2002</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Smotrys and Linder, 2004</xref>). All G protein &#x003b1; subunits (with the exception of transducin) are palmitoylated, and some are additionally modified by myristoylation. The &#x003b1; subunits of Gq/G<sub>11</sub>, including the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> eye&#x02013;specific Gq&#x003b1;, as well as Gs&#x003b1;, G<sub>12</sub>&#x003b1;, and G<sub>13</sub>&#x003b1; are modified only by palmitoylation. The corresponding &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits undergo isoprenylation of a cysteine residue at the so-called CAAX box of the &#x003b3; subunit (for review see <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Wedegaertner, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Resh, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Manning, 2001</xref>). Plasma membrane attachment of the &#x003b1; subunits Gs&#x003b1; and Gq&#x003b1; is dependent on coexpression with the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Evanko et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Furthermore, the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits, having only one membrane attachment signal on the &#x003b3; subunit, are poorly targeted to the plasma membrane and require coexpression of the &#x003b1; subunit for efficient plasma membrane attachment (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Evanko et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Michaelson et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Takida and Wedegaertner, 2003</xref>). Altogether, these studies led to a model of two membrane attachment signals that are needed for plasma membrane attachments and localization of heterotrimeric G protein subunits (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Wedegaertner, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Resh, 1999</xref>). It should be noted, however, that most of these studies have been performed by using various culture cells that were transfected with vectors yielding overexpressed proteins (usually the &#x003b1; and &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits of the heterotrimeric G protein). This procedure is bound to cause distortion of the original stoichiometry of &#x003b1; and &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits, which is difficult to control under these conditions. The extensively studied <italic>Drosophila</italic> visual system combined with the large repertoire of <italic>Drosophila</italic> visual mutants offer a unique opportunity to study in vivo the various roles of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer, its cellular localization, and the functional consequences of altering &#x003b1;/&#x003b2;&#x003b3; stoichiometry.</p><p>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> visual system is a specialized system that is composed of highly polarized and compartmentalized cells that sequester the phototransduction machinery in a specific signaling compartment called the rhabdomere (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Minke and Hardie, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Hardie and Raghu, 2001</xref>). This signaling compartment is functionally equivalent to the vertebrate rod photoreceptor outer segment, which also sequesters the phototransduction machinery in a specific cell compartment. Phototransduction in <italic>Drosophila</italic> is initiated upon the activation of rhodopsin by light and proceeds through a photoreceptor-specific Gq protein (Gq<sub>e</sub>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Scott et al., 1995</xref>), which, in turn, activates the phospholipase C enzyme effector (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Devary et al., 1987</xref>). Upon activation, the eye-specific Gq&#x003b1; subunit (Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>) dissociates from the eye-specific &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer (G&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub>) and translocates, at least in part, from the membrane to the cytosol (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kosloff et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Cronin et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we show (by using a series of eye-specific <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> hypomorph mutants) that the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer has a crucial role in both membrane attachment and rhabdomeral targeting of the &#x003b1; subunit that can account for the decreased light sensitivity previously observed in these mutants (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Dolph et al., 1994</xref>). On the other hand, by using the almost null mutant for the eye-specific Gq&#x003b1; subunit <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>, we found that the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer is dependent on the &#x003b1; subunit for membrane attachment but not for targeting to the rhabdomere, suggesting a role for the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer in targeting the heterotrimer to the photoreceptor signaling compartment (the rhabdomere). An analysis of the protein levels of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunits revealed a surprising twofold excess of the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit over the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit. Mutants that eliminated this excess showed a dramatic increase in spontaneous activity of the phototransduction cascade. Conversely, double mutations that also reduced the level of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and, thereby, restored the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> completely reversed this phenotype. Together, these results provide a significant insight into the strategy used by the photoreceptor cell in vivo to avoid spontaneous activity at the G protein level.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>The levels of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunits in <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptors are maintained independently of one another</title><p>The &#x003b1; subunit of the heterotrimeric G protein and the tightly associated complex of &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits undergo dissociation and reassociation during activation of the phototransduction cascade. Therefore, it is expected that these subunits would influence one another's level, localization, and function. Previous studies that addressed these questions used tagged subunits and heterologous expression in tissue culture cells. Qualitatively, it is now generally accepted that plasma membrane attachment of the &#x003b1; subunit requires coexpression of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunit complex (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Degtyarev et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Evanko et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>), and, reciprocally, plasma membrane attachment of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunit complex requires coexpression of the &#x003b1; subunit (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Michaelson et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Takida and Wedegaertner, 2003</xref>). Although a great deal has been learned from these previous studies, little is known about the localization of G protein subunits in their natural environment and how the stoichiometry of these subunits affects the level, localization, and function of G protein subunits under physiological conditions. To test the effect of various subunits on the level of one another, we have used the <italic>Drosophila</italic> eye&#x02013;specific G&#x003b2; subunit mutants (<italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>) that were described by <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Dolph et al. (1994)</xref> and the eye-specific Gq&#x003b1; subunit mutant (<italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>) that was described by <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Scott et al. (1995)</xref>.</p><p>The hypomorph <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>, <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>2</sup>, and the heterozygote of the most severe mutant, <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+, express the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit protein at levels of 4, 13, and 50% of wild-type flies, respectively (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>). Despite the progressive decrease in the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit level in these mutants, the level of the &#x003b1; subunit was undiminished and is the same level as in wild-type flies (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A). Similarly, in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant, which expresses negligible levels of the &#x003b1; subunit, the level of the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit was the same as in wild-type flies (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> C). Although the levels of the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit that we found in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>2</sup> mutants were higher than those previously reported (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Dolph et al., 1994</xref>), the progressive decrease of the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit protein among these mutants was similar (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B). The eye-specific G&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> subunit, which forms an extremely tight complex with the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit, completely disappeared in the severe <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant but, like G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>, was undiminished in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> D). Therefore, we can conclude that the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants are, in fact, &#x003b2;&#x003b3; mutants and that the effects observed in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants can be ascribed to a decrease in the level of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunit dimer without effecting the level of the &#x003b1; subunit.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>
<bold>The levels of DGq<sub>e</sub> subunits in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic><sup>1</sup> mutants.</bold> (A) The levels of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> were determined for the three different dark-adapted <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants (<italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>, <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>2</sup>, and heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+) using Western blot analysis. Aliquots containing equivalent protein amounts of total head homogenates were separated on a 7.5&#x02013;15% gel and were visualized with a mixture of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> antibodies at saturating concentrations. Each mutant has different levels of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>, whereas the level of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> remains constant. (B) Quantification of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> levels in different G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> mutants. The wild-type percentage level was set as 100%. G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> levels in the heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutant, the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>2</sup> mutant, and the most severe mutant, <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>, are 50, 13, and 4%, respectively. Data represent mean values &#x000b1; SEM (error bars) from seven independent experiments. (C) The levels of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> in dark-adapted <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant and in wild-type flies were determined using Western blot analysis. The results show that G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> levels are maintained independently of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>. (D) Determination of G&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> levels in dark-adapted wild-type, <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>, and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> flies using Western blot analysis shows that the level of G&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> is completely dependent on G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> but not on Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200506082f1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The G&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> subunits are essential for membrane attachment and targeting of the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit to the rhabdomere</title><p>To understand how G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> affects the localization of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>, we extended our analysis to membrane attachment and targeting of the &#x003b1; subunit in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants. As shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, the low levels of &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants cause a progressive decrease in the fraction of the &#x003b1; subunit that is attached to the membrane. Quantitatively, the decrease in membrane attachment of the &#x003b1; subunit is proportional to the percent decrease in the level of the &#x003b2; subunit.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>
<bold>G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> determines the membrane and rhabdomeral localization of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>.</bold> (A) Western blot analysis shows the localization of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in the membrane (P, pellet) and in cytosol (S, supernatant) in dark-adapted <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants. (B) Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> distribution between the membrane and cytosol of dark-adapted <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants and of wild-type flies is represented by the percentage of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in each fraction (P and S) out of the total Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> amount (P + S) in each mutant. Data represent mean values &#x000b1; SEM from five independent experiments. (C) Immunogold EM analysis of cross sections of a single rhabdomere using Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> antibodies that were applied to dark-adapted wild-type flies and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants. Bars, 500 nm. (D) Number of gold particles in a cross section of a single rhabdomere. Each gold particle represents a Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> molecule. Data represent mean values &#x000b1; SEM (error bars) from 20 different rhabdomeres for each mutant. Wild-type percentage level was set as 100%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200506082f2"/></fig><p>The molecules that participate in phototransduction, including the eye-specific DGq<sub>e</sub> subunits, are confined to a specific signaling compartment (the rhabdomere). Thus, we investigated how the decreased levels of &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits affect the targeting of the &#x003b1; subunit to the signaling compartment. Using immunogold EM with antibodies against the eye-specific &#x003b1; subunit, we counted the gold particles in 20 cross sections of equal size from wild-type and mutant rhabdomeres. This analysis revealed that the quantity of the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit in the rhabdomere of different mutants corresponds with the level of the &#x003b1; subunit that is membrane attached (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) and indicates that the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunit complex controls both membrane attachment and rhabdomeral targeting of the &#x003b1; subunit.</p></sec><sec><title>The reduced light sensitivity of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic>e</italic> mutants is caused by the mislocalization of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>
</title><p>One of the major advantages of <italic>Drosophila</italic> for the study of phototransduction in vivo is the ability to examine the electrophysiological response in detail and characterize the phenotype that results from a decrease in a specific phototransduction component, which is caused by mutation. Two physiological phenotypes were observed for <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Dolph et al., 1994</xref>). The first phenotype was a dramatic loss of light sensitivity (reaching a decrease by two orders of magnitude in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant), and the second phenotype was a slow termination of the light response. To address the possibility that the reduced sensitivity to light in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants arises from a reduction in membrane-bound Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>, we reexamined the sensitivity to light in four <italic>Drosophila</italic> mutants with reduced levels of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> show a correlation between the level of membrane-bound Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) and the sensitivity of the response to light (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) in which low levels of membrane-bound Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> correspond to low light sensitivity. The latter was accompanied by a modified waveform of the light-induced current (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, inset). The fact that heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ showed only a minor reduction in the sensitivity to light is consistent with previous results showing that 50% of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> is sufficient to maintain normal sensitivity to light (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Scott et al., 1995</xref>). Together, these results indicate that the loss of light sensitivity is caused by the effect of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants on membrane attachment and targeting of the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit to the signaling compartment (the rhabdomere). Clearly, when rhodopsin and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> are present in different cellular compartments, the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit cannot transfer signals from rhodopsin to the phospholipase C enzyme.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Sensitivity to light in wild-type flies and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants.</bold> Mean peak of the light-induced currents (LIC) in response to increasing intensities of orange light is plotted as a function of the light intensity. <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutants (open circle) showed a 2-log reduction in sensitivity to light, whereas <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>2</sup> mutants (closed triangle) showed an &#x0223c;0.7 log reduction in sensitivity to light. <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ (open triangle) and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+;<italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ (closed square) were not significantly different from wild-type flies (closed circle). Each curve represents a mean of &#x0003e;10 different experiments. Error bars represent SEM. Inset shows whole cell recordings of LIC from isolated ommatidia clamped at &#x02212;70 mV. The maximal orange light intensity was attenuated by 2 log units in all of the traces. Note the different scales for the top and bottom traces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200506082f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Membrane localization of the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit</title><p>To examine the effect of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> on the localization of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>, we measured the distribution of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> between the membrane and cytosol in wild-type and G&#x003b1;q<sup>1</sup> mutant flies. In contrast to the light-dependent translocation of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> from the membrane to the cytosol (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kosloff et al., 2003</xref>), G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> was about equally distributed between the membrane and the cytosol under both light and dark conditions (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, A and B</xref>). A longer period of illumination for up to 4 h did not alter the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> distribution (not depicted). These results suggest that the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex remains partly bound to the membrane even when the &#x003b1; subunit is translocated to the cytosol. Indeed, it has been shown that although rhodopsin&#x02013;G&#x003b1; interactions are reduced upon activation, rhodopsin&#x02013;G&#x003b2;&#x003b3; interactions remain undiminished (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Phillips and Cerione, 1992</xref>). Moreover, electrostatic calculations showed that upon dissociation from the G&#x003b1; subunit, the &#x003b2; subunit of transducin exposed a prominent patch of basic residues that enhanced the membrane affinity of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer by about an order of magnitude (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Murray et al., 2001</xref>). However, it has also been shown in the rat visual system that G&#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits translocate from the outer to the inner rod segment in response to light, albeit at a slower rate than the translocation of the &#x003b1; subunit (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Sokolov et al., 2002</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Membrane attachment and rhabdomeral targeting of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>.</bold> (A) Western blot analysis shows the localization of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> in membrane (P, pellet) and in cytosol (S, supernatant) of wild-type, dark-adapted, or illuminated flies and of dark-adapted <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> flies. Illumination was with blue light for 60 min. In wild-type flies, G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> was about equally distributed between the membrane and the cytosol both under dark and light conditions. In <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant flies, however, G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> failed to reach the membrane and was mostly soluble. (B) Percentage of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> in fractions (P and S) out of the amount of total G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> (P + S) of each treatment. Data represent mean values &#x000b1; SEM (error bars) from 10 independent experiments. (C) Immunogold EM analysis of cross sections of a single rhabdomere from dark-adapted wild-type flies and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant flies using affinity-purified G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> antibodies revealed that G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> is targeted to the rhabdomere even in the near absence of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>. <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant flies were used as a control for the specificity of the antibodies. Bars, 500 nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200506082f4"/></fig><p>The effect of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> on the membrane attachment of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> was further studied using the G&#x003b1;q<sup>1</sup> mutant. In this mutant, which has a negligible level of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>, the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit is localized mainly to the cytosol (&#x0003e;80%; <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, A and B</xref>), suggesting that a newly synthesized G&#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex is dependent on the &#x003b1; subunit for membrane attachment. Failure of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex to bind by itself to the plasma membrane was previously observed in transfected cells (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Evanko et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Michaelson et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Takida and Wedegaertner, 2003</xref>) and in G&#x003b1; RNA interference of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> embryos (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</xref>). However, immunogold EM using specific antibodies against G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> revealed that the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex is targeted to the rhabdomere even in the near absence of the &#x003b1; subunit (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C) but apparently remains soluble within this compartment. This result indicates that the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex is targeted to the rhabdomere independently of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> but depends on the &#x003b1; subunit for tight membrane attachment. The presence of soluble G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> in the rhabdomere can be a result of interactions with protein partners like phosducin (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Sokolov et al., 2004</xref>) and regulators of G protein signaling proteins (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Snow et al., 1998</xref>). Although homologues of these proteins are present in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> genome, their cellular localization in <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptors are currently unknown. The cellular localization of the Gq<sub>e</sub> heterotrimer may be determined by the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex. This finding is consistent with a previous report that ectopic targeting of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex to the mitochondria leads to mitochondrial localization of the Gz&#x003b1; subunit (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Fishburn et al., 2000</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>The G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit is present in excess over the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit</title><p>The presence of 80% of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in a membrane-bound form in wild-type dark-adapted flies (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B, left), whereas only 50% of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> is membrane bound (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B, left), raised the question of the stoichiometry of these two components. To determine the levels of the subunits in vivo, we performed immunoblot analysis with a mixture of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>- and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>-specific antibodies at a concentration five times that required for their saturation. Furthermore, two different anti-G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> antibodies that were raised against two different sequences of the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> protein gave similar results (see SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting). In wild-type flies, the amount of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> was &#x0223c;2.5 times higher than the amount of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5, A and B</xref>). To verify the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunits in wild-type flies, which was determined by Western blotting, we calibrated the immunoblot with the use of purified recombinant <italic>Drosophila</italic> Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> proteins. We determined the concentrations of the recombinant proteins spectrophotometrically by using calculated extinction coefficients of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> = 42,350 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> = 60,000 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at 280 nm. This quantitative analysis of two samples of wild-type fly head homogenate again revealed an excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> of &#x0223c;2.5 times (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> C).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>
<bold>A physiological excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> that is abolished in heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic><sup>1</sup>/+ mutant flies.</bold> (A) Western blot analysis of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> (top band) and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> (bottom band) in dark-adapted wild-type and heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ flies shows an excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in wild-type flies that is abolished in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutant. Western blots were performed with a mixture of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> antibodies. T, total amount in the cell; P, pellet (membrane); S, supernatant (cytosol). (B) The ratio between G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in different fractions. Data represent mean values &#x000b1; SEM (error bars) from 10 independent experiments. (C) Two samples of head homogenates (indicated as A and B) were analyzed by Western blotting along with five samples containing various amounts of recombinant <italic>Drosophila</italic> Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> (top) and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> (bottom) standards (indicated as 1&#x02013;5). Calibration curves were obtained by plotting the amount of ECL signal in each band against the amount of the recombinant protein in the standard. Because the volume of head homogenates that was applied on each gel was different in order to fit the linear range of each calibration curve, Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> amounts in the head homogenates were calculated for 1 &#x003bc;l of homogenate. Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> amounts in each homogenate and the ratio between them are represented in the table at the bottom. Data are representative of six independent experiments. The ratio between G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> was determined as 2.6 &#x000b1; 0.2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200506082f5"/></fig><p>Most of the excess G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> was present in the cytosol, whereas the membrane-bound fraction contained both the &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; subunits in about equal amounts (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5, A and B</xref>). Therefore, in rhabdomere membranes, all of the G&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> molecules, which are in close proximity to rhodopsin, may be associated with the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit. This finding also indicates that in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptor cells, there is a soluble pool of free G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit in the rhabdomere. The localization of soluble G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> in the signaling organelle, the rhabdomere (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>), could be functionally important.</p><p>The unexpected excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> was almost completely abolished in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> heterozygous mutant (<italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+). The ratio between G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in this mutant was &#x0223c;1:1. The decrease in G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> levels of this mutant did not change the ratio between membrane-bound Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>, which remained &#x0223c;1:1. In the soluble fraction, however, we found a large decrease of excess G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>. Although the ratio between soluble G&#x003b2;e and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in wild-type flies was &#x0223c;7:1, the ratio in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutant was reduced to &#x0223c;2.5:1 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5, A and B</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Spontaneous activity of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> mutants</title><p>A new and striking phenotype of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants was revealed in this study. Whole cell patch-clamp recording of dark-adapted mutant photoreceptor cells showed spontaneous, unitary, inward currents that were similar in shape to the single photon responses known as quantum bumps (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Henderson et al., 2000</xref>). The frequency of these spontaneous responses was different for the various <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants. For the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant, only a low frequency of spontaneous bumps was observed, which was not much different from the frequency of spontaneous bumps observed in wild-type flies. A higher frequency of spontaneous bumps was clearly noted for the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>2</sup> mutant, whereas the most dramatic increase in the frequency of spontaneous bumps was observed for the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> heterozygous mutant (<italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+). The high frequency of spontaneous bumps in the heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant is surprising because this mutant has normal sensitivity to light in contrast to the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> homozygote, which is the most severe mutant but has an almost normal frequency of spontaneous bumps (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3</xref> and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). This complex behavior can be explained by the decreased levels of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> observed in the signaling compartment of these mutants (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Indeed, when the bump frequency was normalized to the number of rhabdomeral Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>, a similar bump frequency per rhabdomeral Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> was observed for all of the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants, whereas the wild-type bump frequency remained much lower (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> C).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Spontaneous activation of the visual signaling cascade in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants.</bold> (A) Whole cell recordings of light-induced currents from isolated ommatidia of dark-adapted <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants and wild-type flies clamped at &#x02212;70 mV. Spontaneous bumps are observed in complete darkness at different rates in the various mutants. (B) Histogram plotting the bump frequency of various mutants. Data represent mean values &#x000b1; SEM (error bars) from at least eight different experiments. The difference between the wild-type and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant is not statistically significant (P &#x0003c; 0.1). The statistics include bumps with amplitudes of &#x0003e;2.5 pA, which clearly exceeds the background noise. (C) The bump frequency of various <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants and of wild-type flies was divided by the number of rhabdomeral Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> of each mutant as determined by the immunogold labeling assay (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200506082f6"/></fig><p>To find out whether the high frequency of spontaneous activity is caused by activation of the G protein and not by the spontaneous activation of rhodopsin, we generated a heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutant with highly decreased levels of rhodopsin. To reduce the rhodopsin level in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ flies, we reduced the chromophore level by raising the flies on a carotenoid-deficient medium (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Minke and Kirschfeld, 1979</xref>) for three generations (<italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ Vit A&#x02212;). The metarhodopsin potential (M potential) is a linear electrical manifestation of the level of rhodopsin in fly photoreceptors (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Pak and Lidington, 1974</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Minke and Kirschfeld, 1980</xref>). <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A shows the amplitude of the M potential in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ flies raised on standard medium (top) compared with <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ flies raised on carotenoid-deficient medium (bottom). The virtually complete elimination of M potential after carotenoid deprivation clearly shows that the rhodopsin level was largely reduced in these flies. This conclusion was further supported by measuring the sensitivity to light after carotenoid deprivation, which resulted in a reduction of &#x0223c;300-fold in sensitivity to light without a change in the distribution of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in carotenoid-deprived flies (not depicted). <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> shows that the high rate of spontaneous bumps, which is characteristic of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ flies, was not significantly changed by reduced levels of rhodopsin. This indicates that the high frequency of spontaneous bumps in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutant does not arise from the spontaneous activation of rhodopsin in the dark.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Rhodopsin is not essential for spontaneous bump production in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic><sup>1</sup>/+ mutant.</bold> (A) ERG recordings of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ Vit A&#x02212; responses to a white flash, indicated by arrows. <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ flies that were raised on standard medium displayed M potential similar to that of wild-type flies, whereas the M potential of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ Vit A&#x02212; was abolished. Traces shown are means of 20 consecutive experiments. (B) Whole cell recordings of light-induced currents from isolated ommatidia of dark-adapted <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutants and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ Vit A&#x02212; flies clamped at &#x02212;70 mV. A similar frequency of spontaneous bump was observed in flies reared under both conditions. (C) Histogram plotting the bump frequency of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ Vit A&#x02212; flies in the dark. Data represents mean values &#x000b1; SEM (error bars) from eight different experiments. The difference between <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ Vit A&#x02212; is not statistically significant (P &#x0003c; 0.1). The statistics include only bumps with an amplitude of &#x0003e;2.5 pA, which clearly exceeds the background noise.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200506082f7"/></fig><p>The excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> that was observed in wild-type flies is almost abolished in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ heterozygous mutant (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>); this finding raised the possibility that the excess in wild-type flies prevents the spontaneous activity of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> observed in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ heterozygous mutant. To further test this hypothesis, we crossed the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant with the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant to generate a double mutant containing one copy of the <italic>Gq</italic>&#x003b1;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> gene and one copy of the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> gene (<italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+). The double mutant had about half the level of both Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> as wild-type flies (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> A), restoring the excess G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> that was observed in wild-type flies (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8, B and C</xref>). This mutant showed almost normal sensitivity to light (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) and no spontaneous activity in the dark (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8, D and E</xref>). This result strongly suggests that the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>, rather than the absolute amount of the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit, prevents the spontaneous activation of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptor cells.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>
<bold>The G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> excess over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> is restored in a <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic><sup>1</sup>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic><sup>1</sup>/+ double mutant.</bold> This mutant has almost no spontaneous activity in the dark. (A) <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ double mutants were generated by the crossing of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutants with <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutants. Western blot analysis shows G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> levels in dark-adapted wild type and in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ double mutant. Quantification of the ECL signal shows that the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> level was reduced to &#x0223c;50% and that the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> level was reduced to &#x0223c;60% of wild-type values. The experiment was repeated three times. (B) Western blot analysis of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> (top band) and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> (bottom band) in dark-adapted wild-type and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+;<italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutants shows that the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> is restored in this mutant. Western blots were performed with a mixture of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> antibodies. T, total amount in the cell; P, pellet (membrane); S, supernatant (cytosol). (C) The ratio between G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in different fractions of the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ double mutant is very similar to that of wild-type flies. Data represent mean values &#x000b1; SEM from five different experiments. Data from wild-type flies are the same as in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B and are shown here only for comparison. (D) Whole cell recordings of light-induced currents from isolated ommatidia of dark-adapted <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ double mutants and of wild-type flies clamped at &#x02212;70 mV. Data from wild-type flies are the same as in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A and are shown here only for comparison. (E) Histogram plotting the bump frequency of the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ double mutant compared with that of wild-type flies. Data represent mean values &#x000b1; SEM (error bars) from at least eight different experiments. The difference between wild-type and <italic>Gq</italic>&#x003b1;<italic><sup>1</sup></italic>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ double mutants is not statistically significant (P &#x0003c; 0.1). The statistics include bumps with amplitudes of &#x0003e;2.5 pA, which clearly exceeds the background noise. Data of wild-type flies are the same as in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> B and are shown here only for comparison (note the different bars of <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figs. 6</xref> B and 8 E).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200506082f8"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>The decreased light sensitivity of <italic>Drosophila G</italic>&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> mutants</title><p>When G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> mutants were first isolated (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Dolph et al., 1994</xref>), it was reported that these mutations caused a dramatic decrease in the sensitivity to light, which was ascribed to participation of the &#x003b2; subunit in G protein&#x02013;rhodopsin coupling. Our finding that the decrease in G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants is accompanied by a proportional decrease in Gq&#x003b1; in the rhabdomeral compartment does not support the previously claimed catalytic effect of the &#x003b2; subunit on light sensitivity (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Dolph et al., 1994</xref>). Rather, we conclude that the decrease in light sensitivity of these mutants is caused by the presence of rhodopsin and the major fraction of the G protein &#x003b1; subunit in two different cellular compartments. Clearly, when these two components are present in different cellular locations, the photo-excited rhodopsin is unable to catalyze the exchange of GDP that is bound to the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> for free GTP, and the transduction process is prematurely terminated. The mechanism that underlies the decreased sensitivity to light in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants, therefore, is a structural change in the localization of the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit.</p><p>We also examined how a decrease in the &#x003b1; subunit of the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutant influences membrane attachment and targeting of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits to the rhabdomere. In this case, the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer is soluble and not membrane attached but is still targeted to the rhabdomere. The presence of &#x003b2;&#x003b3; in the rhabdomeral cytosol may be physiologically important for preventing spontaneous activity because the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits are in close proximity to the membrane-bound signaling molecules.</p><p>We have previously shown that the eye-specific Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit translocates from rhabdomeral membranes to the cytosol in response to illumination (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kosloff et al., 2003</xref>). Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> behaves like many other G&#x003b1; subunits, which demonstrate activity-dependent translocation from the membrane to the cytosol (for review see <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Resh, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Manning, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Smotrys and Linder, 2004</xref>). The <italic>Drosophila</italic> eye&#x02013;specific &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer behaves differently from the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit, as it does not show any significant change in its distribution even after prolonged illumination (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). A possible reason for this result might be an interaction between the &#x003b3; subunit of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer and the photoactivated rhodopsin. Such an interaction has been reported for the transducin &#x003b3; subunit and the active form of vertebrate rhodopsin (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kisselev and Downs, 2003</xref>). Both vertebrate and invertebrate photoreceptor cells contain high concentrations of rhodopsin, and even a weak interaction could be significant as a result of mass action. It should be noted, however, that studies in rat retina detected light-dependent movement of both the &#x003b1; and &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits from the rod outer to inner segment, although the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits moved more slowly than the &#x003b1; subunit, suggesting that it might be caused by an interaction of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; complex with phosducin (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Sokolov et al., 2002</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). The different behavior of G&#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits in vertebrate and <italic>Drosophila</italic> might be caused by the difference in stability of the active rhodopsin in these two systems. Whereas vertebrate rhodopsin undergoes bleaching and inactivation, the activated rhodopsin of <italic>Drosophila</italic> is stable for hours (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Minke and Selinger, 1996</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Spontaneous, dark photoreceptor activity in <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> mutants</title><p>A functional hallmark of visual photoreceptors is utmost sensitivity of the capacity for single photon detection. This sensitivity is achieved by very high concentrations of the photoreceptor rhodopsin and its target G protein as well as by the large amplification that is generated during the phototransduction process. High sensitivity also depends on an exceedingly low spontaneous activity (low, dark noise) that sets the limit on the absolute sensitivity of this signaling system. Rhodopsin is the only G protein&#x02013;coupled receptor that has covalently linked 11 cis-retinal that behaves like a &#x0201c;quasi&#x0201d; antagonist in the dark, preventing spontaneous activity. The visual G protein, however, needs special mechanisms to prevent spontaneous activation, but these mechanisms remain unknown.</p><p>The G&#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits are known to bind to G&#x003b1;-GDP switch regions, thereby stabilizing the binding of GDP and suppressing spontaneous receptor-independent activation (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Itoh and Gilman, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Lambright et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Sondek et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Preininger and Hamm, 2004</xref>). To find out whether this interaction is relevant to the <italic>Drosophila</italic> eye&#x02013;specific Gq heterotrimer, whose three-dimensional structure has not been determined, we have constructed a homology model of the DGq<sub>e</sub> heterotrimer (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;) based on the crystal structure of transducin (unpublished data). It appears from the model that the G&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> subunit complex directly contacts the switch I and switch II space regions of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> as was previously reported for other G proteins. Therefore, it is conceivable that the <italic>Drosophila</italic> G&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> complex prevents the spontaneous activation of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> by binding to Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> switch regions. It should be pointed out, however, that the physiological consequences of this effect in vivo have not been described previously. Furthermore, the mechanism that suppresses the spontaneous activity of G proteins under physiological conditions is unknown. In this study, we report (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) the observation of a high frequency of spontaneous activity in the heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutant in which the level of the &#x003b2; subunit was decreased to 50% of its level in wild-type flies. Surprisingly, a further decrease in the level of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>2</sup> and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup> mutants did not increase the frequency of spontaneous activity but rather decreased the frequency. This is easily seen in the most severe mutant (<italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>), which has only 4% of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>, as the spontaneous activity is not much different from the low frequency in wild-type flies. This is probably the reason why the increase in spontaneous activity was not detected in the initial characterization of <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Dolph et al., 1994</xref>). These results indicate that the relationship between the level of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> and the spontaneous activity is not straightforward. We suggest that the observed spontaneous activity of &#x003b2; mutant photoreceptor cells is regulated by two opposite effects of the &#x003b2;&#x003b3; dimer. On the one hand, the decrease in &#x003b2;&#x003b3; levels leaves some G&#x003b1;-GDP unassociated with &#x003b2;&#x003b3;, and this free G&#x003b1;-GDP undergoes spontaneous exchange of the bound GDP for free GTP, leading to spontaneous activity. On the other hand, the decreased level of &#x003b2;&#x003b3; leads to a proportional decrease of G&#x003b1; in the signaling compartment, resulting in a diminished ability to activate the phototransduction process. To test this notion, we normalized the observed rate of spontaneous activity to the number of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunits in the rhabdomeres of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> mutants that lack excess G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>. We found (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> C) similar frequencies of normalized spontaneous activity for all of the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutants, which is consistent with a role of excess &#x003b2;&#x003b3; over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in suppressing spontaneous activity.</p></sec><sec><title>The presence of excess G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptor cell</title><p>One of the unexpected and novel findings of this study is the presence of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> eye&#x02013;specific G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunit in &#x0223c;2.5-fold excess over the Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunit. Because the levels of &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; subunit proteins are maintained independently of one another, unequal levels of these subunits are mechanistically possible. Our calibration curves using purified recombinant G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> and Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> proteins (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> C) verified the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> subunits, which was determined by immunoblot analysis with a mixture of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> antibodies (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A). Furthermore, we have shown that as long as the two antibodies are maintained at saturating concentrations and determinations are performed in the same gel, levels of the &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; subunits are obtained that nicely fit the expected results from gene dosage effects (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A). Furthermore, according to the &#x0201c;two-signal model&#x0201d; for membrane attachment of peripheral membrane proteins, one expects to find equal amounts of membrane-bound Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunits. In accord with this notion, although we found about twofold excess of total G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>, an analysis of these subunits in the membrane-bound fraction gave a ratio of 1:1.</p><p>In the heterozygous <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ mutant, in which there is a reduction of 50% in the level of the &#x003b2; subunit, yielding a &#x003b2;/&#x003b1; ratio of &#x0223c;1, we found a dramatic increase in the spontaneous activity of photoreceptor cells (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figs. 5</xref> and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The critical role of the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> was revealed in the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>q</italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+<italic>;G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>/+ double heterozygous mutant, in which the rate of spontaneous activity was dramatically reduced by restoring the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>. This indicates that the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>, rather than its absolute amount, is important to maintain a low frequency of spontaneous activity. Furthermore, this mutant rules out the possibility that the spontaneous activity we observed was caused by side effects of the <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic> mutation. Altogether, this is the first demonstration of the strategy of excess &#x003b2;&#x003b3; over the &#x003b1; subunit in vivo for the suppression of spontaneous activity at the G protein level.</p><p>Two possible mechanisms can explain how the excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> prevents spontaneous activity. One mechanism could be through participation of the soluble pool of rhabdomeral G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> in accelerating the hydrolysis of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>-GTP if spontaneous exchange occurs. This mechanism is currently under investigation. The second mechanism could be through the stabilization of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub>-GDP, thus preventing the exchange of bound GDP for free GTP. In an insightful, theoretical paper dealing with the spontaneous activity of G proteins by using thermodynamic model simulations, it was found that the concentration of &#x003b2; equal to that of &#x003b1; is barely sufficient to suppress spontaneous activity, whereas a twofold excess of &#x003b2;&#x003b3; over the &#x003b1; subunit produces a large decrease in spontaneous activity (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Onaran et al., 1993</xref>). Altogether, our in vivo studies point to the importance of &#x003b2;&#x003b3; subunits as principle modulators of spontaneous activity and to the relevance of this strategy in vivo.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Fly stocks</title><p>
<italic>Drosophila</italic> of the following strains were used: wild-type, Oregon-R <italic>w</italic> (obtained from W.L. Pak, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN); <italic>Gaq</italic>
<sup>1</sup>, a severe hypomorph for Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> (obtained from C.S. Zuker, University of California, San Diego, San Diego, CA; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Scott et al., 1995</xref>); <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>1</sup>, a severe hypomorph mutant of eye-specific G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>; and <italic>G</italic>&#x003b2;<italic><sub>e</sub></italic>
<sup>2</sup>, a less severe hypomorph mutant of eye-specific G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> (obtained from C.S. Zuker; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Dolph et al., 1994</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Assay of light-dependent G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> localization</title><p>Assay for the light-dependent localization of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> was performed as described previously (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kosloff et al., 2003</xref>). In short, dark-adapted flies were subjected to illumination with activating blue light (18-W white light lamp with a 1-mm&#x02013;thick wide band filter [Schott BG 28; Bes Optics] 12 cm away from the flies) for various durations at 22&#x000b0;C. Termination was performed by moving the flies to 4&#x000b0;C in the dark and promptly separating the fly heads. 10 flies were used for each time point.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of <italic>Drosophila</italic> head homogenate and fractionation</title><p>Heads were separated from 10 flies that were dark adapted overnight (except in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) and homogenized in 1 ml isotonic homogenization buffer (20 mM Tris, pH 7.5, 120 mM KCl, 0.1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 mM PMSF, and 5 mM &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol). Homogenate was either directly precipitated with 5% TCA or subjected to fractionation. Membranes and cytosol fractions were separated by centrifugation (15,800 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C). The pellet was washed and centrifuged again, and the supernatants were combined. Ultracentrifugation at 150,000 <italic>g</italic> for 30 min did not change the distribution of &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; subunits between the fractions. The proteins were precipitated by 5% TCA, ran on SDS-PAGE, and subjected to quantification as described in SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of recombinant <italic>Drosophila</italic> Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> proteins</title><p>cDNA clones of Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> genes were obtained from the Medical Research Council UK gene service. Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> cDNA was amplified and cloned into pQE-80 vector (QIAGEN) that contained an NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal 6&#x000d7; His tag and was expressed in Rosetta bacterial cells (Novagen). The recombinant (His)<sub>6</sub>-Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> protein was then purified on a Ni-Sepharose column (GE Healthcare) and eluted with a 20&#x02013;250-nm imidazole gradient using fast protein liquid chromatography Akta explorer (GE Healthcare).</p><p>G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> cDNA was amplified and cloned into pHis-parallel 1 (pET22) vector (obtained from P. Sheffield, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA) that contained an NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal 6&#x000d7; His tag and was expressed in HMS174 bacterial cells (Novagen). Purified recombinant (His)<sub>6</sub>-G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> was extracted from inclusion bodies by applying 6 M guanidine HCl on a bacterial membrane extract that had been washed three times with 1% Triton X-100. Both proteins were &#x0223c;95% pure as determined by SDS-PAGE and Coomassie blue staining. Recombinant protein concentrations were determined spectrophotometrically by using a calculated molar extinction coefficient of 42,350 for Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and 60,000 for G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> at 280 nm.</p></sec><sec><title>SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting</title><p>Equal protein amounts that were determined by Bradford assay were loaded on the specified gel. For detection of the &#x003b1; or &#x003b2; subunits of DGq<sub>e</sub>, a 10% SDS-PAGE was used. To detect both subunits (&#x003b1; and &#x003b2;) on the same gel, proteins were separated on a gradient 7.5&#x02013;15% SDS-PAGE. For the detection of G&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub>, a 20% SDS-PAGE with 4 M urea was used. The urea was needed for separation of the &#x003b3; subunit from the &#x003b2; subunit. Subsequent to SDS-PAGE separation, proteins were subjected to Western blot analysis using the specified antibodies.</p><p>Two different anti-G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> polyclonal antibodies were made in rabbit as described previously (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Palczewski et al., 1993</xref>). One antibody was made against a peptide from the COOH terminus of the protein (residues 333&#x02013;346), and the other was made against a peptide from the NH<sub>2</sub> terminus (residues 3&#x02013;13).</p><p>For Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> detection, we used anti-Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> polyclonal antibodies that were previously made by us (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kosloff et al., 2003</xref>), and for G&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> detection, rabbit polyclonal antibodies that were directed against the Calliphora G&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> protein were used (obtained from A. Huber, University of Karlsruhe, Karlsruhe, Germany; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Schulz et al., 1999</xref>).</p><p>To determine the ratio between Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> subunits, we performed Western blot analysis using a mixture of anti-Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> and anti-G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> each at a 1:1,000 dilution, which is five times higher than their saturating concentration. To rule out the possibility that the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> excess we observed is caused by the antibodies, we repeated these experiments with the two different G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> antibodies and obtained the same results. To further ensure that the G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> excess over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> was not a result of the antibody concentrations, we repeated this procedure with a higher concentration of anti-Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> or with a twofold dilution (1:2,000) of anti-G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub>. In all of these cases, an excess of G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> over Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> was observed.</p><p>Relative protein amounts on the same gel were determined by quantification of the ECL signal by using the Plus Gel system (LAS-1000; Fuji).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunogold EM</title><p>Immunogold EM was performed as described previously (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kosloff et al., 2003</xref>). All sections were made from flies that were dark adapted overnight. Sections were incubated with either Gq&#x003b1;<sub>e</sub> antibodies (dilution of 1:80) or G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> affinity-purified antibodies (dilution of 1:20). G&#x003b2;<sub>e</sub> antibodies were affinity purified by using Affi-Gel 10 gel (Bio-Rad Laboratories) according to the manufacturer's instructions for anhydrous coupling followed by elution with glycine-HCl, pH 2.5. The secondary antibody used was goat anti&#x02013;rabbit conjugated to 18 nm of gold particles.</p><p>Sections were observed and photographed with a transmission electron microscope (Technai-12; Philips) equipped with a CCD camera (MegaView II; Soft Imaging System) and were visualized with analySIS 3.0 image processing software (Soft Imaging System).</p></sec><sec><title>Electroretinogram (ERG) and M potential</title><p>ERG recordings were performed on intact flies as described previously (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Peretz et al., 1994</xref>). Orange light (OG-590 Schott edge filter; Bes Optics) from a Xenon high pressure lamp (operating at 50 W; model LPS 220; Photon Technology International) was delivered to the compound eye by an optic fiber and was attenuated by natural density filters. The maximal luminous intensity at the eye surface was 12.5 mW/cm<sup>2</sup>. M potential recordings were performed as described previously (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Minke and Kirschfeld, 1980</xref>). In brief, an adapting light of maximal intensity 20-s blue light (Schott BG-28) from the Xenon high pressure lamp was delivered 1 min before each white test stimulus (70 jouls of photographic flash light).</p></sec><sec><title>Whole cell recording</title><p>Dissociated ommatidia were prepared from newly eclosed white-eyed adult flies (&#x0003c;1 h after eclosion; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hardie, 1991</xref>) that were maintained in a 12-h dark/12-h light cycle and kept in the dark 24 h before the experiment. Whole cell patch-clamp recordings were performed as previously described (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Hardie and Minke, 1992</xref>). Signals were amplified with a patch-clamp amplifier (Axopatch 200B; Axon Instruments, Inc.), sampled at 2,000 Hz, and filtered below 1,000 Hz. The bath solution contained 120 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 10 mM <italic>N</italic>-Tris buffer, pH 7.15, 4 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, and 1.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The pipette solution contained 120 mM K gluconate, 2 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 10 mM <italic>N</italic>-Tris buffer, pH 7.15, 4 mM MgATP, 0.4 mM Na<sub>2</sub>GTP, and 1 mM NAD<sup>+</sup>.</p><p>Transillumination of the halogen light source (100 W) was used as previously described (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Peretz et al., 1994</xref>). The orange stimulating light (Schott OG-590) was applied via a condenser lens (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.) and was attenuated by neutral density filters.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank R. Timberg and N. Feinstein from the Electron Microscopy unit (Life Sciences faculty at The Hebrew University) for help with EM; T. Danieli and M. Lebendiker (Wolfson Center for Applied Structural Biology) for help with expression and purification of the recombinant DGq subunits; C. Zuker and W.L. Pak for specific <italic>Drosophila</italic> mutants; and A. Huber for the Calliphora G&#x003b3;<sub>e</sub> antibodies. We thank R. Korenberg, M. Kosloff, and Y. Litvak for carefully reading the manuscript and for helpful discussions.</p><p>This work was supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health (EY-03529 to B. Minke and Z. Selinger), the Israel Science Foundation (to Z. Selinger and B. Minke), the German-Israel Foundation (to B. Minke), and the Minerva Foundation (to B. Minke and Z. Selinger).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cassel, D., and Z. Selinger. <year>1978</year>. Mechanism of adenylate cyclase activation through the beta-adrenergic receptor: catecholamine-induced displacement of bound GDP by GTP. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>4155</fpage>&#x02013;4159.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">212737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cassel, D., H. Levkovitz, and Z. Selinger. <year>1977</year>. The regulatory GTPase cycle of turkey erythrocyte adenylate cyclase. <source>J. Cyclic Nucleotide Res.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;406.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">203612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chen, C.A., and D.R. Manning. <year>2001</year>. Regulation of G proteins by covalent modification. <source>Oncogene.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1643</fpage>&#x02013;1652.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11313912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cronin, M.A., F. Diao, and S. Tsunoda. <year>2004</year>. Light-dependent subcellular translocation of Gqalpha in <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptors is facilitated by the photoreceptor-specific myosin III NINAC. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>4797</fpage>&#x02013;4806.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15340015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Degtyarev, M.Y., A.M. Spiegel, and T.L. Jones. <year>1994</year>. Palmitoylation of a G protein &#x003b1;i subunit requires membrane localization not myristoylation. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>30898</fpage>&#x02013;30903.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7983022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Devary, O., O. Heichal, A. Blumenfeld, D. Cassel, E. Suss, S. Barash, C.T. Rubinstein, B. Minke, and Z. Selinger. <year>1987</year>. Coupling of photoexcited rhodopsin to inositol phospholipid hydrolysis in fly photoreceptors. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>6939</fpage>&#x02013;6943.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3116547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dolph, P.J., H. Man-Son-Hing, S. Yarfitz, N.J. Colley, J.R. Deer, M. Spencer, J.B. Hurley, and C.S. Zuker. <year>1994</year>. An eye-specific G&#x003b2; subunit essential for termination of the phototransduction cascade. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>370</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;61.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8015606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Evanko, D.S., M.M. Thiyagarajan, and P.B. Wedegaertner. <year>2000</year>. Interaction with G&#x003b2;&#x003b3; is required for membrane targeting and palmitoylation of G&#x003b1;s and G&#x003b1;q. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>1327</fpage>&#x02013;1336.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10625681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Evanko, D.S., M.M. Thiyagarajan, D.P. Siderovski, and P.B. Wedegaertner. <year>2001</year>. Gbeta gamma isoforms selectively rescue plasma membrane localization and palmitoylation of mutant Galphas and Galphaq. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>23945</fpage>&#x02013;23953.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11294873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fishburn, C.S., S.K. Pollitt, and H.R. Bourne. <year>2000</year>. Localization of a peripheral membrane protein: Gbetagamma targets Galpha(Z). <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>1085</fpage>&#x02013;1090.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10655488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gotta, M., and J. Ahringer. <year>2001</year>. Distinct roles for Galpha and Gbetagamma in regulating spindle position and orientation in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> embryos. <source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;300.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11231580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hardie, R.C. <year>1991</year>. Voltage-sensitive potassium channels in <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptors. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>3079</fpage>&#x02013;3095.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1941075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hardie, R.C., and B. Minke. <year>1992</year>. The trp gene is essential for a light-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel in <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptors. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>643</fpage>&#x02013;651.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1314617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hardie, R.C., and P. Raghu. <year>2001</year>. Visual transduction in <italic>Drosophila</italic>. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>413</volume>:<fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;193.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11557987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Henderson, S.R., H. Reuss, and R.C. Hardie. <year>2000</year>. Single photon responses in <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptors and their regulation by Ca<sup>2+</sup>. <source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>524</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;194.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Itoh, H., and A.G. Gilman. <year>1991</year>. Expression and analysis of Gs alpha mutants with decreased ability to activate adenylylcyclase. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>266</volume>:<fpage>16226</fpage>&#x02013;16231.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1651937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kisselev, O.G., and M.A. Downs. <year>2003</year>. Rhodopsin controls a conformational switch on the transducin gamma subunit. <source>Structure (Camb).</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;373.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12679015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kosloff, M., N. Elia, and Z. Selinger. <year>2002</year>. Structural homology discloses a bifunctional structural motif at the N-termini of G alpha proteins. <source>Biochemistry.</source>
<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>14518</fpage>&#x02013;14523.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12463750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kosloff, M., N. Elia, T. Joel-Almagor, R. Timberg, T.D. Zars, D.R. Hyde, B. Minke, and Z. Selinger. <year>2003</year>. Regulation of light-dependent Gqalpha translocation and morphological changes in fly photoreceptors. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;468.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12554647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lambright, D.G., J. Sondek, A. Bohm, N.P. Skiba, H.E. Hamm, and P.B. Sigler. <year>1996</year>. The 2.0 A crystal structure of a heterotrimeric G protein. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>379</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;319.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8552184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Michaelson, D., I. Ahearn, M. Bergo, S. Young, and M. Philips. <year>2002</year>. Membrane trafficking of heterotrimeric G proteins via the endoplasmic reticulum and Golgi. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>3294</fpage>&#x02013;3302.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12221133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Minke, B., and K. Kirschfeld. <year>1979</year>. The contribution of a sensitizing pigment to the photosensitivity spectra of fly rhodopsin and metarhodopsin. <source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;540.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">458418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Minke, B., and K. Kirschfeld. <year>1980</year>. Fast electrical potentials arising from activation of metarhodopsin in the fly. <source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;402.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7381425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Minke, B., and Z. Selinger. <year>1996</year>. The roles of trp and calcium in regulating photoreceptor function in <italic>Drosophila</italic>. <source>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;466.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8794093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Minke, B., and R.C. Hardie. 2000. Genetic dissection of <italic>Drosophila</italic> phototransduction. Molecular Mechanisms in Visual Transduction. D.G. Stavenga, W.J. DeGrip, and E.N. Pugh Jr., editors. Elsevier Science Publishing Co. Inc., NY. 449&#x02013;525.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Murray, D., S. McLaughlin, and B. Honig. <year>2001</year>. The role of electrostatic interactions in the regulation of the membrane association of G protein beta gamma heterodimers. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>45153</fpage>&#x02013;45159.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11557749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Onaran, H.O., T. Costa, and D. Rodbard. <year>1993</year>. Beta gamma subunits of guanine nucleotide-binding proteins and regulation of spontaneous receptor activity: thermodynamic model for the interaction between receptors and guanine nucleotide-binding protein subunits. <source>Mol. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;256.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8381511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pak, W.L., and K.J. Lidington. <year>1974</year>. Fast electrical potential from a long-lived, long-wavelength photoproduct of fly visual pigment. <source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>740</fpage>&#x02013;756.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4829527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Palczewski, K., J. Buczylko, L. Lebioda, J.W. Crabb, and A.S. Polans. <year>1993</year>. Identification of the N-terminal region in rhodopsin kinase involved in its interaction with rhodopsin. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>268</volume>:<fpage>6004</fpage>&#x02013;6013.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8383684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Peretz, A., E. Suss-Toby, A. Rom-Glas, A. Arnon, R. Payne, and B. Minke. <year>1994</year>. The light response of <italic>Drosophila</italic> photoreceptors is accompanied by an increase in cellular calcium: effects of specific mutations. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1257</fpage>&#x02013;1267.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8011336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Phillips, W.J., and R.A. Cerione. <year>1992</year>. Rhodopsin/transducin interactions. I. Characterization of the binding of the transducin-beta gamma subunit complex to rhodopsin using fluorescence spectroscopy. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>267</volume>:<fpage>17032</fpage>&#x02013;17039.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1512242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Preininger, A.M., and H.E. Hamm. 2004. G protein signaling: insights from new structures. <italic>Sci. STKE.</italic>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/stke.2182004re3</pub-id>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14762218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Resh, M.D. <year>1999</year>. Fatty acylation of proteins: new insights into membrane targeting of myristoylated and palmitoylated proteins. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta.</source>
<volume>1451</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;16.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10446384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schulz, S., A. Huber, K. Schwab, and R. Paulsen. <year>1999</year>. A novel Ggamma isolated from <italic>Drosophila</italic> constitutes a visual G protein gamma subunit of the fly compound eye. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>37605</fpage>&#x02013;37610.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10608815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Scott, K., A. Becker, Y. Sun, R. Hardy, and C. Zuker. <year>1995</year>. Gq&#x003b1; protein function in vivo: genetic dissection of its role in photoreceptor cell physiology. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>919</fpage>&#x02013;927.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7576640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smotrys, J.E., and M.E. Linder. <year>2004</year>. Palmitoylation of intracellular signaling proteins: regulation and function. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;587.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15189153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Snow, B.E., A.M. Krumins, G.M. Brothers, S.F. Lee, M.A. Wall, S. Chung, J. Mangion, S. Arya, A.G. Gilman, and D.P. Siderovski. <year>1998</year>. A G protein gamma subunit-like domain shared between RGS11 and other RGS proteins specifies binding to Gbeta5 subunits. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>13307</fpage>&#x02013;13312.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9789084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sokolov, M., A.L. Lyubarsky, K.J. Strissel, A.B. Savchenko, V.I. Govardovskii, E.N. Pugh, and V.Y. Arshavsky. <year>2002</year>. Massive light-driven translocation of transducin between the two major compartments of rod cells. A novel mechanism of light adaptation. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;106.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11931744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sokolov, M., K.J. Strissel, I.B. Leskov, N.A. Michaud, V.I. Govardovskii, and V.Y. Arshavsky. <year>2004</year>. Phosducin facilitates light-driven transducin translocation in rod photoreceptors. Evidence from the phosducin knockout mouse. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>19149</fpage>&#x02013;19156.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14973130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sondek, J., A. Bohm, D.G. Lambright, H.E. Hamm, and P.B. Sigler. <year>1996</year>. Crystal structure of a G-protein beta gamma dimer at 2.1A resolution. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>379</volume>:<fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;374.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8552196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Takida, S., and P.B. Wedegaertner. <year>2003</year>. Heterotrimer formation, together with isoprenylation, is required for plasma membrane targeting of G&#x003b2;&#x003b3;. <source>J Biol Chem.</source>
<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>17284</fpage>&#x02013;17290.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wedegaertner, P.B. <year>1998</year>. Lipid modifications and membrane targeting of G&#x003b1;. <source>Biol. Signals Recept.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;135.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9629464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
