<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14745001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1360214</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200311079</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200311079</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Noninvasive two-photon imaging reveals retinyl ester storage structures in the eye</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Imanishi</surname><given-names>Yoshikazu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3b856f0N0x337d2e8">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Batten</surname><given-names>Matthew L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3b856f0N0x337d2e8">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Piston</surname><given-names>David W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baehr</surname><given-names>Wolfgang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palczewski</surname><given-names>Krzysztof</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3b856f0N0x337d2e8">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3b856f0N0x337d2e8">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3b856f0N0x337d2e8">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x3b856f0N0x337d2e8">
<label>1</label>Departments of Ophthalmology, <label>2</label>Pharmacology, and <label>3</label>Chemistry, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98195</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>Department of Molecular Physiology and Biophysics, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN 37232</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>Departments of Ophthalmology, Biology, and Neurobiology and Anatomy, University of Utah Health Science Center, Salt Lake City, UT 84112</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Krzysztof Palczewski, Dept. of Ophthalmology, University of Washington, 1959 NE Pacific St., Box 356485, Seattle, WA 98195-6485. Tel.: (206) 543-9074. Fax: (206) 221-6784. email: <email>palczews@u.washington.edu</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>164</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Visual sensation in vertebrates is triggered when light strikes retinal photoreceptor cells causing photoisomerization of the rhodopsin chromophore 11-cis-retinal to all-trans-retinal. The regeneration of preillumination conditions of the photoreceptor cells requires formation of 11-cis-retinal in the adjacent retinal pigment epithelium (RPE). Using the intrinsic fluorescence of all-trans-retinyl esters, noninvasive two-photon microscopy revealed previously uncharacterized structures (6.9 &#x000b1; 1.1 &#x003bc;m in length and 0.8 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;m in diameter) distinct from other cellular organelles, termed the retinyl ester storage particles (RESTs), or retinosomes. These structures form autonomous all-trans-retinyl ester-rich intracellular compartments distinct from other organelles and colocalize with adipose differentiation-related protein. As demonstrated by in vivo experiments using wild-type mice, the RESTs participate in 11-cis-retinal formation. RESTs accumulate in <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice incapable of carrying out the enzymatic isomerization, and correspondingly, are absent in the eyes of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice deficient in retinyl ester synthesis. These results indicate that RESTs located close to the RPE plasma membrane are essential components in 11-cis-retinal production.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>retinoid cycle; photoreceptor cells; two-photon microscopy; retinal pigment epithelial cells; rhodopsin</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>The online version of this article includes supplemental material.</p></fn><fn><p>Abbreviations used in this paper: 3-D, three-dimensional; ADRP, adipose differentiation-related protein; CRALBP, cellular retinaldehyde-binding protein; LRAT, lecithin:retinol acyltransferase; REST, retinyl ester storage particle; ROS, rod outer segment; RPE, retinal pigment epithelium; RPE65, an RPE-specific 65-kD protein.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Metabolic transformations of retinoids within the retinal photoreceptor and retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) are responsible for the production of the chromophore essential for vision, 11-cis-retinal (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2001</xref>). Within the RPE, all-trans-retinol (vitamin A), a product of photoisomerized and reduced 11-cis-retinal, is esterified with fatty acids in a reaction catalyzed by lecithin:retinol acyltransferase (LRAT; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Saari et al., 1993</xref>). LRAT was identified on the molecular level as a 25-kD protein (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz et al., 1999</xref>) that is expressed in several tissues, including liver and the RPE (for review see <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2000</xref>). All-trans-retinyl esters are intermediate compounds in a pathway (&#x0201c;retinoid cycle&#x0201d;) that recycles 11-cis-retinal, the chromophore of the visual pigments of rod and cone photoreceptors (for review see <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bok, 1985</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2001</xref>). All-trans-retinyl esters have been suggested to be the substrate for a putative isomerohydrolase in the RPE (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Rando, 1991</xref>) and for a retinyl ester hydrolase that produces all-trans-retinol, a substrate for the putative isomerase (for review see <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2000</xref>). Regardless of the enzymatic pathway, 11-cis-retinol is produced, oxidized to 11-cis-retinal, and exported to the photoreceptors where it recombines with opsins to form 11-cis-retinylidene-opsins (rhodopsin, and cone pigments; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; for review see <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Filipek et al., 2003</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Chemistry of retinoid cycle reactions in the vertebrate retina.</bold> Retinoid cycle reactions were reviewed previously (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2001</xref>). In the rod outer segment (ROS), light causes the isomerization (reaction a) of the rhodopsin chromophore, 11-cis-retinylidene (1), to all-trans-retinylidene. All-trans-retinal (2) is hydrolyzed and then reduced (reaction b) in the reaction catalyzed by all<italic>-</italic>trans-retinal&#x02013;specific RDH(s). All-trans-retinol (3) diffuses to the RPE, where it is esterified by LRAT (reaction c) to all-trans-retinyl esters (4). Retinyl esters form RESTs (g). All-trans-retinyl esters can be hydrolyzed by a yet-unidentified retinyl ester hydrolase (reaction h) generating all-trans-retinol. All-trans-retinol (3) or its esters (4) is isomerized to 11-cis-retinol (5) in a reaction that involves an RPE-abundant protein, termed RPE65 (incompletely defined reactions d or i). 11-cis-retinol is then oxidized by 11-cis-RDH and other dehydrogenases to 11-cis-retinal (6) (reaction e) to complete the cycle (modified version from <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Jang et al., 2000</xref>). 11-cis-retinal diffuses back to the ROS, where it recombines with opsin to reform rhodopsin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200311079f1"/></fig><p>Defects in the retinoid cycle may lead to blinding disorders, such as retinitis pigmentosa or macular degeneration (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Rattner et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Dryja, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Baehr et al., 2003</xref>). Among these, the inherited early onset dystrophies are collectively called Leber congenital amaurosis (LCA). LCA is a group of genetically heterogeneous diseases that involves, among others, mutations in LRAT and RPE-specific 65-kD protein (RPE65) genes (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Gu et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Marlhens et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Morimura et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Perrault et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Thompson et al., 2001</xref>). Animal models of these specific LCA were generated (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Redmond et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Batten et al., 2003</xref>) to address functional consequences of the targeted gene disruption on the retinoid metabolism. Recently, somatic gene therapy and pharmacological intervention were successful in restoration of vision in the dog and mouse animal models of LCA, respectively, with the nonfunctional RPE65 gene (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Van Hooser et al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Acland et al., 2001</xref>).</p><p>Although several retinoid metabolites are generated during regeneration of 11-cis-retinal, only retinol and retinyl esters show a weak intrinsic fluorescence (excitation &#x003bb; at &#x0223c;320 nm; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Sears and Kaplan, 1989</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Garwin and Saari, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kuksa et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Zipfel et al., 2003</xref>). Simultaneous absorption of two photons and excitation of intrinsic fluorophores, in conjunction with laser scanning fluorescence microscopy (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Denk et al., 1990</xref>; <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bennett et al., 1996</xref>), has been exploited to generate three-dimensional (3-D) temporal and spectral-resolved images of cells, tissues, or organs (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Euler et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2003</xref>). Here, infrared two-photon microscopy was used to monitor changes in the distribution of vitamin A and its metabolites in the intact mouse eye without mechanical disruption of the essential close contacts between the photoreceptor and the RPE, photobleaching of rhodopsin, or photodamage to the tissue. The retinyl ester storage structures increased in the RPE of wild-type mice exposed to light or in an age-dependent manner in light- and dark-adapted <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice incapable of carrying out the enzymatic isomerization, and they were absent in the eyes of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice deficient in vitamin A. Thus, two-photon microscopy revealed changes in the retinyl ester pool in normal and pathological states in vivo, without disruption of the fragile RPE&#x02013;retina interface.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Identification of retinyl ester storage particles in wild-type RPE</title><p>Two-photon microscopy, with excitation at &#x003bb; = 730 nm directly through the sclera of the dissected mouse eye, revealed a clear image of fluorescent compartments &#x0223c;50 &#x003bc;m (390&#x02013;545-nm emission; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A, red pseudocolor) and within &#x0223c;1&#x02013;40 &#x003bc;m (560&#x02013;700-nm emission) from the surface of the sclera (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A, green pseudocolor). Taking advantage of the layered structure of the eye (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Kolb et al., 2001</xref>), the two fluorescent compartments were localized within the RPE (red) and the sclera (green). Localization of these compartments was deduced based on morphological criteria, such as appropriate distances verified by histological sectioning (unpublished data), differences in the appearance of nuclei in each layer (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A, right column), and on the appearance of the capillaries in the choroid. RPE fluorescence in the unstained eyecup displayed unique elongated structures perpendicular to the cell layer with a length of 6.9 &#x000b1; 1.1 &#x003bc;m, a diameter of 0.8 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;m, and frequency of 36.2 &#x000b1; 2.2 per double-nuclei cells (<italic>n</italic> = 200; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B, a). 3-D projections of these fluorescent structures present in the RPE showed particular localization and remarkable symmetry (Video 1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200311079/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200311079/DC1</ext-link>). Antibodies against RPE-dominant transmembrane 11-cis-retinol dehydrogenase (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B, b), membrane-associated RPE65 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B, c), and soluble cellular retinaldehyde-binding protein (CRALBP; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B, d) confirmed the intracellular position of the autofluorescent structures. 3-D projections of these fluorescent structures (red) and anti-11-cis-retinol dehydrogenase immunostaining (green) in the RPE demonstrated that they did not colocalize (Video 2). Similarly, 3-D projections of these structures (red) and anti-RPE65 immunostaining (green) in the RPE showed that they are present in nonoverlapping cellular compartments (Video 3).</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Identification of autofluorescent structures in the wild-type mouse RPE.</bold> (A) Fluorescence emission from the isolated intact mouse eye. Two fluorescence emissions (390&#x02013;545 nm in red pseudocolor and 560&#x02013;700 nm in green pseudocolor) were observed when excited by a 730-nm mode-locked Ti:Sapphire laser. The right column shows tangential optical sections of the eyecup stained by Hoechst 33342. Note the circular structures in the RPE panel. 4-wk-old mice were used in all experiments. (B) Arrangement of RESTs in the RPE. A projection of the highly fluorescent structures in the RPE in the eyecup that are aligned perpendicularly to the RPE cell layer and that we termed RESTs, or retinosomes (a). The immunolocalization of 11-cis-retinol dehydrogenase (b, green), RPE65 (c, green) and CRALBP (d) in comparison to the autofluorescent RESTs (red). (C) Flash-dependent changes in fluorescence and all-trans-retinol/all-trans-retinyl esters in the RPE cell layer in isolated eyes. Top: a row of images showing the optical sections of the retina, radial to the ocular tissue. The RPE fluorescence (a.u., arbitrary unit) was quantified in a time-dependent manner. The numbers refer to minutes after flash. Middle and bottom graphs show the quantified fluorescence from retinoids and retinoid analysis by HPLC (all-trans-retinol and all-trans-retinyl esters; mean &#x000b1; SD, <italic>n</italic> = 3), respectively. Dashed lines indicate the half-time formation of RESTs and the increase in all-trans-retinol and all-trans-retinyl esters. On the right, the light-dependent changes in the fluorescent signal in different subcellular compartments. (D) Supplementation of all-trans-retinol to the RPE cell layer in the eyecup. (a) The single RPE layer before addition of all-trans-retinol. (b) The RPE after exposure to all-trans-retinol for 2 min. (c) Changes in averaged fluorescence intensity under the same conditions as in a and b (mean &#x000b1; SD, <italic>n</italic> = 30 for three independent measurements). (d) Amount of retinyl ester in eyecup samples of c as quantified by normal phase HPLC (mean &#x000b1; SD, <italic>n</italic> = 3). Bars, 20 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200311079f2"/></fig><p>Bleaching of rhodopsin in the intact rod-dominant mouse eye led to time-dependent increase in fluorescence within the RPE layer with the half-time &#x003c4;<sub>1/2</sub> = 10 min (<italic>n</italic> = 3), without significant changes within the rod outer segments (ROSs; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C, top two left panels). The change paralleled a light-dependent increase in the formation of all-trans-retinol and all-trans-retinyl esters (&#x003c4;<sub>1/2</sub> = 10 min; <italic>n</italic> = 3) in the RPE as determined by normal phase HPLC (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C, bottom left; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Van Hooser et al., 2002</xref>), suggesting these structures contain retinoids. The fluorescence signal localized specifically to these subcellular structures, which we termed retinyl ester storage particles (RESTs), or retinosomes. The fluorescence signal increase coincided with formation of all-trans-retinol/all-trans-retinyl esters (unpublished data). The results for a 60-min incubation in the dark are shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C (right). These data are consistent with earlier observations that the visual cycle does not proceed to the 11-cis-retinoid production in the dissected eyes and eyecups (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Palczewski et al., 1999</xref>), and that under physiological temperature- and oxygen/carbonated-control conditions the reaction mostly proceeds to all-trans-retinyl ester formation (&#x0223c;65%; unpublished data). When the eyecups were incubated with a soluble complex of vitamin A ((2-hydroxypropyl)-&#x003b2;-cyclodextrin&#x000b7;all-trans-retinol), significant increases in fluorescence and all-trans-retinyl ester formation were observed in these structures (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> D, b). The increases in the fluorescence intensity coincided with increases of the retinyl ester content (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> D, c and d), strengthening the argument that these structures contain the fluorescent retinyl esters. No tissue damage was observed after two-photon excitation, as determined by the analysis of histological sections.</p></sec><sec><title>Colocalization of RESTs with adipose differentiation-related protein in wild-type RPE</title><p>Fluorescent RESTs are not a part of Golgi (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> a), mitochondria (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> b), a majority of lysosomes (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> c), the plasma membrane (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> d), or the ER (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> e). RESTs also did not colocalize with autofluorescent A2E, a component of lipofuscin, an age-related by-product of ROS phagocytosis by the RPE (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2000</xref>; unpublished data). NADH and NADPH were poorly excited at 730 nm and were not observed in our experiments, as demonstrated by the lack of mitochondrial fluorescence (see also <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kuksa et al., 2003</xref>). The RESTs did not colocalize with peroxisomes, as visualized by immunofluorescence techniques with catalase, a marker of these organelles (unpublished data). However, using immunocytochemistry, we found that adipose differentiation-related protein (ADRP) colocalizes with the RESTs (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> f). ADRP was shown previously to localize at the vicinity of the plasma membrane involved in the formation and stabilization of lipid droplets (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Gao and Serrero, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Targett-Adams et al., 2003</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Organelle-autonomous localization of RESTs in the wild-type RPE, REST colocalization with ADRP, and the REST ultrastructure.</bold> (a&#x02013;e) Localization of RESTs (red) and other RPE subcellular organelles in the mouse eyecup. (a) Golgi apparatus (light blue); b, mitochondria (green); c, acidic organelles including lysosomes (green); d, plasma membranes (green); e, ER (green); f, colocalization of ADRP and RESTs (yellow) in fixed mouse eyecup. Inset: top, REST localization (red); bottom, immunolocalization of ADRP (green). (g&#x02013;i) Subcellular organization of the RPE by EM. (g) Mouse eyes were fixed 30 min after bleaching of rhodopsin to facilitate all-trans-retinyl ester accumulation in the RPE. Lipid droplet-like structures (&#x0223c;1 &#x003bc;m in the diameter) are often observed close to the cell boundary (arrows). (h) Dark-adapted mouse eye. Lipid droplet-like structures are smaller (arrows) than those observed in g. (i) Higher magnification of the image shown in g. RESTs are indicated by arrows. An electron-dense coating and membranes surrounded the lipid-like structure. Bars: 20 &#x003bc;m (a&#x02013;f), 10 &#x003bc;m (g and h), 1 &#x003bc;m (i).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200311079f3"/></fig><p>Tangential sections of the RPE, analyzed by EM, showed that most of the mouse RPE contained two nuclei (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, g and h</xref>), as observed in rats (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Owaribe et al., 1988</xref>). Moreover, vacuole-like structures with translucent inclusions were often present close to the boundary of the cells (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, g and h</xref>). After flash stimulation of rhodopsin (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> g), the vacuole-like structures were more inflated compared with those kept in the dark (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> h). The diameters of the structures were &#x0223c;1 &#x003bc;m after flash stimulation (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> i). Electron-dense vesicles observed throughout the cell were membrane inclusions (ingested ROS) or peroxisomes. The location, size, and frequency of the vacuole-like structures corresponded with RESTs observed by two-photon microscopy, suggesting that RESTs may incorporate retinyl esters, thereby increasing their volume.</p></sec><sec><title>RESTs in normal and mutant RPE</title><p>If RESTs participate in production of 11-cis-retinal, no light-dependent changes in two-photon excited autofluorescence should be observed in the RPE of mice lacking a functional RPE65 gene, which is essential for chromophore regeneration (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Redmond et al., 1998</xref>). Although the wild-type RPE increased their fluorescence intensity (arbitrary unit) from 0.56 &#x000b1; 0.28 to 1.52 &#x000b1; 0.56 after an intense 10-ms flash that bleached &#x0223c;60% of the pigment (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A, a, b, and g), these changes were not observed in the RPE of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A, c, d, and g). Consistently, the amounts of all-trans-retinyl esters increased from 71.4 &#x000b1; 3.3 to 274.2 &#x000b1; 32.4 pmol for wild-type mice, whereas for the eyes of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice the amount was 207.6 &#x000b1; 19.5 pmol for pre-flash conditions and comparable to 192.3 &#x000b1; 6.6 pmol post-flash (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A, g).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>
<bold>RESTs in the RPE of <italic>Rpe65</italic></bold>
<sup>&#x02212;<bold>/</bold>&#x02212;</sup>
<bold> and <italic>Lrat</italic></bold>
<sup>&#x02212;<bold>/</bold>&#x02212;</sup>
<bold> mice.</bold> (A) The deficiency of light-induced changes of RESTs in the <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mouse eyes. (a and b) RPE autofluorescence in 6-wk-old wild-type mouse before flash stimulation and 30 min after bleaching of rhodopsin, respectively. (c and d) RPE autofluorescence in 3-wk-old <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mouse before flash and after flash stimulation, respectively. (e and f) The RPE cell layer of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mouse before flash and after flash stimulation, respectively. (g) Quantitative determination of all-trans-retinyl esters in a mouse eye by HPLC. Gray bars represent the total amount of all-trans-retinyl ester per eye (left y-axis) under each genetic background at the indicated time after flash stimulation of rhodopsin. Error bars represent mean &#x000b1; SD (<italic>n</italic> = 30 from three mouse eyes). Black bars on the right show the intensity of RPE autofluorescence (right y-axis) from mice of different genetic backgrounds. (B) Age-dependent accumulation of all-trans-retinyl esters into RESTs in the RPE of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. At the age of 1 wk (a), the formation of RESTs is observed as a slight accumulation of all-trans-retinyl esters (a). At the age of 6 wk (b), strong accumulation of all-trans-retinyl esters in RESTs and formation of lipid droplets of all-trans-retinyl esters are observed. 14-wk-old mice (c) show additional fluorophore accumulation in RESTs and form bigger lipid droplets compared with those in 6-wk-old animals. (d) Quantified fluorescence and the level of all-trans-retinyl esters in the eyes of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice at the given age. Gray bars indicate the quantified all-trans-retinyl esters in the eyes of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice of different age. Black bars indicate the quantified fluorescence. The measurements were performed as described in A (g). Bars, 20 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200311079f4"/></fig><p>LRAT could be the enzyme essential for trapping retinoids from bleached photoreceptors and for removing them from the circulation (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2001</xref>). Hence, <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were generated and analyzed (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Batten et al., 2003</xref>). Total retinoid analyses revealed that the eyes of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice contained residual amounts of retinoids (&#x0223c;8.3 pmol/eye in 4-wk-old mice) and no functional rhodopsin (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Batten et al., 2003</xref>). For comparison, &#x0223c;500 pmol retinoid/eye was present in the wild-type or <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> littermates, mostly in opsin-bound 11-cis-retinylidene form. Because only trace amounts of all-trans-retinol and retinyl esters were present in the RPE of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A, g; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Batten et al., 2003</xref>), the RESTs are not formed (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A, e and f). No light-dependent changes in the retinoid levels as assayed by fluorescence or HPLC were observed in the eyes of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A, e&#x02013;g).</p><p>In the RPE of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, age-dependent increase in formation of lipid droplet-like structures filled with a translucent lipid-like substance was attributed to all-trans-retinyl ester accumulation (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Van Hooser et al., 2002</xref>). Therefore, we investigated REST formation as a function of age in the RPE of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Here, a systematic increase of retinoids was observed with increasing age in the RPE of these mice (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B). The increase in RPE fluorescence intensity paralleled the increase in the all-trans-retinyl ester accumulation (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B, d) and formation of a spherical body, morphologically distinct from normal RESTs, within the RPE. These results provide the first direct evidence that the &#x0201c;oil-droplets&#x0201d; (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Redmond et al., 1998</xref>) are formed, at least in part, from all-trans-retinyl esters.</p></sec><sec><title>RESTs and flow of retinoids in the retinoid cycle</title><p>To observe directly whether RESTs participate in the flow of retinoids, we extended our analyses to live mice. We acquired fluorescence images at the periphery of the retina directly through the sclera, using thoroughly dark-adapted and anesthetized mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A). After a light flash, the change in the fluorescence intensity of RESTs paralleled the formation of all-trans-retinyl esters in the RPE of those mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B). The retinyl ester pool peaked at 30 min (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B, b) and the regeneration of 11-cis-retinal is nearly completed within 60 min (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Saari et al., 1998</xref>), corresponding to formation of 11-cis-retinal and disappearance of all-trans-retinal (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B, c). On light stimulation, the number of RESTs appeared to be similar as in the RPE of the dark-adapted mice, but their intensity increased significantly.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>
<bold>RESTs participate in 11-cis-retinal production in mice.</bold> (A) Two-photon vitamin A imaging in the anesthetized wild-type mouse. Images were collected at the peripheral area of the RPE. Intense flashes were given to the eye and images were collected at the given times after flash. The area below a blood vessel shows weaker fluorescence (arrows). Bar, 20 &#x003bc;m. (B) Comparison of fluorescent intensity and the amount of retinoids. (a) Time course of transient changes in fluorescent intensity. Fluorescence was measured for randomly chosen areas. (b and c) Each retinoid species (percentage of total retinoid) was quantified by normal phase HPLC. (b) Changes in the transient amount of all-trans-retinyl esters were observed in parallel to the fluorescent intensity quantified in panel a. All-trans-retinol increased slightly 15 min after flash stimulation and then decreased. (c) Increase of 11-cis-retinal and decay of all-trans-retinal level after flash stimulation. The level of individual retinoid is expressed as a percentage of the total retinoids (sum of retinals, retinols, and retinyl esters). (C) Lack of REST formation in the RPE of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice gavaged with 9-cis-retinal. <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were gavaged as described previously (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Van Hooser et al., 2000</xref>) with 2.5 mg of 9-cis-retinal. After 36 h in the dark, mice were exposed to intense flash that bleached &#x0223c;30% of the visual pigment. One group was analyzed for the retinoid content 1 min after flashes, and the other group was analyzed 3 h after flash followed by dark adaptation (top absorption profile, dark-adapted; middle absorption profile, 1 min after flash; bottom absorption profile, 3 h after flash). Under the same conditions, mice were also analyzed by two-photon microscopy to image the RPE after bleach. Note the lack of ester formation (inset) and REST formation (right panels). Bar, 20 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200311079f5"/></fig><p>To test whether RESTs are essential for the isomerization process, we gavaged <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with 9-cis-retinal, as described previously for <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Van Hooser et al., 2002</xref>). 9-cis-retinal recombined with opsin, forming isorhodopsin, as demonstrated by the analysis of retinoids in the eye, UV-Vis spectroscopy of the detergent extract from the eye, and isolation of isorhodopsin by immunoaffinity chromatography (unpublished data). After bleach, 9-cis-retinal bound to opsin was converted to all-trans-retinal. Without formation of retinyl ester, and hence RESTs, all-trans-retinal/all-trans-retinol were quickly lost from the eye (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> C). Accordingly, no formation of 11-cis-retinal (with different chromatographic and spectral properties from 9-cis-retinal) was observed. These results demonstrate that RESTs participate in retinoid storage and restoration of the chromophore after photobleaching.</p></sec><sec><title>RESTs and ADRP in mutant animals</title><p>Because ADRP colocalized with the RESTs (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> f), we investigated whether its expression and localization is altered in genetically engineered mice that have enhanced accumulation of all-trans-retinyl esters or lack them entirely. The overaccumulation of all-trans-retinyl esters in the RPE of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice coincided with accumulation of ADRP in the RESTs as observed in the eyes of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. In contrast, ADRP was present throughout the RPE cytoplasm of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice lacking retinyl esters (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6, A and B</xref>). In the RPE cells of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, ADRP was expressed at lower levels (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> B), which suggests that ADRP is a protein component of the RESTs.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Colocalization of ADRP and RESTs in the wild-type and mutant RPE.</bold> (A) Immunofluorescent localization of ADRP (green) covisualized with RESTs (red). Left column shows the localization of RESTs imaged by two-photon microscopy. Middle column shows the localization of ADRP. Right column shows the colocalization of ADRP (green) and RESTs (red). The top row is allocated for 4-wk-old wild-type mouse, middle row for 12-wk-old <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mouse, and bottom row for 4-wk-old <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mouse. Colocalization of RESTs and ADRP were observed as yellow color in the wild-type and <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mouse. Localization of ADRP in <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> was diffusive and RESTs were not observed. Bar, 20 &#x003bc;m. (B) Relative abundance of ADRP protein in the eyes of mice with different genetic backgrounds. Eyecup extracts were prepared from half of the eye and were separated by SDS-PAGE, blotted onto membrane, and detected by anti-ADRP antibodies. The method of immunoblots was as described previously (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Haeseleer et al., 2002</xref>), with the exception that a goat anti&#x02013;guinea pig AP-conjugated antibody (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories) was used as the secondary antibody.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200311079f6"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our aim was to use native and genetically modified mice in conjunction with microscopy, HPLC, and immunocytochemistry to understand mechanisms governing the retinoid cycle and visual transduction. Spectrally sensitive noninvasive two-photon microscopy in conjunction with genetically engineered mice lacking key components of the retinoid cycle was used to identify a novel structure in the RPE involved in the production of the visual chromophore, 11-cis-retinal. Two-photon microscopy permitted deep tissue penetration of infrared excitation light in anesthetized mice to monitor regeneration processes of rhodopsin without introducing external fluorophores. Our results revealed the existence of novel structures, RESTs (or retinosomes), that are critical to the formation of 11-cis-retinal.</p><p>In wild-type mice, all-trans-retinol exchanges rapidly between the blood and the RPE (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Qtaishat et al., 2003</xref>). RESTs appear to be essential structures for retaining esterified vitamin A in the eye to support its utilization in formation of the chromophore for visual pigments. RESTs are also essential for trapping all-trans-retinol generated in photoreceptors, which must diffuse across the ECM separating ROSs and the RPE. Subcellular localization of these structures allows efficient trapping of all-trans-retinol from both the choroidal circulation and from photoreceptors after photoisomerization of rhodopsin's chromophore. This process is stalled in the RPE of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Redmond et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Qtaishat et al., 2003</xref>) that overaccumulate all-trans-retinyl esters in aberrantly large RESTs (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><p>The flow of soluble retinoids in either free or protein-bound form is governed by the gradient generated by the conversion of 11-cis- and all-trans-retinol to insoluble all-trans-retinyl esters in the RPE and the conversion of 11-cis-retinal to 11-cis-retinylidene-opsin in rod photoreceptor cells (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2001</xref>). Hence, compartmentalization plays an essential role in driving energetically unfavorable chemical reactions through mass action (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2001</xref>). The all-trans-retinyl esters constitute a storage intermediate in the isomerization pathway from all-trans- to 11-cis-isomers (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Rando, 1996</xref>). The isomerization proceeds through a reaction that involves an unidentified enzyme-retinol intermediate, or a specific subpopulation of all-trans-retinyl esters with properties that are distinct from the bulk of all-trans-retinyl esters (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Stecher et al., 1999</xref>). All-trans-retinyl esters present in the RESTs and formed in situ on the internal membranes where LRAT resides may form two subpopulations, from which only one is used for the isomerization process directly.</p><p>Several molecular components involved in the 11-cis-retinal formation have been identified through biochemical and genetic approaches. RPE65 is thought to be involved in the delivery of all-trans-retinyl esters to the isomerization machinery by the virtue of specific binding of these esters (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Gollapalli et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Mata et al., 2004</xref>). Our analyses add a cell biological view for the formation of retinyl esters during the retinoid cycle. All-trans-retinol likely diffuses first to the ER, where the major fraction is converted to retinyl esters by the ER-localized LRAT. Our in vivo analysis demonstrates that the retinyl esters are next delivered to and stored in RESTs. Blocking the redistribution of all-trans-retinyl esters from RESTs resulted in aberrant accumulation of all-trans-retinyl esters in RESTs as observed in the RPE of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. In photoreceptors of <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice regenerated with 9-cis-retinal, photoisomerization of isorhodopsin (9-cis-retinylidene-opsin) produced all-trans-retinoids, which could not be converted to 11-cis-retinal, hence formation of rhodopsin (11-cis-retinylidene-opsin) was not observed. Free all-trans-retinol could be quickly lost to the circulation, whereas all-trans-retinyl esters are essential in the retention of retinoids in the eye. This observation does not discard the possibility that all-trans-retinol is used directly by a putative isomerase, simply because all-trans-retinyl esters could be the starting substrate for the RPE65&#x02013;hydrolase&#x02013;isomerase complex indispensable in the production of 11-cis-retinol.</p><p>On average, between 20 and 40 ROSs project toward one RPE cell (for review see <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2001</xref>). For efficient transfer of retinoid between the RPE and the photoreceptor cells, the retinoid-processing enzymes should be widely distributed throughout the cell as observed in this and previous reports (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">McBee et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Haeseleer et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Batten et al., 2003</xref>). Once the retinoids are esterified, they are trapped into RESTs (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>), which are composed of all-trans-retinyl esters and at least one additional protein component, ADRP. The formation of self-associating complexes of all-trans-retinyl esters (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 1996</xref>) could facilitate REST formation. Clustering of all-trans-retinyl esters may prevent diffusion of retinoids through the retina, and may circumvent overproduction of all-trans-retinoic acid, an agent known to cause cell differentiation and proliferation (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Mangelsdorf et al., 1995</xref>), thus lowering overall toxicity. However, the symmetric nature of these structures and their intracellular distribution suggest that perhaps additional proteins are also involved. Interestingly, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. (2003)</xref> provided evidence that the lipid droplets in CHO K2 cells are metabolic organelles involved in membrane traffic, and that they contained ADRP as a major protein component of these structures termed adiposomes. It is tempting to speculate that ADRP could be an essential component of the lipid structures throughout the body.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>
<bold>RESTs in the RPE.</bold> The RPE (hexagons) interdigitate with ROSs. Large curved arrows symbolize the flow of retinoids from and to the rod outer segments (OS). RESTs are depicted as elongated red ovals &#x0223c;6.9 &#x003bc;m in length.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200311079f7"/></fig><p>Prior reports of myeloid bodies in the RPE have demonstrated that they vary in size during light adaptation (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Tabor and Fisher, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abran and Dickson, 1992a</xref>,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dickson and Morrison, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cai and Dickson, 1994</xref>), suggesting possible involvement in the retinoid cycle. However, the appearance and location of the REST is different from the myeloid bodies, and the relationship between these two structures is unclear. <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Robison and Kuwabara (1977)</xref> observed accumulation of lipid inclusion droplets along the basal and lateral cell boundaries after injection of the substantial dose of all-trans-retinyl esters. In our experiments, the subcellular localization of the RESTs, a minor component of the RPE, and appearance of these structures differ from those previous observations. Most EM analyses were performed on radial sections of the eye, and hence it was difficult to provide quantitative results for the thin structures perpendicularly aligned to the RPE cell layer. A combination of EM and application of two-photon microscopy to study visual processes using the infrared laser for the excitation of the fluorophores opens a new way to detect and study the subcellular structures.</p><p>In summary, in this work we have used the power of noninvasive, spectrally sensitive two-photon microscopy in conjunction with genetically engineered mice lacking key components of the retinoid cycle to define a novel structure in the RPE, the RESTs (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). Two-photon microscopy has unsurpassed potential to advance our understanding of normal physiological processes and to provide new insights into the pathology of many other eye diseases using suitable mouse models.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>The University of Washington and University of Utah Animal Care Committees approved all of the procedures that used animal experiments. Animals were maintained in complete darkness, and all of the manipulations with animals, dissected eyes, or retinoids were performed under dim red light using a No. 1 Safelight filter (transmittance &#x0003e;560 nm; Kodak). The Balb/c mice were used as a wild type throughout the experiments. <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were obtained from Dr. M. Redmond (National Eye Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD). <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were generated as recently described (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Batten et al., 2003</xref>). Albino lines of <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Lrat</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were maintained in a mixed background of 129Sv, C57Bl/6, and Balb/c. <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were genotyped as described previously (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Redmond et al., 1998</xref>). Mice were anesthetized by i.p. injection using 15 &#x003bc;l/g body weight of 6 mg/ml ketamine and 0.44 mg/ml xylazine diluted with 10 mM phosphate buffer, pH 7.2, containing 100 mM NaCl. The gavage experiments were performed on <italic>Lrat</italic> mice as described for <italic>Rpe65</italic> mice in <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Van Hooser et al. (2002)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Multiphoton vitamin A imaging</title><p>Two-photon excitation microscopy was performed using a confocal microscope (LSM 510 MP-NLO; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.) with LSM510 software v3.0. Briefly, 76-MHz, 100-fs pulses of 730-nm light from a mode-locked Ti:Sapphire laser (Mira-900; Coherent) were focused on the sample by a Plan-Neofluar 40&#x000d7;/1.3 NA objective lens for ex vivo experiments and a Planapochromat 20&#x000d7;/0.75 NA lens for in vivo experiments (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.). The intensity of the laser was measured at the back aperture of the objective lens and kept at &#x0223c;3 mW for ex vivo analysis and &#x0223c;5 mW for in vivo analysis. For 3-D imaging of RESTs in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B, the average power of the laser was kept at &#x0223c;10 mW. Autofluorescence from the sample (390&#x02013;545 nm) was collected by the objective, separated from the excitation light by a dichroic mirror, filtered to remove scattered excitation light, and directed to a photomultiplier tube detector. The objective lens was heated to 37&#x000b0;C by an air stream incubator. A temperature-controlled microscopic stage was installed on the microscope to maintain the reaction at 37&#x000b0;C. Fluorescent intensities reflected in pixel values were calculated by off-line analysis of the collected raw images (SCION image; Scion Co.). Fluorescent intensity was measured for the tangential sections of the RPE, and was averaged per pixel for randomly chosen areas (mean &#x000b1; SD; <italic>n</italic> = 30 from three eyes) enclosing 100 &#x000d7; 100 pixels (&#x0223c;30 &#x000d7; 30 &#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup> for <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B and C and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>; 36 &#x000d7; 36 &#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup> for <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). For separation of the cytoplasmic, nucleic, and REST responses (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B, right), fluorescent intensities were averaged for randomly chosen areas of 25 pixels (&#x0223c;2 &#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup>; <italic>n</italic> = 180 for three independent eyes). In <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> D, the RPE was exposed to 1.4 mM all-trans-retinol caged with 100 mM (2-hydroxypropyl)-&#x003b2;-cyclodextrin for 2 min, and was washed briefly with Ames medium (Sigma-Aldrich) for 3 min.</p><p>For ex vivo imaging, immediately after eye removal, mouse eyes or eyecups were located at the center of a glass-bottomed 35-mm dish and perfused with oxygenized (95% O<sub>2</sub>, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>) Ames medium at 37&#x000b0;C. For in vivo observation, an anesthetized mouse was laid on the temperature-controlled microscopic stage (at 37&#x000b0;C), and the right side of the eye was located on the microscopic cover glass (44-mm-diam, 0.16-mm thickness; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.). In this way, the retina was imaged at the periphery by the laser penetrating through the sclera while the emission fluorescence was collected coming back to the microscopic objective lens. In case of a slight movement of the eye, the same area of the retina was traced using unique texture of the RPE cell layer formed by the randomly arranged single- and dual-nucleated RPE. In most experiments, thoroughly dark-adapted mice were exposed to an intense 10-ms flash that bleached &#x0223c;60% of the pigment.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of retinoids</title><p>Retinoids were stored in <italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylformamide under argon at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C, and the concentrations were determined spectrophotometrically (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Garwin and Saari, 2000</xref>). All retinoids were purified by normal phase HPLC (Ultrasphere-Si, 4.6 mm &#x000d7; 250 mm; Beckman Coulter) with 10% ethyl acetate/90% hexane at a flow rate of 1.4 ml/min (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Van Hooser et al., 2000</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunocytochemistry and fluorescent visualization of subcellular organelles</title><p>Eyecups were prepared by removing anterior segments and neural retinas from the isolated mouse eyes, and the exposed RPE was fixed with 4% PFA for 15 min at 37&#x000b0;C. Immunofluorescence detection of antigens by anti-RPE65 antibody (a gift of M. Redmond, National Eye Institute), anti-CRALBP antibody (a gift of J.C. Saari, University of Washington, Seattle, WA), anti-ADRP (Progen), and anti-11-cis-retinol dehydrogenase (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Haeseleer et al., 2002</xref>) was performed as described previously (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Haeseleer et al., 2002</xref>). Samples were incubated with the primary antibody for 1 h and for 30 min with the secondary antibody conjugated with Cy3 (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories).</p><p>A number of fluorescent dyes (Molecular Probes, Inc.) were applied to the live RPE in the eyecup. Golgi apparatus was visualized by introducing 50 &#x003bc;M BODIPY<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> FL C<sub>5</sub>-ceramide. Two emission ranges were collected (500&#x02013;530 nm for green pseudocolor and 560&#x02013;700 nm for blue pseudocolor) from the fluorophore that had two emission peaks (515 nm and &#x0223c;620 nm) by excitation at 488 nm. Mitochondria were visualized by 200 nM MitoTracker<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Orange CMTMRos, and emissions from 560 to 700 nm were collected by excitation at 543 nm. Acidic organelles including lysosomes were visualized by 200 nM LysoTracker<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Green DND-26, and the emission range from 500 to 550 nm was collected by excitation at 488 nm. For visualization of the plasma membrane, 1 mM FM 4-64 was applied to the RPE and emission was collected at &#x0223c;650 nm (&#x003bb;<sub>ex</sub> = 543 nm). DiOC<sub>6</sub> dye was applied at 5 &#x003bc;g/ml to visualize the ER, and the emission was collected from 500 to 550 nm excited at 488 nm. A2E (green) was visualized by collecting emission from 565 to 615 nm by excitation at 488 nm. Fluorescent signals were covisualized with RESTs using a laser scanning microscope (LSM510; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.) under appropriate filter configuration.</p></sec><sec><title>Image processing</title><p>For figure preparation, Adobe Photoshop<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 6.0 was used for adjustments of brightness and for color balance. 3-D reconstructed projections shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B and in the supplemental videos were generated using LSM510 software v3.0 (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.).</p></sec><sec><title>Transmission EM</title><p>Dark-adapted mice controls or dark-adapted mice exposed to an intense flash (10-ms duration) that bleached &#x0223c;60% of the pigment were used for TEM. Photobleached mice were allowed to recover for 30 min to allow formation of retinyl esters. Mouse eyecups were primarily fixed by immersion in 2.5% glutaraldehyde and 1.6% PFA in 0.08 M Pipes, pH 7.4, containing 2% sucrose initially at RT for &#x0223c;1 h, and then at 4&#x000b0;C for the remainder of 24 h (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Van Hooser et al., 2002</xref>). The eyecups were then washed with 0.13 M sodium phosphate, pH 7.35, and secondarily fixed with 1% OsO<sub>4</sub> in 0.1 M sodium phosphate, pH 7.35, for 1 h at RT. The eyecups were dehydrated through a methanol series and transitioned to the epoxy-embedding medium with propylene oxide. The eyecups were embedded for sectioning in Eponate 812. Ultrathin sections (60&#x02013;70 nm) were stained with aqueous saturated uranium acetate and Reynold's formula lead citrate before survey and micrography with an electron microscope (model CM10; Philips).</p></sec><sec><title>Online supplemental material</title><p>Video 1 shows retinyl ester storage particles in the RPE cells. Three-dimensional projections of retinyl ester storage particles in the RPE cells. Video 2 shows covisualization of retinyl ester storage particles and 11-cis-retinol dehydrogenase. Three-dimensional projections of retinyl ester storage particles (red) and 11-cis-retinol dehydrogenase (green) in the RPE cells. Video 3 shows covisualization of retinyl ester storage particles and RPE65. Three-dimensional projections of retinyl ester storage particles (red) and RPE65 (green) in the RPE cells.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank Drs V. Gerke, R. Rodieck, A. Polans, and A. Moise for insightful comments on the manuscript; Dr. M. Redmond for providing <italic>Rpe65</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice and anti-RPE65 antibody; Dr. J.C. Saari for anti-CRALBP antibody; and D. Possin for the EM analysis.</p><p>This research was supported by National Institutes of Health grants EY09339, EY13385, EY08123 (to W. Baehr), and DK53434 (to D.W. Piston); National Science Foundation grant DBI9871063 (to D.W. Piston); a grant from Research to Prevent Blindness, Inc. (RPB) to the Departments of Ophthalmology at the University of Washington and the University of Utah; the Stargardt and Retinal Eye Disease Fund; a grant from the Macular Vision Research Foundation (to W. Baehr); a Foundation for Fighting Blindness Center grant to the University of Utah; and a grant from the E.K. Bishop Foundation (to K. Palczewski). K. Palczewski and W. Baehr are RPB Senior Investigators.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Abran, D., and D.H. Dickson. <year>1992</year>a. Biogenesis of myeloid bodies in regenerating newt (<italic>Notophthalmus viridescens</italic>) retinal pigment epithelium. <source>Cell Tissue Res.</source>
<volume>268</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>&#x02013;538.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1628309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Abran, D., and D.H. Dickson. <year>1992</year>b. Phospholipid composition of myeloid bodies from chick retinal pigment epithelium. <source>Exp. Eye Res.</source>
<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>737</fpage>&#x02013;745.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1623959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Acland, G.M., G.D. Aguirre, J. Ray, Q. Zhang, T.S. Aleman, A.V. Cideciyan, S.E. Pearce-Kelling, V. Anand, Y. Zeng, A.M. Maguire, et al. <year>2001</year>. Gene therapy restores vision in a canine model of childhood blindness. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;95.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11326284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Baehr, W., S.M. Wu, A.C. Bird, and K. Palczewski. <year>2003</year>. The retinoid cycle and retina disease. <source>Vision Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>2957</fpage>&#x02013;2958.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14611932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Batten, M.L., Y. Imanishi, T. Maeda, D. Tu, A.R. Moise, D. Bronson, D. Possin, R.N. Van Gelder, W. Baehr, and K. Palczewski. 2003. Lecithin:retinol acyltransferase (LRAT) is essential for retention of retinyl esters in the eye and in the liver. <italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic>10.1074/jbc.M312410200.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bennett, B.D., T.L. Jetton, G. Ying, M.A. Magnuson, and D.W. Piston. <year>1996</year>. Quantitative subcellular imaging of glucose metabolism within intact pancreatic islets. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>271</volume>:<fpage>3647</fpage>&#x02013;3651.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8631975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bok, D. <year>1985</year>. Retinal photoreceptor-pigment epithelium interactions. Friedenwald lecture. <source>Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1659</fpage>&#x02013;1694.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2933359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cai, F., and D.H. Dickson. <year>1994</year>. Diurnal change and prolonged dark effect on myeloid bodies in the retinal pigment epithelium of the leopard frog. <source>Curr. Eye Res.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;617.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7956314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Denk, W., J.H. Strickler, and W.W. Webb. <year>1990</year>. Two-photon laser scanning fluorescence microscopy. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>248</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;76.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2321027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dickson, D.H., and C. Morrison. <year>1993</year>. Diurnal variation in myeloid bodies of the chick retinal pigment epithelium. <source>Curr. Eye Res.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;43.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8436009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dryja, T.P. <year>2000</year>. Molecular genetics of Oguchi disease, fundus albipunctatus, and other forms of stationary night blindness: LVII Edward Jackson Memorial Lecture. <source>Am. J. Ophthalmol.</source>
<volume>130</volume>:<fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;563.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11078833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Euler, T., P.B. Detwiler, and W. Denk. <year>2002</year>. Directionally selective calcium signals in dendrites of starburst amacrine cells. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>418</volume>:<fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;852.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12192402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Filipek, S., R.E. Stenkamp, D.C. Teller, and K. Palczewski. <year>2003</year>. G protein-coupled receptor rhodopsin: a prospectus. <source>Annu. Rev. Physiol.</source>
<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>851</fpage>&#x02013;879.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gao, J., and G. Serrero. <year>1999</year>. Adipose differentiation related protein (ADRP) expressed in transfected COS-7 cells selectively stimulates long chain fatty acid uptake. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>16825</fpage>&#x02013;16830.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10358026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Garwin, G.G., and J.C. Saari. <year>2000</year>. High-performance liquid chromatography analysis of visual cycle retinoids. <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>
<volume>316</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;324.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10800683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gollapalli, D.R., P. Maiti, and R.R. Rando. <year>2003</year>. RPE65 operates in the vertebrate visual cycle by stereospecifically binding all-<italic>trans</italic>-retinyl esters. <source>Biochemistry.</source>
<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>11824</fpage>&#x02013;11830.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14529294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gu, S.M., D.A. Thompson, C.R. Srikumari, B. Lorenz, U. Finckh, A. Nicoletti, K.R. Murthy, M. Rathmann, G. Kumaramanickavel, M.J. Denton, and A. Gal. <year>1997</year>. Mutations in RPE65 cause autosomal recessive childhood-onset severe retinal dystrophy. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>194</fpage>&#x02013;197.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9326941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Haeseleer, F., G.F. Jang, Y. Imanishi, C.A. Driessen, M. Matsumura, P.S. Nelson, and K. Palczewski. <year>2002</year>. Dual-substrate specificity short chain retinol dehydrogenases from the vertebrate retina. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>45537</fpage>&#x02013;45546.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12226107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jang, G.F., J.K. McBee, A.M. Alekseev, F. Haeseleer, and K. Palczewski. <year>2000</year>. Stereoisomeric specificity of the retinoid cycle in the vertebrate retina. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>28128</fpage>&#x02013;28138.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10871622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kolb, H., R. Nelson, P. Ahnelt, and N. Cuenca. <year>2001</year>. Cellular organization of the vertebrate retina. <source>Prog. Brain Res.</source>
<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;26.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11420950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kuksa, V., Y. Imanishi, M. Batten, K. Palczewski, and A.R. Moise. <year>2003</year>. Retinoid cycle in the vertebrate retina: experimental approaches and mechanisms of isomerization. <source>Vision Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>2959</fpage>&#x02013;2981.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14611933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Li, C.Y., C.L. Zimmerman, and T.S. Wiedmann. <year>1996</year>. Solubilization of retinoids by bile salt/phospholipid aggregates. <source>Pharm. Res.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>907</fpage>&#x02013;913.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8792431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu, J., Y. Itagaki, S. Ben-Shabat, K. Nakanishi, and J.R. Sparrow. <year>2000</year>. The biosynthesis of A2E, a fluorophore of aging retina, involves the formation of the precursor, A2-PE, in the photoreceptor outer segment membrane. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>29354</fpage>&#x02013;29360.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10887199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu, P., Y. Ying, Y. Zhao, D.I. Mundy, M. Zhu, and R.G. Anderson. 2003. CHO K2 cell lipid droplets appear to be metabolic organelles involved in membrane traffic. <italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic>10.1074/jbc.M311945200.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mangelsdorf, D.J., C. Thummel, M. Beato, P. Herrlich, G. Schutz, K. Umesono, B. Blumberg, P. Kastner, M. Mark, P. Chambon, et al. <year>1995</year>. The nuclear receptor superfamily: the second decade. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>835</fpage>&#x02013;839.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8521507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marlhens, F., C. Bareil, J.M. Griffoin, E. Zrenner, P. Amalric, C. Eliaou, S.Y. Liu, E. Harris, T.M. Redmond, B. Arnaud, et al. <year>1997</year>. Mutations in RPE65 cause Leber's congenital amaurosis. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;141.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9326927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mata, N.L., W.N. Moghrabi, J.S. Lee, T.V. Bui, R.A. Radu, J. Horwitz, and G.H. Travis. 2004. Rpe65 is a retinyl ester binding protein that presents insoluble substrate to the isomerase in retinal pigment epithelial cells. <italic>J. Biol. Chem</italic>. 279:635&#x02013;643. First published on October 7, 2003; 10.1074/jbc. M310042200.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McBee, J.K., V. Kuksa, R. Alvarez, A.R. de Lera, O. Prezhdo, F. Haeseleer, I. Sokal, and K. Palczewski. <year>2000</year>. Isomerization of <italic>all-trans</italic>-retinol to cis-retinols in bovine retinal pigment epithelial cells: dependence on the specificity of retinoid-binding proteins. <source>Biochemistry.</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>11370</fpage>&#x02013;11380.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10985782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McBee, J.K., K. Palczewski, W. Baehr, and D.R. Pepperberg. <year>2001</year>. Confronting complexity: the interlink of phototransduction and retinoid metabolism in the vertebrate retina. <source>Prog. Retin. Eye Res.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;529.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Morimura, H., G.A. Fishman, S.A. Grover, A.B. Fulton, E.L. Berson, and T.P. Dryja. <year>1998</year>. Mutations in the RPE65 gene in patients with autosomal recessive retinitis pigmentosa or leber congenital amaurosis. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>3088</fpage>&#x02013;3093.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9501220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Owaribe, K., J. Kartenbeck, E. Rungger-Brandle, and W.W. Franke. <year>1988</year>. Cytoskeletons of retinal pigment epithelial cells: interspecies differences of expression patterns indicate independence of cell function from the specific complement of cytoskeletal proteins. <source>Cell Tissue Res.</source>
<volume>254</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;315.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3058315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Palczewski, K., J.P. Van Hooser, G.G. Garwin, J. Chen, G.I. Liou, and J.C. Saari. <year>1999</year>. Kinetics of visual pigment regeneration in excised mouse eyes and in mice with a targeted disruption of the gene encoding interphotoreceptor retinoid-binding protein or arrestin. <source>Biochemistry.</source>
<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>12012</fpage>&#x02013;12019.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Perrault, I., J.M. Rozet, S. Gerber, I. Ghazi, C. Leowski, D. Ducroq, E. Souied, J.L. Dufier, A. Munnich, and J. Kaplan. <year>1999</year>. Leber congenital amaurosis. <source>Mol. Genet. Metab.</source>
<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>200</fpage>&#x02013;208.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10527670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Qtaishat, N.M., T.M. Redmond, and D.R. Pepperberg. <year>2003</year>. Acute radiolabeling of retinoids in eye tissues of normal and <italic>rpe65</italic>-deficient mice. <source>Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.</source>
<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1435</fpage>&#x02013;1446.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12657577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rando, R.R. <year>1991</year>. Membrane phospholipids as an energy source in the operation of the visual cycle. <source>Biochemistry.</source>
<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>595</fpage>&#x02013;602.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1988047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rando, R.R. <year>1996</year>. Polyenes and vision. <source>Chem. Biol.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;262.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8807853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rattner, A., H. Sun, and J. Nathans. <year>1999</year>. Molecular genetics of human retinal disease. <source>Annu. Rev. Genet.</source>
<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;131.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10690405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Redmond, T.M., S. Yu, E. Lee, D. Bok, D. Hamasaki, N. Chen, P. Goletz, J.X. Ma, R.K. Crouch, and K. Pfeifer. <year>1998</year>. <italic>Rpe65</italic> is necessary for production of 11-<italic>cis</italic>-vitamin A in the retinal visual cycle. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>344</fpage>&#x02013;351.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Robison, W.G., Jr., and T. Kuwabara. <year>1977</year>. Vitamin A storage and peroxisomes in retinal pigment epithelium and liver. <source>Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1110</fpage>&#x02013;1117.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">924741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ruiz, A., A. Winston, Y.H. Lim, B.A. Gilbert, R.R. Rando, and D. Bok. <year>1999</year>. Molecular and biochemical characterization of lecithin retinol acyltransferase. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>3834</fpage>&#x02013;3841.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9920938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Saari, J.C., D.L. Bredberg, and D.F. Farrell. <year>1993</year>. Retinol esterification in bovine retinal pigment epithelium: reversibility of lecithin:retinol acyltransferase. <source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>291</volume>:<fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;700.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8489497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Saari, J.C., G.G. Garwin, J.P. Van Hooser, and K. Palczewski. <year>1998</year>. Reduction of all-<italic>trans</italic>-retinal limits regeneration of visual pigment in mice. <source>Vision Res.</source>
<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1325</fpage>&#x02013;1333.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9667000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sears, R.C., and M.W. Kaplan. <year>1989</year>. Axial diffusion of retinol in isolated frog rod outer segments following substantial bleaches of visual pigment. <source>Vision Res.</source>
<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1485</fpage>&#x02013;1492.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2635474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Stecher, H., M.H. Gelb, J.C. Saari, and K. Palczewski. <year>1999</year>. Preferential release of 11-<italic>cis</italic>-retinol from retinal pigment epithelial cells in the presence of cellular retinaldehyde-binding protein. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>8577</fpage>&#x02013;8585.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10085092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tabor, G.A., and S.K. Fisher. <year>1983</year>. Myeloid bodies in the mammalian retinal pigment epithelium. <source>Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;391.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6682095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Targett-Adams, P., D. Chambers, S. Gledhill, R.G. Hope, J.F. Coy, A. Girod, and J. McLauchlan. <year>2003</year>. Live cell analysis and targeting of the lipid droplet-binding adipocyte differentiation-related protein. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>15998</fpage>&#x02013;16007.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12591929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Thompson, D.A., Y. Li, C.L. McHenry, T.J. Carlson, X. Ding, P.A. Sieving, E. Apfelstedt-Sylla, and A. Gal. <year>2001</year>. Mutations in the gene encoding lecithin retinol acyltransferase are associated with early-onset severe retinal dystrophy. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;124.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11381255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Van Hooser, J.P., T.S. Aleman, Y.G. He, A.V. Cideciyan, V. Kuksa, S.J. Pittler, E.M. Stone, S.G. Jacobson, and K. Palczewski. <year>2000</year>. Rapid restoration of visual pigment and function with oral retinoid in a mouse model of childhood blindness. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>8623</fpage>&#x02013;8628.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Van Hooser, J.P., Y. Liang, T. Maeda, V. Kuksa, G.F. Jang, Y.G. He, F. Rieke, H.K. Fong, P.B. Detwiler, and K. Palczewski. <year>2002</year>. Recovery of visual functions in a mouse model of Leber congenital amaurosis. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>19173</fpage>&#x02013;19182.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11897783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang, J.W., A.M. Wong, J. Flores, L.B. Vosshall, and R. Axel. <year>2003</year>. Two-photon calcium imaging reveals an odor-evoked map of activity in the fly brain. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;282.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12553914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zipfel, W.R., R.M. Williams, R. Christie, A.Y. Nikitin, B.T. Hyman, and W.W. Webb. <year>2003</year>. Live tissue intrinsic emission microscopy using multiphoton-excited native fluorescence and second harmonic generation. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>7075</fpage>&#x02013;7080.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12756303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
