<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14707114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1887733</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20031104</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20031104</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Inflammation Controls B Lymphopoiesis by Regulating Chemokine CXCL12 Expression</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>Yoshihiro</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Kaiyong</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>Sandra J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>Motonari</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kelsoe</surname><given-names>Garnett</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x38ab510N0x1cfeca8">Department of Immunology, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC 27710</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Garnett Kelsoe, Dept. of Immunology, Box 3010, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, NC 27710. Phone: (919) 613-7815; Fax: (919) 613-7878; email: <email>ghkelsoe@duke.edu</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>199</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Inflammation removes developing and mature lymphocytes from the bone marrow (BM) and induces the appearance of developing B cells in the spleen. BM granulocyte numbers increase after lymphocyte reductions to support a reactive granulocytosis. Here, we demonstrate that inflammation, acting primarily through tumor necrosis factor &#x003b1; (TNF&#x003b1;), mobilizes BM lymphocytes. Mobilization reflects a reduced CXCL12 message and protein in BM and changes to the BM environment that prevents homing by cells from naive donors. The effects of TNF&#x003b1; are potentiated by interleukin 1 &#x003b2; (IL-1&#x003b2;), which acts primarily to expand the BM granulocyte compartment. Our observations indicate that inflammation induces lymphocyte mobilization by suppressing CXCL12 retention signals in BM, which, in turn, increases the ability of IL-1&#x003b2; to expand the BM granulocyte compartment. Consistent with this idea, lymphocyte mobilization and a modest expansion of BM granulocyte numbers follow injections of pertussis toxin. We propose that TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; transiently specialize the BM to support acute granulocytic responses and consequently promote extramedullary lymphopoiesis.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>bone marrow</kwd><kwd>innate immunity</kwd><kwd>TNF&#x003b1;</kwd><kwd>hematopoiesis</kwd><kwd>neutrophilia</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>Y. Ueda and K. Yang contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn><p>The online version of this article includes supplemental material.</p></fn><fn><p>
<italic>Abbreviations used in this paper:</italic> CFU-B, pre&#x02013;B cell CFU; NP-CGG, (4-hydroxy-3-nitrophenyl)acetyl-chicken &#x003b3; globulin; PTX, pertussis toxin; SA, streptavidin.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Severe infections in humans deplete BM lymphocytes and induce the appearance of immature lymphocytes in the blood (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). In mice, analogous responses follow infections (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) or administration of adjuvants (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Within a week of immunization, significant numbers of T cells and both developing and mature B cells are lost from mouse BM, whereas increases in granulocyte numbers and granulocytosis are often observed (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>The mechanisms whereby adjuvants/inflammation elicit BM lymphopenia are not understood but are independent of adaptive immunity (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Could innate immune effectors regulate BM lymphopoiesis? In vitro, IL-1 inhibits B lymphopoiesis and promotes myelopoiesis (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). These effects are reversible, and appear to reflect change in nonhematopoietic BM compartments (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The early stages of B cell development are exceptionally sensitive to apoptosis (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), and the proinflammatory cytokine IFN&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; can suppress B lymphopoiesis by inducing cell death (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). However, this suppression only occurs at pharmacologic doses (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), and does not require signal transducer and activator of transcription 1, the physiologic mediator of IFN signaling (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>Alternatively, as inflammation elicits developing B lymphocytes in the periphery (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), BM lymphopenia could reflect mobilization rather than the interruption of a developmental pathway or cell death. For example, cells with the characteristics of pre&#x02013;B and immature B lymphocytes appear in mouse spleen 2 wk after immunizations with adjuvant (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><p>Here, we demonstrate that adjuvants suppress chemokine CXCL12 expression in the BM and that these reductions coincide with lymphocyte depletion and mobilization of B cell progenitors to the blood and spleen. Recombinant TNF&#x003b1; alone reduces BM CXCL12, and in TNF&#x003b1;-deficient mice, adjuvant-induced suppression of BM CXCL12 is mitigated, BM lymphopenia is much reduced, and mobilization of developing B cells is absent. Adjuvant effects on BM are largely mimicked by pertussis toxin (PTX), which uncouples most chemokine receptor signaling (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>Inflammation redirects immunocyte production in BM to favor granulopoiesis. This redirection is an unrecognized inflammatory response to microbial infection and a novel pathway for the regulation of B lymphopoiesis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Mice.</title><p>Female C57BL/6 (BL/6, CD45.2), B6.SJL-Ptprca/BoAiTac (B6.SJL, CD45.1), B6.129SF2, TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), and TNF receptor I&#x02013; and II&#x02013;deficient (TNFR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>) mice (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) were obtained from the Jackson Laboratories or Taconic Farms. Mice were housed under specific pathogen-free conditions at the Duke University Animal Care Facility and given sterile bedding, water, and food. Mice used in these experiments were 6&#x02013;18 wk old.</p></sec><sec><title>Antigens, Adjuvants, and Cytokines.</title><p>Mice were immunized with single, i.p. injections of 20 or 100 &#x003bc;g (4-hydroxy-3-nitrophenyl)acetyl-chicken &#x003b3; globulin (NP-CGG) in alum or IFA (Sigma-Aldrich; reference <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). NP-CGG contained 10 or 12 mol NP/mol CGG. NP-CGG was emulsified in IFA or precipitated with alum. Some mice were immunized with SRBCs (Duke University Farm) in PBS or injected with 0.2 ml alum or IFA alone. LPS (<italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O127:B8; Sigma-Aldrich) was resuspended in sterile PBS, and mice were injected i.p. with 75 &#x003bc;g LPS. Mouse rTNF&#x003b1;, rIL-1&#x003b2;, rIL-6, and rIFN&#x003b2; were purchased from R&#x00026;D Systems. Pharmacologic doses for each cytokine were confirmed by serial titrations (0.3&#x02013;3.0 &#x003bc;g/mouse). Single doses of 1 &#x003bc;g rTNF&#x003b1;, rIL-1&#x003b2;, or 1,000 U rIFN&#x003b2; in 300 &#x003bc;l PBS were given i.v.; these doses did not produce obvious morbidity. PTX and PTX B oligomer were purchased from List Biological Laboratories.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibodies.</title><p>FITC-, PE-, biotin-, or allophycocyanin-conjugated mAb for mouse B220, Gr-1, CD3, IgM, CD4, CD8, and CD11c were purchased from BD Biosciences. PE-Cy5&#x02013;conjugated mAb for mouse CD4, CD8, TER-119, Gr-1, CD11b, and FITC-conjugated anti-CD45.1 and anti-CD45.2 mAb were purchased from eBioscience. Streptavidin (SA)-allophycocyanin (BD Biosciences) and SA-Texas red (Calbiochem-Novabiochem) identified biotinylated mAb. The 493 mAb (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) binds the fetal stem cell antigen, AA4 (C1qRp/CD93; references <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), and was purified from cloned hybridoma cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Flow Cytometry.</title><p>Mice were killed after injection/immunization, and cells were harvested from spleen, femur, tibia, and blood. RBCs were lysed in ammonium chloride buffer (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) before immunolabeling. Typically, &#x02264;10<sup>6</sup> nucleated cells were suspended in 50&#x02013;100 &#x003bc;l of staining buffer (HBSS with 2% FCS and combinations of labeled mAb) and incubated on ice for 20 min. 7-Aminoactinomycin D (Molecular Probes) was included to identify dead cells. Labeled cells were analyzed/sorted in a FACSCalibur&#x02122; flow cytometer (488 nm argon laser; 633 nm helium neon laser) or a FACStarPlus&#x02122; flow cytometer (488 nm argon laser; 599 nm dye laser) with the OmniComp option. Cytometry data were analyzed with FlowJo software (Treestar Inc.).</p></sec><sec><title>B Cell Colony Forming Unit Assay.</title><p>B cell progenitors were enumerated as pre&#x02013;B cell CFU (CFU-B; reference <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In brief, 10<sup>5</sup> BM cells or 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> splenocytes were mixed with 1 ml IMDM containing 1% methylcellulose, 30% FCS, 0.1 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 2 mM glutamine, and 20 ng/ml IL-7. Suspended cells were plated in 35-mm dishes and cultured at 37&#x000b0;C for 7 d. Colonies with B cell morphology were identified and counted by microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>Adoptive Cell Transfer.</title><p>3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> BM cells from B6.SJL (CD45.1) mice were injected i.v. into BL/6 (CD45.2) recipients immunized 3 d earlier. 1 d after transfer, femoral BM cells and splenocytes were harvested and stained with FITC-conjugated anti-CD45.1 and biotinylated anti-B220 mAb, followed by SA&#x02013;Texas red. Labeled, donor-derived cells were enumerated by flow cytometry to determine homing and migration efficiencies. BM cells from TNFR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (CD45.2) mice were transferred into naive or immunized B6.SJL (CD45.1) mice. Donor B cells recovered from the BM and spleen of recipients were distinguished from host cells by anti-CD45.2 mAb.</p></sec><sec><title>RT-PCR.</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from BM using RNeasy-kits (QIAGEN); 1 &#x003bc;g RNA was reverse transcribed for 1 h at 42&#x000b0;C (Superscript II reverse transcriptase; Invitrogen). PCR was performed on serial dilutions of cDNA using Taq polymerase (Takara Bio Inc.). PCR primers used were as follows: HPRT, forward, 5&#x02032;-GCTGGTGAAAAGGACCTCT-3&#x02032;, reverse, 5&#x02032;-CACAGGACTAGAACACCTGC-3&#x02032;; CXCL12, forward, 5&#x02032;-GTCCTCTTGCTGTCCAGCTC-3&#x02032;, reverse, 5&#x02032;-TAATTTC-GGGTCAATGCACA-3&#x02032;; and CXCL12&#x003b1;, reverse, 5&#x02032;-TGG-GCTGTTGTGCTTACTTG-3&#x02032;; CXCL12&#x003b2;, reverse, 5&#x02032;-CCT-CTCACATCTTGAGCCTCTT-3&#x02032;. Amplification parameters were as follows: initial denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 5 min, 25&#x02013;32 amplification rounds consisting of denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 30 s, annealing at optimal temperatures, and extension for 60 s at 72&#x000b0;C. A final extension round of 72&#x000b0;C for 10 min ended each amplification. Optimal annealing temperatures were as follows: 52&#x000b0;C for HPRT and CXCL12, and 60&#x000b0;C for CXCL12&#x003b1; and -&#x003b2;. PCR products were electrophoresed over 2% agarose gels containing ethidium bromide.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of BM Plasma and CXCL12 ELISA.</title><p>BM plasma was prepared by flushing both femurs and tibia with 500 &#x003bc;l of cold PBS into Eppendorf-type centrifuge tubes. Cells/debris were removed by centrifugation at 3,000 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C; BM plasma was stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C.</p><p>CXCL12 protein concentrations were determined by ELISA. In brief, 96-well plates (BD Falcon&#x02122;; BD Biosciences) were coated overnight with anti-CXCL12 mAb 79018 (R&#x00026;D Systems) (2 &#x003bc;g/ml in 0.1 M carbonate buffer) at 4&#x000b0;C. Serially diluted BM plasma samples were loaded, incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C, and washed with PBS containing 0.1% Tween 20. Bound CXCL12 was detected by biotinylated anti-CXCL12&#x003b1; mAb (BAF310; R&#x00026;D Systems) and horseradish peroxidase&#x02013;SA (Southern Biotechnology Associates, Inc.). Horseradish peroxidase activity was visualized using a tetramethylbenzidine peroxidase substrate kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories). CXCL12 concentrations were determined from purified CXCL12 standards (PeproTech).</p></sec><sec><title>Online Supplemental Material.</title><p>Table S1 summarizes the effects of several inflammatory agents on thymocytes. Fig. S1 illustrates reductions of CXCL12 message in BM by adjuvant and TNF&#x003b1;. Fig. S2 shows that the PTX B oligomer has no effect on BM. Fig. S3 compares the ability of antigens/adjuvants to induce BM lymphopenia. Online supplemental material is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Adjuvants Deplete BM Lymphocytes and Induce the Appearance of Developing B Cells in the Periphery.</title><p>Immunization with NP-CGG/IFA reduces the numbers of developing (CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>) and mature (CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup>; reference <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) BM B cells (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A); losses are evident 3 d after immunization, with maximal reductions coming on days 4&#x02013;6 (CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> B cells, four- to fivefold reductions; CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> B cells, sevenfold) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B). Thereafter, developing and mature B cell numbers in the BM return to normal levels (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B). Both B cell populations decline at similar rates, but losses of CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> cells are significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) greater and more sustained than that of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells. Similar kinetics of loss and recovery are also observed for BM T cells (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref> and unpublished data), indicating that all BM lymphocyte populations are sensitive to adjuvant-induced depletion.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Immunization depletes BM B cells but increases BM granulocyte numbers. BL/6 mice were immunized with NP-CGG/IFA. Lymphocytes and granulocytes from femur and tibia were analyzed by flow cytometry; representative FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> profiles of BM cells (A, B220 and CD93; C, B220 and Gr-1) 3 or 4 d after immunization. Percentages of gated CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>, CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup>, and Gr-1<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells are given. 3 d after immunization, CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> cell numbers fall in the BM (A), whereas Gr-1<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cell numbers change little (C). Dynamics of BM B cell (B) or granulocyte (D) populations indicate that B lymphopenia persists for &#x02265;12 d (B), whereas granulocyte numbers increase (D). Points represent mean &#x000b1; SEM of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> (&#x02022;), CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> (&#x025aa;), and Gr-1<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells (&#x02666;). Asterisks indicate significant differences from controls: *, P &#x0003c; 0.05; **, P &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20031104f1"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table I.</label><caption><p>Effects of Various Inflammatory Agents on BM Cell Populations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">Bone marrow</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center">
<italic>n</italic>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn1">a</xref>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center">Total</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center">B220<sup>lo</sup>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center">B220<sup>hi</sup>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center">Gr-1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center">CD3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">PBS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">216 &#x000b1; 9.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn2">b</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">43.0 &#x000b1; 4.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">31.7 &#x000b1; 3.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">88.1 &#x000b1; 4.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">8.1 &#x000b1; 1.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">NP-CGG/IFA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">264 &#x000b1; 11.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">13.7 &#x000b1; 0.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">7.9 &#x000b1; 0.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">184 &#x000b1; 9.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">1.2 &#x000b1; 0.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">TNF&#x003b1;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">178.4 &#x000b1; 16.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn4">d</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">23.2 &#x000b1; 2.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">13.1 &#x000b1; 1.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">108.2 &#x000b1; 10.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">1.3 &#x000b1; 0.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">IL-1&#x003b2;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">218 &#x000b1; 7.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">33.7 &#x000b1; 3.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">24.6 &#x000b1; 1.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">116.6 &#x000b1; 5.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">4.5 &#x000b1; 0.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">IL-6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">199 &#x000b1; 17.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">45.3 &#x000b1; 1.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">22.2 &#x000b1; 1.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">76.1 &#x000b1; 2.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">3.9 &#x000b1; 0.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn4">d</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">IFN&#x003b2;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">229 &#x000b1; 14.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">44.0 &#x000b1; 7.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">35.4 &#x000b1; 1.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">75.6 &#x000b1; 7.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">11.9 &#x000b1; 2.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">TNF&#x003b1; + IL-1&#x003b2;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">281 &#x000b1; 17.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">13.2 &#x000b1; 3.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">8.5 &#x000b1; 2.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">218.3 &#x000b1; 17.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">1.3 &#x000b1; 0.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left">PTX</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">148 &#x000b1; 9.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">6.9 &#x000b1; 0.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">2.2 &#x000b1; 0.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">99.6 &#x000b1; 7.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char=".">1.3 &#x000b1; 0.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3">c</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><label>a</label><p>Total number of mice from multiple (two to eight) experiments (TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; is a single experiment).</p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><label>b</label><p>Mean &#x000b1; SEM (&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup>) number of cells recovered from the femurs of individual mice 6 d after treatment.</p></fn><fn id="tfn3"><label>c</label><p>P &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></fn><fn id="tfn4"><label>d</label><p>P &#x02264; 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In contrast, BM granulocyte numbers, especially less mature Gr-1<sup>int</sup> cells (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), increase after immunization (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1, C and D</xref>). Gr-1<sup>+</sup> cell numbers significantly increase 1 wk after immunization, reach maximal levels on day 16 (naive, 8.8 &#x000b1; 1.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>; and day 16, 20.4 &#x000b1; 3.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>, P &#x0003c; 0.01), and then gradually fall to normal levels (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> D).</p><p>To determine if adjuvant-induced depletion of BM lymphocytes includes cell mobilization, we enumerated CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> blood cells after immunization. CD93<sup>+</sup> B220<sup>lo</sup> blood cell numbers increased soon after immunization (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, A and B</xref>) , with a peak at day 3 (naive, 5.3 &#x000b1; 1.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml; and day 3, 14.7 &#x000b1; 3.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml, P &#x0003c; 0.05). Developing B cell numbers in blood returned to normal levels (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B, day 8, 3.4 &#x000b1; 0.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml, P = 0.42; day 12, 7.4 &#x000b1; 1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml, P = 0.08; and day 16, 8.9 &#x000b1; 2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml, P = 0.10).</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Appearance of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells in the periphery after immunization. CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> B cells in the blood (BL) and spleen (SPL) of immunized BL/6 mice at days 3&#x02013;16 were characterized and enumerated by flow cytometry. (A) Representative FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> profiles of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> cells in BL and SPL. Percentages of gated CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells are indicated. (B) Kinetics of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cell numbers in BL and SPL after immunization. Asterisks indicate significant differences from controls: *, P &#x0003c; 0.05; **, P &#x0003c; 0.01. (C) Surface IgM expression by CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells in BL and SPL. Shaded areas, solid lines, and dashed lines represent surface IgM expression by CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>, CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup> B220<sup>hi</sup>, and B220<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells, respectively. Percentages of IgM<sup>+</sup> cells in CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cell gates are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20031104f2"/></fig><p>Immunization also increased the fraction of IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells among CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> blood cells. In naive animals, 80&#x02013;90% of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> blood cells are IgM<sup>hi</sup>, transitional B cells (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C; reference <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). 3 d after immunization, the IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> fraction of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> blood cells increased to &#x0223c;45% (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C); adjuvants increase the numbers of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> blood cells by expanding the IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> compartment. As reported previously (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cell numbers in the spleen also increased after immunization (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A). Transient, nonsignificant (P = 0.06) increases immediately followed the peak of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells in blood, but larger and sustained increases began at day 8 (naive, 1.6 &#x000b1; 0.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>; day 8, 3.6 &#x000b1; 0.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>, P &#x0003c; 0.05) and continued until day 16 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B, 11.0 &#x000b1; 0.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>, P &#x0003c; 0.01). In both blood and spleen, CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells did not express CD11b, CD11c, CD8, or TER-119 (unpublished data).</p><p>To determine whether these CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells were B lineage progenitors, we enumerated CFU-B in BM and spleen after immunization. CFU-B are abundant in the BM of naive mice (12.9 &#x000b1; 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/femur), but rare in the spleen (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, A and B</xref> , 0.2 &#x000b1; 0.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/spleen). In 4 d, adjuvants decrease the numbers of BM CFU-B to &#x0223c;25% of controls (P &#x0003c; 0.01); these reductions are sustained until day 8 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> A). Significant increases in splenic CFU-B occur 8 d after immunization (0.5 &#x000b1; 0.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/spleen, P &#x0003c; 0.05), with CFU-B numbers peaking at day 12 (4.3 &#x000b1; 1.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/spleen, P &#x0003c; 0.01) and declining thereafter (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Immunization increases splenic CFU-B numbers. BL/6 mice were immunized with 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> SRBCs in 200 &#x003bc;l IFA. 4&#x02013;16 d later, spleen and BM cells were harvested, and CFU-B were enumerated after culture for 7 d. (A) Femoral BM CFU-B. (B) Splenic CFU-B numbers after immunization. Asterisks indicate significant differences from controls: *, P &#x0003c; 0.05; **, P &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20031104f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>TNF&#x003b1; Mimics Inflammation's Effects on BM.</title><p>To determine if a single proinflammatory cytokine could reproduce adjuvant's effects on BM, we administered rTNF&#x003b1;, rIL-1&#x003b2;, rIL-6, or rIFN&#x003b2; to BL/6 mice and followed changes in lymphocyte and granulocyte numbers.</p><p>Of these cytokines, only TNF&#x003b1; recapitulated the cell mobilizations induced by adjuvant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). 6 d after injection, TNF&#x003b1; reduced BM CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>, CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup>, and CD3<sup>+</sup> cell numbers to 54, 41, and 16% of controls, respectively. In addition, TNF&#x003b1; modestly increased BM granulocyte numbers (123% of controls, P = 0.07). These effects are similar to those of adjuvants, albeit less profound and persistent. For example, adjuvant reduced CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>, CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> B cells in the BM by five- and sevenfold, respectively, whereas TNF&#x003b1; reduced CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> BM cells two- and threefold (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). In contrast to their strong effects on BM, both adjuvants and TNF&#x003b1; induced only modest and transient changes in the thymus (Table S1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1</ext-link>).</p><p>Neither IL-6 nor IFN&#x003b2; significantly altered CD93<sup>+</sup> B220<sup>lo</sup> or CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> BM cell numbers, nor did they change granulocyte numbers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). IL-1&#x003b2; lowered B220<sup>+</sup> BM cell numbers nonsignificantly (&#x0223c;80% of controls, P = 0.11) but significantly expanded granulocytes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>, 132% of controls, P &#x0003c; 0.01).</p><p>Noting that TNF&#x003b1; primarily reduced BM lymphocyte numbers, whereas IL-1&#x003b2; expanded the BM granulocyte compartment, we tested whether these cytokines synergize by injecting 0.5 &#x003bc;g TNF&#x003b1; and 0.5 &#x003bc;g IL-1&#x003b2; singly or in combination. Synergy was obvious; TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; together reduced B220<sup>+</sup> (&#x0223c;30% of controls, P &#x0003c; 0.01) and CD3<sup>+</sup> (16% of controls, P &#x0003c; 0.01) BM cell numbers more effectively than higher doses either cytokine alone (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). Potentiation was also apparent in significantly larger increases in the BM Gr-1<sup>+</sup> populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>, 250% of controls, P &#x0003c; 0.01). In combination, TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; fully recapitulate adjuvant-induced change in BM lymphocyte and granulocyte populations.</p></sec><sec><title>TNF&#x003b1; Mobilizes B Cell Progenitors from the BM.</title><p>To determine if TNF&#x003b1; mobilized BM lymphocytes, we enumerated CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells in the periphery after injecting rTNF&#x003b1;. 3 d after injection, CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells increased two- to threefold in the blood (P &#x0003c; 0.05) and spleen (P &#x0003c; 0.05) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A). In control mice, &#x0223c;15% of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells in blood and spleen were IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup>; after TNF&#x003b1; treatment, IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells comprised 55&#x02013;65% of both CD93<sup>+</sup> B220<sup>lo</sup> populations (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B). Thus, rTNF&#x003b1; mobilizes CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells to peripheral tissues.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>TNF&#x003b1; mobilizes CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells. (A) Representative FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> profiles of blood (BL) and spleen (SPL) cells from PBS- and TNF&#x003b1;-injected mice. Percentages indicate CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells in the lymphocyte gate. (B) IgM expression by CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> B cells from BL and SPL. Shaded areas, solid lines, and dashed lines represent surface IgM expression by CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>, CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup>, and B220<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells, respectively. Numbers indicate percentages of IgM<sup>+</sup> cells in CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cell gates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20031104f4"/></fig><p>If TNF&#x003b1; plays a principal role in adjuvant-induced BM lymphopenia, lymphocyte mobilization should be reduced or absent in TNF knockout animals. We immunized TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice and congenic controls and followed changes in CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> cell numbers in BM, blood, and spleen. 4 d after immunization, substantial losses of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> (27% of controls) and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> (7% of controls) BM cells were evident in B6.129SF2 mice. In contrast, immunization of TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice resulted in approximately twofold reductions of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> (65% of controls) and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> (42% of controls) cells (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Adjuvant-induced BM lymphopenia and B cell mobilization in TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice and congenic controls were immunized with NP-CGG/IFA. 3 d after immunization, B cells in BM and spleen (SPL) were analyzed by flow cytometry. (A) Adjuvant-induced BM lymphopenia is mitigated in TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Bars represent mean &#x000b1; SD of B220<sup>lo</sup> and B220<sup>hi</sup> cell numbers from two femurs of naive (unshaded) or immunized (shaded) mice. Asterisks indicate significant differences from controls: *, P &#x0003c; 0.05; **, P &#x0003c; 0.01. (B) Mobilization of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells is absent in TNF<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Representative FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> profiles for CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> cells in the blood (BL) and SPL of naive and immunized mice are shown. Percentages of BL and SPL CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> lymphocytes (CD11c-, Gr-1&#x02013;, Mac-1&#x02013;, CD8-, and TER-119&#x02013;negative) are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20031104f5"/></fig><p>Although BM lymphopenia was reduced, mobilization of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells was not detectable in TNF&#x003b1; knockouts. 4 d after immunization, CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells increased two- to threefold in the blood (naive, 5.8 &#x000b1; 3.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml; day 4, 18.7 &#x000b1; 0.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml; P &#x0003c; 0.01) and spleen (naive, 1.1 &#x000b1; 0.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/spleen; day 4, 2.5 &#x000b1; 0.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/spleen; P &#x0003c; 0.05) of TNF&#x003b1; sufficient controls (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B). In contrast, CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cell numbers did not increase in the blood (naive, 4.7 &#x000b1; 2.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml; day 4, 3.2 &#x000b1; 3.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup> cells/ml; P = 0.44) or spleen (naive, 0.9 &#x000b1; 0.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/spleen; day 4, 0.5 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/spleen; P = 0.15) of immunized TNF<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B). Thus, TNF&#x003b1; is a principal component of adjuvant-induced BM lymphopenia and mobilization.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunization and TNF&#x003b1; Reduce CXCL12 in the BM.</title><p>CXCL12 and its receptor, CXCR4, are crucial for the homing of hematopoietic progenitor cells (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), and interruption of CXCL12/CXCR4 interaction mobilizes BM stem cells (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Could inflammation/TNF&#x003b1; mobilize BM B cells by reducing BM CXCL12/CXCR4 expression and/or signaling? We measured CXCL12 message in BM by semi-quantitative RT-PCR. In naive mice, CXCL12 mRNA was detected in unsorted BM cells, but absent or much reduced in the B cell, T cell, and granulocyte compartments (Fig. S1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1</ext-link>), consistent with the production of CXCL12 by nonhematopoietic stromal cells (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). 3 d after immunization or i.v. TNF&#x003b1;, levels of CXCL12&#x003b1; and -&#x003b2; mRNA (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) fell twofold in BM, whereas HPRT mRNA levels remained constant (Fig. S1).</p><p>CXCL12 protein in BM plasma also declined after immunization or TNF&#x003b1; injection. In control mice, the average concentration of CXCL12 in BM plasma was 14.0 &#x000b1; 2.0 ng/ml. 3 d after immunization, CXCL12 protein levels dropped sixfold to 2.3 &#x000b1; 2.0 ng/ml (P &#x0003c; 0.01; <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A). These losses were specific, as total protein levels in the BM plasma of control and immunized mice were identical (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A). After immunization, CXCL12 returned to near normal levels by day 8 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> B). This pattern of decreased CXCL12 expression follows the course of BM lymphocyte loss and recovery after immunization (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Adjuvants and TNF&#x003b1; suppress BM CXCL12. (A) Adjuvants and TNF&#x003b1; reduce BM CXCL12 protein, but do not alter total protein levels. Bars represent mean &#x000b1; SD protein concentrations. (B) CXCL12 protein levels in BM plasma of BL/6 mice after immunization. Points represent mean &#x000b1; SD CXCL12 concentrations. Asterisks indicate significant differences from controls: *, P &#x0003c; 0.05; **, P &#x0003c; 0.01. (C) Adjuvant-induced suppression of BM CXCL12 is mitigated in TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. 3 d after immunization, CXCL12 protein concentrations in BM plasma of TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and control mice were determined. Experimental groups are as follows: naive TNF<sup>+/+</sup>, untreated B6.129SF2; NP-CGG/IFA TNF<sup>+/+</sup>, immunized B6.129SF2; naive TNF<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, untreated TNF&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup>; and NP-CGG/IFA TNF<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, immunized TNF<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20031104f6"/></fig><p>TNF&#x003b1; also inhibited BM CXCL12 protein production, but less profoundly than adjuvant. 3 d after TNF&#x003b1;, BM CXCL12 levels fell to 8.3 &#x000b1; 1.6 ng/ml (P &#x0003c; 0.05; <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A). Adjuvant-induced reductions of CXCL12 protein are greater than reductions in mRNA, whereas TNF&#x003b1; induces comparable reductions in both (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> and Fig. S1). We interpret this difference to reflect distinct regulatory mechanisms (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>CXCL12 Reduction in TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Mice.</title><p>In naive B6.129SF2 mice, the average concentration of CXCL12 protein in BM plasma (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> C, 19 &#x000b1; 1.9 ng/ml) is similar to BL/6 mice (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A); 4 d after immunization, BM CXCL12 concentrations fell below detectable levels (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> C, &#x0003c;1 ng/ml). In contrast, immunization of TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice reduces BM CXCL12 levels by &#x02264;50% (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> C, naive, 21 &#x000b1; 1.1 ng/ml; immunized, 11 &#x000b1; 3.4 ng/ml). These reductions were specific, as total BM plasma protein remained constant in all groups (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> C).</p></sec><sec><title>Homing to BM Is Reduced in Immunized Mice.</title><p>If adjuvants mobilize BM lymphocytes by reducing CXCL12, normal cells should be unable to colonize the BM of immunized mice. To test this prediction, BM cells from naive, CD45.1 donors were transferred into naive or immunized CD45.2 recipients; 24 h later, CD45.1 B cells in the BM and spleen were enumerated by flow cytometry.</p><p>CD45.1 donor B cells readily entered the BM of naive recipients. We typically recovered 2.0 &#x000b1; 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CD45.1<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells and 0.4 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CD45.1<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> cells from each femur and tibia from naive hosts (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A). In immunized recipients, we only recovered 0.6 &#x000b1; 0.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CD45.1<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells (30% of controls, P &#x0003c; 0.01) and 0.03 &#x000b1; 0.02 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CD45.1<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> cells (7% of controls, P &#x0003c; 0.01). In contrast, equivalent numbers of CD45.1<sup>+</sup> B220<sup>hi</sup> cells were present in the spleens of both naive (3.1 &#x000b1; 1.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>) and immunized hosts (3.7 &#x000b1; 2.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>), and more CD45.1<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells were consistently recovered from the spleens of immunized than from naive recipients (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A, 14.7 &#x000b1; 2.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> vs. 7.0 &#x000b1; 2.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>; P &#x0003c; 0.01).</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Transferred BM B cells do not home efficiently in immunized recipients. (A) BM cells from naive B6.SJL (CD45.1) animals were transferred into naive or immunized, congenic (CD45.2) recipients. 1 d after transfer, donor B220<sup>lo</sup> and B220<sup>hi</sup> cells in the BM and SPL of recipients were enumerated by flow cytometry. (B) Homing of TNFR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> BM B cells in immunized recipients is impaired. BM cells from naive, TNFR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (CD45.2) mice were transferred into naive and immunized (CD45.1) recipients. 1 d after transfer, donor B cells in the BM and SPL of recipients were enumerated. Bars indicate mean &#x000b1; SD numbers of CD45.2 B cells recovered from naive (unshaded) and immunized (shaded) recipients. Asterisks indicate significant differences from controls: *, P &#x0003c; 0.05; **, P &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20031104f7"/></fig><p>To exclude the possibility that defective BM homing in immunized recipients was due to TNF&#x003b1;-mediated change in the transferred cells, we transferred 1.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> BM cells from TNFR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (CD45.2) into naive or immunized B6.SJL (CD45.1) hosts (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> B). Average recoveries from the BM of naive recipients were 1.4 &#x000b1; 0.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CD45.2<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and 0.4 &#x000b1; 0.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CD45.2<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> TNFR-deficient cells. However, only 0.6 &#x000b1; 0.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CD45.2<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells (43% of controls, P &#x0003c; 0.05) and 0.03 &#x000b1; 0.02 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CD45.2<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> TNFR-deficient cells (10% of controls, P &#x0003c; 0.01) were recovered from the BM of immunized recipients.</p></sec><sec><title>PTX Depletes BM Lymphocytes and Mobilizes Developing B Cells.</title><p>In association with reductions in CXCL12, adjuvant mobilizes BM lymphocytes and increases granulocyte numbers (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), with little effect on thymocytes (Table S1). If CXCL12 reductions cause these changes, a blockade of CXCL12 signals must produce similar results. We injected BL/6 mice with PTX, an inhibitor of many chemokine receptors, including the CXCL12 receptor, CXCR4 (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), and followed its effects on BM and thymus.</p><p>3 d after injecting PTX, CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup> BM cell numbers fell significantly and remained suppressed until day 12. B cell numbers began to recover 12&#x02013;18 d after PTX treatment, reaching normal levels by day 24 (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> A). PTX also lowered CD3<sup>+</sup> BM cell numbers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>) with similar kinetics (unpublished data). These effects were dependent on the ribosyltransferase activity of PTX, as the enzymatically inactive PTX B oligomer had no effect on BM (Fig. S2, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1</ext-link>). PTX had little effect on thymocyte populations (Table S1).</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>PTX elicits BM lymphopenia and mobilizes CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells. BM, blood (BL), and spleen (SPL) cells were harvested from BL/6 mice 0&#x02013;24 d after injection of 300&#x02013;500 ng PTX and analyzed by flow cytometry. (A) Dynamics of BM B cell subsets (left) and granulocytes (right). Points represent mean &#x000b1; SEM numbers of B220<sup>lo</sup> (&#x02022;), B220<sup>hi</sup> (&#x025aa;), and Gr-1<sup>+</sup> (&#x022c4;) cells from two femurs. (B) Appearance of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells in the periphery after PTX treatment. FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> profiles of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells from BL and SPL in PBS- and PTX-treated mice are shown. Percentages of cells in the CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> gate are indicated. (C) PTX elicits populations of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells in BL and SPL. Representative FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> profiles of surface IgM expression by CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells. Shaded areas, solid lines, and dashed lines represent surface IgM expression by CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>, CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup>, and B220<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells, respectively. Percentages of IgM<sup>+</sup> cells in CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cell gates are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="20031104f8"/></fig><p>PTX did not elicit losses of BM granulocytes. Instead, granulocyte numbers in the BM began to increase as soon as 6 d after PTX treatment with peak numbers at day 18. Later, BM granulocyte numbers began a return to basal levels (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> A).</p><p>PTX also mobilized CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> BM cells; 3 d after injecting PTX, CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cell numbers were significantly higher in blood (P &#x0003c; 0.01) and spleen (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> B, P &#x0003c; 0.01). The majority of these peripheral CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells (blood, 56%; spleen, 66%) were surface IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> C).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Infections and adjuvants can produce BM lymphopenia (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). BM B (CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> and CD93<sup>&#x02212;</sup>B220<sup>hi</sup>) and T lymphocyte numbers fall significantly in the first week after immunization with adjuvant, but both compartments begin recoveries in the second week and approach normal levels in the third (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Recovery in the BM is coincident with the appearance of splenic CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells that express RAG1/2 and &#x003bb;5 (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In contrast, BM granulocyte numbers do not fall but increase after immunization (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). These observations suggest that inflammation affects BM hematopoiesis to favor granulocyte production. However, the mechanisms responsible for inflammation-induced changes in the BM are unknown.</p><p>Here, we show that adjuvants suppress BM CXCL12 and mobilize functional B cell progenitors (B220<sup>lo</sup>CD93<sup>+</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells and CFU-B) into the periphery. Both phenomena can be mediated by rTNF&#x003b1;, and both are reduced or absent in TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. A blockade of G<sub>&#x003b1;i</sub>-dependent signaling by PTX recapitulates these effects in the absence of an overt inflammatory response. We conclude that inflammation acts via TNF&#x003b1; and CXCL12 to reduce the BM lymphocyte compartments in preparation for expanded granulocyte production. This model outlines a novel inflammatory response and predicts that innate immune responses are physiologic regulators of central hematopoiesis.</p><sec><title>Regulation of B Lymphopoiesis during Inflammation.</title><p>Adjuvants, LPS, and gram-negative bacteria, but not noninflammatory antigens such as SRBCs (references <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>; Fig. S3, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20031104/DC1</ext-link>) deplete all BM lymphocyte compartments equally (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; references <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The mechanism of depletion has been unclear, but cytokine-driven apoptosis was a favored candidate (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Developing B cells are sensitive to apoptotic signals (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) and severe viral infection or high doses of IFN&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; suppress B lymphopoiesis by apoptosis (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). However, this apoptosis likely represents a pathologic or pharmacologic response (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In our hands, adjuvant-induced depletions of lymphocytes are not biased for developmentally immature compartments (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), are restricted to the BM (Table S1), and unassociated with obvious morbidity or pathology.</p><p>Although we cannot rule out an apoptotic component, adjuvant-induced BM lymphopenia is coincident with a massive mobilization of BM lymphocytes that results in the appearance of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells in the blood and spleen (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). These CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cell populations include functional CFU-B (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>), providing an explanation the findings that the RAG<sup>+</sup> splenocytes elicited by adjuvant are not mature lymphocytes and require functional BM (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>TNF&#x003b1; Mobilizes BM Lymphocytes.</title><p>Adjuvant's effects on BM could be fully reproduced by two proinflammatory cytokines, TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). TNF&#x003b1; significantly decreases BM lymphocyte numbers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>), mobilizes B220<sup>lo</sup>CD93<sup>+</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>), and modestly expands the BM granulocyte compartment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). A central role for TNF&#x003b1; in adjuvant-induced loss of BM lymphocytes was confirmed in TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>) that exhibited much reduced BM lymphopenia and no mobilization of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cells.</p><p>However, residual losses of BM B cells in immunized TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice indicate that inflammation does not act via TNF&#x003b1; only. IL-1&#x003b2; elicited a nonsignificant BM lymphopenia but greatly expanded granulocyte numbers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). The effects of IL-1 in vivo are similar to those observed in vitro by Dorshkind (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) and complement TNF&#x003b1;. Suboptimal doses of TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; synergize to act on BM as profoundly as complex inflamogens (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref> and Fig. S3). Thus, the primary effect of TNF&#x003b1; appears to be the mobilization of BM lymphocytes, whereas IL-1&#x003b2; promotes granulocytic expansion. A similar potentiation has been observed in rats (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Adjuvants and TNF&#x003b1; Suppress BM CXCL12.</title><p>CXCL12 attracts many hematopoietic cells (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>), including progenitor B cells, and is important for their survival, differentiation, and localization (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Both adjuvants and TNF&#x003b1; reduce CXCL12 in the BM, and these reductions mirror lymphocyte mobilization (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6, A and B</xref>). Adjuvant-induced reductions of CXCL12 in TNF&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were substantially less than in controls (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> C) and consistent with reduced BM lymphopenia and lack of CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup> cell mobilization (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Inflammation mobilizes BM lymphocytes by suppressing CXCL12 expression. Although adjuvants lower CXCL12 mRNA approximately threefold, CXCL12 protein falls to &#x0003c;20% of controls; rTNF&#x003b1; reduces BM CXCL12 mRNA and protein to &#x0223c;50% of control levels (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> and Fig. S1). The contrasting ranges of CXCL12 message and protein levels in the BM suggest that inflammation regulates chemokine expression transcriptionally and posttranslationally.</p><p>Consistent with this idea, Fedyk et al. (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) showed that TNF&#x003b1; modestly suppressed CXCL12 transcription in dermal fibroblasts, whereas Petit et al. (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) found that granulocytes substantially lowered CXCL12 levels by elastase-driven proteolysis. Other enzymes secreted by granulocytes (e.g., matrix metalloproteinases and cathepsin G) also inactivate CXCL12 (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Inflammation Alters the BM to Prevent Cell Homing.</title><p>B220<sup>lo</sup> and B220<sup>hi</sup> BM cells from naive donors inefficiently home in immunized recipients (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). Reduced homing efficiency is not due to TNF-mediated change in the transferred cells, as TNFR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> cells do not enter the BM of immunized recipients (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> B). We conclude that inflammation modifies the BM by reducing CXCL12 sufficiently to no longer attract and/or retain lymphocytes. The observation that PTX, a G<sub>&#x003b1;i</sub> poison that inhibits most chemokine signaling (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), mimics inflammation's effects on BM and mobilizes CD93<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>lo</sup>IgM<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>) is consistent with this model, but is not a proof.</p></sec><sec><title>Retention of BM Granulocytes.</title><p>In vitro, granulocytes display strong, G<sub>&#x003b1;i</sub>-dependent chemotaxis to CXCL12 (reference <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> and unpublished data). CXCL12 and CXCR4 are crucial for both myelopoiesis and B lymphopoiesis (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), and mice reconstituted with CXCR4-deficient fetal liver cells have increased numbers of developing granulocytes and B cells in their blood (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). How is it that reductions of CXCL12 or inhibition of chemokine signaling by PTX depletes BM lymphocytes but not granulocytes?</p><p>One possibility is that the chemotactic sensitivities of B cells and granulocytes to CXCL12 differ. If granulocytes respond to significantly lower concentrations of CXCL12 (&#x0223c;1 ng/ml) than lymphocytes, reductions of CXCL12 would favor the retention of granulocytes in the BM. In the absence of CXCL12/CXCR4, such selectivity would be lost. Increased sensitivity to CXCL12 signals would also make granulocytes relatively resistant to nonsaturating doses of PTX.</p><p>Although early myeloid progenitors depend on CXCL12 to enter the BM, Gr-1<sup>int</sup> and Gr-1<sup>hi</sup> granulocytes (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) might be retained there by other chemokines. For example, LPS induces BM stromal cells to express CCL21, a chemokine for myeloid progenitors (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Other myeloid chemoattractants, CCL3 and CCL8, are expressed in BM as well (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). In this model, granulocytes would normally depend on CXCL12 homing/retention signals, but are held in the BM by other chemokines during infection.</p><p>A third possibility is that G<sub>&#x003b1;i</sub>-independent mechanisms retain granulocytes in the BM. Although the initial localization of myeloid progenitors in the BM is CXCL12 and G<sub>&#x003b1;i</sub> dependent (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), retention of developing and mature granulocytes in the BM could be G<sub>&#x003b1;i</sub>-independent (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). These PTX-insensitive pathways could be constitutive or induced by inflammation.</p><p>None of these models are mutually exclusive, and we are in the process of testing each. However, our data show that BM lymphocytes and granulocytes respond differently to environmental cues that control their retention in the BM (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Lymphopoiesis and Granulopoiesis during Inflammation.</title><p>Although severe inflammation may induce apoptosis in BM lymphocytes (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), milder inflammation mobilizes BM lymphocytes to the blood and spleen (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) and establishes extramedullary B lymphopoiesis (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Lymphocyte mobilization is associated with increased numbers of Gr-1<sup>int</sup> cells and expansion of the BM granulocyte compartment (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1, C and D</xref>). The coordination of these changes suggests a regulated, physiologic response. We propose that inflammatory agents elicit TNF&#x003b1; (and other potentiating cytokines) at sites of infection, and perhaps in the BM (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), sufficiently to suppress BM CXCL12. Initially, this suppression occurs by transcriptional inhibition (reference <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and Fig. S1), but later it occurs by proteolysis from an expanded granulocyte compartment (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). IL-1&#x003b2; promotes granulocytic expansion, especially in the presence of TNF&#x003b1; (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). Reduced CXCL12 levels mobilize BM lymphocytes, and initiate extramedullary lymphopoiesis. In the spleen, displaced CFU-B proliferate and differentiate into pre&#x02013;B and immature B cells that express RAG1/2 and &#x003bb;5 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; references <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><p>BM granulocytes appear to expand into generative niches abandoned by mobilized lymphocytes. Although IL-1&#x003b2; promotes myelopoiesis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; reference <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), its effects are strongly potentiated by TNF&#x003b1;-induced mobilizations. This synergy of TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; suggests that lymphopoiesis and myelopoiesis compete in the BM. Competition for space or resources is also implicit in pharmacologic modulations of hematopoiesis (i.e., factors that promote granulocyte development mobilize lymphocyte progenitors [reference <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and vice versa [references <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]).</p><p>Alternatively, it is possible that the recovery of BM lymphocyte compartments and increased granulocyte numbers represents a general increase in the ability of the BM to support hematopoiesis. This increased generative capacity might result from the accumulation of growth resources over the lymphopenic period.</p><p>The utility of increasing granulopoiesis in response to inflammation is obvious. Mature granulocytes are unable to divide and once activated, survive only hours to days. The ability to increase granulocyte production to replenish cells lost in inflammatory responses would be considerably advantageous as persistent neutropenia leads to death from infection (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>)</p><p>The advantage of extramedullary B lymphopoiesis is less obvious. Nonetheless, it is clear that inflammation promotes transient, extramedullary B lymphopoiesis. We think it unlikely that this splenic lymphopoiesis has no physiologic role. The appearance of CFU-B in the spleen is well regulated (unpublished data) and the number of pre&#x02013;B and immature B cells that arise there can comprise 10&#x02013;20% of splenic B220<sup>+</sup> cells (references <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>; unpublished data). Perhaps some fraction of these cells are recruited into local humoral responses (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>)?</p><p>In conclusion, adjuvant-induced BM lymphopenia reflects the mobilization of lymphocytes. This mobilization is mediated by a TNF&#x003b1;/CXCL12 axis that intimately links the innate and adaptive immune systems. Proinflammatory cytokines not only act as immune effectors and organizers of lymphoid tissue but also direct BM hematopoiesis.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We gratefully acknowledge the technical assistance of H. Kondilis, J. Dewey, and M. Murphy.</p><p>This work was supported in part by U.S. Public Health Service grants AI24335, AI49326, and AI56363 (to G. Kelsoe) and by ACS-IRG83-006 (to M. Kondo). H. Kondilis is supported by National Research Service Award AI0552077, Y. Ueda received funds from the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, and M. Kondo is the recipient of a Kimmel Scholar Award.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Young, N.S., B. Baranski, and G. Kurtzman. <year>1989</year>. The immune system as mediator of virus-associated bone marrow failure: B19 parvovirus and Epstein-Barr virus. <source>Ann. NY Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>554</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;80.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2544123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Apperley, J.F., C. Dowding, J. Hibbin, J. Buiter, E. Matutes, P.J. Sissons, M. Gordon, and J.M. Goldman. <year>1989</year>. The effect of cytomegalovirus on hemopoiesis: in vitro evidence for selective infection of marrow stromal cells. <source>Exp. Hematol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;45.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2535697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nagaoka, H., G. Gonzalez-Aseguinolaza, M. Tsuji, and M.C. Nussenzweig. <year>2000</year>. Immunization and infection change the number of recombination activating gene (RAG)&#x02013;expressing B cells in the periphery by altering immature lymphocyte production. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>191</volume>:<fpage>2113</fpage>&#x02013;2120.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10859336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gartner, F., F.W. Alt, R.J. Monroe, and K.J. Seidl. <year>2000</year>. Antigen-independent appearance of recombination activating gene (RAG)&#x02013;positive bone marrow B cells in the spleens of immunized mice. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>192</volume>:<fpage>1745</fpage>&#x02013;1754.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dorshkind, K. <year>1988</year>. Interleukin-1 inhibition of B lymphopoiesis is reversible. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>2053</fpage>&#x02013;2055.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3264197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dorshkind, K. <year>1988</year>. IL-1 inhibits B cell differentiation in long term bone marrow cultures. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>&#x02013;538.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3260256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Griffiths, S.D., D.T. Goodhead, S.J. Marsden, E.G. Wright, S. Krajewski, J.C. Reed, S.J. Korsmeyer, and M. Greaves. <year>1994</year>. Interleukin 7&#x02013;dependent B lymphocyte precursor cells are ultrasensitive to apoptosis. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>179</volume>:<fpage>1789</fpage>&#x02013;1797.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8195708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lin, Q., C. Dong, and M.D. Cooper. <year>1998</year>. Impairment of T and B cell development by treatment with a type I interferon. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>187</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;87.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9419213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Binder, D., J. Fehr, H. Hengartner, and R.M. Zinkernagel. <year>1997</year>. Virus-induced transient bone marrow aplasia: major role of interferon-&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; during acute infection with the noncytopathic lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;530.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9053452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang, J., Q. Lin, H. Langston, and M.D. Cooper. <year>1995</year>. Resident bone marrow macrophages produce type 1 interferons that can selectively inhibit interleukin-7-driven growth of B lineage cells. <source>Immunity.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>475</fpage>&#x02013;484.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7584138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gongora, R., R.P. Stephan, R.D. Schreiber, and M.D. Cooper. <year>2000</year>. Stat-1 is not essential for inhibition of B lymphopoiesis by type I IFNs. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>165</volume>:<fpage>2362</fpage>&#x02013;2366.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10946258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hikida, M., M. Mori, T. Takai, K. Tomochika, K. Hamatani, and H. Ohmori. <year>1996</year>. Reexpression of RAG-1 and RAG-2 genes in activated mature mouse B cells. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>2092</fpage>&#x02013;2094.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8953042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Han, S., B. Zheng, D.G. Schatz, E. Spanopoulou, and G. Kelsoe. <year>1996</year>. Neoteny in lymphocytes: Rag1 and Rag2 expression in germinal center B cells. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>2094</fpage>&#x02013;2097.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8953043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hertz, M., V. Kouskoff, T. Nakamura, and D. Nemazee. <year>1998</year>. V(D)J recombinase induction in splenic B lymphocytes is inhibited by antigen-receptor signalling. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>394</volume>:<fpage>292</fpage>&#x02013;295.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9685161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Papavasiliou, F., R. Casellas, H. Suh, X.F. Qin, E. Besmer, R. Pelanda, D. Nemazee, K. Rajewsky, and M.C. Nussenzweig. <year>1997</year>. V(D)J recombination in mature B cells: a mechanism for altering antibody responses. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>&#x02013;301.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9323210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Meffre, E., F. Papavasiliou, P. Cohen, O. de Bouteiller, D. Bell, H. Karasuyama, C. Schiff, J. Banchereau, Y.J. Liu, and M.C. Nussenzweig. <year>1998</year>. Antigen receptor engagement turns off the V(D)J recombination machinery in human tonsil B cells. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>&#x02013;772.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9705958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Han, S., S.R. Dillon, B. Zheng, M. Shimoda, M.S. Schlissel, and G. Kelsoe. <year>1997</year>. V(D)J recombinase activity in a subset of germinal center B lymphocytes. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;305.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9323211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Monroe, R.J., K.J. Seidl, F. Gaertner, S. Han, F. Chen, J. Sekiguchi, J. Wang, R. Ferrini, L. Davidson, G. Kelsoe, and F.W. Alt. <year>1999</year>. RAG2:GFP knockin mice reveal novel aspects of RAG2 expression in primary and peripheral lymphoid tissues. <source>Immunity.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;212.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10485655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yu, W., H. Nagaoka, M. Jankovic, Z. Misulovin, H. Suh, A. Rolink, F. Melchers, E. Meffre, and M.C. Nussenzweig. <year>1999</year>. Continued RAG expression in late stages of B cell development and no apparent re-induction after immunization. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>400</volume>:<fpage>682</fpage>&#x02013;687.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10458165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cyster, J.G., and C.C. Goodnow. <year>1995</year>. Pertussis toxin inhibits migration of B and T lymphocytes into splenic white pulp cords. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>182</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#x02013;586.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7629515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marino, M.W., A. Dunn, D. Grail, M. Inglese, Y. Noguchi, E. Richards, A. Jungbluth, H. Wada, M. Moore, B. Williamson, et al. <year>1997</year>. Characterization of tumor necrosis factor-deficient mice. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>8093</fpage>&#x02013;8098.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9223320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tacchini-Cottier, F., C. Vesin, M. Redard, W. Buurman, and P.F. Piguet. <year>1998</year>. Role of TNFR1 and TNFR2 in TNF-induced platelet consumption in mice. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>6182</fpage>&#x02013;6186.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9637537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chen, Z., S.B. Koralov, M. Gendelman, M.C. Carroll, and G. Kelsoe. <year>2000</year>. Humoral immune responses in Cr2&#x02212;/&#x02212; mice: enhanced affinity maturation but impaired antibody persistence. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>164</volume>:<fpage>4522</fpage>&#x02013;4532.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rolink, A.G., J. Andersson, and F. Melchers. <year>1998</year>. Characterization of immature B cells by a novel monoclonal antibody, by turnover and by mitogen reactivity. <source>Eur. J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>3738</fpage>&#x02013;3748.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9842916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Norsworthy, P., E. Theodoridis, M. Botto, P. Athanassiou, H. Beynon, C. Gordon, D. Isenberg, M.J. Walport, and K.A. Davies. <year>1999</year>. Overrepresentation of the Fcgamma receptor type IIA R131/R131 genotype in caucasoid systemic lupus erythematosus patients with autoantibodies to C1q and glomerulonephritis. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source>
<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1828</fpage>&#x02013;1832.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10513796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Petrenko, O., A. Beavis, M. Klaine, R. Kittappa, I. Godin, and I.R. Lemischka. <year>1999</year>. The molecular characterization of the fetal stem cell marker AA4. <source>Immunity.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>691</fpage>&#x02013;700.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10403644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McGreal, E.P., N. Ikewaki, H. Akatsu, B.P. Morgan, and P. Gasque. <year>2002</year>. Human C1qRp is identical with CD93 and the mNI-11 antigen but does not bind C1q. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>168</volume>:<fpage>5222</fpage>&#x02013;5232.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11994479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hestdal, K., F.W. Ruscetti, J.N. Ihle, S.E. Jacobsen, C.M. Dubois, W.C. Kopp, D.L. Longo, and J.R. Keller. <year>1991</year>. Characterization and regulation of RB6-8C5 antigen expression on murine bone marrow cells. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;28.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1711076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Loder, F., B. Mutschler, R. Ray, C. Paige, P. Sideras, R. Torres, M. Lamers, and R. Carsetti. <year>1999</year>. B cell development in the spleen takes place in discrete steps and is determined by the quality of B cell receptor&#x02013;derived signals. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;89.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10429672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nagasawa, T., S. Hirota, K. Tachibana, N. Takakura, S. Nishikawa, Y. Kitamura, N. Yoshida, H. Kikutani, and T. Kishimoto. <year>1996</year>. Defects of B-cell lymphopoiesis and bone-marrow myelopoiesis in mice lacking the CXC chemokine PBSF/SDF-1. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>382</volume>:<fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;638.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8757135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ma, Q., D. Jones, P.R. Borghesani, R.A. Segal, T. Nagasawa, T. Kishimoto, R.T. Bronson, and T.A. Springer. <year>1998</year>. Impaired B-lymphopoiesis, myelopoiesis, and derailed cerebellar neuron migration in CXCR4- and SDF-1-deficient mice. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>9448</fpage>&#x02013;9453.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9689100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zou, Y.R., A.H. Kottmann, M. Kuroda, I. Taniuchi, and D.R. Littman. <year>1998</year>. Function of the chemokine receptor CXCR4 in haematopoiesis and in cerebellar development. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>393</volume>:<fpage>595</fpage>&#x02013;599.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9634238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ma, Q., D. Jones, and T.A. Springer. <year>1999</year>. The chemokine receptor CXCR4 is required for the retention of B lineage and granulocytic precursors within the bone marrow microenvironment. <source>Immunity.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;471.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10229189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Aiuti, A., I.J. Webb, C. Bleul, T. Springer, and J.C. Gutierrez-Ramos. <year>1997</year>. The chemokine SDF-1 is a chemoattractant for human CD34<sup>+</sup> hematopoietic progenitor cells and provides a new mechanism to explain the mobilization of CD34<sup>+</sup> progenitors to peripheral blood. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;120.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8996247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Petit, I., M. Szyper-Kravitz, A. Nagler, M. Lahav, A. Peled, L. Habler, T. Ponomaryov, R.S. Taichman, F. Arenzana-Seisdedos, N. Fujii, et al. <year>2002</year>. G-CSF induces stem cell mobilization by decreasing bone marrow SDF-1 and up-regulating CXCR4. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>687</fpage>&#x02013;694. (published erratum in <italic>Nat. Immunol</italic>. 2002. 3:787)
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12068293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tashiro, K., H. Tada, R. Heilker, M. Shirozu, T. Nakano, and T. Honjo. <year>1993</year>. Signal sequence trap: a cloning strategy for secreted proteins and type I membrane proteins. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>261</volume>:<fpage>600</fpage>&#x02013;603.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8342023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fedyk, E.R., D. Jones, H.O. Critchley, R.P. Phipps, T.M. Blieden, and T.A. Springer. <year>2001</year>. Expression of stromal-derived factor-1 is decreased by IL-1 and TNF and in dermal wound healing. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>166</volume>:<fpage>5749</fpage>&#x02013;5754.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11313418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McQuibban, G.A., G.S. Butler, J.H. Gong, L. Bendall, C. Power, I. Clark-Lewis, and C.M. Overall. <year>2001</year>. Matrix metalloproteinase activity inactivates the CXC chemokine stromal cell-derived factor-1. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>43503</fpage>&#x02013;43508.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11571304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Delgado, M.B., I. Clark-Lewis, P. Loetscher, H. Langen, M. Thelen, M. Baggiolini, and M. Wolf. <year>2001</year>. Rapid inactivation of stromal cell-derived factor-1 by cathepsin G associated with lymphocytes. <source>Eur. J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>699</fpage>&#x02013;707.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11241273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ulich, T.R., J. del Castillo, R.X. Ni, and N. Bikhazi. <year>1989</year>. Hematologic interactions of endotoxin, tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF alpha), interleukin 1, and adrenal hormones and the hematologic effects of TNF alpha in Corynebacterium parvum-primed rats. <source>J. Leukoc. Biol.</source>
<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>&#x02013;557.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2786048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bleul, C.C., R.C. Fuhlbrigge, J.M. Casasnovas, A. Aiuti, and T.A. Springer. <year>1996</year>. A highly efficacious lymphocyte chemoattractant, stromal cell&#x02013;derived factor 1 (SDF-1). <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>1101</fpage>&#x02013;1109.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9064327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Delgado, E., V. Finkel, M. Baggiolini, C.R. Mackay, R.M. Steinman, and A. Granelli-Piperno. <year>1998</year>. Mature dendritic cells respond to SDF-1, but not to several beta-chemokines. <source>Immunobiology.</source>
<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>490</fpage>&#x02013;500.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9561368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Broxmeyer, H.E., B.S. Youn, C. Kim, G. Hangoc, S. Cooper, and C. Mantel. <year>2001</year>. Chemokine regulation of hematopoiesis and the involvement of pertussis toxin-sensitive G alpha i proteins. <source>Ann. NY Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>938</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;127; discussion 127&#x02013;128.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11458498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kim, C.H., and H.E. Broxmeyer. <year>1998</year>. In vitro behavior of hematopoietic progenitor cells under the influence of chemoattractants: stromal cell-derived factor-1, steel factor, and the bone marrow environment. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>&#x02013;110.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9414273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rossi, D., and A. Zlotnik. <year>2000</year>. The biology of chemokines and their receptors. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;242.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10837058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zaballos, A., J. Gutierrez, R. Varona, C. Ardavin, and G. Marquez. <year>1999</year>. Cutting edge: identification of the orphan chemokine receptor GPR-9-6 as CCR9, the receptor for the chemokine TECK. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>5671</fpage>&#x02013;5675.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10229797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nakayama, T., K. Hieshima, D. Izawa, Y. Tatsumi, A. Kanamaru, and O. Yoshie. <year>2003</year>. Cutting edge: profile of chemokine receptor expression on human plasma cells accounts for their efficient recruitment to target tissues. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>170</volume>:<fpage>1136</fpage>&#x02013;1140.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wilbanks, A., S.C. Zondlo, K. Murphy, S. Mak, D. Soler, P. Langdon, D.P. Andrew, L. Wu, and M. Briskin. <year>2001</year>. Expression cloning of the STRL33/BONZO/TYMSTR ligand reveals elements of CC, CXC, and CX3C chemokines. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>166</volume>:<fpage>5145</fpage>&#x02013;5154.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11290797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Diacovo, T.G., S.J. Roth, J.M. Buccola, D.F. Bainton, and T.A. Springer. <year>1996</year>. Neutrophil rolling, arrest, and transmigration across activated, surface-adherent platelets via sequential action of P-selectin and the beta 2-integrin CD11b/CD18. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>&#x02013;157.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8704169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Beutler, B., and A. Cerami. <year>1989</year>. The biology of cachectin/TNF&#x02013;a primary mediator of the host response. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>&#x02013;655.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2540776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dorshkind, K. <year>1991</year>. In vivo administration of recombinant granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor results in a reversible inhibition of primary B lymphopoiesis. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>4204</fpage>&#x02013;4208.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2040797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Damia, G., K.L. Komschlies, C.R. Faltynek, F.W. Ruscetti, and R.H. Wiltrout. <year>1992</year>. Administration of recombinant human interleukin-7 alters the frequency and number of myeloid progenitor cells in the bone marrow and spleen of mice. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>1121</fpage>&#x02013;1129.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1536940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Grzegorzewski, K., K.L. Komschlies, M. Mori, K. Kaneda, N. Usui, C.R. Faltynek, J.R. Keller, F.W. Ruscetti, and R.H. Wiltrout. <year>1994</year>. Administration of recombinant human interleukin-7 to mice induces the exportation of myeloid progenitor cells from the bone marrow to peripheral sites. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;385.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8286738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Engle, W.D., and C.R. Rosenfeld. <year>1984</year>. Neutropenia in high-risk neonates. <source>J. Pediatr.</source>
<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>982</fpage>&#x02013;986.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6502353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gessler, P., R. Luders, S. Konig, N. Haas, P. Lasch, and W. Kachel. <year>1995</year>. Neonatal neutropenia in low birthweight premature infants. <source>Am. J. Perinatol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;38.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7710574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Meffre, E., E. Davis, C. Schiff, C. Cunningham-Rundles, L.B. Ivashkiv, L.M. Staudt, J.W. Young, and M.C. Nussenzweig. <year>2000</year>. Circulating human B cells that express surrogate light chains and edited receptors. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;213.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10973277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
