<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17341466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1874590</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl1113</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Involvement of chromatin and histone deacetylation in SV40&#x02009;T antigen transcription regulation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valls</surname><given-names>Ester</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blanco-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>Noem&#x000ed;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aquizu</surname><given-names>Naiara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Piedra</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Estar&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>Conchi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de la Cruz</surname><given-names>Xavier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Balb&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>Marian A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Instituto de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular de Barcelona. CID. Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas (CSIC). Josep Samitier 1,5. Parc Cientific de Barcelona. E-08028 Barcelona. Spain, <sup>2</sup>Institut de Recerca Biom&#x000e9;dica-PCB. Josep Samitier 1, 5. E-08028 Barcelona, Spain and <sup>3</sup>Institut Catal&#x000e0; per la Recerca i Estudis Avan&#x000e7;ats (ICREA). Passeig Llu&#x000ed;s Companys, 23. E-08018 Barcelona, Spain</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondance should be addressed. <phone>34-93-4034961</phone><fax>34-93-4034979</fax><email>mmbbmc@ibmb.csic.es</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1958</fpage><lpage>1968</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Simian Virus 40 (SV40) large T antigen (T Ag) is a multifunctional viral oncoprotein that regulates viral and cellular transcriptional activity. However, the mechanisms by which such regulation occurs remain unclear. Here we show that T antigen represses CBP-mediated transcriptional activity. This repression is concomitant with histone H3 deacetylation and is TSA sensitive. Moreover, our results demonstrate that T antigen interacts with HDAC1 <italic>in vitro</italic> in an Rb-independent manner. In addition, the overexpression of HDAC1 cooperates with T antigen to antagonize CBP transactivation function and correlates with chromatin deacetylation of the TK promoter. Finally, decreasing HDAC1 levels with small interfering RNA (siRNA) partially abolishes T antigen-induced repression. These findings highlight the importance of the histone acetylation/deacetylation balance in the cellular transformation mediated by oncoviral proteins.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Simian virus 40 (SV40) large T antigen (T Ag) is a 708-amino-acid multifunctional oncoviral protein involved in numerous viral and cellular processes, including viral replication, transcriptional activation and repression, and blockade of differentiation and cell transformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). T antigen can be post-translationally modified by phosphorylation, glycosylation, adenylation and ADP ribosylation. Moreover, T antigen can be acetylated by CBP in a p53-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>), although the functional consequences of this modification remain largely unknown. The ability of T Ag to transform cells depends on complex interactions between viral oncoproteins and the various intracellular proteins involved in cell control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>) and transcription regulation, such as p53 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>), pRb and the Rb-related proteins p107 and p130 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6 B7 B8 B9">6&#x02013;9</xref>) and CBP/p300 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10 B11 B12 B13">10&#x02013;13</xref>). T antigen requires the LXCXE motif to interact with the pRb protein family. Two regions in the C-terminal part of the T antigen protein are required for p53 binding. Finally, the regions of T antigen required for CBP/p300 interaction overlap these p53-binding regions. Other oncoviral proteins, such as E1A, also require CBP/p300 and p53 targeting for cell transformation.</p><p>Histone acetylation at the N-terminal tails is a regulatory mechanism that controls gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Histone acetylation levels inside cells are maintained through the coordinated action of histone acetyltransferases (HATs) and deacetylases (HDACs). CBP/p300, a coactivator protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) involved in both proliferative and differentiating pathways, contains HAT activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). CBP/p300 is ubiquitously expressed and regulates a broad spectrum of biological activities such as proliferation, differentiation, cell cycle control and apoptosis. To accomplish such processes, CBP/p300 must be recruited to a specific promoter via interactions with a sequence-specific transcription factor, including CREB, c-Myb, MyoD, E2F1, p53, nuclear hormone receptors, etc.</p><p>In mammalian cells, HDAC1 and HDAC2 are found in multiprotein complexes. These have been implicated as corepressors that associate with different factors such as Rb, Mad, MeCP2, etc., in repressing transcription.</p><p>Several reports have shown that viral oncoproteins select HAT enzymes as cellular partners, in some cases disrupting enzymatic activity. E1A can increase, decrease or redirect CBP/p300 HAT activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19 B20 B21">19&#x02013;21</xref>); while CBP, by interacting with T antigen increases its HAT activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). In addition, CBP, p300 and P/CAF acetylate several viral oncoproteins such as AdE1A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>) and T antigen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>), although the consequences of these modifications remain to be elucidated. Oncoviral proteins also target HDAC complexes: the adenovirus E1B-55K protein interacts with a mSin3A-histone deacetylase 1 complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>); HIV Tat displaces HDAC1, which is bound to SATB1, leading to increased acetylation of promoters <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>); the Epstein-barr virus nuclear antigen 3C interacts with HDAC1 to repress transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>); the E7 oncoprotein from papilloma virus type 16 (HPV16) interacts with HDAC activity, resulting in the stimulation of cell growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>).</p><p>T antigen affects transcription levels of the cAMP-responsive promoter, which is modulated <italic>in vivo</italic> by p300 in REV2 cells. Moreover, by interacting with CBP/p300, T antigen abrogates CBP/p300-mediated transcriptional activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>), although the mechanism involved remains unclear. Here we examine the mechanisms underlying the repressive behavior of T antigen. Our results not only show that T antigen repression is alleviated by increasing cellular acetylation levels via trichostatin A (TSA) treatment, but also that it acts concomitantly with histone H3 deacetylation. Moreover, we have demonstrated that T antigen interacts <italic>in vitro</italic> with HDAC1 in an Rb-independent manner. The data presented in this study link chromatin modification to T antigen transcriptional regulatory potential.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Constructs</title><p>PSG5-T antigen, PSG5-T antigen K1 and PSG5-T antigen PVU-1 plasmids were kindly provided by Dr J. DeCaprio. pcDNA3Gal4-HAT-CBP2, pcDNA3Gal4-HAT, pcDNA3Gal4-CBP (FL) and pcDNA3-HDAC1-Flag constructs have been previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>) and were kindly provided by Dr T. Kouzarides. The Gal4-TK-luciferase and Gal4-hsp70-&#x003b2;gal reporters were supplied by Dr J. Bernues. The pSUPER-Control-siRNA was kindly provided by Dr E. Mart&#x000ed;.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell cultures, transfections and reporter gene assays</title><p>HeLa, CV1 and CV1COS cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) with 10% foetal calf serum (FCS) and grown at 37&#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells were transfected by a standard calcium phosphate coprecipitation (for luciferase and &#x003b2; galactosidase assays) or with a Jet-PEI Kit (Polyplus-Transfection, Illkirch, France) (for ChIPs and siRNA assays) with 0.1&#x02013;2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g (as indicated) of either expression vector and with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g reporter plasmid. The cells were then washed in PBS after 14&#x02009;h and harvested 36&#x02009;h after transfection (except when indicated). They were subsequently washed once in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). Luciferase and &#x003b2; galactosidase assays were performed using a &#x02018;Promega Dual Kit&#x02019; and a &#x02018;Promega Galactosidase Kit&#x02019; respectively, following the manufacturer's instructions. The TSA treatment was conducted at 100&#x02009;nM for 18&#x02009;h.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell extract preparation and protein content estimation</title><p>Total cell extracts were prepared as follows: cells were lysed in 1&#x02009;ml of buffer A (50&#x02009;mM Tris, pH 8, 150&#x02009;mM NaCl, 0.5% NP40, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml of aprotinin and leupeptin, 1&#x02009;mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 50&#x02009;mM NaF and 10&#x02009;mM Na<sub>2</sub>-B-glycerophosphate) by maintaining the cells for 20&#x02009;min on ice; cell debris were removed by centrifugation at 12&#x02009;000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 10&#x02009;min at 4&#x000b0;C. Protein content was measured by using the &#x02018;BIO-RAD protein assay reagent&#x02019; following the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec><title>Chromatin immunoprecipitation analysis (ChIPs)</title><p>HeLa cells were treated with 1% formaldehyde at room temperature for 15&#x02009;min. The reaction was stopped by the addition of glycine to a final concentration of 125&#x02009;mM. Cells were washed once in ice-cold PBS, once in buffer I (0.25% triton X-100, 10&#x02009;mM EDTA, 0.5&#x02009;mM EGTA, 10&#x02009;mM Hepes pH 6.5) and in buffer II (200&#x02009;mM NaCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA, 0.5&#x02009;mM EGTA, 10&#x02009;mM Hepes pH 6.5) at 4&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min. The pellet was then resuspended in lysis buffer (1% SDS, 10&#x02009;mM EDTA, 50&#x02009;mM Tris pH 8.1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml protease inhibitors, 1&#x02009;mM PMSF) and sonicated on ice until the cross-linked chromatin was sheared to an average DNA fragment length of 0.2 &#x02013; 0.5&#x02009;kbp. After centrifugation (10 &#x02013; 45&#x02009;min 12&#x02009;000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>) soluble cross-linked chromatin was diluted 1:10 in immunoprecipitation (IP) buffer (1% triton X-100, 2&#x02009;mM EDTA, 150&#x02009;mM NaCl, 20&#x02009;mM Tris pH 8 and protease inhibitors), divided into aliquots and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. Chromatin preparations were pre-cleared by incubation with Protein A-Sepharose solution: 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g pre-immune serum (35&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g herring sperm DNA (1&#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l), 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;l Protein A-Sepharose CL4B (Amersham-Pharmacia) 10% in TE buffer (50&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/500&#x02009;&#x003bc;l TE) in IP buffer for 2&#x02009;h at 4&#x000b0;C under rotation. The protein A-Sepharose was removed by centrifugation; the pre-cleared chromatin was immunoprecipitated by incubation with the antibody O/N at 4&#x000b0;C. The immunoprecipitates were washed in buffers TSE I (0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 2 Mm EDTA, 20&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 150&#x02009;mM NaCl), TSE II (0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 2 Mm EDTA, 20&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 500&#x02009;mM NaCl), buffer III (0.25&#x02009;M LiCl, 1% NP40, 1% Deoxycholate, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA, 10&#x02009;mM Tris-HC l pH 8), and three times with Tris-EDTA (TE) buffer. Washed pellets were eluted in 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of a solution containing 1% SDS, 0.1&#x02009;M NaHCO3. Eluted pellets were de-cross-linked O/N at 65&#x000b0;C, and then purified in 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;l TE buffer using a DNA purification kit (Amersham-Pharmacia). The DNA was analyzed by PCR. The antibodies used were as follows: rabbit polyclonal antibody against Acetyl H3 (k9, k14) and Poly-acetyl H4 (K5, K8, K12, K16) (Upstate) and HDAC1 (Abcam).</p></sec><sec><title>PCR analysis</title><p>PCR analysis was performed as described by Breiling and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). PCR products measured 220&#x02013;330&#x02009;bp and were resolved by agarose-gel electrophoresis and revealed by staining with ethidium bromide. Decreasing amounts of input DNA (10, 1, 0.1 and 0.01%) were used to determine the linear range of the PCR reactions for each primer pair and IP. The following primer pairs were used: 5&#x02032;CATGTCGATCCGCTCGG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CTTTATGTTTTTGGCGTCTTCCA-3&#x02032;, for TK-luc promoter and 5&#x02032;CCCCAAAGGTTGCCTGGCGG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;CAAGATGAGAGGAGGCTGGG-3&#x02032; for PDGF &#x003b2;-receptor promoter, provided by TIB MOLBIOL (Germany).</p></sec><sec><title>ChIP quantification</title><p>PCR gel bands were quantified with QuantityOne software (Bio-Rad). Values from immunoprecipitated samples were subsequently divided by that corresponding to 1% input sample (the PCR signals of this input sample were not saturated). Bound/input values were then averaged from multiple (at least three) PCR reactions from independent experiments. All data in the figures correspond to percentages of the 1% input sample.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> translations, recombinant proteins and pull-down assays</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> translations and GST pull-downs were performed essentially as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). GST and GST fusion proteins were expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> XA90 using the pGEX (Pharmacia) vector system, for 4&#x02009;h following the addition of 0.1&#x02009;mM IPTG at 30&#x000b0;C. Purification from crude bacterial lysates was performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). PGEX-HDAC1 has been described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The buffer used for the pull-downs was a variation of Z&#x02032; (25&#x02009;mM HEPES pH 7.5, 12.5&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 20% glycerol, 0.1% NP40, 250&#x02009;mM KCl).</p></sec><sec><title>Cell proliferation assays</title><p>Doubling time and saturation density were measured using a modification of a previously described method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). CV1 and CV1COS cells were seeded at a density of 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/60&#x02009;mm plate in CS (10%)-containing DMEM. This time point was considered as day 1. The remaining cultures were incubated with 10% serum-containing DMEM and replenished every day. Cells were trypsinized and counted by a hemocytometer every day.</p></sec><sec><title>siRNA interference</title><p>Target sequences for small interfering RNAs (siRNS) for HDAC1 are available upon request. The oligonucleotides were cloned into a pSUPER vector (OligoEngine) at the <italic>Bgl</italic>II and <italic>Hin</italic>dIII sites. The siRNAs were transfected twice using Jet-Pei&#x02122; (Polyplus-Transfection, Illkirch, France) at 12&#x02009;h intervals. Target sequences for control small interfering RNAs (c-siRNA) were as follows: (forward) CCAGCGCTACGGCTGGCAC; (reverse) GTGCCAGCCGTAGCGCTGG, neither of which cross-hybridize with any human sequence.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>T antigen represses the transcriptional activity of CBP</title><p>Several independent findings indicate that SV40&#x02009;T antigen represses the transcriptional activity of CBP (FL) on the thymidine kinase (TK) promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). On the other hand, our previous results show that T antigen cooperates with HAT-CBP2 to activate the hsp70 promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). This apparent discrepancy may stem from (i) the dual role of T antigen as a promoter-dependent corepressor and coactivator or (ii) the differential effects of T antigen on CBP (FL) and HAT-CBP2. To investigate these possibilities, we first analyzed whether T antigen represses the transcriptional activity of HAT-CBP2 on the TK promoter. To this end, transient transfections into HeLa cells were performed using HAT and CBP2 (which contains the T antigen interaction region) domains of CBP fused to the Gal4 DNA-binding domain (GAL-HAT-CBP2). The transactivation activity due to the fusion protein was measured with a luciferase reporter vector containing five Gal4 DNA-binding sites upstream of the TK promoter (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). T antigen repressed the transcriptional activity mediated by GAL-HAT-CBP2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). Efficient repression depends on the presence of the CBP2 domain (T antigen-binding region), since the transcriptional activity of the GAL-HAT fusion protein lacking the T antigen-interacting region was only slightly (19%) repressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). As previously reported, CBP (FL) activity on the TK promoter was also repressed by T antigen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C). These results indicate not only that T antigen may work as a repressor of CBP (FL) and HAT-CBP2, but also that it requires the T antigen-CBP interacting domain (CBP2).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>T antigen regulates CBP-mediated transcriptional activation. <bold>(A)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of the Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter, 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pcDNA3-Gal-HAT-CBP2, 1 and 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pSG5-T antigen or the empty vector and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of renilla reporter vector. Whole cell extracts were used in the luciferase-renilla assay. The activity derived from the Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter was normalized to 1.0 and the other activities are expressed relative to this. The data represent an average of at least four independent transfections. <bold>(B)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected as in (A), but the pcDNA3-Gal-HAT expression vector was used instead of pcDNA3-Gal-HAT-CBP2. <bold>(C)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of the Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter, 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pcDNA3-Gal-CBP (FL), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pSG5-T antigen or the empty vector and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of renilla reporter vector. Whole cell extracts were used in the luciferase-renilla assay. The transcriptional activities are expressed as in (A). The data represent an average of at least four independent transfections. <bold>(D)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of the Gal4-hsp70-&#x003b2;gal reporter, 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pcDNA3-Gal-CBP (FL), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pSG5-T antigen or the empty vector and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of renilla reporter vector. Whole cell extracts were used in the &#x003b2; galactosidase and renilla assays. The activity derived from the Gal4-hsp70-&#x003b2;gal reporter was normalized to 1.0 and the other activities are expressed relative to this. The data represent an average of at least three independent transfections. A schematic representation of the constructs used is shown at the bottom of each figure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1113f1"/></fig></p><p>These data also suggest that T antigen may play a dual role as a positive or negative regulator of CBP transcriptional activity in a promoter-dependent manner. To confirm this hypothesis, we analyzed whether T antigen acts in tandem with CBP (FL) on the hsp70 promoter to activate transcription. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>D shows that overexpression of T antigen clearly increases the CBP-mediated transcriptional activity on the hsp70 promoter.</p><p>We wanted to better determine the molecular mechanisms involved in T antigen-mediated repression. To this end, we repeated the experiment in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A in the presence of the histone deacetylase inhibitor TSA. The results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> show that the T antigen-induced repression of HAT-CBP2 activity is partially abolished (by 50 &#x02013; 55%). These data suggest that histone deacetylase activity plays a role in T antigen-mediated repression.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>T antigen-mediated repression is TSA sensitive. HeLa cells were transfected as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A and 100&#x02009;nM TSA was added 18&#x02009;h before collection. Whole cell extracts were prepared and used in the luciferase/renilla assay as indicated above. The data represent an average of at least four independent transfections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1113f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Transcriptional repression of CBP by T antigen correlates with chromatin deacetylation</title><p>To assess whether histone deacetylation is involved in T antigen-mediated repression, we analyzed the chromatin acetylation status on the TK promoter using chromatin immunoprecipitation assays (ChIPs). To this end, HeLa cells were transfected with the TK promoter (containing Gal 4 binding sites) and Gal-CBP in the presence or absence of T antigen, as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A. Cross-linked and sonicated chromatin was immunoprecipitated using an antibody directed against acetylated histone H3 (lysines 9 and 14) and against acetylated histone H4 (lysines 5, 8, 12 and 16). The precipitated DNA was analyzed by PCR with primers spanning the TK promoter and the luciferase coding gene region. The resulting data were normalized relative to the 1% (unsaturated) input. The results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A and B indicate that Gal-CBP activation (lane 2) correlates with an increase (2&#x02013;3 fold) in H3 acetylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A and B) as well as a slight increase in H4 acetylation (lane 2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A and B). The addition of T antigen (lane 3) leads to the clear deacetylation of both H3 and H4 to basal levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A and B). No PCR products were detected in extracts subjected to immunoprecipitation with non-specific antiserum (mock) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). These data confirm the previous hypothesis that histone deacetylation acts as a mechanism involved in T antigen repression.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>T antigen repression correlates with histone H3 deacetylation. <bold>(A)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter (lane 1), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of Gal-CBP (FL) (lane 2) and 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pSG5-T antigen (lane 3) and comparative ChIP analysis were performed in parallel with the same number of cells using antibodies that specifically recognize acetylated histone H3 (K 9 and 14) and poly-acetylated histone H4. The immunoprecipitates were analyzed by quantitative PCR using specific primers for the TK promoter. PCR products were resolved in agarose gels and quantified with QuantityOne software (Bio-Rad). A schematic representation of the TK-luciferase promoter and the position of the primers used for ChIP are shown at the bottom of the figure. <bold>(B)</bold> Quantification of PCR products from (A) was conducted as described in Materials and Methods. The values on the <italic>y</italic> axis represent the amount of immunoprecipitated DNA as a percentage of the 1% input sample. Relative histone modification levels were calculated from three independent experiments. <bold>(C)</bold> Comparative ChIP analysis performed in parallel with the same number of CV1 and CV1COS cells using antibodies that specifically recognize acetylated histone H3 (K 9 and 14) and poly-acetylated histone H4. The immunoprecipitates were analyzed by quantitative PCR using specific primers for the PDGF &#x003b2;-receptor promoter. PCR products were resolved in agarose gels and quantified as described in (B). Relative histone modification levels were calculated from two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1113f3"/></fig></p><p>Finally, we wanted to test whether histone deacetylation is involved in the T antigen-mediated repression of a natural promoter. To this end we analyzed the chromatin acetylation status on the PDGF &#x003b2;-receptor promoter. It has been previously shown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>) that T antigen represses this promoter in the absence of pRb and p53 in Saos-2 cells stably expressing T antigen, probably by interfering with the transcriptional activity of Sp1, which utilizes CBP as a coactivator. Thus, we first tested whether histone deacetylation was involved in T antigen-mediated repression of the PDGF &#x003b2;-receptor by testing the chromatin acetylation status on this promoter in CV1 and CV1COS cells. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C shows a clear decrease (4&#x02009;&#x02013;5 fold) in H3 as well as a slight decrease (2 fold) in H4 acetylation in CV1COS compared with CV1 cells. No PCR products were detected in extracts subjected to immunoprecipitation with non-specific antiserum. These results suggest that histone deacetylation is involved in T antigen repression <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>T antigen interacts with Histone Deacetylase 1
(HDAC1) <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>Based on our previous data, we investigated whether T antigen physically interacts with histone deacetylase enzymes. Thus, we therefore performed <italic>in vitro</italic> pull-down assays using 35-S-labeled T antigen. In these experiments, different bacterially expressed GST-HDACs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A) were incubated with 35-S-labeled T antigen. Reaction mixtures were precipitated using GST-resin and the interacting 35-S-T antigen was detected radiographically. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B, HDAC1 clearly interacts with T antigen <italic>in vitro</italic>. Under the same experimental conditions, HDAC1 bound neither to an unrelated GST-protein fusion (data not shown), nor to GST (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). It has been previously shown that T antigen interacts with retinoblastoma products (pRb), thereby inducing cell-cycle progression. On the other hand, several reports have shown that pRb interacts with HDAC1 to mediate transcriptional repression on gene promoters involved in the G1/S phase transition of the cell cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). Thus, we decided to assess whether the T antigen-HDAC1 interaction that we detected was mediated by pRb. To this end, we repeated the previous experiments using two well-characterized T antigen mutants that do not bind pRb (T antigen K1 and PVU-1, see Methods). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B shows clear T antigen K1, PVU-1 and HDAC1 interacting signals.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>T antigen interacts with HDAC1 <italic>in vitro</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold> Protein gel of GST-HDAC1(51-482) and GST-HDAC1(1-382) fusion proteins expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and used in the <italic>in vitro</italic> pull-down experiment in (B). <bold>(B)</bold> GST, GST-HDAC1(1-382) and GST-HDAC1(51-482) fusion proteins were expressed in <italic>E. Coli</italic>. Binding of the fusion proteins to T antigen WT and pRb-binding mutants [K1 (E107K) and PVU-1 (dl-107-112Y)] <italic>in vitro</italic> was determined using an <italic>in vitro</italic> pull-down experiment (see Material and Methods). Input represents 50% of total T antigen input. The arrow indicates the T antigen or T antigen mutant's position in the gel. <bold>(C)</bold> 35-S-labeled T antigen was bound to the GST-CBP2 fusion protein. Binding of the complex GST-CBP2-TAg, GST-CBP2 and GST to 35-S-labeled HDAC1 <italic>in vitro</italic> was determined by an <italic>in vitro</italic> pull-down experiment (left panel). The position of T antigen and HDAC1 in the gel is indicated with arrows. Protein gel of GST-CBP2 and GST proteins expressed in <italic>E. Coli</italic> and used in the <italic>in vitro</italic> pull-down experiment (right panel).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1113f4"/></fig></p><p>We then sought to determine whether T antigen could bridge CBP and HDAC1 cofactors. To this end, GST-CBP was bound to 35-S-labeled T antigen using an <italic>in vitro</italic> pull-down assay. The complex GST-CBP-T antigen as well as the recombinant GST-CBP were incubated with 35-S-labeled HDAC1. The reaction mixtures were precipitated using GST-resin and the interacting HDAC1 was detected either radiographically or via western blot (data not shown). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C shows that T antigen is capable of bridging CBP and HDAC1. It is worth noting that in the absence of T antigen, GST-CBP interacts weakly with HDAC1. However, previously bound T antigen clearly increases this interaction, suggesting that T antigen helps to recruit HDAC1 to the CBP-regulated promoters.</p><p>Afterwards, we analyzed whether T antigen and HDAC1 also interact <italic>in vivo</italic> by conducting co-immunoprecipitation experiments using CV1COS cells, and by two-hybrids analysis, however, no clear interaction was observed.</p></sec><sec><title>HDAC1 cooperates with T antigen to antagonize the transcriptional activity of CBP</title><p>Our previous results showed that T antigen not only represses the transcriptional activity of CBP via histone H3 deacetylation, but that it also interacts with HDAC1 <italic>in vitro</italic>. We therefore tested the ability of HDAC1 to cooperate with T antigen in repressing transcription and decreasing histone H3 and H4 acetylation levels. To this end, transient transfections into HeLa cells were performed using Gal-CBP, T antigen and the TK promoter fused to the luciferase reporter gene (as described above) overexpressing (or not) HDAC1. T antigen repression and histone acetylation levels were subsequently analyzed by luciferase and ChIPs assays, respectively. Our results show that overexpression of HDAC1 results in increased T antigen-induced transcriptional repression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A), as well as in decreased histone H3 and H4 acetylation levels, even under basal acetylation conditions (lane 4) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). This process is concomitant with HDAC1 recruitment to the promoter (lanes 3 and 4) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). Only a partial transcriptional repression (24%) by HDAC1 alone was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A, lane 5), consistently with the ability of HDAC1 to interact weakly with CBP (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C).
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>HDAC1 acts in tandem with T antigen to antagonize the transcriptional activity of CBP. <bold>(A)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of the Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter, 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of Gal-CBP (FL), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pSG5-T antigen, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pcDNA3-HDAC1 and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of renilla reporter vector. Whole cell extracts were used in the luciferase-renilla assay. The activity derived from the Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter was normalized to 1.0 and the other activities are expressed relative to this. The data represent an average of at least five independent transfections. A schematic representation of the constructs used is shown at the bottom of the figure. <bold>(B)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter (lane 1), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of Gal-CBP (FL) (lane 2), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pSG5-T antigen (lane 3) and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pcDNA3-HDAC1 (lane 4) and comparative ChIP analysis were performed in parallel with the same number of cells using antibodies that specifically recognize acetylated histone H3 (K 9 and 14), poly-acetylated histone H4 and HDAC1. The immunoprecipitates were analyzed by quantitative PCR as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A. Quantification of the acetyl-H3 and acetyl-H4 ChIPs bands (as described in Materials and Methods) is shown at the bottom part of the figure. <bold>(C)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of the Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of renilla reporter, 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of Gal-CBP (FL), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pSG5-T antigen and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pcDNA3-HDAC1 together with 8&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of HDAC1(1, 2 and 3) or control siRNA vectors. Total cell extracts were prepared 48&#x02009;h after transfection and used in the luciferase-renilla assay. The activity derived from the Gal4-TK-luciferase reporter in the presence of the control siRNA vectors was normalized to 1.0 and the other activities are expressed relative to this. The diagrams show the relative protein levels obtained from three independent experiments. <bold>(D)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with 8&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of control siRNA or different HDAC1 siRNA (1, 2 or 3) alone or in combination. Total cells extracts were prepared 80&#x02009;h after transfection and the levels of endogenous HDAC1 protein were detected by western blot analysis. The decrease of HDAC1 levels reached 90%; however, when the HDAC1 levels were analyzed 48&#x02009;h after transfection the observed decrease was modest (20&#x02013;30%) (data not shown). The experiment in (C) was performed 48&#x02009;h after transfection due to the low activation of TK promoter by Gal-CBP after that time. <bold>(E)</bold> HeLa cells were transfected as in (A) and the levels of T antigen protein in the presence of control siRNA or HDAC1 siRNA were analyzed by Western blot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1113f5"/></fig></p><p>To further analyze the necessity of HDAC1 for mediating T antigen repression <italic>in vivo</italic>, we performed transcriptional assays (as indicated above) in the presence of small interfering RNAs (siRNAs), which partially block the expression of HDAC1 (HDAC1-siRNA) following an extended expression period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>D) and control siRNA (c-siRNA). The results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C show that in the presence of HDAC1 siRNA, T antigen-mediated repression is partially reduced (from 60 to 30%). siRNA control did not affect T antigen-induced repression. The T antigen expression levels were not affected by the presence of the siRNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>E). Based on these results, we would suggest that HDAC1 contributes to T antigen-mediated repression <italic>in vivo</italic>, although we cannot discard the participation of other deacetylases or co-repressors in this process.</p><p>Following CV1 SV40 infection, T antigen induces the stimulation of cell growth for which it requires CBP interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). As our results suggest that CBP-mediated transcriptional activity may be repressed by T antigen, we decided to analyze whether HDAC1 levels could affect T antigen-stimulated cell growth. To this end, CV1 and CV1COS cells were transfected with Flag-HDAC1, or with the vector alone. We then analyzed the doubling time of the cells as well as Flag-HDAC1 levels over four days after transfection. The results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>) show a clear decrease in cell growth in CV1COS cells, suggesting that HDAC1 levels affect T antigen-induced cell growth stimulation.
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>HDAC1 levels affect cell growth. Doubling times of CV1 and CV1COS cells transfected with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of pcDNA3-Flag-HDAC1, or the vector alone, were measured as described in the Material and Methods section. Doubling time and the Flag-HDAC1 levels were determined by counting cells every day and by western blot analysis, respectively. Results shown represent the mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments, in which each sample was analyzed in triplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1113f6"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this report, we have shown that T antigen represses CBP-mediated transcriptional activity. This repression is concomitant with histone H3 deacetylation and is TSA sensitive. On the other hand, our results indicate that T antigen interacts with HDAC1 <italic>in vitro</italic> and overexpression of HDAC1 not only acts in tandem with T antigen to antagonize CBP transactivation function, but also that it correlates with chromatin deacetylation on the TK and PDGF &#x003b2;-receptor promoters. Finally, decreasing the HDAC1 levels by use of siRNAs partially abolishes the repression induced by T antigen. The results from these experiments are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Summary of T Antigen repression</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity To TSA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3 Deacetylation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">H4 Deacetylation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDAC1 Overexpression</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDAC1 SiRNA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T Ag&#x02013; HDAC1 interaction</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (<italic>in vitro</italic>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>Our data suggest that acetylase and deacetylase activities play key roles in the viral growth promoted by T antigen, revealing that the latter interacts with both HAT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) and HDAC activities. Given that they have opposite roles in transcriptional regulation, the interaction of these two activities through T antigen might appear paradoxical. However, we believe that T antigen stimulates growth by altering gene expression patterns; thus, the activation of one gene set might be as necessary as the repression of another.</p><p>The possible presence of both activities in one complex might facilitate more efficient and rapid changes in promoter acetylation. In fact, recent studies have shown that HAT and HDAC may be found in the same complexes. For example, HDAC1 may interact with the HAT enzymes p300 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>) or P/CAF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), leading to greater control of global histone acetylation inside the cell. Another possibility is that HAT and HDAC reciprocally modulate their enzymatic activity or T antigen function by cross-acetylation/deacetylation. In this context, we must mention that T antigen exists as an acetylated protein <italic>in vivo</italic>. p53 targets T antigen for acetylation by CBP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). HDAC-T antigen interaction could favor T antigen deacetylation, thereby changing its regulatory capabilities.</p><p>Other viral proteins have also been found to associate with HDAC activities [E7 interacts with the Mi2-NRD complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>)], and in particular with the HDAC1 enzyme, such as the adenovirus-2 E1B-55K protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>) and the Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 3C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). As well as the retroviral Tax (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) and Tat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39 B40 B41">39&#x02013;&#x02009;41</xref>) proteins, the T antigen viral oncoprotein can associate with both HDAC and HAT enzymes. This suggests that the control of acetylation/deacetylation equilibrium is a critical step in viral-induced cell transformation.</p><p>Our results suggest that acetylase and deacetylase activities play key roles in the viral growth promoted by T antigen. Indeed, our findings show that a viral oncoprotein may manipulate gene expression by interacting with both acetyltransferase and deacetylase activities. These observations underscore the relevance of both the acetylation/deacetylation pathways as well as chromatin status, in cell proliferation and viral infection.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We would like to thank Dr B. Pi&#x000f1;a for suggestions and technical help. We also thank Dr J. DeCaprio for providing the pSG5-T antigen and pSG5-T K1 and PVU-1 mutants, Dr T. Kouzarides for pCDNA3CBP-HAT-CBP2, pCDNA3CBP-HAT, pGEX-HDAC1(1-382) and pGEX-HDAC1(51&#x02013;482), Dr J. Bernues for Gal4-hsp70-&#x003b2;gal and Gal4-TK-luc. This study was supported by grants SAF2002-00741, SAF2005-01285, Gen2003-20642, BIO2003-09327, BFU2006-01493 and CSD2006-00049 from the Ministerio de Ciencia y Tecnolog&#x000ed;a. N.B.G., N.A. and D.P. are the recipients of a PCB, I3P (CSIC) and FI (from the Catalonia government) studentships, respectively.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA tumour virus transforming proteins and the cell cycle</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev</source><year>1993</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8453277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>DeCaprio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p53 targets Simian Virus 40 large T antigen for acetylation by CBP</article-title><source>J. of Virology</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>8245</fpage><lpage>8253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15254196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>DeCaprio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular transformation by SV40 large T antigen: interaction with host proteins</article-title><source>Seminars in Cancer Biology</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11243895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The p53 protein and its interactions with the oncogene products of the small DNA tumor viruses</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>1990</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2142553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Corneillie</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Espiritu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into the mechanism of inhibition of p53 by simian virus 40 large T antigen</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2746</fpage><lpage>2753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10082540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeCaprio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludlow</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Figge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shew</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsilio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Paucha</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SV40 large tumor antigen forms a specific complex with the product of the retinoblastoma susceptibility gene</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1988</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2839300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludlow</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeCaprio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The retinoblastoma susceptibility gene product undergoes cell cycle-dependent dephosphorylation and binding to and release from SV40 large T</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2154332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cobrinik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowdy</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittnacht</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The retinoblastoma protein and the regulation of cell cycling</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci</source><year>1992</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1412705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harlow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adenovirus E1A targets key regulators of cell proliferation</article-title><source>Cancer Surv</source><year>1992</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1353412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaciuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simian virus 40 large-T antigen expresses a biological activity complementary to the p300-associated transforming function of the adenovirus E1A gene products</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2116</fpage><lpage>2124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1848672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludlow</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lill</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldread</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Arany</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Modjtahedi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>DeCaprio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of p300 and CBP with simian virus 40 large T antigen</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3454</fpage><lpage>3464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8668161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avantaggiati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Graessmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SV40 large T antigen and adenovirus E1a oncoproteins interact with distinct isoforms of the transcriptional co-activator, p300</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2236</fpage><lpage>2248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8641289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lill</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tevethia</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Modjtahedi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p300 family members associate with the carboxyl terminus of simian virus 40 large tumor antigen</article-title><source>J. Virol</source><year>1997</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8985331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hebbes</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Crane-Robinson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A direct link between core histone acetylation and transcriptionally active chromatin</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1988</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1395</fpage><lpage>1402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3409869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone acetylation in chromatin and chromosomes</article-title><source>Semin. Cell. Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8562915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Newsome</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>DeCaprio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of the adenovirus E1A-associated 300-kD protein (p300) reveals a protein with properties of a transcriptional adapter</article-title><source>Genes &#x00026; Dev</source><year>1994</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7523245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CBP co-activator is a histone acetyltransferase</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>384</volume><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8967953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogryzko</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiltz</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Russanova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Howars</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The transcription coactivators p300 and CBP are histone acetyltransferase</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>953</fpage><lpage>959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8945521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamamori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogryzko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of histone acetyltransferases p300 and PCAF by the bHLH protein twist and adenoviral oncoprotein E1A</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10025406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ait-Si-Ali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barre</surname><given-names>F-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dkhissi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnaghi-Jaulin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Girault</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Knibiehler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ducommun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Trouche</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harel-Bellan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone acetyltransferase activity of CBP is controlled by cycle-dependent kinases and oncoprotein E1A</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>396</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9823900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakravarti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogryzko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A viral mechanism for the inhibition of p300 and P/CAF acetyltransferase activity</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10025405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valls</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Cruz</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Balb&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SV40&#x02009;T antigen modulates CBP histone acetyltransferase activity</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3114</fpage><lpage>3122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12799439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acetylation of adenovirus E1A regulates binding of the transcriptional corepressor CtBP</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>14323</fpage><lpage>14328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madison</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaciuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundblad</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acetylation of the adenovirus-transforming protein E1A determines nuclear localization by disrupting association with importing-alpha</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>38755</fpage><lpage>38763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12161448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Punga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Akusjarvi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The adenovirus-2 E1B-55K protein interacts with a mSin3A/histone deacetylase 1 complex</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><year>2000</year><volume>476</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10913622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Purbey</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Galande</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Displacement of SATB1-bound histone deacetylase 1 corepressor by the human immunodeficiency virus type 1 transactivator induces expression of interleukin-2 and its receptor in T cells</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1620</fpage><lpage>1633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15713622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radkov</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Touito</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Allday</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 3C interacts with histone deacetylase to repress transcription</article-title><source>J. of Virology</source><year>1999</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>5688</fpage><lpage>5697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10364319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miska</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCance</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The E7 oncoprotein associates with Mi2 and histone deacetylase activity to promote cell growth</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2449</fpage><lpage>2458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10228159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Balb&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Haus-Seuffert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisterernst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The acetyltransferase activity of CBP stimulates transcription</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2886</fpage><lpage>2893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9582282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breiling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>General transcription factors bind promoters repressed by Polycomb group proteins</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>412</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11493924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagerman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Balb&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>E1A directly binds and regulates the P/CAF acetyltransferase</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>4469</fpage><lpage>4477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9687513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>La Thangue</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p300/CBP proteins: HATs for transcriptional bridges and scaffolds</article-title><source>J. Cell. Sci</source><year>2001</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>2363</fpage><lpage>2373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11559745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uramoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackzell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetterskog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballagi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Funa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>pRb, Myc and p53 are critically involved in SV40 large T antigen repression of PDGF beta-receptor transcription</article-title><source>J. Cell. Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>3855</fpage><lpage>3865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15265983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miska</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCance</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinoblastoma protein recruits histone deacetylase to repress transcription</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9468139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiegler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Forcales</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De Luca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deacetylase recruitment by the C/H3 domain of the acetyltransferase p300</article-title><source>Oncogen</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2177</fpage><lpage>2187</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamagoe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenardo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of histone acetylases and deacetylases in vivo</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>1033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12529406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Camelo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanin</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangond</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone deacetylase 3 represses HTLV-1 tax transcription</article-title><source>Oncol. Rep</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16865259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Orden</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyborg</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insight into the tumor suppressor function of CBP through the viral oncoprotein tax</article-title><source>Gene Expr</source><year>2000</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11097423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Counterregulation of chromatin deacetylation and histone deacetylase occupancy at the integrated promoter of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) by the HIV-1 repressor YY1 and HIV-1 activator Tat</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2965</fpage><lpage>2973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11940654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel substrate specificity of the histone acetyltransferase activity of HIV-1-Tat interactive protein Tip60</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>30595</fpage><lpage>30598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9388189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benkirane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogryzko</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeang</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of integrated provirus requires histone acetyltransferase. p300 and P/CAF are coactivators for HIV-1 Tat</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>24898</fpage><lpage>24905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9733796</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
