<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142231</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1669737</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl922</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Phospho3D: a database of three-dimensional structures of protein phosphorylation sites</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zanzoni</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ausiello</surname><given-names>Gabriele</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Via</surname><given-names>Allegra</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gherardini</surname><given-names>Pier Federico</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Helmer-Citterich</surname><given-names>Manuela</given-names></name></contrib><aff><institution>Centre for Molecular Bioinformatics, Department of Biology</institution><addr-line>University of Rome &#x02018;Tor Vergata&#x02019;, Rome 00133, Italy</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +39 067 259 4314; Fax: +39 062 023 500; Email: <email>andreas@cbm.bio.uniroma2.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D229</fpage><lpage>D231</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2006 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Phosphorylation is the most common protein post-translational modification. Phosphorylated residues (serine, threonine and tyrosine) play critical roles in the regulation of many cellular processes. Since the amount of data produced by screening assays is growing continuously, the development of computational tools for collecting and analysing experimental data has become a pivotal task for unravelling the complex network of interactions regulating eukaryotic cell life. Here we present Phospho3D, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cbm.bio.uniroma2.it/phospho3d"/>, a database of 3D structures of phosphorylation sites, which stores information retrieved from the phospho.ELM database and is enriched with structural information and annotations at the residue level. The database also collects the results of a large-scale structural comparison procedure providing clues for the identification of new putative phosphorylation sites.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The phosphorylation of specific protein residues is a crucial event in the regulation of several cellular processes, operating on activation, deactivation or recognition of the target protein. A great deal of eukaryotic proteins (&#x0223c;30% in the human genome) undergo this reversible post-translational modification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>). Phosphorylation on serine/threonine or tyrosine residues is accomplished by protein kinases (PKs), one of the largest protein families, comprising 1.5&#x02013;2.5% of all eukaryotic genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>).</p><p>Although the amount of data produced in various screening assays is steadily growing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>), experimental identification of phosphoproteins and the determination of individual phosphorylation sites remains a difficult and time-consuming task. Hence, the implementation of computational tools proves to be very useful for collecting and analysing experimental data.</p><p>Several sequence-based methods to predict phosphorylation sites were developed using different computational approaches such as regular expressions with context-based rules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>), position-specific scoring matrices (PSSMs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>), artificial neural networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>), support vector machines (SVMs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>), hidden Markov models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>) and iterative statistical methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>). All these methods are based on the hypothesis that the sequence surrounding the phosphorylated residue represents the main determinant for kinase specificity. They are reasonably accurate and work well with a number of specific kinases. However, the specificity determinants and rules remain elusive for a large number of protein kinases that display a number of substrates sharing little or no sequence similarity in the known phosphopeptides. We propose that, at least in some cases, the rules of kinase specificity may reside in the presence of structural determinants which only occasionally overlap with sequence <italic>consensi</italic> and which might be independent of the residue order in protein sequences.</p><p>Here we describe Phospho3D, a database of 3D structure of phosphorylation sites. It collects information retrieved from the phospho.ELM database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>) and is enriched with structural information and diverse annotations at the residue level. In addition, the database stores the results of a large-scale local structural comparison which suggest functional annotation of phosphorylation sites by 3D similarity. Cases of significant structural similarity between phosphorylation sites may indicate that they are phosphorylated by the same kinase.</p></sec><sec><title>DATABASE CONSTRUCTION AND CONTENT</title><p>The Phospho3D database was constructed by collecting data from the phospho.ELM database which gathers experimentally verified phosphorylation sites manually extracted from the literature. The phospho.ELM dataset used in this work (version 4.0) contains 5314 phosphorylation sites, or instances, belonging to 1805 different sequences.</p><p>The correspondence between phospho.ELM sequences and the Protein Data Bank (PDB) chains was established via the Seq2Struct resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>), an exhaustive collection of annotated links between SwissProt-TrEMBL and PDB sequences. Links are based on sequence alignment using pre-established highly reliable thresholds. From a list of 4530 sequence&#x02013;structure links (for further details see website documentation), only the ones having the phosphorylable residue in the alignment region were retained, this resulting in 2726 instances (166 unique phospho.ELM instances on 1219 protein chains).</p><p>The basic information stored in Phospho3D consists of the instance, its flanking sequence (10 residues) and any residue whose distance from the instance does not exceed 12 &#x0212b; thus defining a 3D neighbourhood which we define as <italic>zone</italic>.</p><p>For each <italic>zone</italic>, annotation at the residue level is provided, namely solvent accessibility supplied by the NACCESS program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>), secondary structure assignment given by the DSSP program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>) and residue conservation as from the Consurf-HSSP database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>).</p><p>Users can also retrieve information extracted from the phospho.ELM dataset; for instance, the Medline reference PMID and, when available, the kinase(s) that phosphorylate(s) the given site.</p><p>In addition, for each <italic>zone</italic> the results of a large-scale local structural comparison versus a representative dataset of PDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>) protein chains from eukaryotic organisms are also given. The comparison was carried out using the Query3D sequence/fold independent algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>). Structural matches are assessed by two criteria: structural similarity and biochemical similarity. The structural similarity demands that matching residues have a root mean square deviation (r.m.s.d.) lower than a given threshold, whereas the biochemical similarity is evaluated using a Dayhoff substitution matrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>). The score of the match is the number of matching residues which fulfil the similarity criteria. The significance of the score is evaluated by calculating the <italic>Z</italic>-score over the score distribution of the query <italic>zone</italic> comparison to the whole dataset.</p></sec><sec><title>THE WEB INTERFACE</title><p>The Phospho3D database can be searched by kinase name, by PDB identification code or keyword. A browsing function has been also implemented.</p><p>The information returned to the user consists of a brief description of the PDB structure(s) which fulfil the search criterion and of a list of instances presented along with associated information (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). For each instance, the user can select three options related to the surrounding structural zone: a graphical view using the Jmol Java Applet (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmol.org"/>); a tabular view reporting the <italic>zone</italic> annotation at the residue level; a list of 3D matches identified by local structural comparison. Each match can be visualized using Jmol. A tabular view of the matching residues is also presented (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>In the central panel a list of instances for the PDB file 1A52 is shown. For each of them, users can visualize the corresponding <italic>zone</italic> via the Jmol viewer, the annotation at the residue level and the results of the large-scale local structural comparison. For each structural match the score, the <italic>Z</italic>-score, and the rmsd are reported along with the SCOP fold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>) of the matching PDB files.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl922f1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSION AND FUTURE PERSPECTIVES</title><p>The Phospho3D database is a useful tool for the analysis of the structural features of experimentally verified phosphorylation sites. Moreover, it provides the results of a large-scale local structural comparison between the <italic>zones</italic> and a representative set of eukaryotic protein chains. The results of such a comparison identify new putative phosphorylation sites and suggest the kinase(s) responsible for phosphorylation.</p><p>Phospho3D will be regularly updated as soon as the new Phospho.ELM datasets are released. The annotations will be integrated as a feature in the pdbFun server (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>). We are also planning to identify and annotate those sites which are recognized by protein phosphatases and phosphoresidues-binding modules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>).</p><p>The Phospho3D dataset (annotations at the residue level and structural comparison results) is available upon request.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Francesca Diella for support and suggestions and for providing the Phospho.ELM dataset. We acknowledge the support of AIRC, Telethon (GGP04273), a PNR 2001&#x02013;2003 (FIRB art.8) and a PNR 2003&#x02013;2007 (FIRB art.8). Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by AIRC.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement.</italic> None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origins of protein phosphorylation</article-title><source>Nature Cell. Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>E127</fpage><lpage>E130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plowman</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudarsanam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of protein kinase signaling from yeast to man</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ficarro</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brill</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phung</surname><given-names>Q.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ericson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Profiling of tyrosine phosphorylation pathways in human cells using mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12522270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumby</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brekken</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of phosphoproteins and their phosphorylation sites in the WEHI-231 B lymphoma cell line</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Proteomics</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14729942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brill</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ficarro</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherji</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stettler-Gill</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust phosphoproteomic profiling of tyrosine phosphorylation sites from human T cells using immobilized metal affinity chromatography and tandem mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Anal. Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>2763</fpage><lpage>2772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15144186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beausoleil</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jedrychowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-scale characterization of HeLa cell nuclear phosphoproteins</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>12130</fpage><lpage>12135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15302935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puntervoll</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linding</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gemund</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabanis-Davidson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattingsdal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausiello</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brannetti</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ELM server: a new resource for investigating short functional sites in modular eukaryotic proteins</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3625</fpage><lpage>3630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obenauer</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scansite 2.0: proteome-wide prediction of cell signaling interactions using short sequence motifs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3635</fpage><lpage>3641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gammeltoft</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence and structure-based prediction of eukaryotic protein phosphorylation sites</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10600390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iakoucheva</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Radivojac</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikes</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Obradovic</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunker</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The importance of intrinsic disorder for protein phosphorylation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1037</fpage><lpage>1049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plewczynski</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tkacz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Godzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rychlewski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A support vector machine approach to the identification of phosphorylation sites</article-title><source>Cell. Mol. Biol. Lett.</source><year>2005</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimm</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of phosphorylation sites using SVMs</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>3179</fpage><lpage>3184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horng</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsou</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incorporating hidden Markov models for identifying protein kinase-specific phosphorylation sites</article-title><source>J. Comput. Chem.</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1032</fpage><lpage>1041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15889432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An iterative statistical approach to the identification of protein phosphorylation motifs from large-scale data sets</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1391</fpage><lpage>12398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16273072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diella</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gemund</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linding</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Via</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuster</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sicheritz-Ponten</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phospho.ELM: a database of experimentally verified phosphorylation sites in eukaryotic proteins</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>79</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15212693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Via</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanzoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmer-Citterich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seq2Struct: a resource for establishing sequence-structure links</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15454411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><collab>NACCESS Computer Program.</collab><year>1993</year><comment>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University College, London</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dictionary of protein secondary structure: pattern recognition of hydrogen-bonded and geometrical features</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>1983</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2577</fpage><lpage>2637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6667333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pupko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Tal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ConSurf-HSSP database: the mapping of evolutionary conservation among homologs onto PDB structures</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2005</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15614759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>T.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissig</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shindyalov</surname><given-names>I.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Protein Data Bank</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ausiello</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Via</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmer-Citterich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Query3d: a new method for high-throughput analysis of functional residues in protein structures</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>S5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16351754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dayhoff</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orcutt</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model of evolutionary change in proteins</article-title><source>Atlas Prot. Seq. Struct.</source><year>1978</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>352</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ausiello</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanzoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Via</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmer-Citterich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>pdbFun: mass selection and fast comparison of annotated PDB residues</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W133</fpage><lpage>W137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Espanel</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huguenin-Reggiani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Huijsduijnen</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SPOT technique as a tool for studying protein tyrosine phosphatase substrate specificities</article-title><source>Protein Sci.</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2326</fpage><lpage>2334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12237455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walchli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Espanel</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrenga</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cesareni</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Huijsduijnen</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probing protein-tyrosine phosphatase substrate specificity using a phosphotyrosine-containing phage library</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14578355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smerdon</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of <italic>in vitro</italic> peptide-library screens in the analysis of phosphoserine/threonine-binding domain structure and function</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struct.</source><year>2004</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15139812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murzin</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chothia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SCOP: a Structural Classification Of Proteins database for the investigation of sequences and structures</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7723011</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
