<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576670</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1935007</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm453</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fine-tuning of intrinsic N-Oct-3 POU domain allostery by regulatory DNA targets</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alazard</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mourey</surname><given-names>Lionel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ebel</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Konarev</surname><given-names>Peter V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petoukhov</surname><given-names>Maxim V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>Dmitri I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Erard</surname><given-names>Monique</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Institut de Pharmacologie et de Biologie Structurale, 205 Route de Narbonne, 31077 Toulouse, <sup>2</sup>Institut de Biologie Structurale, UMR 5075 CEA-CNRS-UJF, 41 rue Jules Horowitz, 38027 Grenoble, France and <sup>3</sup>European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Hamburg Outstation, EMBL c/o DESY, D-22603 Hamburg, Germany and Institute of Crystallography, Russian Academy of Sciences, Leninsky pr. 59, 117333 Moscow, Russia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+33 (0) 562175496</phone><fax>+33 (0) 562175994</fax><email>Monique.Erard@ipbs.fr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>4420</fpage><lpage>4432</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The &#x02018;POU&#x02019; (acronym of Pit-1, Oct-1, Unc-86) family of transcription factors share a common DNA-binding domain of approximately 160 residues, comprising so-called &#x02018;POUs&#x02019; and &#x02018;POUh&#x02019; sub-domains connected by a flexible linker. The importance of POU proteins as developmental regulators and tumor-promoting agents is due to linker flexibility, which allows them to adapt to a considerable variety of DNA targets. However, because of this flexibility, it has not been possible to determine the Oct-1/Pit-1 linker structure in crystallographic POU/DNA complexes. We have previously shown that the neuronal POU protein N-Oct-3 linker contains a structured region. Here, we have used a combination of hydrodynamic methods, DNA footprinting experiments, molecular modeling and small angle X-ray scattering to (i) structurally interpret the N-Oct-3-binding site within the HLA DR&#x003b1;&#x02009;gene promoter and deduce from this a novel POU domain allosteric conformation and (ii) analyze the molecular mechanisms involved in conformational transitions. We conclude that there might exist a continuum running from free to &#x02018;pre-bound&#x02019; N-Oct-3 POU conformations and that regulatory DNA regions likely select pre-existing conformers, in addition to molding the appropriate DBD structure. Finally, we suggest that a specific pair of glycine residues in the linker might act as a major conformational switch.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The high-throughput functional identification and structural characterization of transcriptional networks are major objectives of post-genomic research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3 B4">1&#x02013;4</xref>). Predictive methods have an important role to play in this endeavor since the large number of protein/DNA and protein/protein interactions involved in transcriptional regulation precludes their systematic study by X-ray crystallography or NMR. Since transcription factor families are generally specified by highly conserved consensus DNA-binding domains (DBD) as well as common strategies of interaction with target DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) DBD homology modeling is a particularly relevant approach (see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) and references herein). Equally, the prepositioning of a DBD within its DNA-binding site can often be inferred by homology, a step that most docking programs cannot yet address <italic>ab initio</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). However, despite these advantages, the prediction of DBD/DNA complex 3D structures is by no means straightforward, as exemplified by complexes involving the POU DBD.</p><p>The &#x02018;POU&#x02019; (acronym of Pit, Oct, Unc) family of transcription factors is defined on the basis of a common DBD of approximately 160 residues, first identified in the mammalian proteins Pit-1 and Oct-1 and the nematode factor Unc-86 [for a review, see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>)]. The POU DBD comprises two distinct, highly conserved sub-domains, termed &#x02018;POUs&#x02019; and &#x02018;POUh&#x02019;, which contain respectively four and three &#x003b1;-helices and are connected by a flexible linker, variable in sequence and length. The crystallographic structure of the complex between the POU domain of the ubiquitous protein Oct-1 and the octamer ATGCAAAT has revealed that POUs interacts with the tetramer ATGC in a similar fashion to the phage repressors, whereas the POUh interaction with the tretramer AAAT resembles that of a homeodomain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>).</p><p>If all the POU domains can bind to the prototypic octamer ATGCAAAT, they also recognize numerous other AT-rich sequences due to the flexibility of the linker joining the two sub-domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Remarkably, crystallographic structures of various Pit-1 or Oct-1 POU/DNA complexes have shown that the <italic>cis</italic> elements of a DNA target recognized respectively by POUs and POUh neither have to be contiguous nor even to belong to the same DNA strand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11 B12 B13">11&#x02013;13</xref>). Taken together, these structures have revealed two distinct patterns of POU homodimerization, based on different relative positionings of POUs and POUh, and depending on the type of DNA target. The &#x02018;PORE&#x02019; (Palindromic Oct-1 Responsive Elements) DNA motifs induce a POU conformation similar to that found in the initial Oct-1 POU/octamer complex. By contrast, the &#x02018;MORE&#x02019; (More palindromic Oct-1 Responsive Element) DNA motifs elicit a POU conformation analogous to that first discovered in Pit-1 POU/DNA complexes.</p><p>N-Oct-3, the human equivalent of the mouse Brn-2 protein, is widely expressed in the developing central nervous system, and necessary to maintain neural cell differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). It is also implicated in the development of the neural-crest-derived melanocytic lineage and its over-expression in melanocytes leads to tumorigenesis <italic>via</italic> the dysregulation of a number of genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15 B16 B17 B18">15&#x02013;18</xref>). The fact that N-Oct-3 can interact with such a variety of targets is due to the structural plasticity of its POU domain. In a previous report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), we have shown that the N-Oct-3 DBD, in addition to forming the classical homodimers in association with PORE and MORE sequences, can also adopt a novel mode of homodimerization when bound to a set of neuronal promoters, including the CRH (corticotropin-releasing hormone) gene promoter. We have demonstrated that this pattern is induced by a structural motif that we have termed &#x02018;NORE&#x02019; (N-Oct-3 Responsive Element).</p><p>In the current study, we have used a combination of hydrodynamic methods, DNA footprinting experiments, molecular modeling and small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) to address the following questions: (i) How should the N-Oct-3-binding site within the HLA DR&#x003b1; promoter be read structurally and translated into a new POU domain allosteric conformation? (ii) How do transitions between free and bound conformations occur and what are the molecular mechanisms involved? Our results lead us to conclude that there might exist a continuous spectrum of free and &#x02018;pre-bound&#x02019; N-Oct-3 POU conformations. In addition, a specific pair of glycine residues in the linker likely acts as a major conformational switch.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>DNA targets and N-Oct-3 DBD preparation</title><p>Twenty-four base-pair oligonucleotides corresponding respectively to the (&#x02212;127/&#x02212;104) and (&#x02212;57/&#x02212;34) fragments of the rat CRH gene promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>) and the human HLA DR&#x003b1; gene promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), and encompassing the N-Oct-3 POU homodimer-binding sites, were prepared and purified as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). The two sequences are as follows:</p><p>(CRH) <sup>5&#x02032;</sup>GCTCCTGCATAAATAATAGGGCCC<sup>3&#x02032;</sup> - (DR&#x003b1;) <sup>5&#x02032;</sup>AATTGATTTGCATTTTAATGGTCA<sup>3&#x02032;</sup></p><p>A 100&#x02009;bp fragment encompassing the DR&#x003b1; promoter sequence was generated by PCR using the plasmid pSVODR&#x003b1;lacZ (kindly provided by Dr Goding) and two flanking primers. DNAse I footprinting assays were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).</p><p>The N-Oct-3 His-tag DBD was purified as before with the exception of the final gel filtration on a Superdex 75 HR 16/60 column instead of the heparin sepharose chromatography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). Protein samples were concentrated and buffer exchanged with 25&#x02009;mM Tris pH 7.5, 500&#x02009;mM&#x02009;NaCl, 1% glycerol, 2&#x02009;mM DTT, by ultrafiltration using Microcon centrifugal filter devices, then stored at &#x02013;70&#x000b0;C and thawed prior to the experiments. The concentration was calculated from absorption measurements at 280&#x02009;nm using an estimated molar extinction coefficient of 12&#x02009;900&#x02009;M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;.cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The dispersity of each protein preparation was assessed by dynamic light scattering (DLS) measurements using a DynaPro molecular sizing instrument. The N-Oct-3 DBD folding was checked by circular dichroism using a Jobin-Yvon Mark VI dichrograph.</p></sec><sec><title>FPLC size-exclusion chromatography</title><p>Analytical size-exclusion chromatography was performed at 5&#x000b0;C on a Superdex 75 16/60 column (Pharmacia) equilibrated with 50&#x02009;mM Tris pH 7.5, 0.1&#x02009;M NaCl, 2% glycerol, 2&#x02009;mM DTT. The column was calibrated using the Pharmacia low molecular weight calibrating kit containing bovine serum albumin (M = 67&#x02009;kDa, Rs = 35.5&#x02009;&#x000c5;), ovalbumin (M = 43&#x02009;kDa, Rs = 30.5&#x02009;&#x000c5;), chymotrypsinogen (M = 25&#x02009;kDa, Rs = 20.9&#x02009;&#x000c5;) and ribonuclease A (M = 13.7&#x02009;kDa, Rs = 16.4&#x02009;&#x000c5;). Hydrodynamic or Stokes radii (Rs) were calculated from the plot of (&#x02013;log Kav)<sup>1/2</sup> versus Rs.</p></sec><sec><title>Analytical ultracentrifugation</title><p>Sedimentation velocity analysis was performed using a Beckman XL-I analytical ultracentrifuge and an AN-60 TI rotor (Beckman Instruments). Experiments were carried out at 12&#x000b0;C in 50&#x02009;mM Tris pH 7.5, 0.5&#x02009;M NaCl, 2% glycerol, 0.3&#x02009;mM TCPH at protein concentrations of 1 and 2&#x02009;mg/ml. Samples of 400&#x02009;&#x000b5;l were loaded into 12-mm path-length double-sector cells and centrifuged at 42&#x02009;000&#x02009;r.p.m. Their absorbance was recorded at 280&#x02009;nm. The solvent density, &#x003c1;, and viscosity, &#x003b7;, were measured at 20&#x000b0;C as 1.027&#x02009;g/ml and &#x003b7;/&#x003b7;<sub>H20</sub> = 1.134 using a density-meter DMA 5000 and viscosity-meter AMVn (Anton PAAR). The values at 12&#x000b0;C were determined to be 1.028&#x02009;g/ml and &#x003b7; = 1.398 cp. The partial specific volume of the protein, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkm453i1.jpg"/></inline-formula>, was estimated from the amino acid composition at 0.731&#x02009;ml/g using the SEDNTERP program (V1.01; developed by Haynes, Laue, and Philo; available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bbri.org/RASMB/rasmb.html">http://www.bbri.org/RASMB/rasmb.html</ext-link>).</p><p>Data processing was carried out using the SEDFIT program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.analyticalultracentrifugation.com/">http://www.analyticalultracentrifugation.com/</ext-link>). Continuous distributions were obtained considering 200 particles of frictional ratio 1.5 with sedimentation coefficients between 0.1 and 5.0&#x02009;S, and using a regularization procedure (<italic>F</italic> ratio 0.7) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). The non-interacting single-component model analysis was used to determine independently the sedimentation coefficient (<italic>s</italic>) and molecular mass (<italic>M</italic>) from the sedimentation velocity profiles. The two analyses take advantage of a systematic noise evaluation procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). The corrected sedimentation coefficients, <italic>s</italic><sub>20,</sub><italic><sub>w</sub></italic>, were derived from the experimental ones (<italic>s</italic>) using the following equation:
<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="gkm453um1"/></disp-formula></p><p>The Svedberg equation was used to relate <italic>s, M</italic> and the hydrodynamic radius <italic>R</italic><sub>H</sub> as follows:
<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="gkm453um2"/></disp-formula></p></sec><sec><title>Molecular modeling</title><p>Models were generated using the <italic>Accelrys</italic> modules InsightII, Biopolymer, Discover, Docking, Homology and Decipher (version 2005), run on a Silicon Graphics Fuel workstation, following the main outlines as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Models of the 24&#x02009;bp DNA fragments from the CRH and DR&#x003b1; gene promoters were built based on respective local homology with the NORE motif (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) and the MORE motif [PDB accession number: 1E3O (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>)] after assignment of the POUs and POUh tetrameric binding sites. The four inter base-pair structural parameters (rise, twist, tilt and roll) were inferred from the homologous templates. The N- and C-terminal regions of the N-Oct-3 DBD were modeled in an extended conformation. The two-step docking was performed as before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).</p><p>An automated conformational search procedure based on torsion driving was applied to the CRH-induced form of the N-Oct-3 DBD. The Gly 98 &#x003a6; and Gly 110 &#x003c8; dihedral angles were selected as rotors, and systematically modified by 18&#x000b0; increments in the &#x02013;180&#x000b0; to 180&#x000b0; range. The 441 resulting conformers were first filtered out using an energy threshold (&#x0003c;2.10<sup>4</sup>&#x02009;kcal/mol), and then divided into structural families. Each cluster was defined by conformations with similar relative orientations of the POUs and POUh sub-domains and overall backbone configurations superimposable within 4&#x02013;5&#x02009;&#x000c5;.</p></sec><sec><title>Scattering experiments and data analysis</title><p>The synchrotron radiation X-ray scattering data were collected on the X33 camera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) of the European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL) at the storage ring DORIS III (Deutsches Elektronen Synchrotron) using a linear gas detector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). The scattering patterns from the free N-Oct-3 DBD and from the 24-bp CRH and DR&#x003b1; promoter fragments, either free or in complex with the DBD, were measured at several solute concentrations between 2.5 and 8&#x02009;mg/ml and in 50&#x02009;mM Tris pH 7.5, 0.4&#x02009;M NaCl, 2% glycerol, 2&#x02009;mM DTT. The data were collected at 12&#x000b0;C at a sample-detector distance of 2.3&#x02009;m covering the momentum transfer range 0.15 &#x0003c; <italic>s</italic> &#x0003c; 3.5&#x02009;nm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<italic>s</italic> = 4&#x003c0;sin<italic>&#x003b8;</italic>/<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>, where 2<italic>&#x003b8;</italic> is the scattering angle and <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0.15&#x02009;nm the X-ray wavelength). The data collected in 15 successive 1-minute frames to check the radiation damage were normalized and processed using the program PRIMUS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). The difference curves after buffer subtraction were extrapolated to infinite dilution following standard procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>).</p><p>The maximum particle dimensions <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> were estimated using the orthogonal expansion program ORTOGNOM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The forward scattering values <italic>I</italic>(0) and the radii of gyration <italic>R</italic><sub>g</sub> were evaluated using the Guinier approximation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>) and by using the indirect transform package GNOM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>), which also provides the distance distribution functions <italic>p</italic>(<italic>r</italic>) of the particles. The molecular masses (<italic>M</italic>) of the solutes were evaluated by comparison of the forward scattering with that from a reference solution of bovine serum albumin (<italic>M</italic> = 66&#x02009;kDa).</p><p>The scattering patterns from the predicted models of the free N-Oct-3 DBD, the CRH and DR&#x003b1; DNA fragments, and their respective complexes, were computed using the program CRYSOL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). Given the atomic coordinates, the program fits the experimental scattering curve by adjusting the excluded volume of the particle and the contrast of the hydration layer surrounding the particle in solution to minimize the discrepancy estimated as follows:
<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="gkm453um3"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>N</italic> is the number of experimental points, <italic>c</italic> is a scaling factor, <italic>I</italic><sub>exp</sub>(<italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic>), <italic>I</italic><sub>calc</sub>(<italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic>) and <italic>&#x003c3;</italic>(<italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic>) are the experimental and calculated intensity, and the experimental error at the momentum transfer <italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic>, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>Hydrodynamic properties show that free N-Oct-3 POU is monomeric</title><p>The N-Oct-3 DNA-binding domain (DBD) purifies as a single species of 20&#x02009;kDa molecular mass as judged by SDS-PAGE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). In order to investigate the oligomerization state and hydrodynamic radius of this POU domain, we first carried out dynamic light scattering (DLS) and analytical gel filtration experiments. DLS measurements recorded at 20&#x000b0;C and at a maximal concentration of 4&#x02009;mg/ml indicated a low polydispersity and a narrow particle size distribution diagram corresponding to a hydrodynamic radius of 29.3&#x02009;&#x000c5; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). The purified N-Oct-3 POU domain eluted from a FPLC-size exclusion chromatography column between the 43 and 25&#x02009;kDa calibration proteins and the elution volume served to calculate its Stokes radius (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C). The resulting Rs value of 27.6&#x02009;&#x000c5; was very similar to that calculated by DLS, but significantly higher than those of globular proteins of an equivalent molecular weight. This indicates the presence of either a dimer or an elongated monomer in solution.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Characterization of the N-Oct-3 POU domain. (<bold>A</bold>) Detection of a single band with the expected N-Oct-3 DBD molecular mass by Coomassie-blue staining in 13% SDS-PAGE (see the molecular mass markers on the right). (<bold>B</bold>) Dynamic light scattering of the N-Oct-3 DBD (see text). (<bold>C</bold>) Calibration curve obtained by FPLC size-exclusion chromatography of globular proteins of known Stokes radii &#x02018;Rs&#x02019; (see the Materials and Methods section). The arrow indicates the elution position of the N-Oct-3 POU domain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm453f1"/></fig></p><p>The N-Oct-3 DBD was then submitted to sedimentation velocity analysis, and the data were processed as described in the Materials and Methods section. A selection of sedimentation profiles performed in the same conditions, along with their best-fits using a single component, are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A, the corresponding residuals being displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B. Identical sedimentation coefficients were obtained (1.84&#x02009;S) at the two concentrations used (1 and 2&#x02009;mg/ml), and the deduced molecular mass (21&#x02009;kDa) indicates, when compared with the theoretical mass (19.9&#x02009;kDa), that the N-Oct3 DBD is a monomer. In addition, the analysis of the sedimentation profiles in terms of a continuous distribution of elongated particles showed narrow single peaks at both concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C). This clearly demonstrates the homogeneity of the solution and the lack of any association&#x02013;dissociation processes, thereby confirming the monomeric status of the free N-Oct-3 DBD. Thus we can conclude that the N-Oct-3 POU homodimers which bind to a variety of DNA targets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) do not exist prior to complex formation, but are a consequence of specific interactions with target DNAs.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Sedimentation velocity analysis of the N-Oct-3 DBD. (<bold>A</bold>) Sedimentation velocity absorbance profiles were obtained at 12&#x000b0;C at a rotor speed of 42&#x02009;000&#x02009;r.p.m. and scans were recorded at 280&#x02009;nm for 21&#x02009;h. The data analysis was performed using 22 regularly spaced profiles. The best-fit profiles corresponding to a single-component model are superimposed on the experimental data. For clarity, only one profile out of two is shown. (<bold>B</bold>) Corresponding residuals at a 2&#x02009;mg/ml DBD concentration. (<bold>C</bold>) Continuous distributions of sedimentation coefficients obtained by considering elongated proteins of frictional ratio 1.5; protein concentration 1&#x02009;mg/ml (dotted line) and 2&#x02009;mg/ml (continuous line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm453f2"/></fig></p><p>The question then arises as to whether the elongated shape of the free N-Oct-3 DBD indicated by the hydrodynamic data reflects a single conformation or represents the average of a collection of conformers. In addition, we would like to determine the molecular mechanisms responsible for the transitions between the free and DNA-bound conformations. To attempt to answer these questions, we have performed a comparative analysis of two regulatory conformations of N-Oct-3 POU, either induced by the NORE motif of the CRH gene promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) or by an element of the HLA DR&#x003b1; gene promoter. In the latter case, it was first necessary to characterize the interaction between the N-Oct-3 POU and its DNA target.</p></sec><sec><title>Structural reading of the N-Oct-3-binding site within the HLA DR&#x003b1; gene promoter and POU domain allostery: a combined footprinting and molecular modeling approach</title><p>We have previously shown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) that the N-Oct-3 POU domain can adopt three different conformations and corresponding homodimerization patterns in response to the particular distribution of potential POUs and POUh tetrameric binding sites which characterize the respective PORE, MORE and NORE motifs evoked earlier. In the same report, we defined a structural framework suitable for the analysis of any interaction between the N-Oct-3 POU domain and a DNA target. Most importantly, the POUs and POUh tetrameric binding sites for each monomer are non-contiguous and on opposite strands in the MORE mode, whereas they are contiguous and on the same strand in the PORE mode. This results in a different relative positioning of the POUs and POUh sub-domains within each monomer between the two modes. Finally, the NORE motif designates the 14-bp sequence element TNNRTAAATAATRN (N: any nucleotide; R: purine residues) which is common to a set of neuronal promoters, including the CRH gene promoter, and which is capable of eliciting a novel homodimerization mode exclusive to the N-Oct-3 DBD. Both the NORE and PORE motifs elicit a &#x02018;POUh-dominant&#x02019; mode of N-Oct-3 DBD homodimerization with a strong anchoring into the DNA minor groove. However, in the case of the NORE mode, the two POUh-binding sites are overlapping, which explains the non-cooperative character of the homodimerization.</p><p>DNAse I footprinting is a particularly valuable tool to determine which homodimerization mode is elicited by a given DNA regulatory element. Bearing in mind the strong correlation between N-Oct-3 over-expression in melanomas and the up-regulation of HLA-DR&#x003b1; gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>), we used this approach, coupled to molecular modeling, to analyze N-Oct-3 binding to the HLA-DR&#x003b1; gene promoter. Electrophoretic mobility shift assays (EMSA) showed that the N-Oct-3 POU domain binds as a non-cooperative homodimer to the DR&#x003b1; DNA, a 24-bp DNA fragment of the HLA-DR&#x003b1; gene promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>), with an effective dissociation constant <italic>K<sub>d</sub></italic><sub>1</sub> of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>&#x02009;M for the first monomer (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A legend) and an apparent dissociation constant <italic>K<sub>d</sub></italic><sub>2</sub> &#x02264; 2.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>&#x02009;M for the second monomer [see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B legend; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>)]. DNAse I footprinting of the first N-Oct-3 DBD binding to a promoter fragment encompassing this high-affinity binding site reveals a total protection of both DNA strands (lanes 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B). We therefore deduce that the relative positioning of the POUs and POUh sub-domains within this first bound monomer must be elicited by a MORE-type motif, the only one with POUs and POUh-binding sites on both strands of the DNA.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>EMSA analysis of the interaction between the N-Oct-3 DBD and the DR&#x003b1; DNA. (<bold>A</bold>) Experiments were performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>), except that the DNA concentration was set to 200&#x02009;pM. Lane 1 corresponds to free DNA (&#x02018;D&#x02019;). The protein concentration was increased by 2-fold step increments starting from 38&#x02009;pM (lanes 2&#x02013;15). The assay at 610&#x02009;pM DBD concentration (lane 6) resulted in 50% equimolecular C1 complex formation, indicating an apparent dissociation constant <italic>K<sub>d</sub></italic> of 0.61&#x02009;nM. Accurate calculation gave an effective <italic>K<sub>d</sub></italic> of 0.5&#x02009;nM. (<bold>B</bold>) In these assays, radiolabeled DR&#x003b1; DNA was mixed with an excess of cold probe, to a final 400&#x02009;nM concentration. Lane 1 corresponds to free DNA (&#x02018;D&#x02019;). The protein concentration was increased by 2-fold step increments starting from 2.44&#x02009;nM (lanes 2&#x02013;9 and 11&#x02013;15). An additional assay using the 437&#x02009;nM intermediate protein concentration (lane 10) resulted in 100% equimolecular N-Oct-3 DBD/DR&#x003b1; DNA complex (&#x02018;C1&#x02019;) formation, indicating an interaction stoichiometry of 400&#x02009;nM. Note the non-cooperative mode of the N-Oct-3DBD homodimerization on the DR&#x003b1; DNA, as revealed by sequential 1:1 (&#x02018;C1&#x02019;) and 2:1 (&#x02018;C2&#x02019;) complex assembly. As the 2.560&#x02009;&#x000b5;M protein concentration induces 100% C2 complex formation (lane 13), it must be &#x02265;100-fold the apparent dissociation constant <italic>K<sub>d</sub></italic><sub>2</sub> for the second site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm453f3"/></fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Footprinting analysis of N-Oct-3 POU bound to the HLA DR&#x003b1; gene promoter. (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Autoradiograms of 12% polyacrylamide denaturing gels showing the DNAse I footprints on the upper (&#x02018;US&#x02019;) and lower (&#x02018;LS&#x02019;) strands of the DR&#x003b1; promoter fragment. Lanes 1: total footprint generated by the first POU binding (red color-coding). Lanes 2: cleavage products of a mixture comprising 75% complex and 25% free DNA. Lanes 3: cleavage products of a mixture comprising 25% complex and 75% free DNA. Lanes 4: free DNA cleavage products (in the absence of protein). Lanes 5&#x02013;6: Maxam-Gilbert chemical sequencing references (cleavage after purine and pyrimidine residues, respectively). (<bold>C</bold>) Assignment of the POUs and POUh tetrameric binding sites deduced from the footprints (see text). The respective display codes for the first and the second N-Oct-3 POU domains binding sites are brown and blue. The first and second POUh tetrameric sub-sites are underlined in brown and blue, respectively, to compensate for the overlap with the POUs-binding sub-sites. The green marking in (A) and (B) points to an AT motif which does not interact with the DBD. The nucleotide numbering of the upper and lower strands in the 5&#x02032;-3&#x02032; direction is respectively 1&#x02013;24 and 1B-24B.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm453f4"/></fig></p><p>A MORE motif is characterized by two strong POUs anchoring sites on opposite DNA strands and on either side of the pseudo-dyad axis. The sequence of these binding sites is most often ATG(/A)C, but an ATNN motif is sufficient to establish the highly specific set of interactions with the conserved Gln and Thr residues of the POUs recognition helix. Based on the DNAse I footprint, the A12T13T14T15 tetramer on the upper strand and the overlapping A12BT13BG14BC15B tetramer on the lower strand of the HLA-DR&#x003b1; gene promoter possess the appropriate structural requirements for the two POUs-binding sites in the MORE configuration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). In line with this, the non-cooperativity of the homodimerization observed by EMSA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B) is consistent with the overlap of the two POUs-binding sites. Furthermore, the mutagenesis of the A12T13T14 triplet is sufficient to abolish the binding of both monomers (data not shown).</p><p>Following the assignment of the two POUs-binding sites as A12T13T14T15 on the upper strand and A12BT13BG14BC15B on the lower strand, the two corresponding POUh-binding sites can now be predicted as G14BC15BA16BA17B and T14T15T16A17 respectively, based on the known MORE motif organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). In this mode, each POUh-binding site overlaps the POUs-binding site of the other monomer on the same strand (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C and its legend). The extent of the DNAse I footprint on the lower strand as a consequence of the first monomer binding designates G14BC15BA16BA17B as the first POUh-binding site (lane 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B), and hence the A12T13T14T15 as the first POUs-binding site. This implies that the A12BT13BG14BC15B tetramer on the lower strand is the second POUs-binding site and the T14T15T16A17 tetramer on the upper strand is the second POUh-binding site.</p><p>It is important to underline that, as for the so-called canonical sequence of the human immunoglobulin heavy chain gene promoters IgG V<sub>H</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), the prototypic octamer sequence ATGCAAAT on the lower strand is not &#x02018;read&#x02019; as a single continuous POU-binding site but, instead, as the second POUs-binding site (ATGC) overlapping the first POUh-binding site (GCAA). As a consequence, the terminal AT is still cleaved by DNAse I since it does not take an active part in the interaction (see green-colored marking in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B and C).</p><p>Now that the POUs and POUh-binding sites have been assigned, the bound structure of the HLA DR&#x003b1; promoter DNA fragment can be built and docked with the corresponding sub-domains. The resulting model is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A and B. It is known that the generic MORE mode can accommodate variable spacings between the two POUs insertion sites. For example the &#x02018;MORE+2&#x02019; mode, corresponds to a 2&#x02009;bp spacing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). Following this nomenclature, the DR&#x003b1;/DBD complex represents a new MORE subtype, which can be designated by &#x02018;MORE-2&#x02019;. In this mode, the two POUs DNA recognition helices are inserted into overlapping sites in the major groove (see the red-colored star in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B).
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Modeling of the N-Oct-3 POU binding to the HLA DR&#x003b1; gene promoter. (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Predicted structures of the 1:1 (A) and 2:1 (B) complexes between the N-Oct-3 DBD and the 24&#x02009;bp DR&#x003b1; DNA, based on the footprinting analysis. The nucleotides in contact with the first and second POU monomers are displayed in Van der Waals surface mode, using the same color-coding as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C. The N-Oct-3 display code is: brown- or turquoise-colored cylinders for the &#x003b1;-helices of the first or second POU respectively, a dark-brown or dark-blue colored coil for the linker of the first or second POU, and a gray-colored ribbon for the POUh N-terminal extension. (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) Comparative analysis of the DR&#x003b1;-induced N-Oct-3 POU conformation (C) with the previously identified CRH-induced conformation (D). The two bound conformations can be interconverted by rotation around a virtual hinge Gly 98 &#x02013; Gly 110 axis, taking the POUs orientation as a fixed reference. In (C) and (D), the two brown-colored arrows mark the direction of the first and third helices of POUh. The distance between the amide groups of two critical residues, Gln 63 and Asn 162, in the respective POUs and POUh DNA recognition helices (&#x02032;RH<sub>dist</sub>&#x02032;) is monitored in &#x000c5;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm453f5"/></fig></p><p>If regulatory conformations of the N-Oct-3 POU domain require molding by the respective DNA structure, we need to ask what is the molecular mechanism responsible for this remarkable adaptation to the promoter structure.</p></sec><sec><title>A pair of Gly residues in the N-Oct-3 POU linker as potential actors in the conformational switch: a combined molecular mechanics and SAXS approach</title><p>A comparative analysis of the N-Oct-3 POU conformation induced by the DR&#x003b1; DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C) with that induced by the CRH DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>D) taking the position of the POUs as a fixed reference, reveals that the two POUh sub-domain orientations can be superimposed by an &#x0223c;180&#x000b0; rotation around the linker taken as a virtual axis.</p><p>Before dealing with the structural determinants of N-Oct-3 linker flexibility, we first need to recall its distinctive features. Using circular dichroism, we previously observed an increase in the &#x003b1;-helical content of the N-Oct-3 DBD when binding to its DNA targets, in contrast to the Oct-1 DBD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Since the only significant difference between these two highly conserved DBDs is their respective linker sequences, we engineered chimeric proteins where the N-Oct-3 and the Oct-1 linkers were interchanged. This showed that the replacement of the N-Oct-3 DBD linker by that of Oct-1 abolished the increase in &#x003b1;-helical structure, whereas the replacement of the Oct-1 linker by that of N-Oct-3 resulted in the typical increase in the &#x003b1;-helical content following protein/DNA complex formation. Since a number of reliable secondary structure prediction methods indicated that the heptapeptide motif IDKIAAQ specific to the N-Oct-3 linker could adopt an &#x003b1;-helical structure, we built another set of chimeric proteins where this heptapeptide was removed from the N-Oct-3 linker and embedded within the Oct-1 linker. As the results were similar to those for the entire linker interchange experiments, we concluded that the ability of the N-Oct-3 linker to adopt an &#x003b1;-helical structure when binding to a DNA target could be ascribed to the IDKIAAQ motif (see its location in the DBD sequence in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). We now show that the potential secondary structure of this heptapeptide motif can also be stabilized independently of DNA binding, when free DBD concentrations are greater than 0.7&#x02009;mg/ml (see Figure S1 and its legend), which are the conditions of the hydrodynamic and SAXS experiments reported here. Note that the link between protein folding and molecular concentration has been revealed in a number of recent works [see for example (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>)]. Thus the N-Oct-3 linker has the characteristics of a &#x02018;helical linker&#x02019; as defined by George and Heringa based on an extensive compilation of inter-domain linkers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Interestingly, the helical heptapeptide IDKIAAQ is preceded by the 4-residue motif SPTS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A), shown to form a &#x003b2;-turn in a number of proteins and polypeptides, the structures of which were solved by crystallography or NMR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42 B43 B44">42&#x02013;44</xref>).
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Conformational search by torsion driving. (<bold>A</bold>) Location of the linker (brown-coded) within the sequence of the N-Oct-3 DBD: the Gly 98 and Gly 110 residues (highlighted) flank the SPTSIDKIAAQ undecapeptide (underlined). Other critical features are the Gln 63 and Asn 162 residues (red-coded) in the respective POUs and POUh DNA recognition helices (purple-coded). Display code for the remaining elements as follows: gray for the POUh N-terminal arm, blue for helices 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, green for the regions between secondary structure elements, black for exogenous regions resulting from the DBD cloning. (<bold>B&#x02013;D</bold>) Clustering of molecular mechanics-derived structures in families of potential free forms (B, C) and extended conformers (D). The conformers C&#x003b1; traces are structurally aligned within a 4&#x02013;5&#x02009;&#x000c5; R.M.S. range in each cluster. (<bold>E&#x02013;G</bold>) The conformers Cf 183 (E), Cf 194 (F) and Cf 221 (G) are the best representatives of each family, respectively FI (B), FII (C) and NF (D). In all cases, Gly 98 and Gly 110 are coded in brown, Gln 63 and Asn 162 in red, the POUs and POUh recognition helices in purple. RH<sub>dist</sub> is monitored in &#x000c5;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm453f6"/></fig></p><p>A crucial feature of hinge residues is that they have very few packing constraints in their main chain atoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>). As such, the Gly residues are well suited to promote hinge motion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). The two Gly residues present in the N-Oct-3 DBD linker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A) could therefore act as major molecular pivots in the conformational transitions. To examine this further, we performed automated conformational searches by systematically sampling the &#x003d5; and &#x003c8; dihedral angles of Gly 98 and Gly 110, using the CRH-bound conformation as a starting structure. We found the combination of Gly 98&#x003d5; and Gly 110 &#x003c8; dihedral angles to be the most efficient to explore the N-Oct-3 DBD conformational space (see the Materials and Methods section and Figure S3A and B). After filtering using an energy threshold, the resulting conformers could be clustered within a discrete number of conformational families, based on overall R.M.S. values of 4&#x02013;5&#x02009;&#x000c5; and corresponding to different relative orientations of the POUs and POUh sub-domains such as those displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B&#x02013;D. In order to identify potential free forms amongst these structures, we first compared their calculated radius of gyration (<italic>R</italic><sub>g</sub>) to the free N-Oct-3 DBD hydrodynamic radius. To select the most likely candidates, we then combined molecular mechanics with SAXS methodology following the main outlines of a recent study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>).</p><p>Processed X-ray scattering patterns corresponding to the free N-Oct-3 DBD are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A and B (data groups 1), alongside those from the free DNA fragments (data groups 2) and from the equimolecular N-Oct-3 DBD/DNA complexes (data groups 3). The structural parameters computed from the experimental data, including the radius of gyration (<italic>R</italic><sub>g</sub>) and maximum particle dimension (<italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub>), are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. The estimated effective mass (<italic>M</italic><sub>eff</sub>) of the free N-Oct-3 DBD agrees within experimental error with the value expected from the sequence (<italic>M</italic><sub>seq</sub>), confirming that the protein is monomeric in solution. The distance distribution functions computed from the experimental data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>) emphasize the elongated shape of the free form(s), and the similarities between the gyration radii of the free N-Oct-3 DBD and of its complexes with each promoter DNA fragment. Note the good agreement between the free N-Oct-3 DBD gyration and hydrodynamic radii.
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Small angle X-ray scattering patterns. (<bold>A</bold>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) Experimental scattering pattern for the free N-Oct-3 DBD (dots), and computed scattering curves for the CRH-bound conformation (solid red line), the Cf 183 conformer (solid turquoise line) and the Cf 221 conformer (dashed green line). (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>) Experimental (dots) and computed (color-coded) scattering patterns corresponding to the free CRH DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) and the equimolecular N-Oct-3 DBD/CRH complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) Experimental scattering pattern for the free N-Oct-3 DBD (dots), and computed scattering curves for the DR&#x003b1;-bound conformation (solid blue line), the Cf 194 conformer (solid magenta line) and the Cf 221 conformer (dashed green line). (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>) Experimental (dots) and computed (color-coded) scattering patterns corresponding to the free DR&#x003b1; DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) and the equimolecular N-Oct-3 DBD/DR&#x003b1; complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). The scattering patterns have been offset in the logarithmic scale for better visualization.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm453f7"/></fig>
<fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Distance distribution functions of the free N-Oct-3 DBD (green), the free CRH DNA (magenta), the N-Oct-3/CRH (red) and the N-Oct-3/DR&#x003b1; (blue) complexes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm453f8"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Summary of the structural parameters computed from the scattering data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sub>g</sub> (nm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">D<sub>max</sub> (nm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">M<sub>eff</sub> (kDa)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">M<sub>seq</sub> (kDa)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c7;</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-Oct-3 DBD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.93 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 &#x000b1; 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (CRH-bound)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 (DR&#x003b1;&#x02212;bound)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (Cf 183)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (Cf 194)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 (Cf 221)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRH DNA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 &#x000b1; 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR&#x003b1; DNA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-Oct-3/CRH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 &#x000b1; 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-Oct-3/DR&#x003b1;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.85 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 &#x000b1; 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>R<sub>g</sub>, D<sub>max</sub> and M<sub>eff</sub> designate, respectively, the radius of gyration, maximum size and effective molecular mass, calculated from the scattering data. For DNA-containing samples, the fact that the DNA contrast is higher than that of the protein was taken into account when estimating the M<sub>eff</sub> value. M<sub>seq</sub> is the molecular mass of the solutes predicted from the appropriate sequence. &#x003c7; denotes the discrepancy between the experimental data and the scattering curves computed from the models. In the case of the N-Oct-3 DBD, the &#x003c7; values have been calculated for the bound conformations, induced by the CRH or DR&#x003b1; DNA, and for conformations derived from molecular mechanics.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>In all cases, the theoretical scattering patterns of the predicted structures were computed using the program CRYSOL and then compared to the experimental data. The accuracy of the fit was assessed by the discrepancy value &#x003c7; as explained in the Material and Methods section, where typical values between 0.8 and 1.1 indicate good agreement. Thus, the computed scattering curves corresponding to the models of both the CRH DNA fragment and the N-Oct-3 DBD/CRH complex agree well with the respective experimental curves, with discrepancy values of 1.05 and 1.09, respectively (data groups 2 and 3 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; Figure S2A). The same observations can be made for the models of the DR&#x003b1; DNA fragment and the N-Oct-3 DBD/DR&#x003b1; complex (data groups 2 and 3 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B and respective discrepancy values of 0.82 and 1.09 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; Figure S2B). Fitting the computed scattering curves of the N-Oct-3 DBD in the predicted CRH- or DR&#x003b1;-bound conformations with the experimental data for the free N-Oct-3 DBD yields slightly higher discrepancy values (see respective &#x003c7; values of 1.18 and 1.23 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and data groups 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A and B). In order to accurately interpret this in terms of similarities versus differences between free and bound conformations, we must first build a referential of free-form models. For this, we systematically computed the theoretical scattering curves of the molecular mechanics-derived structures and fitted them to the free DBD experimental data.</p><p>According to their <italic>&#x003c7;</italic> values in the 1.06&#x02013;1.09 range, a number of conformers appear as good candidates to represent free N-Oct-3 DBD conformations. These can be divided into two distinct clusters which are themselves part of larger conformational families, &#x02018;FI&#x02019; and &#x02018;FII&#x02019;, defined by respective overall R.M.S. values of 4.9&#x02009;&#x000c5; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B) and 4.4&#x02009;&#x000c5; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). Importantly, the <italic>&#x003c7;</italic> value dispersion observed in both cases, 1.06&#x02013;1.19 and 1.06&#x02013;1.27 respectively, is compatible with the conservation of a given overall POU domain conformation within each family.</p><p>A more detailed analysis indicates that each conformational family contains structural sub-classes characterized by a particular distance between the POUs and POUh recognition helices (&#x02018;RH<sub>dist</sub>&#x02019;) within the 18&#x02013;35&#x02009;&#x000c5; range. Interestingly, the conformers with the lowest RH<sub>dist</sub> (Figure S3B) tend to be less energetically stable (Figure S3A), but are closer to the respective CRH- and DR&#x003b1;-bound conformations for which RH<sub>dist</sub> is comprised within the 15&#x02013;20&#x02009;&#x000c5; range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C and D). Taken together, these results imply that the two populations of putative free forms, F1 and FII, most likely coexist, and also that there could be a structural continuum running from free to less stable &#x02018;pre-bound&#x02019; conformations. In line with this, the fitted scattering curve of the CRH-bound modeled structure is very close to that of &#x02018;Cf 183&#x02019; (see the respective red- and turquoise-colored curves of data group 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A, and the corresponding <italic>&#x003c7;</italic> values of 1.18 and 1.09 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), Cf 183 being the best FI representative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>E). Similarly, the fitted scattering curve of the DR&#x003b1;-bound modeled structure is very close to that of &#x02018;Cf 194&#x02019; (see the respective blue- and magenta-colored curves of data group 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B, and the corresponding <italic>&#x003c7;</italic> values of 1.23 and 1.08 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), Cf 194 being the best FII representative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>F). By contrast, the fitted scattering curve of &#x02018;Cf 221&#x02019; significantly deviates from the free N-Oct-3 DBD experimental data with a <italic>&#x003c7;</italic> value of 1.90 (see the dashed green-colored curve in data group 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A and B, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Indeed, this conformer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>G), with its higher <italic>R</italic><sub>g</sub> (32&#x02009;&#x000c5;) and RH<sub>dist</sub> (50&#x02009;&#x000c5;) values, cannot represent the free form and belongs to a large conformational family of extended structures, characterized by RH<sub>dist</sub> values within the 40&#x02013;50&#x02009;&#x000c5; range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>D).</p><p>Model fitting against experimental SAXS data is a useful means to interpret scattering information in terms of higher-resolution structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>). Fitting of multiple models generated by molecular mechanics or dynamics has also been applied to analyze conformer ensembles in solution, especially in relation to protein unfolding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>). Along these lines, a recent report [see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>) and references therein] has explored how multiple well-defined protein conformations in a sample influence the scattering data. Test cases were established, based on simulation of SAXS data from reconstituted ensembles of protein structures, such as ensembles comprising various weighted proportions of the extended and collapsed states of calmodulin, a protein comprising two globular domains connected by a flexible helical linker. One of the main conclusions of this study is that the ability of <italic>ab initio</italic> modeling to differentiate static structures from dynamic structures depends strongly on the extent of the variability of the ensemble. Hence, an <italic>ab initio</italic> low-resolution model of the free N-Oct-3 DBD can be expected to reflect distinct properties from respective members of the FI and FII conformational families, but probably not from members of the same family. Indeed, a molecular envelope of the N-Oct-3 DBD generated using the GASBOR program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>) can accommodate the DR&#x003b1;- and the CRH-bound conformations at different sites (see Figure S4 and its legend). As these conformations bear similarities with the respective overall structures of the FI or FII families&#x02019; members, this lends support to the likely coexistence of these two conformational families, inasmuch as they are energetically equiprobable (see Figure S3 and its legend).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>CONCLUDING REMARKS</title><p>Initially structural studies performed on the POU-type DNA-binding domain showed that individual POUs and POUh sub-domains could be considered as rigid bodies when interacting with DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>). The adaptability of several POU proteins to a variety of DNA targets was then ascribed to the flexibility of the linker joining the POU sub-domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>). However, despite the critical importance of the linker with regards to the molding of specific regulatory POU conformations to the target DNA, no detailed molecular mechanism for this flexibility has so far been proposed. One of the main reasons for this of course is that neither Oct-1 nor Pit-1 POU linker structures can be resolved in the available crystallographic data derived from POU/DNA complexes.</p><p>The N-Oct-3 DBD linker has dual structural properties. On the one hand, it contains a helical peptide motif, in common with approximately half of the known inter-domain linkers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>), which might constrain the relative orientation of the two POU sub-domains. On the other hand, this linker also functions as a hinge region, as best exemplified in the transition between the CRH- and the DR&#x003b1;-bound conformations. A number of studies dealing with hinge motion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45 B46 B47 B48">45&#x02013;48</xref>) designate the pair of Gly residues present in the linker as potential key-players in the N-Oct-3 DBD conformational transitions. Based on these working hypotheses, we have combined various hydrodynamic and SAXS data with the results of a conformational search through torsion driving. We have shown that the linker flexibility resulting from rotations around this pair of Gly residues is sufficient to generate the transitions between the free and bound conformations, whilst at the same time respecting the local structuring of the linker. We have identified two families of putative free N-Oct-3 POU conformations, which can be interconverted by rotation around a virtual Gly&#x02013;Gly hinge axis. As specified earlier in the text, the distances between the DNA recognition helices (&#x02018;RH<sub>dist</sub>&#x02019;) in these conformers lie within the 18&#x02013;35&#x02009;&#x000c5; range, which favors the concerted DNA-binding activity of the two POU sub-domains. There might exist an equilibrium between these two families of putative free conformers and, for each family, between best free form representatives and less stable &#x02018;pre-bound&#x02019; conformers. We propose that NORE- or MORE-2-type DNA motifs select conformers closer to the final CRH-or DR&#x003b1;-bound conformations, respectively. Note that the importance of the Gly residues does not exclude the contribution of other residues to the overall flexibility of the linker, especially in the final adjustements required upon DNA binding.</p><p>In conclusion, our results indicate that regulatory DNA regions most likely select pre-existing N-Oct-3 DBD conformations, in addition to molding the appropriate DBD structure. More generally, our study emphasizes the necessity not only to employ a structural reading of nucleic regulatory sequences but also to integrate information about protein flexibility when predicting functional structure. Indeed a number of recent studies address the critical issue of the indirect readout of promoter DNA sequences (for example see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58 B59 B60 B61">58&#x02013;61</xref>), whilst new concepts and methods are emerging to explore protein flexibility and allostery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>). Along these lines, combining an ensemble optimization method with SAXS is a highly promising approach as perfectly illustrated in our recently published study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm453_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="nar_gkm453_1.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank David Barker for critical reading of the manuscript. R.A. and L.M. are grateful for financial support from the European Community to access the X33 EMBL beamline at DESY (Contract N&#x000b0; RII3/CT/2004/5060008 of the FP6 Program &#x02018;Research Infrastructure Action&#x02019;). This work was supported by research grants from the R&#x000e9;gion Midi-Pyr&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;es (AO N&#x000b0;. 03001137) and from the &#x02018;Action Concert&#x000e9;e Incitative Biologie Cellulaire, Mol&#x000e9;culaire et Structurale&#x02019; (AO N&#x000b0;050031). Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional networks: reverse-engineering gene regulation on a global scale</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15556037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lardenois</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalmel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leveillard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Poch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PromAn: an integrated knowledge-based web server dedicated to promoter analysis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>W578</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16845074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Siggia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stubb: a program for discovery and analysis of cis-regulatory modules</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>W555</fpage><lpage>W559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16845069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunewardena</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accounting for structural properties and nucleotide co-variations in the quantitative prediction of binding affinities of protein-DNA interactions</article-title><source>Pac. Symp. Biocomput</source><year>2006</year><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17094254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garvie</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of specific DNA sequences</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11741530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeWeese-Scott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moult</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular modeling of protein function regions</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2004</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15146492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moult</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyck</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vajda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vakser</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wodak</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CAPRI: a critical assessment of predicted interactions</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2003</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12784359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Latchman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>POU family transcription factors in the nervous system</article-title><source>J. Cell Physiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10199551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klemm</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rould</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aurora</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pabo</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the Oct-1 POU domain bound to an octamer site: DNA recognition with tethered DNA-binding modules</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8156594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The POU domain: versatility in transcriptional regulation by a flexible two-in-one DNA-binding domain</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1679</fpage><lpage>1693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7622033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon-del-Rio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of Pit-1 POU domain bound to DNA as a dimer: unexpected arrangement and flexibility</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1997</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9009203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Remenyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomilin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinbold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholer</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmanns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential dimer activities of the transcription factor Oct-1 by DNA-induced interface swapping</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11583619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scully</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunyak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Viadiu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooshmand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allosteric effects of Pit-1 DNA sites on long-term repression in cell type specification</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>1131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11073444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A CNS-specific POU transcription factor, Brn-2, is required for establishing mammalian neural cell lineages</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1993</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>1206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8274283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Easty</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goding</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The POU domain transcription factor Brn-2: elevated expression in malignant melanoma and regulation of melanocyte-specific gene expression</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1995</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2157</fpage><lpage>2164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7478537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The control of gene expression in melanocytes and melanomas</article-title><source>Melanoma Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8873046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The brn-2 gene regulates the melanocytic phenotype and tumorigenic potential of human melanoma cells</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1995</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7651733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellbrock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dexter</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goding</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Brn-2 transcription factor links activated BRAF to melanoma proliferation</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2923</fpage><lpage>2931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alazard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elbaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vossen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Icre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Erard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the 'NORE' (N-Oct-3 responsive element), a novel structural motif and composite element</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15767276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Seasholtz</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rat corticotropin-releasing hormone gene: sequence and tissue-specific expression</article-title><source>Mol. Endocrinol</source><year>1987</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3274895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo footprint analysis of the HLA-DRA gene promoter: cell-specific interaction at the octamer site and up-regulation of X box binding by interferon gamma</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1992</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>7601</fpage><lpage>7605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1502171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millevoi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thion</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vossen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghisolfi-Nieto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Erard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atypical binding of the neuronal POU protein N-Oct3 to noncanonical DNA targets. Implications for heterodimerization with HNF-3 beta</article-title><source>Eur. J. Biochem</source><year>2001</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11168419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Size-distribution analysis of macromolecules by sedimentation velocity ultracentrifugation and lamm equation modeling</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>2000</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1606</fpage><lpage>1619</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10692345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sedimentation analysis of noninteracting and self-associating solutes using numerical solutions to the Lamm equation</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>1998</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1503</fpage><lpage>1512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9726952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sedimentation equilibrium analysis of interference optical data by systematic noise decomposition</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem</source><year>1999</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10415089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MHJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>X-ray diffraction and scattering on disordered systems using synchrotron radiation</article-title><source>Nucl. Instrum. Methods</source><year>1983</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>469</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulin</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kempf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MHJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Data acquisition systems for linear and area X-ray detectors using delay line readout</article-title><source>Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A</source><year>1988</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>320</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dauvergne</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The localization method used at EMBL</article-title><source>Nucl. Instrum. Meth</source><year>1982</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>224</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konarev</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Volkov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokolova</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MHJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PRIMUS &#x02013; a Windows-PC based system for small-angle scattering data analysis</article-title><source>J. Appl. Crystallogr</source><year>2003</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>1282</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feigin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><source>Structure Analysis by Small-angle X-ray and Neutron Scattering</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Plenum Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A direct indirect method of small-angle scattering data treatment</article-title><source>J. Appl. Crystallogr</source><year>1993</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>267</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guinier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>La diffraction des rayons X aux tres petits angles; application a l'etude de phenomenes ultramicroscopiques</article-title><source>Ann. Phys. (Paris)</source><year>1939</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>237</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of the regularization parameter in indirect transform methods using perceptual criteria</article-title><source>J. Appl. Crystallogr</source><year>1992</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>503</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Barberato</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MHJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CRYSOL &#x02013; a program to evaluate X-ray solution scattering of biological macromolecules from atomic coordinates</article-title><source>J. Appl. Crystallogr</source><year>1995</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>768</fpage><lpage>773</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Crothers</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 Tat-derived peptides with TAR RNA</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1995</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>8885</fpage><lpage>8895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7612630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomilin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Remenyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leidel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vriend</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmanns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholer</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergism with the coactivator OBF-1 (OCA-B, BOB-1) is mediated by a specific POU dimer configuration</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11136971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dugast-Darzacq</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Egloff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cooperative dimerization of the POU domain protein Brn-2 on a new motif activates the neuronal promoter of the human aromatic L-amino acid decarboxylase gene</article-title><source>Brain Res. Mol. Brain Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14741405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vossen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alazard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Erard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristic patterns of N Oct-3 binding to a set of neuronal promoters</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>1049</fpage><lpage>1058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15178247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Klimov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thirumalai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular crowding enhances native state stability and refolding rates of globular proteins</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>4753</fpage><lpage>4758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15781864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosgen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettitt</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolen</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein folding, stability, and solvation structure in osmolyte solutions</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>2005</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>2988</fpage><lpage>2997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16113118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Heringa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An analysis of protein domain linkers: their classification and role in protein folding</article-title><source>Protein Eng</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SPXX, a frequent sequence motif in gene regulatory proteins</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1989</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2500531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the SPXX motif</article-title><source>Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B. Biol. Sci</source><year>1991</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>235</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nitta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hikichi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the YSPTSPS repeat containing two SPXX motifs in the CTD of RNA polymerase II: NMR studies of cyclic model peptides reveal that the SPTS turn is more stable than SPSY in water</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2001</year><volume>1548</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11451441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesk</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chothia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Domain closure in lactoferrin. Two hinges produce a see-saw motion between alternative close-packed interfaces</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8230220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesk</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chothia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural mechanisms for domain movements in proteins</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1994</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>6739</fpage><lpage>6749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8204609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olah</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosnick</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trewhella</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of the cAMP-dependent protein kinase catalytic subunit and its contraction upon binding the protein kinase inhibitor peptide</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1993</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>3649</fpage><lpage>3657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8385485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wriggers</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakravarty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of protein functional dynamics by peptide linkers</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>2005</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15880774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nollmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Byron</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavior of Tn3 resolvase in solution and its interaction with res</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>2005</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1920</fpage><lpage>1931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Augustus</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Spicer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for the differential regulation of DNA by the methionine repressor MetJ</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>34269</fpage><lpage>34276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16963446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowhurst</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhandiram</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Millett</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Doniach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Forman-Kay</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of molecular size within an unfolded state ensemble using small-angle X-ray scattering and pulse field gradient NMR techniques</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11829506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of multiple well defined conformations on small-angle scattering of proteins in solution</article-title><source>Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Petoukhov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of domain structure of proteins from X-ray solution scattering</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>2001</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>2946</fpage><lpage>2953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boelens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Verrijzer</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Vliet</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaptein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR studies of the POU-specific DNA-binding domain of Oct-1: sequential 1H and 15N assignments and secondary structure</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1993</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>6032</fpage><lpage>6040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8507639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tilborg</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Laat</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Boelens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Vliet</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaptein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of the Oct-1 POU homeodomain determined by NMR and restrained molecular dynamics</article-title><source>J. Biomol. NMR</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7663141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Strating</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Laat</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Vliet</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linker length and composition influence the flexibility of Oct-1 DNA binding</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2043</fpage><lpage>2053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9155030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The POU domain: versatility in transcriptional regulation by a flexible two-in-one DNA-binding domain</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1679</fpage><lpage>1693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7622033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Arauzo-Bravo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ReadOut: structure-based calculation of direct and indirect readout energies and specificities for protein-DNA recognition</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>W124</fpage><lpage>W127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16844974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Vuyst</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Genest</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Culard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atypical recognition of particular DNA sequences by the archaeal chromosomal MC1 protein</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>10369</fpage><lpage>10377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16042414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Everaers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indirect readout: detection of optimized subsequences and calculation of relative binding affinities using different DNA elastic potentials</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>5638</fpage><lpage>5649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17038333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aeling</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Opel</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tretyachenko-Ladokhina</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lathrop</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Senear</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indirect recognition in sequence-specific DNA binding by Escherichia coli integration host factor: the role of DNA deformation energy</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>39236</fpage><lpage>39248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17035240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gierasch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The changing landscape of protein allostery</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16423525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Echols</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Milburn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hespenheide</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>EZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Database of Macromolecular Motions: new features added at the decade mark</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D296</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernado</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylonas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Petoukhov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackledge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural characterization of flexible proteins using small-angle X-ray scattering</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2007</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>5656</fpage><lpage>5664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17411046</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
