<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1919480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm316</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intramolecular DNA quadruplexes with different arrangements of short and long loops</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rachwal</surname><given-names>Phillip A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Findlow</surname><given-names>I. Stuart</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>Joern M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>Keith R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>School of Biological Sciences, University of Southampton, Bassett Crescent East, Southampton SO16 7PX, UK and <sup>2</sup>School of Chemistry, University of Southampton, Highfield, Southampton SO17 1BJ, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+44 23 8059 4374</phone><fax>+44 23 8059 4459</fax><email>k.r.fox@soton.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>4214</fpage><lpage>4222</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We have examined the folding, stability and kinetics of intramolecular quadruplexes formed by DNA sequences containing four G<sub>3</sub> tracts separated by either single T or T<sub>4</sub> loops. All these sequences fold to form intramolecular quadruplexes and 1D-NMR spectra suggest that they each adopt unique structures (with the exception of the sequence with all three loops containing T<sub>4</sub>, which is polymorphic). The stability increases with the number of single T loops, though the arrangement of different length loops has little effect. In the presence of potassium ions, the oligonucleotides that contain at least one single T loop exhibit similar CD spectra, which are indicative of a parallel topology. In contrast, when all three loops are substituted with T<sub>4</sub> the CD spectrum is typical of an antiparallel arrangement. In the presence of sodium ions, the sequences with two and three single T loops also adopt a parallel folded structure. Kinetic studies on the complexes with one or two T<sub>4</sub> loops in the presence of potassium ions reveal that sequences with longer loops display slower folding rates.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>DNA sequences that contain four or more closely spaced G-tracts can fold to form intramolecular quadruplexes, which consist of stacked G-quartets that are linked by three loops between the four G-strands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3 B4">1&#x02013;4</xref>). These structures are stabilized by monovalent cations (especially potassium) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) and can adopt a variety of different folding patterns dependent on the relative orientation of the strands and the position of the loops. G-rich sequences with the potential to form quadruplex structures are common in genomic DNA and these have been identified in several biologically important regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7 B8 B9">7&#x02013;9</xref>). The most widely studied is telomeric DNA, which in higher eukaryotes is composed of repeats of the sequence GGGTTA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) and for which about 50&#x02013;100 bases at the 3&#x02032;-end are single stranded. A number of other non-telomeric G-rich DNA sequences may also form quadruplexes and these have been identified in the promoters of <italic>c-myc</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12 B13 B14 B15">12&#x02013;15</xref>), Ki-<italic>ras</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), <italic>bcl</italic>2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17 B18 B19">17&#x02013;19</xref>), <italic>c-kit</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>), VEGF gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) and HIF 1&#x003b1; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>), as well as in fragile X-syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) and other trinucleotide repeat sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), the retinoblastoma susceptibility gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>), the chicken &#x003b2;-globin gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>) and the insulin gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). G-rich sequences are especially abundant in gene promoter regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) and there is an overabundance of G-rich sequences in the regulatory regions of muscle-specific genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>).</p><p>For intramolecular quadruplexes, the four G-tracts are separated by loops. These are of various lengths and can be as short as a single nucleotide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29 B30 B31">29&#x02013;31</xref>). Genomic searches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) have revealed many G-rich sequences which may be able to adopt these structures, the most common of which are successive G-tracts that are separated by single T or A residues. The loops can be arranged in several different ways; double-chain reversal (propeller) loops link two adjacent parallel strands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>), while edgewise or diagonal loops link two antiparallel strands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Some structures contain both edge-wise and propeller loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34 B35 B36">34&#x02013;36</xref>). In the all-parallel (propeller) structures, the nucleotides are in the <italic>anti</italic> conformation, while the other structures have different combinations of <italic>anti</italic> or <italic>syn</italic> glycosidic bonds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). It is known that loop length and sequence affect quadruplex stability and structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37 B38 B39 B40">37&#x02013;40</xref>). Sequences with single nucleotide loops between the G<sub>3</sub> tracts only adopt a parallel structure, while longer loops can also adopt an antiparallel arrangement of the strands. Quadruplex stability is also affected by the sequence of the loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39 B40 B41">39&#x02013;41</xref>), and the bases that flank the quadruplex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42 B43 B44">42&#x02013;44</xref>).</p><p>There is considerable variation in quadruplex structure, depending on the DNA sequence and the ionic conditions. The biological function of quadruplexes may well depend on the folded conformation that is adopted, especially if this involves interaction with specific proteins. Such an effect has been suggested for the NHE element of the c-myc promoter, which can in principle adopt multiple conformations. Since the loops can have a considerable effect on quadruplex folding and stability, we have examined how changes in loop length affect quadruplex properties. One very stable intramolecular quadruplex contains four G<sub>3</sub> tracts that are linked by single T residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>) and this is known to be an inhibitor of HIV integrase. We have used variations on this sequence to examine the importance of loop length on quadruplex folding and stability. In this study, we have systematically replaced each of the single T loops with T<sub>4</sub> and have used CD, fluorescence melting, 1D-NMR, gel electrophoresis and kinetic studies to examine the effect of loop length and position on quadruplex folding and stability.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Oligonucleotides</title><p>All oligonucleotides were synthesized on an Applied Biosystems ABI 394 automated DNA/RNA synthesiser on the 0.2&#x02009;&#x000b5;mole scale using the standard cycles of acid-catalysed detritylation, coupling, capping and iodine oxidation procedures. Phosphoramidite monomers and other reagents were purchased from Applied Biosystems, Proligo and Link Technologies. The sequences of the oligonucleotides used in this work are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. Fluorescently labelled oligonucleotiodes were used in all the experiments. These were labelled at the 5&#x02032;-end with 6-amidohexylfluorescein (FAM), and at the 3&#x02032;-end with dabcyl using C7 dabcyl cpg (Link Technologies). Oligonucleotides were purified by gel filtration using Nap10 columns (GE Healthcare) and analysed by gel electrophoresis. The bases adjacent to the fluorophore and quencher were the same (T) for all the oligonucleotides to avoid any differences in their effects on quadruplex formation and stability.
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Sequences of the quadruplex-forming oligonucleotides used in this work</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</th><th colspan="7" align="center" rowspan="1">Sequence</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="7" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loop 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loop 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loop 3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d-F-TGGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGT-Q</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d-F-TGGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGT-Q</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d-F-TGGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGT-Q</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d-F-TGGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGT-Q</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d-F-TGGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGT-Q</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d-F-TGGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGT-Q</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>F = FAM; Q = dabcyl.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Fluorescence melting studies</title><p>The thermal melting temperatures of the quadruplexes were determined using the fluorescence melting technique that we have developed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>) and have used previously for assessing the stability of related quadruplexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). When the sequence adopts a folded structure the quencher and fluorophore are in close proximity and the fluorescence is quenched. When the structure melts, these groups become separated and there is a large increase in fluorescence. Since the fluorophore and quencher are anchored on relatively long aliphatic tethers the quenching does not depend on the quadruplex topology and the fluorescence is quenched for both parallel and antiparallel complexes. Fluorescence melting experiments were conducted in a Roche LightCycler as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>) in a total reaction volume of 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l. Oligonucleotides (final concentration 0.25&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) were prepared in 10&#x02009;mM lithium phosphate pH 7.4, which was supplemented with various concentrations of potassium chloride or sodium chloride. The LightCycler has one excitation source (488&#x02009;nm) and the changes in fluorescence were measured at 520&#x02009;nm. For several of the oligonucleotides initial experiments revealed that there was considerable hysteresis between the heating and annealing profiles when the temperature was changed at 0.2&#x000b0;C.s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, indicating that the process was not at thermodynamic equilibrium. Melting experiments were therefore performed at a much slower rate of heating and cooling (0.2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) by changing the temperature in 1&#x000b0;C steps, leaving the samples to equilibrate for 5&#x02009;min at each temperature before recording the fluorescence. Under these conditions, no hysteresis was observed (except for some experiments with G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>). In a typical experiment, the oligonucleotides were first denatured by heating to 95&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min. They were then annealed by cooling to 30&#x000b0;C at 0.2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and melted by heating to 95&#x000b0;C at the same rate. The fluorescence was recorded during both the annealing and melting steps. In some instances, the formation of intramolecular or intermolecular complexes was examined by determining the melting curves using a range of oligonucleotide concentrations (0.1&#x02013;10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M). Melting temperatures (<italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> values) were determined from the first derivatives of the melting profiles using the Roche LightCycler software.</p></sec><sec><title>Thermodynamic and kinetic analysis</title><p><italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> values were obtained from the maxima of the first derivatives of the melting profiles using the LightCycler software or, together with &#x00394;<italic>H</italic>, from van't Hoff analysis of the melting profiles using FigP for Windows. The fraction folded was calculated as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>) from the difference between the measured fluorescence and the upper and lower baselines. All reactions were performed at least twice and the calculated <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> values usually differed by &#x0003c;0.5&#x000b0;C with a 5% variation in &#x00394;<italic>H</italic>. Since &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> = 0&#x02009;at the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>, &#x00394;<italic>S</italic> was estimated as &#x00394;<italic>H</italic>/<italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>. Values for &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> at 310&#x02009;K were then estimated from &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> = &#x00394;<italic>H</italic> &#x02013; <italic>T</italic>&#x00394;<italic>S</italic>. The van't Hoff analysis assumes that &#x00394;<italic>H</italic> is independent of temperature (i.e. &#x00394;<italic>C<sub>p</sub></italic> = 0), that the reaction is only a two-step process (i.e. that there are no significant reaction intermediates) and that there is only one folded form of the quadruplex. The number of specifically bound monovalent cations (&#x00394;<italic>n</italic>), was calculated from the slopes of plots of &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> against log[M<sup>+</sup>] as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>).</p><p>Hysteresis between the melting and annealing profiles occurs when the reaction is not at thermodynamic equilibrium as a result of the slow folding and/or unfolding kinetics. Individual folding (<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>) and unfolding (<italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub>) rate constants can be derived from this hysteresis as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Temperature jump kinetics</title><p>The kinetics of quadruplex unfolding were also determined by measuring the rate of change of fluorescence after rapidly increasing the temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>). The quadruplexes were equilibrated at a temperature around the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>, which was then rapidly increased by 5&#x000b0;C at the fastest rate on the LightCycler (20&#x000b0;C.s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). This temperature change causes the quadruplex to partially unfold, moving along the melting curve. Although the theoretical dead-time under these conditions is only 0.25&#x02009;s, all fluorescence changes that occurred in the first 2&#x02009;s were ignored, during equilibration to the new temperature. Successive temperature-jumps were then recorded on the same sample by further increasing the temperature by 5&#x000b0;C. Each experiment was repeated at least twice. The time-dependent changes in fluorescence were fitted by an exponential function <italic>F<sub>t</sub></italic> = <italic>F</italic><sub>f</sub> &#x000d7; (1 &#x02212; e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><italic><sup>kt</sup></italic>) + <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>, using SigmaPlot 10, where <italic>F<sub>t</sub></italic> is fluorescence at time <italic>t, F</italic><sub>0</sub> is the initial fluorescence and <italic>F</italic><sub>f</sub> is total change in fluorescence (the final fluorescence is <italic>F</italic><sub>f</sub> + <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>). The relaxation rate constant (<italic>k</italic>) obtained from this analysis is equal to the sum of the folding (<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>) and unfolding (<italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub>) rate constants. Arrhenius plots of ln(<italic>k</italic>) against 1/<italic>T</italic> were constructed from these data and used to estimate the activation energy <italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub> and pre-exponential factor <italic>A</italic> [<italic>k</italic> = <italic>A</italic> &#x000d7; exp(&#x02212;<italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub>/<italic>RT</italic>)].</p></sec><sec><title>Gel electrophoresis</title><p>Non-denaturing gel electrophoresis was performed using 14% polyacrylamide gels, which were run in TBE buffer that had been supplemented with 20&#x02009;mM KCl. Bands in the gels were visualised under UV light. The oligonucleotide concentration was 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;M.</p></sec><sec><title>Circular dichroism</title><p>CD spectra were measured on a Jasco J-720 spectropolarimeter as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). Oligonucleotide solutions (5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) were prepared in 10&#x02009;mM lithium phosphate pH 7.4, containing either 200&#x02009;mM potassium chloride or 200&#x02009;mM sodium chloride. The samples were heated to 95&#x000b0;C and annealed by slowly cooling to 15&#x000b0;C over a period of 12&#x02009;h. Spectra were recorded between 220 and 320&#x02009;nm in 5&#x02009;mm path length cuvettes. Spectra were averaged over 10 scans, which were recorded at 100&#x02009;nm.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> with a response time of 1&#x02009;s and a bandwidth of 1&#x02009;nm. A buffer baseline was subtracted from each spectrum and the spectra were normalized to have zero ellipticity at 320&#x02009;nm.</p></sec><sec><title>Proton NMR</title><p>One-dimensional <sup>1</sup>H NMR experiments were performed on a Varian Inova 600&#x02009;MHz spectrometer. Oligonucleotides were prepared in 200&#x02009;mM potassium phosphate pH 7.4 and were annealed by heating to 95&#x000b0;C before slowly cooling to 15&#x000b0;C. 300&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of the oligonucleotide sample was mixed with 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l D<sub>2</sub>O and placed in a Shigemi NMR tube. The final strand concentration was 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M. 1D proton NMR spectra were recorded at 25&#x000b0;C with a sweep width of 25&#x02009;p.p.m., WATERGATE water suppression, an acquisition time of 0.5&#x02009;s and 32&#x02009;k scans. Data were processed using VNMR software (Varian Inc.) with zero filling and resolution enhancement.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>A variety of physical techniques were used to examine the folding, stability and kinetics of the intramolecular quadruplexes that are formed by sequences containing four G<sub>3</sub> tracts separated by either single T or T<sub>4</sub> loops, in different combinations. The sequences of these oligonucleotides are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p><sec><title>Circular dichroism</title><p>Intramolecular quadruplexes can adopt a variety of different topologies in which the strands run in different orientations with lateral, edgewise or diagonal loops. Circular dichroism has frequently been used to indicate whether these fold in a parallel or antiparallel configuration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>). Parallel quadruplexes, in which the glycosidic bonds are all <italic>anti</italic>, display a positive CD signal around 265&#x02009;nm, with a negative peak at 240&#x02009;nm. In contrast, antiparallel topologies, with both <italic>syn</italic> and <italic>anti</italic> bonds, exhibit a positive signal at around 295&#x02009;nm, with a negative signal or shoulder around 260&#x02009;nm. CD spectra for these oligonucleotides, in the presence of sodium or potassium ions, are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> [other studies with related sequences have shown that the fluorophores do not affect the CD spectra (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>)].
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>CD spectra of the fluorescently-labelled quadruplex-forming oligonucleotides in the presence of 10&#x02009;mM lithium phosphate pH 7.4 containing 200&#x02009;mM KCl (<bold>a</bold>) or 200&#x02009;mM NaCl (<bold>b</bold>). G<sub>3</sub>T, black; G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T, red; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T, blue; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub>, pink; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T, green; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>, cyan. The inset to the upper panel shows the CD spectrum of G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> in the presence of different concentrations of KCl: black 1&#x02009;mM; red, 5&#x02009;mM; green 20&#x02009;mM; blue 50&#x02009;mM; pink, 200&#x02009;mM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm316f1"/></fig></p><p>In the presence of potassium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) all the sequences, except G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> show CD spectra with a positive peak around 265&#x02009;nm and a minimum around 240&#x02009;nm, which is typical of the parallel configuration. In contrast, G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> displays a positive peak at 295&#x02009;nm, indicative of an antiparallel topology. Quadruplexes with single nucleotide loops are thought to be only able to form &#x02018;propeller-type&#x02019; fold-back loops generating parallel-stranded complexes, while longer T<sub>4</sub> loops can form lateral, edgewise or diagonal loops. These CD spectra suggest that the presence of only one single T loop is sufficient to induce the formation of a parallel-stranded structure and that the complexes only adopt an antiparallel arrangement when all the loops are longer. In general, these CD spectra were independent of the potassium concentration in the range 20&#x02013;200&#x02009;mM K<sup>+</sup>, though pronounced changes were observed for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> (inset to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>a). For this sequence a secondary peak is visible around 260&#x02009;nm at low potassium ion concentrations, which disappears as the potassium ion concentration is increased; this is accompanied by an increase in the peak at 295&#x02009;nm. The presence of isoelliptic points in these spectra suggests that this sequence may adopt two distinct structural forms in the presence of low or high potassium ion concentrations.</p><p>In the presence of sodium ions, the CD spectra for G<sub>3</sub>T, G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T are again typical of a parallel topology, with peaks around 265&#x02009;nm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>b). However, the addition of a second T<sub>4</sub> loop results in spectra with equal-sized peaks at 265&#x02009;nm and 295&#x02009;nm. It has been suggested that sodium ions promote the formation of antiparallel topologies and it is possible that the two longer T<sub>4</sub> loops are laterally arranged, while the single T loop is in a fold-back arrangement. This mixed spectrum could indicate the co-existence of parallel and antiparallel topologies in solution, but a hybrid structure containing both <italic>syn</italic> and <italic>anti</italic> bonds seems more likely; this will be considered further in the Discussion. The spectrum of G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> is similar in the presence of sodium and potassium ions, with a peak at 295&#x02009;nm, suggesting an antiparallel topology.</p></sec><sec><title>Gel mobility</title><p>We further compared the global structures of these sequences by examining their mobilities in polyacrylamide gels that had been supplemented with 20&#x02009;mM KCl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Each of the sequences ran as a single band, with the exception of G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> which is smeared, possibly because this sequence is less stable under these conditions (<italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> &#x0223c; 40&#x000b0;C, see below). G<sub>3</sub>T has the greatest mobility, as expected as it has the lowest molecular weight. Surprisingly we find that G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T has a lower mobility than G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T and similarly G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> is slower than G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T. It appears that the presence of a single T in the central loop reduces the mobility. This will be considered in the Discussion.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Mobility of the quadruplex-forming oligonucleotides on a 14% polyacrylamide gel supplemented with 20&#x02009;mM KCl.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm316f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Imino proton NMR spectra</title><p>One of the defining features of structures that contain G-quartets is the appearance of imino proton resonances between 10.5 and 12.0&#x02009;p.p.m. in NMR spectra (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>). Examination of this region of NMR spectra has often been used to assess whether the sequence adopts a unique structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>) and the presence of multiple or ill-defined peaks is evidence for the existence of multiple structures. The imino proton spectra for each of these sequences are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>. It can be seen that the spectra of G<sub>3</sub>T, G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T, G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> display between 10 and 12 well-resolved and sharp peaks, indicative of well-defined structures. In the cases where 10 or 11 peaks are resolved, the intensities indicate that one or two imino protons have degenerate chemical shifts. Hence, the number of hydrogen-bonded imino protons is 12, as expected for three stacked G-quartets. G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T also shows 12 major peaks, though the spectrum contains some minor peaks, which might indicate the presence of a small amount of a second structure. In contrast, the imino proton spectrum of G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> shows multiple peaks confirming that it adopts more than one stable conformation.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>1D imino proton NMR spectra of the quadruplex-forming oligonucleotides. The samples (100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) were prepared in 200&#x02009;mM potassium phosphate pH 7.4. The top panel shows the 1D-NMR spectrum for G<sub>3</sub>T between 5 and 15&#x02009;p.p.m., while the other panels show the imino proton region for each oliogonucleotide. The individual peaks are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm316f3"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Fluorescence melting curves</title><p>Representative fluorescent melting curves for these sequences are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> in the presence of potassium and sodium ions. The <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> values at different ionic strengths, along with the calculated values for &#x00394;<italic>H</italic>, are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>. The samples were melted and annealed at 0.2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; no hysteresis was observed at this rate of temperature change (except for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> at low ionic strengths). The melting temperatures were all independent of concentration (between 0.1 and 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M; Supplementary material <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) confirming that these oligonucleotide sequences form intramolecular (not intermolecular) complexes. As expected, all the complexes are more stable in potassium than sodium ions. G<sub>3</sub>T is the most stable and, in the presence of potassium, substituting a T<sub>4</sub> loop instead of a loop with a single T decreases the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> by about 20&#x000b0;C, irrespective of whether the replacement is in a central (G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T) or peripheral loop (G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T), though G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T is about 2&#x02013;3&#x000b0;C more stable than G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T. Replacing a second T loop with T<sub>4</sub> causes a further 20&#x000b0;C decrease in <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T is about 2&#x02013;4&#x000b0;C more stable than G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub>. In each case, the sequence with a single T in the central loop is slightly less stable than the equivalent sequence with T<sub>4</sub> in the same position. Replacing all three single T loops with T<sub>4</sub> decreases the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> by a further 10&#x000b0;C, though the melting and annealing curves with this sequence show hysteresis at low ionic strengths and the melting (but not the annealing) profiles are biphasic.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Fluorescence melting profiles for the quadruplex-forming oligonucleotides. The reactions were performed in 10&#x02009;mM lithium phosphate pH 7.4 containing either 20&#x02009;mM KCl (left hand panel) or 200&#x02009;mM NaCl (right hand panel). The temperature was changed at 0.2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The curves show the fraction folded (&#x003b1;) as a function of temperature, calculated as described in the Methods section. G<sub>3</sub>T, black; G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T, red; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T, blue; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub>, pink; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T, green; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>, cyan.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm316f4"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p><italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> and &#x00394;<italic>H</italic> values for the fluorescently labelled quadruplex-forming oligonucleotides, determined in the presence of 10&#x02009;mM lithium phosphate pH 7.4 containing different concentrations of KCl. The samples were heated and cooled at a rate of 0.2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">[KCl] mM</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>&#x000b0;C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> kJ.mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>&#x000b0;C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> kJ.mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>&#x000b0;C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> kJ.mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>&#x000b0;C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> kJ.mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>&#x000b0;C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> kJ.mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>&#x000b0;C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> kJ.mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;242 &#x000b1; 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;271 &#x000b1; 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;227 &#x000b1; 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;208 &#x000b1; 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;275 &#x000b1; 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;259 &#x000b1; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;250 &#x000b1; 15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;266 &#x000b1; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;258 &#x000b1; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;184 &#x000b1; 13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;205 &#x000b1; 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;267 &#x000b1; 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;262 &#x000b1; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;207 &#x000b1; 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;227 &#x000b1; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5/37.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;284 &#x000b1; 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;275 &#x000b1; 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;225 &#x000b1; 13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;246 &#x000b1; 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0/51.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;234 &#x000b1; 11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;247 &#x000b1; 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;269 &#x000b1; 13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;266 &#x000b1; 10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;256 &#x000b1; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;276 &#x000b1; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;293 &#x000b1; 9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>n</italic></td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">2.13 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">2.29 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">2.31 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">2.75 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">2.89 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">4.01 &#x000b1; 0.16</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>*Indicates a biphasic melting profile. All reactions were performed at least twice and the calculated <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> values usually differed by &#x0003c;0.5&#x000b0;C. &#x00394;<italic>H</italic> values were typically calculated for melting profiles for which the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> was between 40&#x000b0;C and 80&#x000b0;C. Missing values at low concentrations of KCl correspond to complexes for which the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>s were too low to measure (&#x0003c;30&#x000b0;C), while those at high ionic strengths (especially G<sub>3</sub>T) were too stable (<italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> &#x0003e; 85&#x000b0;C).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>The relative order of stability is the same in the presence of sodium ions (Supplementary material <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Replacing one T loop with T<sub>4</sub> decreases the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> by 15&#x02013;20&#x000b0;C, and a second substitution causes a further 10&#x000b0;C decrease. Replacing all three loops with T<sub>4</sub> does not affect the stability any further and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> has a similar <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> to G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub>. As seen with potassium, sequence isomers with a central T<sub>4</sub> loop are slightly more stable than those with a central T loop (i.e. G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T &#x0003e; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> and G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T &#x0003e; G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T).</p><p>&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> values for the quadruplex single-strand transition in the presence of potassium were derived from these melting profiles by van't Hoff analysis, assuming that the reaction is a two-state equilibrium, and the values are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>. These are typical of those for similar quadruplexes and show a general decrease in &#x00394;<italic>H</italic> as the overall loop length increases. As previously reported for other quadruplexes, &#x00394;<italic>H</italic> increases with ionic strength, consistent with the presence of specific cation binding sites within the quadruplex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). The slopes of plots of &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> against log[M<sup>+</sup>] can be used to determine the stoichiometry of cation binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) yielding values of &#x00394;<italic>n</italic> (the difference between the number of ions bound in the folded and unfolded states) and the values of &#x00394;<italic>n</italic> in the presence of potassium are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>. For an antiparallel structure containing three stacked G-quartets, &#x00394;<italic>n</italic> would be expected to be either two (the number of potassium ions located between the stacked quartets) or four (including two more ions that may be coordinated between the loops and the terminal quartets). A value of two seems more likely for a parallel topology with single nucleotide loops, in which the loops do not interact with the terminal quartets. The values of &#x00394;<italic>n</italic> are between two and three for all the complexes that contain at least one loop with a single T residue, though there is a steady increase in this value with increased numbers of T<sub>4</sub> loops, which will be considered further in the Discussion. &#x00394;<italic>n</italic> is larger for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>, consistent with the suggestion that it adopts a different topology, though this value may not be accurate as there is some hysteresis in its melting profiles at low potassium concentrations and the NMR data suggest that it adopts more than one conformation.</p></sec><sec><title>Kinetics of quadruplex formation</title><sec><title>Hysteresis</title><p>The fluorescence melting experiments shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> were performed at a rate of temperature change of 0.2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and only G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> showed hysteresis between the melting and annealing profiles. On increasing the rate to 2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> there was a 7&#x02013;10&#x000b0;C hysteresis for the sequences with two T<sub>4</sub> loops in the presence of potassium, though the melting and annealing profiles were identical for the sequences with single T<sub>4</sub> loops. The sequences with single T<sub>4</sub> loops only displayed hysteresis when the rate of heating was increased to 12&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, while the melting and annealing curves for G<sub>3</sub>T were always superimposable. Representative heating and annealing curves at different rates of heating and cooling in the presence of 20&#x02009;mM potassium are shown in Supplementary material <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and the different <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> values are summarized in Supplementary <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. No hysteresis was observed for any of these sequences in the presence of sodium at even the fastest rate of heating and cooling. Differences between the melting and annealing curves arise because the reaction is not at thermodynamic equilibrium and indicate that either the folding or the unfolding process is slow. The folding (<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>) and unfolding (<italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub>) rate constants for the unimolecular folding reaction can be obtained by analysis of these data as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>a shows the melting and annealing profiles for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub>, determined at 12&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively, while similar plots for G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T are included in Supplementary material, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref> shows Arrhenius plots for the folding and unfolding rates constructed from these data for G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>a) and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>b). The kinetic parameters derived from these Arrhenius plots are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>. Several factors are apparent from these kinetic data. Firstly, the association reaction shows unusual temperature dependence, with an apparent negative activation energy, i.e. the reaction is faster a lower temperatures. This has been noted by others and is consistent with the reaction occurring by a nucleation-zipper mechanism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). Secondly, the data for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T are very similar to G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T is similar to G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T, suggesting that the distribution of the different loops is less important than their length. Thirdly, the unfolding parameters are very similar for all four oligonucleotides, while the folding parameters vary according to the loop lengths. For the association reaction both ln(A) and <italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub> are less negative for the complexes with longer loops. This kinetic analysis was not performed for G<sub>3</sub>T as it showed no hysteresis and for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> as the melting and annealing curves were biphasic.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Hystersis between the melting and annealing profiles for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T (upper panel, with a temperature change of 12&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> (lower panel, with a temperature change of 2&#x000b0;C.min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the presence of 10&#x02009;mM lithium phosphate pH 7.4 containing 20&#x02009;mM KCl. (<bold>b</bold>) temperature-jump relaxation profiles for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T (upper panel) and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> (lower panel. The traces show the rate of approach to a new equilibrium following a rapid 5&#x000b0;C increase in temperature to the value shown. The profiles have been normalized to show the fractional change in fluorescence with time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm316f5"/></fig>
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Arrhenius plots showing the temperature dependence of the kinetic parameters for G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> (<bold>a</bold>) and G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T (<bold>b</bold>). Open symbols were derived from the hysteresis between the melting and annealing profiles; <italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub>, open circles; <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, open triangles. Filled circles show the time constants obtained from the temperature-jump experiments (<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> + <italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm316f6"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Kinetic parameters for folding (<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>) and unfolding (<italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub>) of the quadruplex-forming oligonucleotides determined from analysis of the hysteresis between melting and annealing curves</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub> (kJ mo1<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ln (A) s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub> (kJ mo1<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ln (A) s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;93 &#x000b1; 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36 &#x000b1; 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182 &#x000b1; 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 &#x000b1; 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;88 &#x000b1; 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34 &#x000b1; 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178 &#x000b1; 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 &#x000b1; 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48 &#x000b1; 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24 &#x000b1; 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 &#x000b1; 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 &#x000b1; 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;59 &#x000b1; 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;27 &#x000b1; 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 &#x000b1; 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 &#x000b1; 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The experiments were performed in 10&#x02009;mM lithium phosphate pH 7.4 containing 20&#x02009;mM potassium chloride. <italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub> is the activation energy (kJ.mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and A is the pre-exponential factor from the equation <italic>k</italic> = Ae<sup>(&#x02013;</sup><italic><sup>E</sup></italic><sup>a/RT)</sup>. No values are presented for G<sub>3</sub>T as it does not show any hysteresis, or G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> as more than one folded configuration exists in solution.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Temperature-jump kinetics</title><p>In order to confirm the kinetic data obtained from the hysteresis experiments we performed temperature-jump relaxation kinetics on these complexes. In this technique, the temperature of the complex (maintained around the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>) is rapidly increased (by 5&#x000b0;C) and the time-dependent changes in fluorescence are recorded as the reaction relaxes to a new equilibrium. Representative temperature-jump relaxation profiles for these complexes are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>b and reveal a slow time-dependent relaxation to the new equilibrium, which is clearly faster for the complexes with two short loops than the ones with two long loops. The kinetic curves at different temperatures were fitted with single exponential functions and the rate constants obtained are presented as Arrhenius plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>. For this unimolecular reaction the apparent rate constant for the relaxation is equal to the sum of the folding and unfolding rate constants (<italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub> + <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>). Although it is not possible to resolve these individual components, at low temperatures the sum is dominated by <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, while the sum approximates to <italic>k</italic><sub>&#x02212;1</sub> at high temperatures. It can be seen that there is excellent agreement between the rate constants determined by the two independent methods for each of the sequences, confirming that sequences with longer loops display slower rates of folding with little effect on the rate of unfolding.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>Topology</title><p>Circular dichroism is often used to indicate the folding topology of DNA quadruplexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>). Antiparallel quadruplexes typically have a positive CD signal at around 295&#x02009;nm, while parallel quadruplexes display a positive signal around 260&#x02009;nm. These differences reflect both the arrangements of the strands and the <italic>syn/anti</italic> orientations around the glycosidic bonds. Parallel topologies have all-<italic>anti</italic> glycosidic angles, while antiparallel ones have both <italic>syn</italic> and <italic>anti</italic> in varying ratios. However, it is clear that these spectral signatures are not necessarily an indicator of quadruplex folding as some exceptions have been noted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>). Nonetheless, CD spectra are useful indicators of changes in global quadruplex configuration for series of related oligonucleotides. In the presence of potassium, all the oligonucleotides that contain at least one single T loop exhibit a similar CD spectrum that is indicative of a parallel topology. It therefore appears that in potassium the presence of only one single T loop, in any position, is sufficient to promote all the other loops to form a fold-back propeller-like structure. In principle, these oligonucleotides could adopt several different folded configurations, yet the NMR and gel electrophoresis experiments suggest that only one predominates. When all three loops contain T<sub>4</sub>, there is a dramatic change in the CD spectrum to a form that is consistent with antiparallel folding, though the details are dependent on the ionic strength suggesting that G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> can adopt multiple configurations. This again is consistent with the NMR and electrophoresis experiments, which suggest the presence of multiple folded forms. Previous studies have suggested that the quadruplex formed by d(G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>G<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> adopts an antiparallel hairpin dimer in the presence of both sodium and potassium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>).</p><p>A similar effect is seen for G<sub>3</sub>T, G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T and G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T in the presence of sodium ions and these display CD spectra that are consistent with parallel topologies. However, the greater propensity to form antiparallel structures in the presence of sodium is seen with T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T and T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> loops, which have CD spectra with peaks at both 260&#x02009;nm and 295&#x02009;nm. This may indicate the presence of multiple structural forms, but it is more likely due to the formation of a structure that contains both edgewise (T<sub>4</sub>) and fold-back (T) loops, as observed with other sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34 B35 B36">34&#x02013;36</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Stability</title><p>The fluorescence melting experiments show that the number of short loops, rather than their position, has the greatest effect on quadruplex stability. In the presence of potassium ions, G<sub>3</sub>T is the most stable and in concentrations above 5&#x02009;mM it does not display a melting transition. Substituting a T<sub>4</sub> into either the first or second loop decreases the <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic> by about 20&#x000b0;C, with a further 20&#x000b0;C decrease on introducing a second T<sub>4</sub> substitution. The same effect is seen in the presence of sodium ions though there is only a small decrease in stability on changing the third loop to T<sub>4</sub>, consistent with the CD spectra which show that G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub>, G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> display some antiparallel characteristics in contrast to all the other oligonucleotides.</p><p>It is noticeable that sequences with a single T loop in the central position are less stable and have lower gel mobilities than their sequence isomers with T<sub>4</sub> in this position (i.e. compare T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub> loops with T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T and T<sub>4</sub>-T-T with T-T<sub>4</sub>-T). It appears that folded structures with a central T<sub>4</sub> loop are more compact and have higher thermal stability. There is then a further decrease in stability when all three loops are composed of T<sub>4</sub>, which as noted above adopts a different configuration.</p></sec><sec><title>Potassium ion binding</title><p>The variation of &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> with ionic strength allows us to estimate the difference in the number of potassium ions specifically bound to the folded and unfolded structures. This value is close to two for G<sub>3</sub>T as expected, since two potassium ions can bind between the three stacked quartets. Although the precise values of &#x00394;<italic>n</italic> should be interpreted with caution, it is noticeable that there is a steady increase in this value as the number of longer loops is increased. The value of &#x00394;<italic>n</italic> is similar for G<sub>3</sub>T-T<sub>4</sub>-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T and is lower than for both G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T<sub>4</sub>-T and G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>-T-T<sub>4</sub>. These results suggest that the longer loops are involved in cation binding. The larger value of &#x00394;<italic>n</italic> seen with G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> may not be significant, as this sequence adopts multiple configurations.</p></sec><sec><title>Kinetic analysis</title><p>Comparing the kinetic parameters for the sequences with one or two T<sub>4</sub> loops (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>) reveals that the unfolding parameters are very similar, while there are clear differences in the folding reaction. Complexes with longer loops have higher (less negative) activation energies for the association reaction and larger values for the pre-exponential factor (which is related to the entropy of the transition state). In comparison, no hysteresis is observed with G<sub>3</sub>T and temperature-jump experiments showed a very fast re-equilibration, while G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub> has slower folding and unfolding parameters, though not as slow as G<sub>4</sub>T<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). It is clear that the folding of intramolecular structures with only single T loops is fast, and we imagine that when one loop is composed of a single nucleotide the G-tracts on either side rapidly associate, forming a platform to which the other G-tracts can bind. The results with the oligonucleotides containing one or two T<sub>4</sub> loops suggest that the position of the single-base loop has little effect on the kinetics and that the most important factor is the number of longer loops.</p><p>It is interesting to note that none of these sequences show any hysteresis in the presence of sodium ions, even though G<sub>3</sub>T and those with two single T loops appear to adopt a similar global structure. The higher stability and slower kinetics in the presence of potassium may therefore reflect conformational changes subsequent to the initial folding events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm316_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="nar_gkm316_1.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>PAR is supported by a research studentship from BBSRC.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quadruplex DNA: sequence, topology and structure</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>5402</fpage><lpage>5415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17012276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G-quartets 40 years later: From 5&#x02032;-GMP to molecular biology and supramolecular chemistry</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl</source><year>2004</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14755695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuryavyi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA architecture: from G to Z</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16714104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simonsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G-quadruplex DNA structures - Variations on a theme</article-title><source>Biol. Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>382</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11405224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sodium-potassium switch in the formation of 4-stranded G4-DNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>344</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2320109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghuraman</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cech</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mono-valent cation induced atructure of telomeric DNA - the G-quartet model</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2590943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huppert</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of quadruplexes in the human genome</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>2908</fpage><lpage>2916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huppert</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G-quadruplexes in promoters throughout the human genome</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17169996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly prevalent putative quadruplex sequence motifs in human DNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>2901</fpage><lpage>2907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation of parallel 4-stranded complexes by guanine-rich motifs in DNA and its implications for meiosis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1988</year><volume>334</volume><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3393228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telomeric DNA dimerizes by formation of guanine tetrads between hairpin loops</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1989</year><volume>342</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2601741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambrus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of the biologically relevant G-quadruplex element in the human c-<italic>MYC</italic> promoter. implications for G-quadruplex stabilization</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>2048</fpage><lpage>2058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15697230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rangan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedoroff</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of duplex to G-quadruplex transition in the c-myc promoter region by a small molecule</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>4640</fpage><lpage>4646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11035006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddiqui-Jain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grand</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bearss</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct evidence for a G-quadruplex in a promoter region and its targeting with a small molecule to repress c-<italic>MYC</italic> transcription</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>11593</fpage><lpage>11598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12195017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simonsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pecinka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubista</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA tetraplex formation in the control region of c-myc</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1167</fpage><lpage>1172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9469822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cogoi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xodo</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G-quadruplex formation within the promoter of the KRAS proto-oncogene and its effect on transcription</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2536</fpage><lpage>2549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16687659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR solution structure of the major G-quadruplex structure formed in the human BCL2 promoter region</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>5133</fpage><lpage>5144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16998187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Dexheimer</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambrus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An intramolecular G-quadruplex structure with mixed parallel/antiparallel G-strands formed in the human BCL-2 promoter region in solution</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2006</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>1096</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16433524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dexheimer</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deconvoluting the structural and drug-recognition complexity of the G-quadruplex-forming region upstream of the bcl-2 P1 promoter</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2006</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>5404</fpage><lpage>5415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16620112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reszka</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Huppert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zloh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladame</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Putative DNA quadruplex formation within the human c-<italic>kit</italic> oncogene</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2005</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>10584</fpage><lpage>10589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16045346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>KX</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusche</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Facilitation of a structural transition in the polypurine/polypyrimidine tract within the proximal promoter region of the human VEGF gene by the presence of potassium and G-quadruplex-interactive agents</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>6070</fpage><lpage>6080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16239639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Armond</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebbinghaus</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for the presence of a guanine quadruplex forming region within a polypurine tract of the hypoxia inducible factor 1 alpha promoter</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>16341</fpage><lpage>16350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16331995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fragile-X syndrome d(CGG)<sub>n</sub> nucleotide repeats form a stable tetrahelical structure</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>4950</fpage><lpage>4954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8197163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsugami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Uesugi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katahira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intramolecular higher order packing of parallel quadruplexes comprising a G:G:G:G tetrad and a G(:A):G(:A):G(:A):G heptad of GGA triplet repeat DNA</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>28147</fpage><lpage>28153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12748183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murchie</surname><given-names>AIH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>DMJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinoblastoma susceptibility genes contain 5&#x02032; sequences with a high propensity to form guanine-tetrad structures</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1738603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodford</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weitzmann</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Usdin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chicken beta-globin gene promoter forms a novel &#x0201c;cinched&#x0201d; tetrahelical structure</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>5208</fpage><lpage>5214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8617804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unusual DNA structure of the diabetes susceptibility locus IDDM2 and its effect on transcription by the insulin promoter factor Pur-1/MAZ</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>12508</fpage><lpage>12512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11070077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yafe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Etzioni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisman-Shomer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation and properties of hairpin and tetraplex structures of guanine-rich regulatory sequences of muscle-specific genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>2887</fpage><lpage>2900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15908587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topology variation and loop structural homology in crystal and simulated structures of a bimolecular DNA quadruplex</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2006</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>5480</fpage><lpage>5487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16620121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pommier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ion selective folding of loop domains in a potent anti-HIV oligonucleotide</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1997</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>12498</fpage><lpage>12505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9376354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Modi</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Propeller-type parallel-stranded G-quadruplexes in the human c-myc promoter</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>8710</fpage><lpage>8716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15250723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MPH</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of parallel quadruplexes from human telomeric DNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>417</volume><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12050675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of the human telomeric repeat d[AG<sub>3</sub>(T<sub>2</sub>AG<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>] G-tetraplex</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>1993</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8081740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambrus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Bialis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human telomeric sequence forms a hybrid-type intramolecular G-quadruplex structure with mixed parallel/antiparallel strands in potassium solution</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2723</fpage><lpage>2735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16714449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuryavyi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the human telomere in K+ solution: An intramolecular (3+1) G-quadruplex scaffold</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2006</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>9963</fpage><lpage>9970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16866556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different loop arrangements of intramolecular human telomeric (3+1) G-quadruplexes in K+ solution</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>5715</fpage><lpage>5719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17040899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cevec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Plavec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of loop residues and cations on the formation and stability of dimeric DNA G-quadruplexes</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>15238</fpage><lpage>15246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16285727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Huppert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neidle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loop-length-dependent folding of G-quadruplexes</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>16405</fpage><lpage>16415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15600342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Risitano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of loop size on the stability of intramolecular DNA quadruplexes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2598</fpage><lpage>2606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smirnov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of loop sequence and size on DNA aptamer stability</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2000</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1462</fpage><lpage>1468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Risitano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability of intramolecular DNA quadruplexes: Comparison with DNA duplexes</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>6507</fpage><lpage>6513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12767234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallenbach</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of thymine tract length on the structure and stability of model telomeric sequences</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1993</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>3596</fpage><lpage>3603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8466901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallenbach</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and stability of sodium and potassium complexes of dT<sub>4</sub>G<sub>4</sub> and dT<sub>4</sub>G<sub>4</sub>T</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1992</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2455</fpage><lpage>2459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1547229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merkina</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetic stability of intermolecular DNA quadruplexes</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>2005</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15849241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potassium-induced loop conformational transition of a potent anti-HIV oligonucleotide</article-title><source>J Biomol. Struct. Dyn</source><year>1997</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9440003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darby</surname><given-names>RAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sollogoub</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McKeen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Risitano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High throughput measurement of duplex, triplex and quadruplex melting curves using molecular beacons and a LightCycler</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>e39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachwal</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exceptionally slow kinetics of the intramolecular quadruplex formed by the Oxytricha telomeric repeat</article-title><source>Org. Biomol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>4153</fpage><lpage>4157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16267597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mergny</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of thermal melting curves</article-title><source>Oligonucleotides</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15025917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimmel</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biophysical Chemistry.</source><year>1980</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>W. H. Freedman and Company</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernal-Mendez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leumann</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability and kinetics of nucleic acid triplexes with chimaeric DNA/RNA third strands</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2002</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>12343</fpage><lpage>12349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12369823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rougee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Faucon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mergny</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Barcelo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannangeli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garestier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Helene</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics and thermodynamics of triple-helix formation - effects of ionic-strength and mismatches</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1992</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>9269</fpage><lpage>9278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1390713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermodynamic and kinetic stability of intermolecular triple helices containing different proportions of C<sup>+</sup>.GC and T.AT triplets</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>5598</fpage><lpage>5606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14500823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balagurumoorthy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brahmachari</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasisekharan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hairpin and parallel quartet structures for telomeric sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>4061</fpage><lpage>4067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1508691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balagurumoorthy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brahmachari</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and stability of human telomeric sequence</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>21858</fpage><lpage>21869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8063830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rachwal</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of G-tract length on the structure and stability of intramolecular DNA quadruplexes</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2007</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>3036</fpage><lpage>3044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17311417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feigon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshlap</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>H-1 NMR spectroscopy of DNA triplexes and quadruplexes</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1995</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8569497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dapic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdomerovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Peberdy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trent</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biophysical and biological properties of quadruplex oligodeoxyribonucleotides</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2097</fpage><lpage>2107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12682360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Randazzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccialli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Petraccone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Giancola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayol</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of an 8-bromodeoxyguanosine incorporation on the parallel quadruplex structure [d(TGGGT)]<sub>4</sub></article-title><source>Org. Biomol. Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14747859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keniry</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Strahan</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of the Na<sup>+</sup> form of the dimeric guanine quadruplex [d(G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>G<sub>3</sub>)]<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>Eur. J. Biochem</source><year>1995</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7588810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strahan</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Keniry</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR structure refinement and dynamics of the K<sup>+</sup>-[d(G<sub>3</sub>T<sub>4</sub>G<sub>3</sub>)]<sub>2</sub> quadruplex via particle mesh Ewald molecular dynamics simulations</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>1998</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>968</fpage><lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9675197</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
