<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eCAM</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Evidence-based Complementary and Alternative Medicine</journal-id><journal-title>Evidence-based Complementary and Alternative Medicine : eCAM</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1741-427X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1741-4288</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17549238</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1876611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ecam/nel083</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles - Basic Sciences</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Inhibition of Release of Vasoactive and Inflammatory Mediators in Airway and Vascular Tissues and Macrophages By a Chinese Herbal Medicine Formula for Allergic Rhinitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lenon</surname><given-names>George Binh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Chun Guang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Charlie Changli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thien</surname><given-names>Francis Chung Kong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Story</surname><given-names>David Frederick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>The Chinese Medicine Research Group, RMIT University Bundoora West Campus and <sup>2</sup>Alfred Hospital and Monash University Melbourne, Victoria, Australia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>For reprints and all correspondence: George Lenon, RMIT University, Plenty Road, Bundoora, Melbourne, VIC 3049, Australia. Tel: +613-992-56587; Fax: +613-992-57178; E-mail: <email>george.lenon@rmit.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2006 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons"><p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license><abstract><p>Herbal therapies are being used increasingly for the treatment of allergic rhinitis. The aim of this study was to investigate the possible pharmacological actions and cellular targets of a Chinese herbal formula (RCM-101), which was previously shown to be effective in reducing seasonal allergic rhinitis symptoms in a randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial. Rat and guinea pig isolated tissues (trachea and aorta) were used to study the effects of RCM-101 on responses to various mediators. Production of leukotriene B<sub>4</sub> in porcine neutrophils and of prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub> and nitric oxide (NO) in Raw 264.7 cells were also measured. In rat and guinea pig tracheal preparations, RCM-101 inhibited contractile responses to compound 48/80 but not those to histamine (guinea pig preparations) or serotonin (rat preparations). Contractile responses of guinea pig tracheal preparations to carbachol and leukotriene C<sub>4,</sub> and relaxant responses to substance P and prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub> were not affected by RCM-101. In rat aortic preparations, precontracted with phenylephrine, endothelium-dependent relaxant responses to acetylcholine and endothelium-independent relaxant responses to sodium nitroprusside were not affected by RCM-101. However, RCM-101 inhibited relaxations to <sc>l</sc>-arginine in endothelium-denuded rat aortic preparations, which had been pre-incubated with lipopolysaccharide. RCM-101 did not affect leukotriene B<sub>4</sub> formation in isolated porcine neutrophils, induced by the calcium ionophore A23187; however, it inhibited prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub> and NO production in lipopolysaccharide-stimulated murine macrophages (Raw 264.7 cells).The findings indicate that RCM-101 may have multiple inhibitory actions on the release and/or synthesis of inflammatory mediators involved in allergic rhinitis.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>allergic rhinitis</kwd><kwd>Chinese herbal medicine</kwd><kwd>histamine</kwd><kwd>inducible nitric oxide synthase</kwd><kwd>inflammation</kwd><kwd>leukotriene B<sub>4</sub></kwd><kwd>prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub></kwd><kwd>seasonal allergic rhinitis formula (RCM-101)</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Seasonal allergic rhinitis (SAR), also known as hay fever or pollinosis, is a common allergic condition worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). SAR is an immune response to a wide variety of pollens from grasses, weeds and trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). It involves the interaction of the allergens with specific IgE antibodies bound to high-affinity Fc&#x0025b; receptors on the surface of mast cells and basophils in the nasal mucosa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). This induces degranulation of these cells, resulting in the release of a number of mediators, which are responsible for a cascade of symptoms. The early symptoms of SAR, such as sneezing and rhinorrhea, are due to the rapid release of particular mediators, histamine being considered the most significant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Other mediators, such as prostaglandins, leukotrienes and nitric oxide (NO) are generally associated with the late phase responses, which predominantly cause nasal obstruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>).</p><p>SAR is usually treated symptomatically with histamine H<sub>1</sub> receptor antagonists, sympathomimetic vasoconstrictors and corticosteroids. However, these agents are associated with certain undesirable side effects and, frequently, do not provide complete symptom relief (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Because of the shortcomings of conventional therapies, alternatives have been sought. Certain traditional Chinese herbal formulae have long been used for treating SAR in China and other Asian countries/regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>), although generally their effectiveness has not been critically evaluated. Recently, we conducted a randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial of a traditional Chinese herbal formula for the treatment of SAR. We demonstrated that the formula, which will be referred to as RCM-101, was effective in reducing SAR symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). The present study was undertaken to identify possible cellular targets and pharmacological actions that may be involved in the beneficial effects of RCM-101 in SAR.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>RCM-101</title><p>RCM-101 contains 18 herbal ingredients, selected by the principles of Chinese medicine theory. Each herb was supplied in a granulated form by the Min Tong Pharmaceutical Company, Taichong, Taiwan. The company holds Good Manufacturing Practice (GMP) certification from the Australian Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA). Each authenticated, quality certified raw herb was tested for heavy metals and washed and dried. The dried material was extracted in boiling water for 1&#x02013;1.5 h and the aqueous extract separated by filtration (100 mesh). The extract was heated (50&#x02013;60&#x000b0;C) under reduced pressure (50&#x02013;70 mm Hg) to reduce the water content to 60% (2&#x02013;5 h). The concentrated extract of each herb was individually combined with an excipient (starch) and the product dried and ground into fine granules. For each preparation, 1 g of granulated product was equivalent to 5 g of the raw herb. The granulated herbal preparations were supplied, sterilized, in sealed plastic bottles.</p><p>The granulated individual herbal ingredients were combined in the proportions given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and encapsulated (500 mg per capsule, New Product Development Pty Ltd, Queensland, Australia). The capsules provided a convenient dose-form for our clinical trial of the formula for SAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>), such that the dosage of each individual herb was within the range recommended by the Chinese Pharmacopeia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). For the current study, granules of the herbal formula were taken from the capsules and extracted as described below. All of the herbal ingredients of RCM-101 are listed as active raw herbs for medicines in the Australian Register of Therapeutic Goods.
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Composition of RCM-101 (% of granulated herbs by weight<sup>*</sup>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Botanical name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Flos Magnoliae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Magnolia liliflora</italic> (Desr.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xin Yi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Frutus Schisandrae Chinensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Schisandra chinensis</italic> (Turcz.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu Wei Zi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Frutus Terminaliae Chebulae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">He Zi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Frutus Xanthii Sibirici</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Xanthii sibirici</italic> Patr. Ex Widd.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cang Er Zi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Herba Asari</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Asarum sieboldii</italic> Miq.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xi Xin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Herba Menthae Haplocalysis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mentha haplocalyx</italic> Briq.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bo He</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Herba Schizonepetae Tenuifoliae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Schizonepeta tenuifolia</italic> Briq.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jing Jie</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pericappium Citri Reticulatae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Citrus reticulata</italic> Blanco</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen Pi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Radix Angelicae Sinensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Angelica sinensis</italic> (Oliv.) Diels</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dang Gui</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Radix Astragali Membranaceus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Astragalus membranaceus</italic> (Fisch.) Bge</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huang Qi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Radix Bupleuri</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bupleurum chinense</italic> D.C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chai Hu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Radix Codonopsitis pilosulae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Codonopsis pilosula</italic> (Franch.) Nannf.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dang Shen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Radix Glycyrrhizae Uralensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Glycyrrhiza uralensis</italic> (Fisch.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gan Cao</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Radix Saposhnikoviae Divaricata</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Saposhnikovia divaricata</italic> (Turcz.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fang Feng</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhizoma Atractylodis Macrocephalae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Atractylodes macrocephala</italic> Koidz</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bai Zhu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhizoma Cimicifugae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cimicifuga foetida</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sheng Ma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhizoma Ligustici Chuanxiong</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ligusticum chuanxiong</italic> (Hort.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chuan Xiong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Semen Plantaginis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Plantago asiatica</italic> L. Wild.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Che Qian Zi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>One gram of each granulated herb is equivalent to 5 g of the dry weight of the raw herb.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Reagents</title><p>5-Hydroxytryptamine (serotonin), histamine sulfate, phenylephrine hydrochloride, acetylcholine chloride, compound 48/80, sodium nitroprusside (SNP), prostaglandin E<sub>2,</sub> leukotriene C<sub>4</sub>, substance P, carbamyl-choline-chloride (carbachol), <italic>N</italic><sup>G</sup>-nitro-<sc>l</sc>-arginine methyl ester (<sc>l</sc>-NAME), <sc>l</sc>-arginine, lipolysaccharide <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, human recombinant interferon-&#x003b3;, methysergide maleate, mepyramine maleate, calcium ionophore A23187, Hanks' balanced salt solution, RPMI 1640 medium, fetal bovine serum (FBS), gentamycin and nordihydroguaiaretic acid (NDGA) were obtained from the Sigma Chemical Company (St Louis, MO, USA). The immune-enzyme analysis (IEA) kit, arachidonic acid, prostaglandin B<sub>2</sub> (PGB<sub>2</sub>), leukotriene B<sub>4</sub> (LTB<sub>4</sub>), 6-trans LTB<sub>4</sub>, 6-trans-12 epi LTB<sub>4</sub>, 5-hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acid (5-HETE) and 15-hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acid (15-HETE) were obtained from the Cayman Chemical Company (Ann Arbor, MI, USA). HPLC-grade methanol was supplied by Selby-Biolab (Clayton, Victoria, Australia). All other reagents were of analytical quality and obtained from Merck Pty Ltd (Kilsyth Victoria, Australia).</p><p>The composition of the physiological salt solution (PSS) was (mM) as follows: NaCl, 118; KCl, 4.7; NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 25; MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.45; KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1.03; and CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 2.5.</p></sec><sec><title>Extraction of RCM-101</title><p>The granulated combined herbal formula was extracted with distilled water (123 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) at room temperature with continuous agitation for 4 h. The aqueous extract was collected by centrifugation (5000 r.p.m. for 10 min) and vacuum filtration. The extract was freeze-dried and the resultant powder redissolved in water in a concentration of 10 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Each 1000 mg of granulated herbal formula yielded a mean of 17.4 &#x000b1; 2.6 mg of freeze-dried powder. This solution was stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C, being diluted to the desired concentrations on the day of use.</p></sec><sec><title>Functional Studies</title><p>All experimental procedures involving animals were approved by RMIT University Animal Ethics Committee and were conducted in conformity with the Australian National Health and Medical Research Council guidelines.</p><p>Rats (Sprague-Dawley, 200&#x02013;300 g) and guinea pigs (Dunkin&#x02013;Harley, 300&#x02013;450 g) of both sexes were used. The animals were killed by asphyxiation with 95% CO<sub>2</sub> and then decapitated. Aortae and tracheae from rats and tracheae from guinea pigs were removed and set-up in organ baths as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). In brief, each aorta and trachea was cut into four cylindrical lengths (5 mm) and each &#x02018;ring&#x02019; was mounted, vertically, in an 8 ml organ bath containing PSS bubbled with 95% O<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2.</sub> The preparations were maintained at 37&#x000b0;C under a resting tension of 2 g wt (aortic rings) or 1 g wt (tracheal rings) and were allowed to equilibrate for 60 min before commencing experimental procedures.</p><sec><title>Guinea Pig Tracheal Preparations</title><p>The concentration of RCM-101 extract (freeze-dried powder) used in all experiments with guinea pig tracheal preparations was 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The effects of RCM-101 on contractile responses to histamine, leukotriene C<sub>4</sub> (LTC<sub>4</sub>) and compound 48/80 were investigated separately in tracheal preparations. The effects of the herbal formula on relaxant responses to substance P and prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub> (PGE<sub>2</sub>) were investigated in tracheal preparations that had been precontracted with carbachol (10 &#x003bc;M), again only one agonist being used in each preparation. With LTC<sub>4</sub> and PGE<sub>2</sub>, a submaximal response was elicited in the absence and then in the presence of RCM-101 (LTC<sub>4</sub>, 30 nM; PGE<sub>2</sub>, 1 &#x003bc;M). For histamine (0.1&#x02013;100 &#x003bc;M) and substance P (0.1&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;M), concentration response relationships were established, first in the absence and then in the presence of RCM-101.</p><p>To study the effects of RCM-101 on contractions of guinea pig trachea induced by compound 48/80, in each tracheal preparation, a near maximal response to histamine (30 &#x003bc;M) was first established and then the preparation was challenged once with compound 48/80 (0.125 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) in the presence of either RCM-101 extract, vehicle or the H<sub>1</sub>-histamine antagonist, mepyramine (100 &#x003bc;M). In each case the contractile response to compound 48/80 was expressed as a percentage of the maximal histamine response.</p></sec><sec><title>Rat Tracheal Preparations</title><p>To investigate the effect of RCM-101 on contractile responses of rat tracheal preparations to serotonin, responses to serotonin (10 &#x003bc;M) were obtained first in the absence and then in the presence of RCM-101 extract. To study the effects of the herbal formula on contractions induced by compound 48/80, in each tracheal preparation, a near maximal response to 10 &#x003bc;M serotonin was established and then the preparation was challenged once with compound 48/80 (0.125 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), in the presence of either RCM-101 extract, vehicle or the serotonin antagonist methysergide (100 &#x003bc;M). In each case, the contractile response to compound 48/80 was expressed as a percentage of the response to serotonin. As with guinea pig tracheal preparations, the concentration of RCM-101 extract used in all experiments with rat tracheal preparations was 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Rat Aortic Preparations</title><p>To investigate the effect of RCM-101 on endothelium-dependent relaxations, cumulative concentration&#x02013;response relationships to the relaxant actions of acetylcholine (0.03&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;M) were established in phenylephrine (1 &#x003bc;M)-contracted aortic rings in the absence and then presence of RCM-101 extract (0.04, 0.1 or 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) or vehicle. RCM-101 or vehicle was introduced into the PSS 15 min before re-establishing the concentration&#x02013;response relationship.</p><p>To investigate the effect of RCM-101 on endothelium-independent relaxations, the vascular endothelium was removed by gently rubbing the vessel lumen with a pair of forceps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). The preparations were then set-up in organ baths as described above, and contracted with 1 &#x003bc;M phenylephrine. Successful endothelium removal was confirmed by the failure of acetylcholine (10 &#x003bc;M) to produce relaxation. Cumulative concentration&#x02013;response relationships to the relaxant actions of SNP (0.001&#x02013;1 &#x003bc;M) were established in the absence and then presence of RCM-101 extract (0.04, 0.1 or 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) or vehicle (15 min incubation).</p><p>In some preparations, the effect of RCM-101 on inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS)-dependent relaxations was investigated as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Briefly, endothelium-denuded preparations, as described above, were incubated with lipopolysaccharide (LPS, 100 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) for 6 h, and then responses to <sc>l</sc>-arginine (10, 30 and 100 &#x003bc;M, added cumulatively) were established in phenylephrine (1 &#x003bc;M) contracted preparations, in the absence or presence of RCM-101 extract (0.1, 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) or vehicle. In these experiments RCM-101 was present throughout the incubation with LPS and <sc>l</sc>-arginine challenges, being introduced into the bathing solution 15 min before contracting the preparations with phenylephrine (except where indicated otherwise).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Cell Culture Studies</title><sec><title>Leukotriene B<sub>4</sub> Production</title><p>Synthesis of leukotriene B<sub>4</sub> (LTB<sub>4</sub>) was induced in neutrophils as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Porcine blood was collected from a local abattoir. Neutrophils were isolated using a Percoll gradient and suspended in Hanks' buffer, containing 5 mM HEPES. Suspended neutrophils (2.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells per ml) were incubated (37&#x000b0;C) with arachidonic acid (2.5 &#x003bc;M) together with RCM-101 extract, NDGA or vehicle, for 5 min. Formation of LTB<sub>4</sub> was then initiated by adding the calcium ionophore A23187 (2.5 &#x003bc;M) and, 5 min later, the reaction was terminated by adjusting the pH to 3 with citric acid. Prostaglandin B<sub>2</sub> (PGB<sub>2</sub>, 45 ng) and 15-HETE (83 ng) were then added as internal standards. The reaction mixture was extracted with 5 ml of chloroform/methanol (7:3, v/v) and dried under vacuum. The residue was dissolved in 120 &#x003bc;l of the HPLC mobile phase (methanol/water/acetic acid, 76/34/0.08, v/v/v, pH 3.0) and leukotriene metabolites were separated using a Waters HPLC system equipped with an auto sampler, a multisolvent delivery system and a Waters 996 Photodiode Array Detector. Standard curves were prepared for LTB<sub>4</sub> (10&#x02013;200 ng) and 5-HETE (500&#x02013;800 ng) (in neutrophil suspensions).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub> Production</title><p>Murine macrophages (Raw 264.7 cells; American Type Culture Collection, Rockville, MD, USA) were grown in RPMI 1640 medium, supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated FBS, 100 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> gentamycin, 1.5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sodium bicarbonate and 10 mM HEPES, at 37&#x000b0;C, in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells were subcultured once a week by harvesting them with trypsin/EDTA and seeding them in 75 cm<sup>2</sup> flasks. Once confluent, the cells were seeded in 24-well plates (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well), in serum-free RPMI medium and then incubated with LPS (1 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) for 24 h, in the absence or presence of RCM-101 extract (1, 100 or 1000 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The supernatant was collected and PGE<sub>2</sub> was detected using an EIA kit. The assay depends on competition between PGE<sub>2</sub> and PGE<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;acetylcholinesterase conjugate (PGE<sub>2</sub>-tracer) for a limited amount of monoclonal PGE<sub>2</sub> antibody. The assays were carried out according to the manufacture's protocol, in triplicate. PGE<sub>2</sub> release was calculated using software supplied by the kit manufacturer.</p></sec><sec><title>NO Production</title><p>Raw 264.7 cells were cultured as described above, except that interferon-&#x003b3; (10 ng ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was added to the wells during incubation with LPS/RCM-101. NO production was measured from the amount of the stable metabolite of NO, nitrite ion. Aliquots of 5 &#x003bc;l of cell culture medium were added to 1 ml of 0.03 M potassium iodide solution, acidified to pH with 0.07 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. Nitrite ion was then determined by an electrochemical method using an amiNO-700 sensor and an inNO system (Innovative Instruments Inc., USA). The apparatus was calibrated with acidified nitrite solution, over the range of 50&#x02013;200 nM, in accordance with the manufacturer's specification. The sensitivity of the sensor was determined to be 123 &#x000b1; 8.9 pA nM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<italic>n</italic> = 25).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data are expressed as means &#x000b1; standard errors of the mean (SEM). The statistical significance of differences between means was determined by unpaired, two-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic>-test or, for more than two groups, by first testing for global differences by one- or two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and then testing for differences between predetermined pairs of means by Dunnet's test. Probability levels less than 0.05 (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) were taken to indicate significant differences. For the 5-lipoxygenase assay, the data were analyzed using Water Millenium Software, Version 3.2, results being expressed as percentage inhibition, the vehicle control being taken as 0% inhibition.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Contractile Responses Induced by Compound 48/80 Markedly Reduced in Guinea Pig Trachea</title><p>RCM-101 extract (0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) did not significantly affect contractile responses to histamine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>A). Similarly, contractile responses to carbachol (0.1&#x02013;30 &#x003bc;M) and LTC<sub>4</sub> (30 ng ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were unaltered by RCM-101 in the same concentration (data not shown). Relaxant responses of tracheal preparations, precontracted with 10 &#x003bc;M carbachol, to PGE<sub>2</sub> (1 &#x003bc;M) and substance P (0.1&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;M) were also unaltered by RCM-101 (data not shown). In contrast, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>B, contractile responses induced by compound 48/80 (125 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were markedly reduced by RCM-101 (0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The histamine H<sub>1</sub> antagonist (100 &#x003bc;M) mepyramine, reduced responses to 48/80 to about the same extent as RCM-101 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>B).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Guinea pig tracheal preparations. (<bold>A</bold>) Histamine-induced contractions were unaffected by RCM-101 (0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Data are means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = number of preparations). (<bold>B</bold>) Inhibition of compound 48/80-induced contractions by RCM-101 (0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and mepyramine (100 &#x003bc;M). Responses are expressed as percentages of the response to 30 &#x003bc;M histamine. Data are means &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, Student's unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nel083f1"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Contractile Responses Induced by Compound 48/80 Markedly Reduced in Rat Trachea</title><p>Contractile responses to 10 &#x003bc;M serotonin were not significantly affected by 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> RCM-101 extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>A). However, as with guinea pig tracheal preparations, contractions of rat tracheal preparations induced by compound 48/80 (125 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were significantly reduced by 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> RCM-101 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>B). RCM-101 also slowed the rate of onset of contraction of rat tracheal preparations to compound 48/80, the maximum tension developing in 2.6 &#x000b1; 0.2 min (<italic>n</italic> = 12) in the vehicle-treated group and in 6.2 &#x000b1; 0.5 min (<italic>n</italic> = 8) in the presence of RCM-101. Compound 48/80 responses were also reduced by 100 &#x003bc;M methysergide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>B).
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Rat tracheal preparations. (<bold>A</bold>) Contractions to serotonin (10 &#x003bc;M) were unaffected by RCM-101 (0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Data are means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = number of preparations). (<bold>B</bold>) Inhibition of compound 48/80-induced contractions by RCM-101 (0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and methysergide (100 &#x003bc;M). Responses are expressed as percentages of pre-treatment serotonin response. Data are means &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, Student's unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nel083f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of iNOS-Mediated Relaxations of Endothelium-Denuded Rat Aortic Preparations to <sc>l</sc>-Arginine</title><p>In LPS-treated endothelium-denuded aortic preparations, precontracted with phenylephrine (1 &#x003bc;M), <sc>l</sc>-arginine (10, 30 and 100 &#x003bc;M) produced concentration-dependent relaxation. The presence of RCM-101 extract (0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) during the 6 h incubation with LPS markedly reduced the responses to <sc>l</sc>-arginine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). A lower concentration of RCM-101 (0.1 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) introduced for the LPS incubation, produced smaller reductions in <sc>l</sc>-arginine responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). If RCM-101 was only introduced into the tissue bathing solution 15 min before the first exposure to <sc>l</sc>-arginine, the responses to <sc>l</sc>-arginine were not significantly different from control responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). In contrast, <sc>l</sc>-NAME (100 &#x003bc;M), introduced 15 min before the first exposure to <sc>l</sc>-arginine, markedly reduced the <sc>l</sc>-arginine responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Endothelium-denuded, phenylephrine-contracted rat aortic preparations in which NO synthase was induced by incubation for 6 h with lipopolysaccharide (LPS). RCM-101 (0.1 and 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), when present throughout LPS incubation, inhibited responses to <sc>l</sc>-arginine. The responses were unaffected by RCM-101 (0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) when it was introduced 15 min before the first <sc>l</sc>-arginine challenge. In contrast, <sc>l</sc>-NAME (100 &#x003bc;M), introduced 15 min before the first <sc>l</sc>-arginine challenge, inhibited the responses. Data plotted are means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = number of preparations). <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, two-way ANOVA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nel083f3"/></fig></p><p>The inhibitory effects of RCM-101 (present during LPS incubation) and of <sc>l</sc>-NAME (introduced after LPS incubation) were only partly reversed by repeated exchanges of the tissue bathing solution over a 5 min period (data not shown).</p><p>RCM-101 extract (0.04, 0.1 and 0.4 mg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) did not significantly affect endothelium-dependant relaxations to acetylcholine (0.03&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;M) or endothelium-independent relaxations to SNP (0.001&#x02013;1 &#x003bc;M) (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>LPS-Stimulated Prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub> Production in Murine Macrophages Blocked by RCM-101</title><p>Unstimulated murine macrophage (Raw 264.7) cells incubated in serum-free RPMI medium for 24 h had a baseline concentration of PGE<sub>2</sub> of 52 &#x000b1; 10 pg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Incubating the cells with LPS (1 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) increased the PGE<sub>2</sub> level to 7442.4 &#x000b1; 766 pg ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<italic>n</italic> = 6). This was reduced in a concentration-dependent manner by RCM-101 extract (10, 100 and 1000 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), when present during incubation with LPS. Indomethacin, present during LPS incubation, in each of the concentrations tested (1, 10 and 100 &#x003bc;M), completely blocked PGE<sub>2</sub> production. The data are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Inhibition of PGE<sub>2</sub> production in LPS-stimulated Raw 264.7 cells by RCM-101 and indomethacin. Data plotted are mean (&#x000b1;SEM) percentage inhibition of control PGE<sub>2</sub> production (<italic>n</italic> = 6 in each case). <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, one-way ANOVA and Dunnet's test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nel083f4"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>RCM-101 Did Not Affect LTB<sub>4</sub> Synthesis in Porcine Neutrophils</title><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, LTB<sub>4</sub> formation in porcine neutrophils was not significantly affected by RCM-101 extract in concentrations of 1, 10 and 100 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. In contrast, NGDA (0.1&#x02013;10 &#x003bc; g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, produced concentration-dependent inhibition of LTB<sub>4</sub> production.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>LTB<sub>4</sub> formation in porcine neutrophils was unaffected by RCM-101 (1, 10 and 100 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Nordihydroguaiaretic acid (NDGA; 0.1, 1 and 10 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) produced concentration-dependent inhibition of LTB<sub>4</sub> formation. Data plotted are means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 8 in each case). <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, one-way ANOVA and Dunnet's test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nel083f5"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of LPS/Interferon-&#x003b3;-Induced NO Production in Murine Macrophages</title><p>The concentration of NO in the culture medium of unstimulated murine macrophage (Raw 264.7) cells was 46.31 &#x000b1; 8.0 nM (<italic>n</italic> = 6). The concentration in the cell culture medium after incubation of RAW 264.6 with LPS and interferon-&#x003b3; was 768.8 &#x000b1; 125.5 nM. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>, RCM-101 extract (10&#x02013;1000 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) reduced the NO level in a concentration-dependent manner.
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Inhibition of LPS/interferon-&#x003b3;-stimulated NO production (determined as the stable metabolite nitrite) in Raw 264.7 cells by RCM-101. Data plotted are mean percentage of control NO production (&#x000b1;SEM; <italic>n</italic> = 6 in each case). <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, one-way ANOVA and Dunnet's test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nel083f6"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In SAR, mast cell-derived mediators, such as histamine, are generally considered to be responsible for the acute allergic symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). These mediators act on the smooth muscle cells of small blood vessels, blood platelets, mucous glands and on sensory nerve endings to produce symptoms such as nasal congestion, nasal and throat itching, sneezing and hypersecretion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>The present study has demonstrated that a Chinese herbal formula RCM-101, which is effective in the symptomatic treatment of SAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>), inhibits the contractile responses of rat and guinea pig tracheal preparations to the mast cell activator, compound 48/80. However, the aqueous extract of RCM-101 did not affect contractile responses of tracheal preparations elicited by exogenous histamine (guinea pig preparations) or serotonin (rat preparations), most likely this indicates that RCM-101 inhibits the release of histamine and serotonin in the respective tracheal preparations. The involvement of histamine and serotonin in compound 48/80-induced responses is evidenced by the findings with specific histamine and serotonin antagonists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). It is noted, however, that although mepyramine and methysergide markedly reduced the effects of compound 48/80 they did not abolish the responses, indicating that mediators other than histamine or serotonin may also be involved. Indeed, given that mast cells contain a variety of inflammatory mediators, in addition to histamine (or serotonin), it is possible that the inhibitory action of RCM-101 on the responses to compound 48/80 may have been due to the blockade of the contractile action of an agent or agents other than histamine (or serotonin).</p><p>Previous studies suggest that prostaglandins and leukotrienes are likely to be involved in the late phase symptoms of SAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). For example, serotonin induces sneezing and rhinorrhea without congestion while leukotrienes and prostaglandins cause congestion without rhinorrhea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Among different leukotrienes, LTB<sub>4</sub> is released during the immediate phase response by infiltrating neutrophils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>).</p><p>PGE<sub>2</sub> has been shown to be involved in both the early and late phases of SAR. In the early phase, PGE<sub>2</sub> is released from mast cells whilst, in the late phase, it is released from basophils and eosinophils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). In the present study, in which production of PGE<sub>2</sub> by murine macrophages was initiated by LPS, RCM-101 inhibited PGE<sub>2</sub> production. The exact mechanism involved in the inhibition was not investigated; however, it may involve modification of cyclooxygenase (COX) activity or of expression of the enzyme. There are two isoforms of COX, and the isoform responsible for the induced PG production is COX-2. Previous studies have shown that the herbs <italic>Rhizome Cimicifugae</italic> and <italic>Radix Glycyrrhizae</italic>, which are constituents of RCM-101, have potent COX<sub>2</sub> inhibitory effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). In addition, <italic>Radix Glycyrrhizae</italic> is known to have anti-inflammatory activity. Both topical and oral administration glycyrrhetinic acid, a constituent of <italic>Radix Glycyrrhizae</italic>, prevent ear edema and to inhibits PGE<sub>2</sub> and LTC<sub>4</sub> formation in mice, induced by arachidonic acid, with approximately the same potency as NDGA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>).</p><p>NO is an important mediator in various inflammatory processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). In SAR, the level of NO in the parasinus is dependent on iNOS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>), and there is evidence that exhaled NO is elevated in subjects with allergic rhinitis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). It has been suggested that increased production of NO in the nasal mucosa may promote vasodilatation and modulate the responsiveness/activity of sensory nerves, leading to nasal congestion, rhinorrhea and sneezing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). The present finding of inhibition by RCM-101 of <sc>l</sc>-arginine-induced vasodilatation in LPS-treated aortic rings indicates that RCM-101 may inhibit iNOS-dependent NO production, since the responses to exogenous NO were not affected by RCM-101. The finding that RCM-101 was without effect on responses of rat aortic preparations when it was introduced after the preparations had been incubated for a prolonged period with LPS (15 min before <sc>l</sc>-arginine), indicates that unlike <sc>l</sc>-NAME (NOS inhibitor), it does not interfere with the action of preformed iNOS. Previous studies in denuded rat aorta have demonstrated induction of NO synthase by LPS, leading to increased production of NO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). The finding that the herbal formula inhibited LPS/interferon-&#x003b3;-induced NO production by murine macrophage cells further supports the suggestion that RCM-101 inhibits iNOS-dependent NO production. Further studies will be necessary to elucidate the exact mechanism involved in inhibition of iNOS-mediated NO production by RCM-101, which may involve modification of existing enzyme activity or altered expression of iNOS protein or its gene.</p><p>The present findings with RCM-101 are consistent with previous studies on some of the individual herbal ingredients of the formula. Naturally occurring furanocoumarins (imperatorin and deltoin), isolated from <italic>Radix Saposhnikoviae</italic>, inhibited iNOS protein expression but not the enzyme itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). Polysaccharides from <italic>Angelica sinensis</italic> have also been shown to reduce the levels of endogenous NO and the expression of iNOS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Luteolin, which is present in <italic>Herba Schizonepetae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>), markedly lowers NO production by reducing iNOS enzyme expression without inhibiting the enzyme activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Polyacetylenes isolated from <italic>Radix Saposhnikoviae</italic> were found to inhibit NO production induced by LPS/interferon-&#x003b3; in macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). In addition, costunolide, found in <italic>Magnolia grandiflora</italic>, reduced NO production by downregulating iNOS mRNA. It also reduced iNOS expression by inhibiting binding of the transcription factor nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-&#x003ba;B). Costunolide was also shown to inhibit phosphorylation of I&#x003ba;B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>), thereby enhancing its inhibitory action on NF-&#x003ba;B. <italic>Radix Glycyrrhizae</italic> increases blood cortisone levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>), which may, in turn, inhibit iNOS gene transcription by decreasing NF-&#x003ba;B activity and inducing I&#x003ba;B-&#x003b1; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Thus, it is likely that multiple ingredients of RCM-101 may be involved in its inhibition of iNOS-dependent NO production. RCM-101 did not inhibit eNOS-dependent relaxations to acetylcholine or direct relaxations to the NO donor, SNP. The inhibition of the iNOS pathway by RCM-101 indicates that it selectively interferes with inflammatory processes in the late phase of SAR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, the results obtained in this study indicate that RCM-101 may have multiple pharmacological actions including inhibition of histamine release from mast cells, inhibition prostaglandin formation and inhibition of inducible NO synthase-mediated NO production/response in target cells. The exact inhibitory mechanisms and which herbal constituents contribute to these effects require further investigation.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge RMIT University for providing a Postgraduate Research Scholarship for G.L.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Willan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determining a minimal important change in a disease-specific quality of life questionnaire</article-title><source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8283197</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crown</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Olufade</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal versus perennial allergic rhinitis: drug and medical resource use patterns</article-title><source>Value Health</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12859586</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignola</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Demoly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Links between rhinitis and asthma</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2003</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12859545</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Cauwenberge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of rhinitis&#x02014;the specialist's opinion</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>1998</year><volume>28</volume><issue>Suppl 6</issue><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9988432</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baraniuk</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis of allergic rhinitis</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>1997</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>S763</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9042069</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Cauwenberge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Watelet</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights in the pathogenesis of allergic rhinitis</article-title><source>Curr Probl Dermatol</source><year>1999</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10374056</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Casale</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nedocromil sodium is rapidly effective in the therapy of seasonal allergic rhinitis</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>1993</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8388007</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castel-Branco</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Double-blind comparison of levocabastine eye drops with sodium cromoglycate and placebo in the treatment of seasonal allergic conjunctivitis</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>1991</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1685691</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagnall</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antihistamines: topical vs oral administration</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>1996</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8735853</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Greiff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammarlund</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedbys</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Malcus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comparison of budesonide nasal dry powder with fluticasone propionate aqueous nasal spray in patients with perennial allergic rhinitis</article-title><source>Rhinology</source><year>1995</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7784789</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>But</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chinese herbal medicine in the treatment of asthma and allergies</article-title><source>Clin Rev Allergy Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8932956</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaphle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbal medicine research in Taiwan</article-title><source>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16550238</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thien</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Costa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment for seasonal allergic rhinitis by Chinese herbal medicine: a randomized placebo controlled trial</article-title><source>Altern Ther Health Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14526714</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Pharmacopoeia of The People's Republic of China.</collab><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chemical Industry Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that part of the NANC relaxant response of guinea-pig trachea to electrical field stimulation is mediated by nitric oxide</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1991</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2043935</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikawati</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The lack of compound 48/80-induced contraction in isolated trachea of mast cell-deficient Ws/Ws rats <italic>in vitro</italic>: the role of connective tissue mast cells</article-title><source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>2000</year><volume>402</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10958897</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Messent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>MacAllister</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoguanidine selectively inhibits inducible nitric oxide synthase</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1993</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7507781</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meachem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Majewski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endothelium removal induces iNOS in rat aorta in organ culture, leading to tissue damage</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>E125</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9886958</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auranofin stimulates LTA hydrolase and inhibits 5-lipoxygenase/LTA synthase activity of isolated human neutrophils</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>1990</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1233</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2157444</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naclerio</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allergic rhinitis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1991</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1875971</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Immunology</source><year>1994</year><edition>2nd edn.</edition><publisher-loc>New York, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>W.H. Freemen and Company</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joos</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauwels</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of 5-hydroxytryptamine and mast cells in the tachykinin-induced contraction of rat trachea in vitro</article-title><source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>1997</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9424020</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignola</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathophysiology of allergic rhinitis</article-title><source>Int Arch Allergy Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8688666</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mygind</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thestrup-Pedersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Essential Allergy</source><year>1996</year><edition>2nd edn.</edition><publisher-loc>Carlton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Blackwell Science</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effects of <italic>Cimicifugae rhizoma</italic> extracts on histamine, bradykinin and COX-2 mediated inflammatory actions</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11113994</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effect of glycyrrhetinic acid derivatives on arachidonic acid-induced mouse ear oedema</article-title><source>J Pharm Pharmacol</source><year>1988</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2900308</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durland</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Durland</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Prazma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide is a mediator of the late-phase response in an animal model of nasal allergy</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>706</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10793351</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yajin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased expression of inducible nitric oxide synthase in nasal epithelial cells in patients with allergic rhinitis</article-title><source>Laryngoscope</source><year>1999</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>2015</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10591366</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Basclain</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Peroni</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garlepp</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression and localization of the inducible isoform of nitric oxide synthase in nasal polyp epithelium</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>1998</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9515595</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnal</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Didier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rami</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>M'Rini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlet</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nasal nitric oxide is increased in allergic rhinitis</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>1997</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9146927</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kharitonov</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajakulasingam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Durham</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nasal nitric oxide is increased in patients with asthma and allergic rhinitis and may be modulated by nasal glucocorticoids</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>1997</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9003212</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryden</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Devoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased levels of exhaled nitric oxide during nasal and oral breathing in subjects with seasonal rhinitis</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>768</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8613633</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnal</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rami</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murris-Espin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasto</surname><given-names>IAM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nasal nitric oxide concentration in paranasal sinus inflammatory diseases</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10065673</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moritoki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hisayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondoh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaishi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition by triptoquinone-A of LPS and IL-1 beta-primed induction of NO synthase in rat thoracic aorta</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>L49</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inducible nitric oxide synthase inhibitor of the Chinese herb I. <italic>Saposhnikovia divaricata</italic> (<italic>Turcz</italic>.) <italic>Schischk</italic></article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>1999</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10530783</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Modulation of <italic>Angelica sinensis</italic> polysaccharides on the expression of nitric oxide synthase and Bax, Bcl-2 in liver of immunological liver-injured mice]</article-title><source>Zhonghua Gan Zang Bing Za Zhi</source><year>2001</year><volume>9</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11509139</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>Traditional Chinese Medicine: Molecular Structures, Natural Sources and Application</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>Hampshire, England</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheon</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of naturally occurring flavonoids on nitric oxide production in the macrophage cell line RAW 264.7 and their structure-activity relationships</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>1999</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10449184</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A sesquiterpene lactone, costunolide, from <italic>Magnolia grandiflora</italic> inhibits NF-kappa B by targeting I kappa B phosphorylation</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11301852</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kase</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishige</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between the antidiarrhoeal effects of Hange-Shashin-To and its active components</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10479755</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakishita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Banba</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dexamethasone suppresses iNOS gene expression by inhibiting NF-kappaB in vascular smooth muscle cells</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>2001</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11508649</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>






