<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17376805</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1874645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm052</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Methods Online</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chemical modification of Ce(IV)/EDTA-based artificial restriction DNA cutter for versatile manipulation of double-stranded DNA</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Yoji</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>Masao</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aiba</surname><given-names>Yuichiro</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>Takafumi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Wen</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Jing-Min</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uehara</surname><given-names>Akihiko</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>Yoshihito</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>Makoto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Research Center for Advanced Science and Technology, The University of Tokyo, 4-6-1 Komaba, Meguro-ku, Tokyo 153-8904, Japan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+81&#x02009;3&#x02009;5452&#x02009;5200</phone><fax>+81&#x02009;3&#x02009;5452&#x02009;5209</fax><email>komiyama@mkomi.rcast.u-tokya.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e53</fpage><lpage>e53</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A monophosphate group was attached to the terminus of pseudo-complementary peptide nucleic acid (pcPNA), and two of thus modified pcPNAs were combined with Ce(IV)/EDTA for site-selective hydrolysis of double-stranded DNA. The site-selective DNA scission was notably accelerated by this chemical modification of pcPNAs. These second-generation artificial restriction DNA cutters (ARCUTs) differentiated the target sequence so strictly that no scission occurred even when only one DNA base-pair was altered to another. By using two of the activated ARCUTs simultaneously, DNA substrate was selectively cut at two predetermined sites, and the desired fragment was clipped and cloned. The DNA scission by ARCUT was also successful even when the target site was methylated by methyltransferase and protected from the corresponding restriction enzyme. Furthermore, potentiality of ARCUT for manipulation of huge DNA has been substantiated by site-selective scission of genomic DNA of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (composed of 4,600,000&#x02009;bp) at the target site. All these results indicate promising applications of ARCUTs for versatile purposes.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Preparation of artificial restriction enzymes has been attracting significant interests of chemists and biochemists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3 B4 B5 B6 B7 B8 B9 B10 B11">1&#x02013;11</xref>). One of the promising applications of these tools is to manipulate genomic DNAs which are too huge to treat with naturally occurring restriction enzymes. Progress in this field has been remarkable and several man-made tools for site-selective scission of single-stranded DNA were already prepared (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12 B13 B14">12&#x02013;14</xref>). Double-stranded DNA was cut by (i) conjugation of DNA binders with restriction enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), (ii) use of metal complexes of sequence-recognizing proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>), and (iii) protection of target site from methylation followed by restriction enzyme digestion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19 B20 B21 B22">19&#x02013;22</xref>). However, there have been few feasible tools to hydrolyze DNA site selectively at desired site.</p><p>Recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>), we combined Ce(IV)/EDTA complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24 B25 B26">24&#x02013;26</xref>) (molecular scissors for hydrolysis of phosphodiester linkages in single-stranded DNA) with two pseudo-complmentary peptide nucleic acid (pcPNA) additives (site-selective DNA activators), and hydrolyzed double-stranded DNA at the target site. In pcPNAs, thymine and adenine in conventional peptide nucleic acids (PNAs) (with poly[<italic>N</italic>-(aminoethyl)glycine] backbone) are replaced with pseudo-complementary bases 2-thiouracil (U) and 2,6-diaminopurine (D), respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Accordingly, their invasion into double-stranded DNA is facilitated by the following two factors: (i) destabilization of pcPNA/pcPNA duplex by steric repulsion between 2-S atom of U and 2-NH<sub>2</sub> of D, and (ii) stabilization of pcPNA/DNA duplex by three hydrogen bonds between D and T. In the Ce(IV)/EDTA-based DNA cutters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>), predetermined sites in both DNA strands are kept single-stranded through invasion of two pcPNAs of appropriate sequences (see the top of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>a). These single-stranded portions are &#x02018;hot spots&#x02019; for the scission by Ce(IV)/EDTA and selectively cleaved. Both the scission-site and scission-specificity can be easily altered according to our needs, since the lengths and sequences of pcPNA additives are freely chosen. Furthermore, completely hydrolytic character of the scission was confirmed by ligation of the scission fragments with foreign DNA to recombinant DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Promotion of site-selective scission of double-stranded DNA through attachment of monophosphate groups to N-termini of pcPNA additives. The Ce(IV)/EDTA complex is accumulated near the target site through electrostatic interactions. (<bold>b</bold>) Sequences of the pcPNAs and the DNA around the target site 1. The P, U and D in PNA1-P and PNA2-P represent L-phosphoserine, 2-thiouracil, and 2,6-diaminopurine, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Through invasion of these pcPNAs, three nucleotides in both strands are kept unpaired, and the monophosphate groups on the pcPNAs are placed near these sites. (<bold>c</bold>) Gel-shift assay for the formation of invasion complexes of pcPNAs with or without the terminal monophosphate groups. Lane 1, 130-mer double-stranded DNA; lane 2, with PNA1/PNA2; lane 3, with PNA1-P/PNA2-P; lane 4, with PNA3/PNA4; lane 5, with PNA3-P/PNA4-P. Invasion conditions: [130-mer double-stranded DNA] = 50&#x02009;nM, [each of pcPNAs] = 300&#x02009;nM, and [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0 and 50&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h. The 130-mer double-stranded DNA used in (c) has the same sequence as T1776-G1905 of the 4361-mer DNA in (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm052f1"/></fig></p><p>Here we show that the scission efficiency of ARCUTs is further promoted by attaching monophosphate groups (or iminodiacetate groups) to the termini of pcPNA additives and placing them near the target scission-sites (the bottom of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>a). As a result, these modified ARCUTs are applicable for still more versatile purposes. For example, DNA substrate is cut at two predetermined sites and the desired fragment is clipped. Furthermore, it has been confirmed that the site-selective scission occurs only when both strands of DNA and two pcPNA additives are completely complementary with each other, and thus alteration of even one DNA base-pair to another totally inhibits the scission. Significant features of ARCUTs are further evidenced by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) site-selective scission of genomic DNA of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (4.6&#x02009;Mb) and (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) site-selective scission of enzymatically methylated DNA, both of which are hardly achievable by naturally occurring restriction enzymes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Materials</title><p>For the preparation of the pcPNA additives, Boc-protected monomers of 2-thiouracil and 2,6-diaminopurine [synthesized according to the literatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>)] were used together with commercially available Boc-protected monomers and (4-methylbenzhydryl)amine resin (both from ABI) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). In order to introduce <sc>l</sc>-phosphoserine to N-terminus, <italic>N</italic>-Fmoc-<italic>O</italic>-benzyl-<sc>l</sc>-phosphoserine (from Novabiochem) was attached after the final deprotection of Boc group of pcPNA. Fmoc groups were removed by 20% piperidine/<italic>N</italic>-methyl-2-pyrrolidinone for 15&#x02009;min, and the resultant phosphate-modified pcPNA was removed from the resin by &#x02018;low&#x02013;high TFMSA method&#x02019;. In order to introduce iminodiacetate groups to N-terminus or C-terminus, appropriately protected monomers (synthesized according to the Supplementary Scheme) were used. All these pcPNAs were purified by reversed-phase HPLC and characterized by MALDI-TOFMS (Bruker, AutoFLEX).</p><p>The substrate DNA for the site-selective scission was prepared by linearizing pBR322 plasmid DNA with EcoRI (both from Takara). To introduce a mismatched site into this DNA substrate, mutated double-stranded DNA was amplified from pBR322 by overlapping PCR using mutated primers. The resultant DNA was inserted into the corresponding site of pBR322 by a conventional method using restriction enzymes and a ligase. After cloning in JM109, the plasmid was purified by QIAprep Spin Miniprep Kit (from Qiagen) and digested with EcoRI to convert form I into form III. The 130-mer double-stranded DNA having the same sequence as T1776-G1905 of the 4361-mer DNA was prepared by PCR using the following two primers; 5&#x02032;-FAM-TACCGCCAGTTGTTTACCCT-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CGTGTAAGGGGGATTTCTGT-3&#x02032;, and purified by QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (from Qiagen). DNA oligomers were prepared on an ABI 394 DNA/RNA synthesizer using the phosphoroamidite monomers (from Glen Research), purified by reversed-phase HPLC and characterized by MALDI-TOFMS. The Ce(IV)/EDTA complex was prepared by mixing 20&#x02009;mM solution of Ce(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub> (from Nacalai Tesque) in water and 20&#x02009;mM EDTA&#x000b7;&#x02009;4Na (from Tokyo Kasei Kogyo) in HEPES buffer, and then the pH was adjusted to 7.0 with small amounts of NaOH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Site-selective scission of double-stranded 4361-mer DNA by the second-generation ARCUT</title><p>At pH 7.0 (5&#x02009;mM HEPES buffer without addition of NaCl), double-stranded 4361-mer DNA (linearized pBR322) was incubated with a combination of two pcPNAs at 50&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h. Then, NaCl was added to a final concentration of 100&#x02009;mM. The DNA hydrolysis was started by adding aqueous solution of Ce(IV)/EDTA. Typical cleavage conditions: [4361-mer DNA] = 8&#x02009;nM, [each of pcPNAs] = 200&#x02009;nM, [Ce(IV)/EDTA] = 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;M, [NaCl] = 100&#x02009;mM, and [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0. After a predetermined reaction time, ethylenediaminetetramethylenephosphonic acid (aqueous solution adjusted to pH 7.0) was added to a final concentration of 500&#x02009;&#x000b5;M to stop the reaction. The mixture was further incubated for 1&#x02009;h at 50&#x000b0;C, and then subjected to 0.8% agarose gel electrophoresis. The bands were detected by staining with GelStar (from Cambrex), and quantified by assuming that the band intensity is proportional to the length of fragment.</p></sec><sec><title>Double digestion of DNA for clipping of desired fragment and its characterization</title><p>By using four pcPNA additives simultaneously, substrate DNA was cut at two sites and the fragment was purified by agarose gel electrophoresis. The cloning vector was prepared by treating pUC18 with HindIII, BamHI, and then calf intestinal alkaline phosphatase (all from Takara). Two ligation joints (5&#x02032;-pAGCTATCATCAGTAACCC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-pGATCACTCAAGACGATAG-3&#x02032;) were attached to the ends of linearized pUC18 vector by DNA Ligation Kit (from Takara), and the termini of the vector were made complementary with the termini of the fragment clipped by the ARCUT. Then the double-digested fragment was ligated with the vector, and transfected into JM109 and cultured on LB-agar media. Colonies containing the recombinant plasmid were picked up by colony PCR, and cultured in 2&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;YT media. The plasmid DNA was purified with QIAprep Spin Miniprep Kit, and its sequence was determined on an ABI PRISM 310 Genetic Analyzer. The sequencing results showed that the corresponding scission fragment was selectively combined with the modified vector (see the Results and Discussion section for details). Although the scission was not restricted to one phosphodiester linkage for each strand, the desired fragment was picked up in the ligation step, as shown in ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Site-selective scission of genomic DNA of <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>Using Genomic-tip 100/G (from Qiagen), <italic>E. coli</italic> genomic DNA was prepared from K12 strain (MG1655), and was dissolved in 1&#x02009;mM Tris buffer (pH 8.5). This stock solution of genomic DNA was diluted with 5&#x02009;mM HEPES buffer containing 10&#x02009;mM NaCl. The invasion complex was formed by incubating the mixture at 50&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;h in the presence of pcPNA additives. NaCl was added to a final concentration of 100&#x02009;mM, and then the DNA hydrolysis was started by the addition of Ce(IV)/EDTA. Cleavage conditions: [<italic>E. coli</italic> genomic DNA] = 20&#x02009;ng/&#x003bc;l, [Ce(IV)/EDTA] = 0&#x02013;40&#x02009;&#x003bc;M, [each of pcPNAs] = 400&#x02009;nM, [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM, [Tris] = 0.5&#x02009;mM, [NaCl] = 100&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0 and 37&#x000b0;C for 64&#x02009;h. After stopping the reaction with ethylenediaminetetramethylenephosphonic acid, the product was treated with PstI in the presence of buffer M (both from Takara) at 37&#x000b0;C for 4&#x02009;h.</p><p>Digoxigenin-labeled probe was prepared by using PCR DIG Probe Synthesis Kit (from Roche) from <italic>E. coli</italic> genomic DNA. Southern blotting and hybridization were performed according to the recommended protocol, and the probe on the membrane was detected with anti-digoxigenin-AP and AttoPhos Substrate Set (both from Roche).</p></sec><sec><title>Gel-shift assay for the formation of invasion complex</title><p>Invasion complex composed of the FAM-labeled 130-mer double-stranded DNA (T1776-G1905 in the 4361-mer DNA) and pcPNA additives was prepared as described above. Invasion conditions: [130-mer double-stranded DNA] = 50&#x02009;nM, [each of pcPNAs] = 300&#x02009;nM, and [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0 and 50&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h. Loading buffer containing bromophenol blue (0.05%) and glycerol (30%) in 0.5&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;TBE buffer was added, and the mixture was subjected to 10% non-denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE). The bands were detected by staining with GelStar.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>Invasion complex formation of pcPNA additives bearing terminal monophosphates</title><p>In order to facilitate the gel-shift assay, a 130-mer double-stranded DNA having exactly the same sequence as T1776-G1905 of the 4361-mer DNA substrate was used. The invasion site exists almost in the middle of this DNA. An <sc>l</sc>-phosphoserine was attached to the N-terminus of pcPNA, and two of these modified pcPNAs were incubated with the DNA. One of the pcPNA additives (PNA1-P) is complementary with C1823-C1835 of the upper strand of the DNA, and has a monophosphate on its N-terminal serine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>b). Another additive PNA2-P is complementary with G1826-C1838 of the lower strand, and also has a monophosphate at the N-terminus. As clearly evidenced by the gel-shift assay in lane 3 of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>c, these two modified pcPNA additives efficiently invaded the DNA in spite of the additional negative charges on the monophosphates. Invasion was nearly completed under the conditions employed. In this invasion complex, three nucleotides in both strands of the DNA (C1836-G1838 of the upper strand and G1823-A1825 of the lower strand) remained unpaired and the monophosphate groups on the pcPNAs were placed at the edges of these single-stranded portions. These single-stranded portions are highly susceptible to the hydrolysis by Ce(IV)/EDTA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). The PNA3-P/PNA4-P combination also invaded the double-stranded DNA almost completely (lane 5 of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>c). The two monophosphates on the pcPNAs were placed at the edges of the single-stranded portions composed of unpaired five nucleotides.</p></sec><sec><title>Terminal monophosphates on the pcPNA additives for the promotion of site-selective scission of double-stranded DNA</title><p>The invasion complex of the substrate 4361-mer DNA (prepared by cutting pBR322 with EcoRI) with PNA1-P/PNA2-P was treated with Ce(IV)/EDTA at pH 7.0 and 50&#x000b0;C for 17&#x02009;h. The result of agarose gel electrophoresis (stained with GelStar) is presented in lane 3 of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>a. Only two scission bands were observed at around 1800 and 2500&#x02009;bp, exactly as expected from the site-selective scission by this ARCUT (1830 and 2530&#x02009;bp fragments should be formed). The yield for each of the two scission-fragments was 35% under the conditions employed. It is noteworthy that this scission was much faster than that in lane 4 where unmodified pcPNAs were used (the yields of the fragments by PNA1/PNA2 combination were less than 13%). Notable promotion by the two terminal monophosphates on the pcPNA additives is clearly evidenced. When there existed five unpaired nucleotides at the target site and pcPNA additives had the terminal monophosphates (PNA3-P/PNA4-P), the scission was still faster and the yields of scission fragments were 43% (lane 3 of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>b). The site-selective scission at all other DNA sequences investigated was also accelerated by phosphate modification of pcPNA additives (see Supplementary Figure 1). These promotions of scission efficiencies are crucially important for various applications, and the advantages are especially explicit when substrate DNA is cut at two sites to clip a desired fragment (<italic>vide infra</italic>).
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Site-selective hydrolysis of the double-stranded 4361-mer DNA using monophosphate-bearing pcPNA additives: (<bold>a</bold>) three unpaired nucleotides and (<bold>b</bold>) five unpaired nucleotides for each strand of the substrate DNA. Lane 1, without PNA and Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 2, Ce(IV)/EDTA only; lane 3, PNA1-P/PNA2-P (or PNA3-P/PNA4-P in (b)) + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 4, PNA1/PNA2 (or PNA3/PNA4) + Ce(IV)/EDTA; M, 1000&#x02009;bp ladder. Reaction conditions: [4361-mer DNA (linearized pBR322)] = 8&#x02009;nM, [each of pcPNAs] = 200&#x02009;nM, [Ce(IV)/EDTA] = 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;M, [NaCl] = 100&#x02009;mM, and [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0 and 50&#x000b0;C for 17&#x02009;h.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm052f2"/></fig></p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, the lengths of single-stranded DNA portions in the invasion complex were systematically changed. In all the cases, the promotion by the terminal monophosphates of pcPNA additives was evident (compare lanes 3 versus 4, 5 versus 6, 7 versus 8 and 9 versus 10, respectively). The magnitude of promotion by the monophosphates increased as the number of unpaired nucleotides at the target site decreased. Thus, the second-generation ARCUT showed notable site-selective scission in lane 7 where only one nucleotide (for each strand) remained unpaired at the target site. The site-selective scission was also successful even when there existed no unpaired nucleotide at the target site (lane 9). In either case, however, the corresponding first-generation ARCUT was almost completely inactive (lanes 8 and 10). In the first-generation ARCUT, the DNA scission requires rather long single-stranded portions, since otherwise steric repulsion by either the nucleobases or the main-chains of DNA and pcPNA is dominant. In the second-generation ARCUT, however, these factors are satisfactorily compensated by the accumulation of the Ce(IV) complex by the monophosphates at the target site.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Sequences of pcPNA additives used to investigate the effect of length of single-stranded portions in DNA substrate. By the PNA3/PNA4, PNA1/PNA2, PNA5/PNA6, and PNA7/PNA8 combinations, five, three, one and zero nucleotides in the DNA are kept unpaired, respectively. (<bold>b</bold>) Effect of the length of unpaired portions on the promotion by monophosphate groups. Lane 1, without PNA and Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 2, Ce(IV)/EDTA only; lane 3, PNA3-P/PNA4-P + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 4, PNA3/PNA4 + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 5, PNA1-P/PNA2-P + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 6, PNA1/PNA2 + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 7, PNA5-P/PNA6-P + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 8, PNA5/PNA6 + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 9, PNA7-P/PNA8-P + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 10, PNA7/PNA8 + Ce(IV)/EDTA; M, 1000&#x02009;bp ladder. Reaction conditions: [4361-mer DNA] = 8&#x02009;nM, [each of pcPNAs] = 200&#x02009;nM, [Ce(IV)/EDTA] = 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;M, [NaCl] = 100&#x02009;mM, and [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0 and 50&#x000b0;C for 17&#x02009;h. All the pairs of pcPNAs satisfactorily invaded the substrate DNA, as was completely substantiated by the gel-shift assay (data not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm052f3"/></fig></p><p>Absolute necessity of the phosphate modification of pcPNA additives for the efficient DNA scission is further evidenced by the following results. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) With the use of non-phosphorylated pcPNAs, sufficiently high scission efficiency was never achieved even when these additives were employed at high concentrations. The efficiency obtained when [PNA1] = [PNA2] = 500&#x02009;nM, for example, was almost the same as the value at [PNAs] = 200&#x02009;nM (in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>a). (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) The scission efficiency with non-phosphorylated pcPNAs was not improved even when these additives were incubated with the DNA for a prolonged time (e.g. 6&#x02009;h) in the invasion process (in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, the incubation time was 1&#x02009;h). (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>) The conversion of DNA scission by Ce(IV)/EDTA with non-phosphorylated pcPNAs (PNA1/PNA2) was only 15% when the reaction time was prolonged to 27&#x02009;h (with the use of phosphorylated pcPNAs, much higher conversions were accomplished at the reaction time 17&#x02009;h, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>a). Apparently, the phosphate groups directly accelerate the scission of phosphodiester linkages, rather than they promote the invasion process.</p></sec><sec><title>Recognition of mismatch for the site-selective DNA scission</title><p>The C&#x02013;G pair at 1829 of the linearized pBR322 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>b) was systematically changed to another base-pair, and the mutant DNAs were treated with Ce(IV)/EDTA in the presence of PNA3-P/PNA4-P combination. When this C&#x02013;G pair was exchanged with an A&#x02013;T pair, the DNA was never cleaved by the ARCUT (Supplementary Figure 2). Other mismatched DNA substrates involving 1-bp alteration were also never hydrolyzed. The change of only 1-bp was strictly recognized by the ARCUT. These results indicate that only the target site can be selectively cut by an ARCUT, even when substrate DNA is huge and there exist many similar sequences therein.</p></sec><sec><title>Clipping of desired fragments by using two of the second-generation ARCUTs</title><p>Clipping of a desired fragment from huge DNA is crucially important in molecular biology and biotechnology. In order to obtain the fragment in reasonable yield, substrate DNA must be cut at two predetermined sites with sufficiently high conversions. The present second-generation ARCUT is active enough to fulfill this requirement. In the following example, 1010-mer DNA was clipped in situ (not in a stepwise manner) from the 4361-mer double-stranded DNA (2840 &#x02212; 1830 = 1010). In the presence of two pairs of pcPNA additives (PNA3-P/PNA4-P in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>b and PNA9-P/PNA10-P in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>a), the 4361-mer DNA was treated with Ce(IV)/EDTA. The former pcPNA combination promotes the scission at around 1830&#x02009;bp (the target site 1) as described above, whereas the selective scission with the PNA9-P/PNA10-P combination occurs at around 2840&#x02009;bp (the target site 2).
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Sequences of pcPNA additives used for the double digestion of 4361-mer DNA (linearized pBR322) by second-generation ARCUT. By combining PNA9-P/PNA10-P (or PNA9/PNA10) with Ce(IV)/EDTA, the site 2 around 2840&#x02009;bp is hydrolyzed. Accordingly, 1010&#x02009;bp fragment should be obtained when this ARCUT is used simultaneously with the other ARCUT (PNA3-P/PNA4-P or PNA3/PNA4). (<bold>b</bold>) Gel-electrophoresis patterns for the double digestion. Lane 1, without PNA and Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 2, Ce(IV)/EDTA only; lane 3, PNA3/PNA4/PNA9/PNA10 + Ce(IV)&#x02013;EDTA; lane 4, PNA3-P/PNA4-P/PNA9-P/PNA10-P + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 5, PNA3/PNA4/PNA9-P/PNA10-P + Ce(IV)/EDTA; lane 6, PNA3-P/PNA4-P/PNA9/PNA10 + Ce(IV)/EDTA; M, 1000&#x02009;bp ladder. Reaction conditions: [4361-mer DNA] = 8&#x02009;nM, [each of pcPNAs] = 200&#x02009;nM, [Ce(IV)/EDTA] = 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;M, [NaCl] = 100&#x02009;mM, and [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0 and 45&#x000b0;C for 40&#x02009;h.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm052f4"/></fig></p><p>The electrophoresis patterns for the clipping experiments are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>b. By combining these two pairs of chemically modified pcPNA additives, the scissions at the two sites were satisfactorily efficient and the desired fragment was obtained in 10% yield (the bottom band in lane 4). This fragment was cloned and its sequence was completely characterized, as described in the Materials and methods section. When two combinations of unmodified pcPNAs (PNA3/PNA4 and PNA9/PNA10) were used, however, the corresponding band was too weak because of low scission efficiencies at both of the target sites, and the clipping was unsuccessful (lane 3). It is concluded that the monophosphate groups on the pcPNA additives are absolutely necessary for the efficient clipping of the desired fragment. Other scission bands in lanes 3 and 4 (around 2800, 2500, 1800 and 1500&#x02009;bp) came from the scission of the 4361-mer DNA at either one of the two target sites. As expected, all the bands in lane 4 were stronger than the corresponding bands in lane 3. Consistently, when either of the two ARCUTs was first-generation and the other was second-generation (lanes 5 and 6), the scission was efficient only at the site of the second-generation ARCUT and the clipping was unsatisfactory.</p></sec><sec><title>Attachment of other negatively charged groups to pcPNA additives for promotion of the site-selective DNA hydrolysis</title><p>Two iminodiacetate groups were bound to the N-terminus of each of PNA3 and PNA4, and these pcPNAs were combined with Ce(IV)/EDTA. The 4361-mer DNA was selectively and efficiently hydrolyzed at the target site, and the scission efficiency was comparable with that obtained with the use of two pcPNAs bearing a monophosphate (see Supplementary Figure 3). Attachment of iminodiacetate groups to the C-terminus of pcPNA was also effective (Supplementary Figure 4).</p><p>Still more negative charges were placed at the target site by introducing two iminodiacetate groups to both the N-termini and the C-termini of PNA3 and PNA4 (four iminodiacetate groups for each additive). However, the site-selective scission by Ce(IV)/EDTA was inefficient (data not shown). According to gel-shift assay, these additives only poorly invaded the double-stranded DNA. Many negative charges on the additives repel the negative charges of the DNA substrate. Consistently, the DNA scission was hardly promoted when two EDTA groups were introduced to the N-terminus of each of the pcPNAs. The invasion of two pcPNA additives is essential for the present site-selective DNA scission.</p></sec><sec><title>Site-selective hydrolysis of methylated target-site by ARCUT</title><p>Some of the naturally occurring restriction enzymes cannot digest DNA when the DNA nucleobases at the scission sites are methylated by methyltransferase. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>, the effects of this methylation on the ARCUT reactions are investigated. The two cytosine groups in BamHI site of pET28b (GGATC*C/CC*TAGG) were first methylated by BamHI methyltransferase, and the methylated plasmid was then treated with ARCUT. These pcPNA additives (PNA11 and PNA12 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>a) were designed so that the target scission site involves the BamHI site. The methylated plasmid was promptly converted to its linearized form III (lane 3 of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>b). Upon further digestion of the product with EcoRV, two bands were formed as indicated by the arrows (lane 5). Their sizes are consistent with the double digestion at the methylated site by the ARCUT and then by EcoRV (1380 and 3990&#x02009;bp). The efficiency of the ARCUT scission was almost the same as that for the scission of non-methylated DNA (compare lane 2 with lane 3, and lane 4 with lane 5). Site-selective scission of plasmid DNA by ARCUTs was also notably promoted by introducing monophosphate groups to the pcPNA additives, and the magnitudes of acceleration were similar to those observed for the scission of non-supercoiled 4361-mer DNA (data not shown).
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Sequences of pcPNA additives used for the scission of the methylated site. In the invasion complex formed with PNA11 and PNA12, five nucleotides are kept unpaired, and BamHI site (GGATCC/CCTAGG) is located therein. (<bold>b</bold>) Site-selective scission of the BamHI-methylated site by ARCUT. Lane 1, BamHI-methylated plasmid without ARCUT treatment; lane 2, ARCUT treatment of non-methylated plasmid; lane 3, ARCUT treatment of BamHI-methylated plasmid; lane 4, ARCUT and EcoRV treatments of non-methylated plasmid; lane 5, ARCUT and EcoRV treatments of BamHI-methylated plasmid; lane 6, BamHI and EcoRV treatments of non-methylated plasmid; lane 7, BamHI and EcoRV treatments of BamHI-methylated plasmid. The products of double digestion by ARCUT/EcoRV are designated by the arrows. The form II DNA was formed by the scission of only one DNA strand by the ARCUT. Conditions for the ARCUT reactions: [pET28b] = 5&#x02009;nM, [each of pcPNAs] = 50&#x02009;nM, [Ce(IV)/EDTA] = 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;M, [NaCl] = 100&#x02009;mM, and [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0 and 45&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;h.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm052f5"/></fig></p><p>When the methylated DNA was treated with BamHI and then with EcoRV, however, only the form III DNA was produced (lane 7). As already reported by many workers, BamHI hardly digested the methylated DNA (data not shown). The double digestion occurred only when the substrate was not methylated (lane 6). In the ARCUT reactions, the methylation does not affect much the Watson&#x02013;Crick hydrogen bondings between the DNA and the pcPNA additives, and thus the invasion complex is successfully formed even with the methylated DNA. Thus, the hydrolysis of the phosphodiester linkages by Ce(IV)/EDTA is little affected by the methylation of cytosine.</p></sec><sec><title>Site-selective scission of genomic DNA (4.6&#x02009;Mb) using ARCUT</title><p>One of the most important features of ARCUT is the potentiality for site-selective hydrolysis of huge DNA. In order to confirm this argument, genomic DNA of <italic>E. coli</italic> was cut at the predetermined site in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>. This DNA is composed of 4.6&#x02009;Mb and about 1000 times as large as plasmid DNA. Naturally occurring restriction enzymes are not very useful for its manipulation, since their scission sites should appear too often in this large DNA. For widely employed restriction enzymes recognizing a 6-base sequence, for example, the scission sites should appear at every 4<sup>6</sup> (=4096) bps according to statistical calculation.
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Site-selective scission of genomic DNA of <italic>E. coli</italic> (4.6 Mb) by ARCUT. As shown in (<bold>a</bold>), the downstream of <italic>dam</italic>, which is located around 3.5&#x02009;Mb, was targeted by the ARCUT. In (<bold>b</bold>), the genomic DNA was treated with the ARCUT and then with PstI, and the product was subjected to Southern blotting and hybridization by digoxigenin-labeled probe corresponding to <italic>dam</italic>. Conditions for the ARCUT treatment: [<italic>E. coli</italic> genomic DNA] = 20&#x02009;ng/&#x003bc;l, [Ce(IV)/EDTA] = 0&#x02013;40&#x02009;&#x003bc;M, [each of pcPNAs] = 400&#x02009;nM, [HEPES] = 5&#x02009;mM, [Tris] = 0.5&#x02009;mM and [NaCl] = 100&#x02009;mM at pH 7.0 and 37&#x000b0;C for 64&#x02009;h.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm052f6"/></fig></p><p>As presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>a, downstream of <italic>dam</italic> (a gene coding DNA adenine methyltransferase) was chosen as the target site for the ARCUT scission (the choice of this site is arbitrary). The genomic DNA of <italic>E. coli</italic> was first incubated with Ce(IV)/EDTA in the presence of both PNA13 and PNA14. Then, the product was further treated with a restriction enzyme PstI to cut the DNA at the PstI site in the upstream of <italic>dam</italic> and prepare an easily analyzable fragment. The resultant product was subjected to agarose gel electrophoresis, and detected by Southern blotting and hybridization with digoxigenin-labeled probe corresponding to <italic>dam</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>b). As shown in lanes 2&#x02013;4, a new band was clearly observed at the size 4.0&#x02009;kb, which is consistent with the ARCUT/PstI double digestion of the genomic DNA (the length of this DNA was confirmed by using digoxigenin-labeled lambda/HindIII marker). Consistently, this 4.0&#x02009;kb fragment was not formed in the absence of Ce(IV)/EDTA (lane 1) and its amount increased with increasing concentration of Ce(IV)/EDTA (lane 4 &#x0003e; lane 3 &#x0003e; lane 2). When the genomic DNA was directly treated with PstI (without the foregoing ARCUT treatment), however, only one fragment of much larger size was detected (the band near the top of the gel). This fragment was formed by the PstI scission at both the upstream and downstream side of the dam (the latter PstI site is located at &#x0223c;20&#x02009;kb downstream of <italic>dam</italic> as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>a). The site-selective scission of genomic DNA by the ARCUT at the target site has been confirmed.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>By attaching either monophosphate or iminodiacetate groups to N-termini of pcPNA additives, second-generation artificial restriction DNA cutters (ARCUTs) have been developed. These groups on the additives are placed near the target site to accumulate the Ce(IV)/EDTA thereto and promote the scission efficiency. These arguments are consistent with the previous findings that selective scission of single-stranded DNA at gap-sites by Ce(IV)/EDTA was promoted by attaching these groups to oligonucleotide additives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The promotion of scission efficiency by the chemical modification of pcPNAs is crucial for various applications. For example, the desired fragment is clipped from substrate DNA by using two of these second-generation ARCUTs simultaneously (without the modification, the clipping is unsuccessful). Furthermore, the scission by ARCUTs is achievable even at enzymatically methylated sites.</p><p>One of the most significant advantages of ARCUTs is the free tunability of its scission-site and site-specificity. For example, the ARCUT in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>a recognizes 16-base DNA sequence (two 13-mer pcPNAs are shifting each other by 3 bases). Statistically, this scission site appears only once in every 4<sup>16</sup>-base sequence which is longer than the whole genome of human beings (4<sup>16</sup> &#x0003e; 3&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>). Furthermore, DNA scission by ARCUTs occurs only when both strands of this DNA and both of the pcPNA additives are completely complementary with each other (see Supplementary Figure 2). Even when only 1bp in the DNA is converted to another, the scission by ARCUT never occurs. This remarkable sequence differentiation is critical for site-selective scission of huge DNA, since many similar sequences should appear in various parts of this DNA. All these properties of ARCUTs presented here indicate promising applications in the cloning of genomic DNA, DNA shuttling from cloning vector to destination vector, and others.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data is availabale at NAR online.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We would like to thank National BioResource Project <italic>E. coli</italic> of National Institute of Genetics (Japan) for a kind gift of <italic>E. coli</italic> K12 strain. This work was supported by a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT), Japan. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charge was also provided by MEXT.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumaoka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress towards synthetic enzymes for phosphoester hydrolysis</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9914189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hegg</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Burstyn</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toward the development of metal-based synthetic nucleases and peptidases: a rationale and progress report in applying the principles of coordination chemistry</article-title><source>Coord. Chem. Rev</source><year>1998</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>165</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blasko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruice</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent studies of nucleophilic, general-acid, and metal ion catalysis of phosphate diester hydrolysis</article-title><source>Acc. Chem. Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>484</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Takasaki</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and nuclease activity of simple dinuclear metal complexes: quantitative dissection of the role of metal ions</article-title><source>Acc. Chem. Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>493</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000e4;mer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA hydrolysis by inorganic catalysts</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol</source><year>1999</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>767</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bashkin</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrolysis of phosphates, esters and related substrates by models of biological catalysts</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10600728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sreedhara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalytic hydrolysis of DNA by metal ions and complexes</article-title><source>J. Biol. Inorg. Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11372193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lanthanide-mediated DNA hydrolysis</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11282348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthetic artificial peptidases and nucleases using macromolecular catalytic systems</article-title><source>Acc. Chem. Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12859217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA hydrolysis promoted by di- and multi-nuclear metal complexes</article-title><source>Coord. Chem. Rev</source><year>2004</year><volume>248</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>168</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mancin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scrimin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tecilla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonellato</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial metallonucleases</article-title><source>Chem. Commun</source><year>2005</year><fpage>2540</fpage><lpage>2548</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cerium(IV)-oligoDNA hybrid as highly selective artificial nuclease</article-title><source>Supramol. Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumaoka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-selective DNA hydrolysis by combining Ce(IV)/EDTA with monophosphate-bearing oligonucleotides and enzymatic ligation of the scission fragments</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>10285</fpage><lpage>10291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15315441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelder</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokhir</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000e4;mer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence selective hydrolysis of linear DNA using conjugates of Zr(IV) complexes and peptide nucleic acids</article-title><source>Inorg. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>8618</fpage><lpage>8620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14686836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasegaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hybrid restriction enzymes: Zinc finger fusions to Fok I cleavage domain</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1156</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8577732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenschmidt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoncsits</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeltsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pingoud</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wende</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pingoud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developing a programmed restriction endonuclease for highly specific DNA cleavage</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>7039</fpage><lpage>7047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16356926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacic</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence-selective DNA cleavage by a chimeric metallopeptide</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2003</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>6656</fpage><lpage>6662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12769574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence-selective and hydrolytic cleavage of DNA by zinc finger mutants</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>15374</fpage><lpage>15375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15563152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dervan</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-site enzymatic cleavage of yeast genomic DNA mediated by triple helix formation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1991</year><volume>350</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1848684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameriniotero</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective cleavage of human DNA: RecA-assisted restriction endonuclease (RARE) cleavage</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1991</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>1494</fpage><lpage>1497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1962209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veselkov</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Demidov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank-Kamenetskii</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PNA as a rare genome-cutter</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>214</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8538785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izvolsky</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Demidov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank-Kamenetskii</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence-specific protection of duplex DNA against restriction and methylation enzymes by pseudocomplementary PNAs</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2000</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>10908</fpage><lpage>10913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10978178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Uehara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-selective and hydrolytic two-strand scission of double-stranded DNA using Ce(IV)/EDTA and pseudo-complementary PNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>e153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumaoka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrolysis of oligonucleotides by homogeneous Ce(IV)/EDTA complex</article-title><source>Chem. Lett</source><year>2000</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>357</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preferential hydrolysis of gap and bulge sites in DNA by Ce(IV)/EDTA complex</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>e102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12364619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Branum</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Tipton</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Que</surname><given-names>L</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Double-strand hydrolysis of plasmid DNA by dicerium complexes at 37&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2001</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>1898</fpage><lpage>1904</lpage><comment>(Other complex of Ce(IV) for DNA hydrolysis was also reported.)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11456810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Double duplex invasion by peptide nucleic acid: A general principle for sequence-specific targeting of double-stranded DNA</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>11804</fpage><lpage>11808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10518531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Uehara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aburatani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical-reaction-based site-selective DNA cutter for PCR-free gene manipulation</article-title><source>ChemBioChem</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16491499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haaima</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased DNA binding and sequence discrimination of PNA oligomers containing 2,6-diaminopurine</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>4639</fpage><lpage>4643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9358176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gildea</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Egholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchardt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Solid-phase synthesis of peptide nucleic acids</article-title><source>J. Peptide Sci</source><year>1995</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9222994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arishima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oligonucleotide bearing ethylenediamine-<italic>N,N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>&#x02032;-triacetates for gap-selective DNA hydrolysis by Ce<sup>4+</sup>/EDTA</article-title><source>ChemBioChem</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15540227</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
