<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17148473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1761444</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl998</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>BASC: an integrated bioinformatics system for <italic>Brassica</italic> research</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>Timothy A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>Erica G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>Christopher G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Geraldine A. C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>Ross</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Batley</surname><given-names>Jacqueline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>Jason E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mongin</surname><given-names>Emmanuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stupka</surname><given-names>Elia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>Bruce</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spangenberg</surname><given-names>German</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Plant Biotechnology Centre</institution><addr-line>Victorian AgriBiosciences Centre, 1 Park Drive, Bundoora, Victoria 3083, Australia</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Victorian Bioinformatics Consortium</institution><addr-line>Victorian AgriBiosciences Centre, 1 Park Drive, Bundoora, Victoria 3083, Australia</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Australian Centre for Plant Functional Genomics, Primary Industries Research Victoria, Department of Primary Industries</institution><addr-line>Victorian AgriBiosciences Centre, 1 Park Drive, Bundoora, Victoria 3083, Australia</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><sup>4</sup><institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution><addr-line>CA 94720-3102, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au5"><sup>5</sup><institution>McGill Centre for Bioinformatics, McGill University</institution><addr-line>Montreal, Quebec, Canada</addr-line></aff><aff id="au6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Telethon Institute of Genetics and Medicine</institution><addr-line>Via Pietro Castellino 111, Napoli 80131, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="au7"><sup>7</sup><institution>IBM Australia</institution><addr-line>60 City Road, Southbank, Victoria, Australia</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +61 3 9479 5633; Fax: +61 3 9479 3618; Email: <email>dave.edwards@dpi.vic.gov.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D870</fpage><lpage>D873</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2006 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The BASC system provides tools for the integrated mining and browsing of genetic, genomic and phenotypic data. This public resource hosts information on <italic>Brassica</italic> species supporting the Multinational <italic>Brassica</italic> Genome Sequencing Project, and is based upon five distinct modules, ESTDB, Microarray, MarkerQTL, CMap and EnsEMBL. ESTDB hosts expressed gene sequences and related annotation derived from comparison with GenBank, UniRef and the genome sequence of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. The Microarray module hosts gene expression information related to genes annotated within ESTDB. MarkerQTL is the most complex module and integrates information on genetic markers, maps, individuals, genotypes and traits. Two further modules include an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> EnsEMBL genome viewer and the CMap comparative genetic map viewer for the visualization and integration of genetic and genomic data. The database is accessible at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.pbcbasc.latrobe.edu.au"/>.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Modern high throughput technologies deliver a wealth of biological data. The increased complexity and abundance of biological data has made it difficult for researchers to gain a comprehensive view of this information. In order to improve accessibility, numerous computational tools and databases have been established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>). However, their independent development has resulted in diverse data structures and formats, limiting the ability to query across data types. To overcome some of these limitations, we have developed a bioinformatics system that integrates gene and genome DNA sequence, gene expression, molecular genetic marker, phenotypic trait and population data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Where possible, established open source database systems have been incorporated, permitting the integration and exchange of public data. The use of bioperl and MySQL, together with EnsEMBL coding standards further promote the interpretability of this system with external databases.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Overview of <italic>Brassica</italic> BASC module integration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl998f1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>DATA AND PROCESSING</title><p>The ESTDB module functionality is based on previous <italic>Brassica</italic> sequence databases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>) and consists of proprietary and public expressed sequences. New sequences are collated quarterly and processed through an automated annotation pipeline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). Total sequence numbers within the database are <italic>Brassica napus</italic> (91&#x02009;658), <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> (6485), <italic>Brassica juncea</italic> (8576), <italic>Brassica rapa</italic> (21&#x02009;256) and <italic>Brassica nigra</italic> (3267). Where the original trace files are available, the annotation pipeline uses Phred to call the bases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>). Crossmatch (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phrap.org/"/>) and RepeatMasker (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.repeatmasker.org/"/>) are used to remove vector sequences and to identify and mask repeat sequences. Processed sequences are clustered using D2 cluster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>) and assembled using Phrap (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phrap.org/"/>). Each assembly is stored in the database along with individual EST and consensus sequences. Parameters relating to sequence processing, assembly and annotation are maintained and linked from the associated results pages. The current database (Version 4, August 2006) contains 47&#x02009;555 unigenes made up of 17&#x02009;939 consensus and 29&#x02009;616 singleton sequences. Functional annotation is assigned to the unigenes by sequence similarity to entries within UniProt and GenBank, using BLAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>). A cut-off value of <italic>E</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> is applied, with results parsed, stored and indexed in the database. Of the unigene sequences, 70% have a significant match with either UniProt or GenBank. Intermediate Gene Ontology (GO) annotation is derived via mapping to UniProt, with 40% of the unigenes annotated with at least one GO term. Sequences are compared with the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome sequence using WU-BLAST (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.wustl.edu/"/>) to identify the best matching ortholog. These similarities are displayed using the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> EnsEMBL genome viewer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). Additional links to related molecular genetic marker and gene expression data are maintained. The Microarray module provides a platform for storing and visualizing gene expression data. The database stores both raw and normalized data and includes results from hydridizations of <italic>Brassica</italic> unigene cDNA microarrays representing 7000 unigenes.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><italic>Brassica</italic> BASC EST sequence processing and annotation pipeline.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl998f2"/></fig><p>The MarkerQTL module stores a variety of data relating to molecular genetic markers, individuals, populations, genotypes, genetic and trait maps and phenotypic information. Data has been incorporated from the <italic>B.napus</italic> IMSORB project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Brassica.bbsrc.ac.uk/IMSORB/"/>), the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council (BBSRC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>) and the Osborn lab at the University of Wisconsin (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://osbornlab.agronomy.wisc.edu/"/>).</p><p>The EnsEMBL and CMap modules are both open source tools developed by the European Bioinformatics Institute (EBI) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>) and The Generic Model Organism Database Project (GMOD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>), respectively. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> EnsEMBL genome browser was developed by the Nottingham <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Stock Centre (NASC) in the UK and allows the anchoring of biological features to the genome sequence of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. In collaboration with NASC, we have anchored the <italic>Brassica</italic> unigenes from the BASC ESTDB module and the <italic>B.oleracea</italic> whole genome shotgun sequences produced by The Institute for Genome Research (TIGR) and Cold Spring Harbor (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tigr.org/tdb/e2k1/bog1/"/>) to the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome. <italic>B.rapa</italic> Bacterial Artificial Chromosomes (BAC) end sequences, produced by the Multinational <italic>Brassica</italic> Genome Sequencing Project, have also been mapped by their candidate syntenic locus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). The <italic>Brassica</italic> BASC CMap displays genetic maps for <italic>Brassica</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. The current version hosts data for 6 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, 6 <italic>B.juncea</italic>, 9 <italic>B.napus</italic>, 3 <italic>B.rapa</italic> and 8 <italic>B.oleracea</italic> maps, with consensus maps generated using a rule-based approach. One QTL map for <italic>B.napus</italic> has been included, with measurements for 13 traits and 181 QTL. The genetic viewer and genome browser permit the identification of syntenic regions between <italic>Brassica</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and the translation of trait information in the form of QTL on genetic maps in CMap and MarkerQTL, to gene and genome information through the EnsEMBL browser.</p></sec><sec><title>QUERY TOOLS AND USER INTERFACE</title><p>The web interface provides multiple routes to query the various databases. The inter-related structure of the system permits cross-linking and browsing between divergent data and cross searching of complex data types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). Modules may be searched independently or together. All relevant data is indexed, and searching by keyword using MySQL Boolean operators or accession number will retrieve associated sequence and annotation data, as well as molecular marker, gene expression or phenotypic trait information. A BLAST interface permits a similarity based search with an amino acid or DNA sequence. Analysis parameters for sequence assembly and annotation are linked from the relevant pages and help pages. Example searches are also provided.</p><p>Typical results from the ESTDB module would include EST or consensus gene sequence, cDNA library information, sequence annotation, including UniRef, GenBank and significant GO categories and links to syntenic regions within <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. The results are displayed in both tabular and graphical format (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). Microarray results include gene expression values across treatments for a gene, experiment and sample details. The MarkerQTL MarkerView displays information related to a marker assay such as SSR, SNP, RFLP or AFLP parameters, including sequence information, amplification primers and any associated maps or locus information where available (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). Markers may be selected within a defined region of a map, by association with other mapped markers, through associated QTL loci, or with a defined distribution across a genome. CMap enables the comparison of genetic markers and traits between maps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>) as well as the exploitation of information from the complete genome sequence of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. By using this comparative map viewer, users can quickly identify traits in similar positions on other genetic maps. The development of consensus maps further enables the identification of molecular markers around the trait of interest for further characterization in specific populations. The integrated nature of the BASC bioinformatics system allows users to traverse between annotated gene sequence data, gene expression information, molecular genetic marker, genetic map and trait data with a few clicks of the mouse.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Examples of data visualization, Sequence annotation in tabular and graphical format (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>Brassica</italic> QTLview (<bold>B</bold>) and <italic>Brassica</italic> CMap (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl998f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>FUTURE DEVELOPMENTS</title><p>The structure of the database and application programming interface (API) offers the flexibility to add additional datasets and expand the current capabilities, including additional species such as wheat, barley and legumes. As the <italic>Brassica</italic> genome sequencing progresses, EnsEMBL based <italic>Brassica</italic> genome views will be included to display and compare this information and extend comparisons between <italic>Brassica</italic> species and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Additional gene expression, gene, trait and genetic map information will be incorporated as it becomes available.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by Primary Research Industries Victoria (PIRVic).</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement.</italic> None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant Bioinformatics: from genome to phenome</article-title><source>Trends Biotechnol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15109809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spangenberg</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New computational tools for <italic>Brassica</italic> genome research</article-title><source>Comp. Funct. Genomics</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18629157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>G.A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spangenberg</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Brassica</italic> ASTRA: an integrated database for <italic>Brassica</italic> Genomic Research</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>D656</fpage><lpage>D659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendl</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred. I. Accuracy assessment</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hide</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>d2_cluster: a validated method for clustering EST and full-length cDNA sequences</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1135</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10568753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>G.A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spangenberg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrating and interrogating diverse <italic>Brassica</italic> data within an EnsEMBL structured database</article-title><source>Acta Hortic.</source><year>2006</year><volume>706</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moule</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient large-scale development of microsatellites for marker and mapping applications in <italic>Brassica</italic> crop species</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1103</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15067397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caccamo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clamp</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ensembl 2005</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>D447</fpage><lpage>D453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>I.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>K.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teytelman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gramene, a tool for grass genomics</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1606</fpage><lpage>1613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12481044</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
