<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15337779</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1361683</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200406148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200406148</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bend propagation drives central pair rotation in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> flagella</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>David R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakatsugawa</surname><given-names>Masako</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1cbca20N0x379c5e8">Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, State University of New York Upstate Medical University, Syracuse, NY 13210</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to D.R. Mitchell, Dept. of Cell and Developmental Biology, State University of New York Upstate Medical University, 750 E. Adams St., Syracuse, NY 13210. Tel.: (315) 464-8575. Fax: (315) 464-8535. email: <email>mitcheld@upstate.edu</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>166</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>715</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Regulation of motile 9+2 cilia and flagella depends on interactions between radial spokes and a central pair apparatus. Although the central pair rotates during bend propagation in flagella of many organisms and rotation correlates with a twisted central pair structure, propulsive forces for central pair rotation and twist are unknown. Here we compared central pair conformation in straight, quiescent flagella to that in actively beating flagella using wild-type <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> and mutants that lack radial spoke heads. Twists occur in quiescent flagella in both the presence and absence of spoke heads, indicating that spoke&#x02013;central pair interactions are not needed to generate torque for twisting. Central pair orientation in propagating bends was also similar in wild type and spoke head mutant strains, thus orientation is a passive response to bend formation. These results indicate that bend propagation drives central pair rotation and suggest that dynein regulation by central pair&#x02013;radial spoke interactions involves passive central pair reorientation to changes in bend plane.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cilia; radial spoke; dynein; motility; microtubule</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>Abbreviation used in this paper: CP, central pair apparatus.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Because all major phylogenetic divisions of eukaryotes contain organisms with 9+2 organelles, the ancestor of all extant eukaryotes must have been a single-celled organism with a 9+2 flagellum (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Baldauf et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Cavalier-Smith, 2002</xref>). Therefore, the central pair microtubule complex evolved very early as an essential element in flagellar motility, and this machinery has survived with little modification during evolution into today's phylogenetically diverse organisms. Flagella become paralyzed when either the central pair or radial spokes are missing (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Witman et al., 1978</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Baccetti et al., 1979</xref>), but the precise function of these structures remains elusive. To better understand the conserved function of central pair complexes, it is essential to first understand the relationship between these asymmetric structures and the pattern of dynein activation necessary for bend propagation. This task is complicated by the apparent rotation of the central pair in cilia and flagella of some organisms but not of others (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Omoto et al., 1999</xref>). Our results explain this dichotomy and support a specific model of central pair-based regulation of ciliary and flagellar motility.</p><p>Regulation of eukaryotic ciliary and flagellar motility is essential for a wide range of biological processes such as sperm chemotaxis and mucociliary clearance in metazoans and foraging behavior in smaller aquatic eukaryotes. Radial spokes tightly associate with the nine outer doublet microtubules and project toward a central pair apparatus (CP) with which they form transient contacts. During flagellar bending, doublet microtubules slide and spokes must move along the CP surface. Although the CP is nearly circular in cross section, its underlying structure and biochemistry are highly asymmetric (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Adams et al., 1981</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell, 2003a</xref>). In addition, rows of radial spokes on each doublet align with different surfaces of the CP that each form unique sites of potential interaction, and these interaction sites change as the CP rotates. We recently determined (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell, 2003b</xref>) that the <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagellar CP, like that of <italic>Paramecium tetraurelia</italic> cilia (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Omoto and Kung, 1980</xref>), twists in actively beating flagella so that the CP surface facing each row of spokes in bent regions is different from the CP surface facing the same row of spokes in straight regions between bends. When swimming cells were fixed for electron microscopy, the plane through the two CP microtubules was always parallel to the bend plane in curved segments and CP microtubule C1 was nearest the outer edge of each curve. Similar CP orientations in principal and reverse bends were related by 180&#x000b0; twists in interbend regions.</p><p>The constant relationship between CP orientation and bend position in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella suggests that bend propagation may drive CP rotation. If the CP is inherently twisted, forced propagation of one CP orientation along with propagation of each bend would result in CP rotation. However, it is equally possible that CP rotation is the driving force that induces bend propagation and that CP twist is caused by the torque of a rotation force. If CP rotation and twist are active processes, then they must occur either through torque generated between CP projections and radial spokes or at sites of CP attachment to flagellar distal tip structures. A rotation force at the tip is unlikely to drive bend propagation because bends form at the proximal end in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella and because the CP continues to rotate after its partial extrusion from flagellar tips (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kamiya, 1982</xref>). We set out to determine if CP rotation and twist are causally linked to bend propagation and if radial spoke interactions with CP projections are required for this process. We conclude that bend propagation drives CP rotation, rather than the reverse, and use this conclusion as a basis to constrain models of radial spoke&#x02013;central pair regulation of flagellar dynein activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>CP orientation in adherent wild-type flagella</title><p>To test the effects of bend propagation on CP orientation, we exploited the natural tendency of the biflagellate <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> to alternate between periods of continuous swimming (when suspended in a liquid medium) and periods of quiescence (when a solid surface is encountered). In <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic>, quiescence is initiated by adhesion of a portion of one flagellar surface to a solid substrate (e.g., the coverslip), followed by a rapid reduction in beat frequency and adhesion of the second flagellum (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 2004</xref>). Cessation of beating usually leads to surface adherence by both flagella along nearly their entire lengths from their tips to a region near the cell body, with the two flagella pointing in opposite directions. Although quiescent flagella can engage in surface motility to translocate cells by gliding (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bloodgood, 1981</xref>), they cannot actively generate or propagate bends unless quiescence is overridden by suppressor mutations (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 2004</xref>). Electron microscopy of adherent, quiescent flagella was used to determine CP orientation in the absence of bend formation or propagation. The types of images generated and their interpretations are diagrammed in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. If a plane through the CP remains parallel to the section plane, then both CP microtubules should remain visible in the part of the flagellum exposed by the section; if the CP is perpendicular to the section plane, then only a single CP should be visible; if the CP twists, then parallel views will alternate with perpendicular views. Ideal alignments of twisted regions will reveal one of the two microtubules throughout the section while the other microtubule passes in and out of the section plane. Sections cut through quiescent cells perpendicular to the coverslip (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A) confirm that only 1&#x02013;2 &#x003bc;m at the proximal end of each flagellum is curved, and the rest of the &#x0223c;12-&#x003bc;m-long flagellum is closely adherent to the flat coverslip surface. Sections cut parallel to the coverslip expose the distal 5&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;m of many flagella (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B). In 45 examples of wild-type flagella that revealed CP orientation over lengths of at least 5 &#x003bc;m, twisting of the CP was observed 67% of the time (30 flagella). None of the 30 flagella with CP twists had more than one twist in the regions (up to 10 &#x003bc;m) visible in these sections. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C is an example of a twisted CP in a quiescent wild-type flagellum. To emphasize changes in CP orientation over extended lengths, original images (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, C and D</xref>, insets) were distorted by a linear scale transform. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> D shows two examples of CP that do not appear to twist within the region available for analysis, and in both flagella the CP are parallel to the coverslip. Overall, in straight segments where no twist was observed, CP orientation was apparently random because parallel, perpendicular, and 3/4 views were seen with similar frequency. In contrast, most curved segments of quiescent flagella had a parallel CP conformation. Because these flagella are not beating, bend propagation does not provide forces that cause central pair twist or that result in an orientation parallel to the bend plane in curved regions.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Diagram illustrating the central pair images expected from longitudinal thin sections through flagella.</bold> Thin sections of CP that are parallel to the section plane reveal both CP microtubules. If the CP is perpendicular, the section reveals a single CP microtubule. If the CP is twisted, parallel and perpendicular views alternate and one CP microtubule tracks from one edge to the other edge of the parallel views.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200406148f1"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Central pair orientation in quiescent wild-type flagella.</bold> (A) A section perpendicular to the glass surface (dashed line) shows one adherent cell and basal regions of both flagella as they exit the cell wall. (B) Low magnification view parallel to the glass surface shows many pairs of flagella. Arrow in C indicates location of a CP twist, whereas no twists are visible in either flagellum in D. Images in C and D have been distorted by a linear scale transformation in one dimension to emphasize CP orientations; insets in each figure show undistorted images. Bars: (A and insets C and D) 1 &#x003bc;m; (B) 5 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200406148f2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>CP orientation in adherent spoke-defective flagella</title><p>To determine the contribution of spoke&#x02013;CP interactions to torque generation, we compared wild-type strains with mutant strains <italic>pf1</italic> and <italic>pf17</italic>, which fail to assemble the CP-interactive radial spoke heads and have paralyzed flagella (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 1979</xref>). Electron microscopy of straight, quiescent flagella that lack spoke heads was used to find out whether the CP is inherently straight or twisted in vivo, in the absence of any potential spoke-dependent torque. Initial attempts to fix quiescent <italic>pf17</italic> flagella produced few useful images because spoke-defective paralyzed mutant strains rarely adhered to the glass surface by their flagella. To increase sample size, images were obtained by fixing adherent <italic>pf1sup-pf1</italic> flagella. The <italic>sup-pf1</italic> mutations are bypass suppressor mutations in an outer row dynein heavy chain (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Porter et al., 1994</xref>) and restore motility but not spoke structure (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 1982</xref>). Although <italic>sup-pf1</italic> by itself is quiescence defective, <italic>pf1sup-pf1</italic> double mutants are not (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>As illustrated in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, formation of CP twists does not depend on interactions between radial spoke heads and CP projections. Straight segments of <italic>pf1</italic> and <italic>pf17</italic> flagella often contained twisted CP, and in one image (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, A</xref> and A') two CP twists occur within one visible segment. Where adherent flagella were curved, the CP remained parallel to the section plane (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, C and C</xref>'), similar to the orientation in curved segments of adherent wild-type flagella (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> D). Overall, lack of spoke heads had no apparent effect on CP orientation in quiescent flagella, which suggests that spoke head interactions with the CP are not important determinants of CP shape or orientation under these quiescent conditions.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Central pair orientation in quiescent spoke-defective flagella.</bold> Each pair of images includes one undistorted image (A&#x02013;C) and one image distorted to emphasize CP orientation (A'&#x02013;C'). (A and A') A <italic>pf17</italic> flagellum in which the CP has two twists (arrows). (B and B') A <italic>pf1sup-pf1</italic> flagellum with one twist (arrow). (C and C') A curved <italic>pf1sup-pf1</italic> flagellum with one twist (arrow) between bends of opposite curvature. CP microtubules are parallel to the substrate in curved regions. Bars, 1 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200406148f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>CP orientation during bend propagation in spoke-defective flagella</title><p>The combination of a spoke assembly mutation (e.g., <italic>pf1</italic>) and a bypass suppressor mutation (e.g., <italic>sup-pf1</italic>) in one cell results in motile flagella, even though spoke heads remain absent (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 1982</xref>). Although these suppressed spoke-defective strains beat with abnormal waveforms and reduced beat frequencies, they continuously propagate large-amplitude base-to-tip bends in the absence of functional CP&#x02013;radial spoke interactions (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Brokaw et al., 1982</xref>). We fixed swimming <italic>pf1sup-pf1</italic> cells to preserve propagating bends and observed CP orientation in bent and straight flagellar segments to learn whether or not spokes contribute to maintaining the parallel CP orientation previously seen in bends of wild-type flagella (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell, 2003b</xref>). In all images of curved flagellar segments that revealed CP orientation in these cells, CP microtubules were side by side (parallel orientation). These included principal bends (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, A&#x02013;C) and reverse bends (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, B and D</xref>). Twists in straight segments (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B) were similar to those seen previously in wild-type flagella (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell, 2003b</xref>). In further support of a model in which the CP undergoes a 180&#x000b0; twist between principal and reverse bends, the C1-associated 32-nm repeat projections, when visible, always faced the outside of both principal bend (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C) and reverse bend (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> D) curves. Thus, CP orientation is parallel, with C1 facing the outside of the curve, in each propagating bend even though radial spoke heads are missing.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Central pair orientation in beating spoke-defective flagella.</bold> (A and C) CP orientation (emphasized by parallel white lines in the enlargements) is parallel to the bend plane in principal bends. (B) The CP twists (arrow) in a straight region between principal and reverse bends (image distorted by a linear transformation; inset shows an undistorted image). The 32-nm repeat projection (small arrows) diagnostic for C1 appears along the outer edge of both principal bends (C) and reverse bends (D). Insets show the location of enlarged regions. Bars: (insets) 1 &#x003bc;m; (enlargements) 100 nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200406148f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The CP is inherently twisted in vitro</title><p>The apparent twisting tendency of the CP in vivo, even in the absence of radial spoke heads, was further examined in vitro in preparations of extruded and partially purified CP. As previously described (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kamiya et al., 1982</xref>), once extruded, the <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> CP become left-handed helices (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A). When extruded CP were negatively stained, flattening of helices onto the specimen grid formed either coils, in which the direction of curvature did not change, or sinusoidal shapes, in which curvature changed direction one or more times (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B). All curved regions displayed the two CP microtubules side-by-side, with C1 (identified on the basis of its 32-nm repeat projections) along the outside edge of the curve (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> D). Transitions in curve direction were accompanied by a twist in the CP (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> C) that maintained C1 along the outside edge. The helical shape of these CP in vitro is consistent with a CP that, if straightened, should contain at most two twists (one twist per helical turn), and if allowed to curve, would always have the C1 microtubule along its outer edge.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>
<bold>Helical shape of extruded CP complexes.</bold> (A) CP extruded from wild-type flagella and visualized by dark field microscopy are helical. Two images in the top row show one CP at different focal planes. Black lines indicate the borders of individual images assembled for this panel. (B&#x02013;D) Helical CP flatten onto specimen grids when negatively stained. Changes in curvature (boxed region in B, enlarged in C) are accompanied by twists (C, arrow). The two CP microtubules are side by side in curved regions (C and D) with C1 (marked by 32-nm repeat projections, small arrows in D) along the outer edge of each curve. A dashed line in C follows the midline of the C1 microtubule as it passes through a twist. Bars: (A) 5 &#x003bc;m; (B) 1 &#x003bc;m; (C and D) 100 nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="200406148f5"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our results show that the <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> CP complex has the properties of an inherently helical structure that takes on a curved conformation in flagellar bends and a twisted conformation when it is forced to straighten. We confirm previous reports (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kamiya et al., 1982</xref>) that the <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> CP complex is helical when extruded and unconstrained by surrounding doublets, similar to the conformation of extruded <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> ciliary CP complexes (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell, 1980</xref>). Straightening a helix induces twists, and we show that in vivo, in straight, quiescent flagella, the CP is twisted. By using mutants that lack radial spoke heads, we further show that such twists are not formed by torque exerted through CP&#x02013;radial spoke interactions; instead, absence of spokes may correlate with more frequent twists. Our only two examples of flagella in which the CP twists through more than 180&#x000b0; were both obtained from samples that lacked spoke heads.</p><p>Previous studies of wild-type cells that were fixed while swimming revealed a constant CP orientation in bends, such that both CP microtubules are parallel to the bend plane, with C1 nearest the outer edge of the bend (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell, 2003b</xref>). Here we show that this bend-specific orientation is independent of bend propagation because it occurs in curved, quiescent flagella, and is also independent of spoke head interactions because it occurs during bend propagation in spoke head mutants. Similar CP conformations in flagella that retain or lack radial spoke heads show that spoke&#x02013;CP interactions are not important determinants of CP orientation in these flagella. Our data do not rule out an effect of spoke&#x02013;central pair interactions on CP orientation, but suggest that any such effect provides subtle modulation of a primarily spoke-independent orientation mechanism.</p><p>A mechanism consistent with these results would be that an inherently helical CP conforms to axonemal curvature generated by dynein-dependent doublet sliding. When the axoneme curves, the CP always curves with C1 along its outer edge because this shape constitutes a minimum energy CP conformation. Straight flagellar segments between bends force the CP to straighten, which can only be accommodated by a CP twist. During active bend propagation, successive CP curves and twists must also propagate, and it is this propagation of a twisted conformation that results in CP rotation. As each bend elongates, inherent curvature of the CP forces an orientation that keeps specific CP projections directed toward radial spokes along doublets with active dyneins. This relationship is maintained for every bend, in both the principal and reverse bend directions, and propagates with each bend along the axoneme. Regulatory signals, transmitted from CP projections through spokes to modulate dyneins, could simultaneously alter the activity of dyneins in every bend.</p><p>Of what advantage is a rotating CP, and why has rotation been abandoned in some cell types? We contend that bend-dependent CP orientation automatically adjusts the CP regulatory machinery to changes in principal bend direction, and therefore is retained in organelles that must change beat direction. For example, in <italic>P. tetraurelia</italic>, major changes in effective stroke direction are modulated by changes in calcium ion concentration through a beat-independent mechanism (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Naitoh and Kaneko, 1972</xref>). Simultaneously, beat frequency, as well as more subtle changes in effective stroke direction, are modulated by changes in cAMP and cGMP (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bonini and Nelson, 1988</xref>), which act in part through changes in the phosphorylation of dynein subunits (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Hamasaki et al., 1991</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Noguchi et al., 2000</xref>). The signal transduction pathway from cyclic nucleotide to outer row dynein phosphorylation has been well studied in <italic>P. tetraurelia</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Barkalow et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Satir et al., 1995</xref>), and a similar pathway involving inner row dyneins has been identified in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic>. Phosphorylation of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> inner row I1 dynein occurs through a CP&#x02013;radial spoke&#x02013;modulated cAMP-dependent protein kinase cascade (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Howard et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Habermacher and Sale, 1997</xref>), alters doublet sliding velocities (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Sale, 1992</xref>), and has been linked to phototaxis (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">King and Dutcher, 1997</xref>). Thus, although CP orientation is itself determined initially by bend formation, the resulting CP orientation provides a platform for CP&#x02013;radial spoke modulation of the bend shape (waveform) and propagation velocity (beat frequency), and this regulation of waveform and beat frequency can be independent of effective stroke direction. Not surprisingly, <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella continue to beat with essentially planar waveforms and to respond in a limited way to shifts in calcium concentration even in the absence of radial spoke&#x02013;central pair interactions (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Wakabayashi et al., 1997</xref>), confirming that CP orientation is a response to, not a determinant of, bend plane. Our model predicts that cell types in which CP orientation has become fixed should beat with a fixed bend plane that does not require subtle changes in effective stroke direction (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell, 2004</xref>). In the case of ctenophore macrocilia, in which the CP does not rotate (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Tamm and Tamm, 1981</xref>), hundreds of cilia must beat in unison within each macrocilium, and their geometry precludes effective strokes that vary from a fixed bend plane. These cilia can reverse effective stroke direction in response to calcium signals, but maintain the same axonemal bend plane during forward and reverse beating episodes (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Tamm and Tamm, 1981</xref>). Likewise, typical metazoan spermatozoa, which have a fixed CP orientation and planar bends, modulate asymmetry, rather than bend plane, to effect tactic responses (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Brokaw, 1979</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Cook et al., 1994</xref>). The apparently fixed CP orientation of lamellibranch gill cilia (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Gibbons, 1961</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Warner and Satir, 1974</xref>) may also correspond with a single effective stroke direction, as the primary response of these organelles to calcium-mediated signals is quiescence, rather than reorientation (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Walter and Satir, 1978</xref>). This model also explains evolutionary loss of the CP in organelles that beat with helical, rather than planar, bends (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Gibbons et al., 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Nonaka et al., 1998</xref>) because these organelles need not modulate bend direction or waveform symmetry.</p><p>Confirmation of this model requires more information on CP orientation from organisms that can modulate effective stroke orientation, as well as better information about the ability of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> to alter beat orientation during tactic responses. To understand the mechanisms of CP-based waveform and beat frequency regulation, we also need better information on central pair proteins and their interactions with radial spoke heads. Recent advances in analyzing proteins of the <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> radial spoke (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) and central pair (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Lefebvre, 1996</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell and Sale, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Rupp et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Mitchell, 2004</xref>), together with continued characterization of mutations affecting CP function (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Wargo and Smith, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Wargo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Mitchell, 2004</xref>), provide promise that advances should not be far off.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>
<italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> strains used for this study included wild-type strain 137c, spoke head assembly mutants <italic>pf1</italic> and <italic>pf17</italic>, and pf suppressor <italic>sup-pf1-9</italic> (<italic>S-54)</italic> (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 2004</xref>). The <italic>S-54</italic> strain was backcrossed to wild type before crossing with <italic>pf1</italic> to obtain a double mutant strain. Fixation of waveforms during forward swimming followed our previously described methods (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell, 2003b</xref>). To fix quiescent flagella, cells were pipetted onto clean coverslips and allowed to settle and adhere for 1 min. Medium was gently decanted and replaced with 3% glutaraldehyde in minimal medium (made by mixing 3 ml of 8% glutaraldehyde with 5 ml of medium). After 5 min, the solution was replaced with 1% glutaraldehyde, 50 mM phosphate, pH 6.9, and fixation continued for 1 h at RT. After a brief buffer rinse, coverslips were post-fixed with buffered 1% OsO<sub>4</sub> for 1 h and processed through standard dehydration and flat embedding in epoxy resin. Sections were stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate and examined in an electron microscope (model 100CX II; Jeol). Negatives were digitized at 1,200 or 2,400 dpi on a flatbed scanner (model Powerlook II; UMAX), and resulting images were processed in Photoshop 6.0 to adjust gamma and contrast. Selected images were further transformed by a 2&#x02013;3-fold reduction in scale in one dimension to emphasize small changes in CP rotation. In each case a nontransformed image is provided for comparison.</p><p>Extruded central pair complexes were produced spontaneously from reactivated axonemes as follows. Flagella isolated from wild-type cells by standard procedures (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Witman, 1986</xref>) were resuspended in HMDEK (30 mM Hepes, 5 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mM DTT, 0.5 mM EGTA, 25 mM potassium acetate, and 1 mM PMSF, pH 7.4) and mixed with an equal volume of HMDEK containing 1% NP-40 and 2 mM ATP to initiate reactivation. Reactivated axonemes were set at RT until beating stopped (30&#x02013;60 min). This preparation was triturated gently to dissociate CP complexes from the distal ends of axonemes and spun in a microfuge at 6,000 rpm for 4 min. The supernatant solution was retained as an enriched CP fraction. Extruded CP were imaged under darkfield illumination (Aksiokop; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.; 40&#x000d7; oil immersion, irised 0.5&#x02013;1.0 NA objective), or were applied to carbon formvar-coated grids and negatively stained with 1% uranyl acetate for EM. Darkfield images were recorded at RT on film (TMax P3200; Kodak), and negatives were scanned at 2,400 dpi on a flatbed scanner. Positive (inverted) images were adjusted for contrast and gamma in Photoshop 6.0.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported in part by grants from the National Institutes of Health (GM44228) and the National Science Foundation (9982062).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Adams, G.M.W., B. Huang, G. Piperno, and D.J.L. Luck. <year>1981</year>. Central-pair microtubular complex of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella: polypeptide composition as revealed by analysis of mutants. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;76.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7028763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Baccetti, B., A.G. Burrini, A. Maver, V. Pallini, and T. Renieri. <year>1979</year>. &#x0201c;9 + 0&#x0201d; immotile spermatozoa in an infertile man. <source>Andrologia.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;443.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">161145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Baldauf, S.L., A.J. Roger, I. Wenk-Siefert, and W.F. Doolittle. <year>2000</year>. A kingdom-level phylogeny of eukaryotes based on combined protein data. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>290</volume>:<fpage>972</fpage>&#x02013;977.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11062127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Barkalow, K., T. Hamasaki, and P. Satir. <year>1994</year>. Regulation of 22S dynein by a 29-kD light chain. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;735.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8045936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bloodgood, R.A. <year>1981</year> Flagella-dependent gliding motility in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic>
<source>Protoplasma.</source>
<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;192.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bonini, N.M., and D.L. Nelson. <year>1988</year>. Differential regulation of <italic>Paramecium</italic> ciliary motility by cAMP and cGMP. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1615</fpage>&#x02013;1623.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2836435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brokaw, C.J. <year>1979</year>. Calcium-induced asymmetrical beating of triton-demembranted sea urchin sperm flagella. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;411.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">479307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brokaw, C.J., D.J.L. Luck, and B. Huang. <year>1982</year>. Analysis of the movement of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella: the function of the radial-spoke system is revealed by comparison of wild-type and mutant flagella. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>722</fpage>&#x02013;732.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7085755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cavalier-Smith, T. <year>2002</year>. The phagotrophic origin of eukaryotes and phylogenetic classification of Protozoa. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;354.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11931142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cook, S.P., C.J. Brokaw, C.H. Muller, and D.F. Babcock. <year>1994</year>. Sperm chemotaxis: egg peptides control cytosolic calcium to regulate flagellar responses. <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>165</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;19.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8088428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gibbons, B.H., I.R. Gibbons, and B. Baccetti. <year>1983</year>. Structure and motility of the 9 + 0 flagellum of eel spermatozoa. <source>J. Submicrosc. Cytol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;20.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6842644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gibbons, I.R. <year>1961</year>. The relationship between the fine structure and direction of beat in gill cilia of a lamellibranch mollusc. <source>J. Biophys. Biochem. Cytol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;205.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13898346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Habermacher, G., and W.S. Sale. <year>1997</year>. Regulation of flagellar dynein by phosphorylation of a 138-kD inner arm dynein intermediate chain. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;176.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9008711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hamasaki, T., K. Barkalow, J. Richmond, and P. Satir. <year>1991</year>. cAMP-stimulated phosphorylation of an axonemal polypeptide that copurifies with the 22S dynein arm regulates microtubule translocation velocity and swimming speed in <italic>Paramecium</italic>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>7918</fpage>&#x02013;7922.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1654550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Howard, D.R., G. Habermacher, D.B. Glass, E.F. Smith, and W.S. Sale. <year>1994</year>. Regulation of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagellar dynein by an axonemal protein kinase. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>1683</fpage>&#x02013;1692.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7798320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Huang, B., G. Piperno, and D.J.L. Luck. <year>1979</year>. Paralyzed flagella mutants of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>254</volume>:<fpage>3091</fpage>&#x02013;3099.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">429335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Huang, B., Z. Ramanis, and D.J.L. Luck. <year>1982</year>. Suppressor mutations in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> reveal a regulatory mechanism for flagellar function. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;124.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6461414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kamiya, R. <year>1982</year>. Extrusion and rotation of the central-pair microtubules in detergent-treated <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella. <source>Prog. Clin. Biol. Res.</source>
<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;173.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7100176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kamiya, R., R. Nagai, and S. Nakamura. 1982. Rotation of the central-pair microtubules in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella. Biological Functions of Microtubules and Related Structures. H. Sakai, H. Nohri, and G.G. Borisy, editors. Academic Press, New York. 189&#x02013;198.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">King, S.J., and S.K. Dutcher. <year>1997</year>. Phosphoregulation of an inner dynein arm complex in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> is altered in phototactic mutant strains. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;191.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9008712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mitchell, B.F., L.E. Grulich, and M.M. Mader. <year>2004</year>. Flagellar quiescence in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic>: characterization and defective quiescence in cells carrying sup-pf-1 and sup-pf-2 outer dynein arm mutations. <source>Cell Motil. Cytoskeleton.</source>
<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;196.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14743351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mitchell, D.R. 1980. Dynein binding to isolated microtubules from <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> cilia. Effects of magnesium, adenosine triphosphate, and monovalent ions. Ph.D. thesis. Syracuse University, Syracuse, NY. 103 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mitchell, D.R. <year>2003</year>a. Reconstruction of the projection periodicity and surface architecture of the flagellar central pair complex. <source>Cell Motil. Cytoskeleton.</source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;199.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12789663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mitchell, D.R. <year>2003</year>b. Orientation of the central pair complex during flagellar bend formation in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic>. <source>Cell Motil. Cytoskeleton.</source>
<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>120</fpage>&#x02013;129.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14506709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mitchell, D.R. <year>2004</year> Speculations on the evolution of 9+2 organelles and the role of central pair microtubules. <source>Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>In press</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mitchell, D.R., and W.S. Sale. <year>1999</year>. Characterization of a <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> insertional mutant that disrupts flagellar central pair microtubule-associated structures. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>144</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;304.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9922455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Naitoh, Y., and H. Kaneko. <year>1972</year>. Reactivated triton-extracted models of paramecium: modification of ciliary movement by calcium ions. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;524.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5032354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Noguchi, M., T. Ogawa, and T. Taneyama. <year>2000</year>. Control of ciliary orientation through cAMP-dependent phosphorylation of axonemal proteins in <italic>Paramecium caudatum</italic>. <source>Cell Motil. Cytoskeleton.</source>
<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;271.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10744859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nonaka, S., Y. Tanaka, Y. Okada, S. Takeda, A. Harada, Y. Kanai, M. Kido, and N. Hirokawa. <year>1998</year>. Randomization of left-right asymmetry due to loss of nodal cilia generating leftward flow of extraembryonic fluid in mice lacking KIF3B motor protein. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>829</fpage>&#x02013;837.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9865700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Omoto, C.K., and C. Kung. <year>1980</year>. Rotation and twist of the central-pair microtubules in the cilia of <italic>Paramecium</italic>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;46.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7419599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Omoto, C.K., I.R. Gibbons, R. Kamiya, C. Shingyoji, K. Takahashi, and G.B. Witman. <year>1999</year>. Rotation of the central pair microtubules in eukaryotic flagella. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;4.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9880321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Porter, M.E., J.A. Knott, L.C. Gardner, D.R. Mitchell, and S.K. Dutcher. <year>1994</year>. Mutations in the <italic>SUP-PF-1</italic> locus of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> identify a regulatory domain in the &#x003b2;-dynein heavy chain. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>1495</fpage>&#x02013;1507.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8089181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rupp, G., E. O'Toole, and M.E. Porter. <year>2001</year>. The <italic>Chlamydomonas PF6</italic> locus encodes a large alanine/proline-rich polypeptide that is required for assembly of a central pair projection and regulates flagellar motility. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>739</fpage>&#x02013;751.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11251084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Satir, P., K. Barkalow, and T. Hamasaki. <year>1995</year>. Ciliary beat frequency is controlled by a dynein light chain phosphorylation. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>68</volume>(Suppl.):<fpage>222S</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7787076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smith, E.F., and W.S. Sale. <year>1992</year>. Regulation of dynein-driven microtubule sliding by the radial spokes in flagella. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>257</volume>:<fpage>1557</fpage>&#x02013;1559.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1387971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smith, E.F., and P.A. Lefebvre. <year>1996</year>. <italic>PF16</italic> encodes a protein with armadillo repeats and localizes to a single microtubule of the central apparatus in <italic>Chlamydomonas flagella</italic>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;370.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8636214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smith, E.F., and P.A. Lefebvre. <year>1997</year>. <italic>PF20</italic> gene product contains WD repeats and localizes to the intermicrotubule bridges in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;467.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9188098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tamm, S.L., and S. Tamm. <year>1981</year>. Ciliary reversal without rotation of axonemal structures in ctenophore comb plates. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;509.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6114102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wakabayashi, K., T. Yagi, and R. Kamiya. <year>1997</year>. Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent waveform conversion in the flagellar axoneme of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> mutants lacking the central-pair radial spoke system. <source>Cell Motil. Cytoskeleton.</source>
<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;28.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9295138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Walter, M.F., and P. Satir. <year>1978</year>. Calcium control of ciliary arrest in mussel gill cells. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>&#x02013;120.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">359573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wargo, M.J., and E.F. Smith. <year>2003</year>. Asymmetry of the central apparatus defines the location of active microtubule sliding in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;142.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12518061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wargo, M.J., M.A. McPeek, and E.F. Smith. <year>2004</year>. Analysis of microtubule sliding patterns in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagellar axonemes reveals dynein activity on specific doublet microtubules. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>2533</fpage>&#x02013;2544.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15128866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Warner, F.D., and P. Satir. <year>1974</year>. The structural basis of ciliary bend formation. Radial spoke positional changes accompanying microtubule sliding. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;63.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4424314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Witman, G.B. <year>1986</year>. Isolation of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagella and flagellar axonemes. <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>
<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;290.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3821567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Witman, G.B., J. Plummer, and G. Sander. <year>1978</year>. <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> flagellar mutants lacking radial spokes and central tubules. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>729</fpage>&#x02013;747.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">632325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yang, P., D.R. Diener, J.L. Rosenbaum, and W.S. Sale. <year>2001</year>. Localization of calmodulin and dynein light chain LC8 in flagellar radial spokes. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>1315</fpage>&#x02013;1326.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yang, P., C. Yang, and W.S. Sale. <year>2004</year>. Flagellar radial spoke protein 2 is a calmodulin binding protein required for motility in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>. <source>Eukaryot. Cell.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;81.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang, H., and D.R. Mitchell. 2004. Cpc1, a <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> central pair protein with an adenylate kinase domain. <italic>J. Cell Sci.</italic>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.01297</pub-id>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
