<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17289751</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1874604</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm042</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Methods Online</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quantitative surface-enhanced resonance Raman scattering of phthalocyanine-labelled oligonucleotides</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Macaskill</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chernonosov</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koval</surname><given-names>V. V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lukyanets</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fedorova</surname><given-names>O. S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Faulds</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR2"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Centre for Molecular Nanometrology, WestCHEM, Department of Pure and Applied Chemistry, University of Strathclyde, 295 Cathedral Street, Glasgow, UK G1 1XL, <sup>2</sup>Institute of Chemical Biology and Fundamental Medicine, Lavrentyev Avenue 8, Novosibirsk 630090, Russia, <sup>3</sup>Institute of Human Ecology, Sovetskii Avenue 18, Kemerovo 650099, Russia and <sup>4</sup>Organic Intermediates &#x00026; Dyes Institute, B. Sadovaya, 1/4, Moscow 103787, Russia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>0141&#x02009;548&#x02009;4701</phone><fax>0141&#x02009;552&#x02009;0876</fax><email>Karen.Faulds@strath.ac.uk</email></corresp><corresp id="COR2"><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Correspondence may also be addressed to D. Graham. <phone>0141&#x02009;548&#x02009;4701</phone><fax>0141&#x02009;552&#x02009;0876</fax><email>Duncan.Graham@strath.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e42</fpage><lpage>e42</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The evaluation of phthalocyanine labels for the surface-enhanced resonance Raman scattering (SERRS) detection of oligonucleotides is reported. Three phthalocyanine-labelled oligonucleotides were assessed, each containing a different metal centre. Detection limits for each labelled oligonucleotide were determined using two excitation frequencies where possible. Limits of detection as low as 2.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup>&#x02009;mol.&#x02009;dm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> were obtained which are comparable to standard fluorescently labelled probes used in previous SERRS studies. The identification of two phthalocyanine-labelled oligonucleotides without separation was also demonstrated indicating their suitability for multiplexing. This study extends the range of labels suitable for quantitative surface-enhanced resonance Raman scattering with silver nanoparticles and offers more flexibility and choice when considering SERRS for quantitative DNA detection.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Surface-enhanced resonance Raman scattering (SERRS) has been shown to be a more sensitive and specific detection method for the direct analysis of DNA compared to the more commonly used method of fluorescence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). SERRS produces fingerprint spectra making it a more suitable technique for multiplexed identification of the components of a mixture without separation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). While multiplexing is possible to a certain degree with fluorescence detection, the technique is limited due to the broad and often overlapping spectra obtained.</p><p>While Raman spectroscopy produces relatively weak spectra, enhancements of 10<sup>14</sup> have been seen using SERRS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). In order for this to occur, the analyte must be able to absorb onto a suitable metal surface (providing the surface enhancement) and contain a chromophore approximately coincident with the excitation frequency (leading to resonance enhancement). This combination results in a highly sensitive technique for which single molecule detection has been demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). While DNA does not meet these requirements, many commonly used fluorescent labels do and as the metal surface commonly used quenches fluorescence, background interference is minimized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>).</p><p>Previously, DNA labelled with six commercially available dyes (Cy3, TAMRA, Texas Red, Cy3.5, Cy5 and Rhodamine 6G) has been detected by SERRS using gold nanoparticles with a silver coating singly and as multiplexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). In a separate study, silver nanoparticles were used as the metal substrate in the quantitative study of eight oligonucleotides labelled with the commonly used dyes FAM, TET, HEX, TAMRA, R6G, ROX, Cy3 and Cy5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Linear calibration graphs and limits of detection (in some cases as low as 0.5 fmol) were obtained for each of the dyes analysed. That study was then extended to include BODIPY TR-X, Cy3.5, Cy5.5 and Yakima yellow-labelled oligonucleotides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Labelled probes have also been used in DNA assays based on SERRS. Vo Dinh <italic>et al</italic>. used a cresyl fast violet-labelled primer which was successfully incorporated into PCR for subsequent SERRS detection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Graham <italic>et al</italic>. have also demonstrated SERRS detection in multiplex genotyping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). In this study, the presence or absence of three different genotypes was determined without separation.</p><p>While DNA detection by SERRS has been clearly demonstrated to be a powerful technique, there remains a need to expand the range of labels that can be used. Moreover, the range of families of compounds that can be used should be widened as many of the labels used so far in this technique are structurally related and therefore give similar, but distinguishable spectra. This article therefore presents the assessment of three phthalocyanine-labelled oligonucleotides as SERRS probes. Similar dyes have been reported as near-IR fluorescence labels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) and have also been used to investigate sequence-specific modification of DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). However, their properties as SERRS labels have not been reported until now.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Labelled oligonucleotides</title><p>The labelled oligonucleotides were prepared using a previously reported method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). The oligonucleotides were synthesized by standard phosphoramidite chemistry and contained a&#x02014;O-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>NH<sub>2</sub> linker at the 5&#x02032;-end. Succinimidyl esters of phthalocyanines were then coupled to the oligonucleotides while still attached to the control pore glass (CPG). The conjugates were then cleaved from the CPG with concentrated ammonium hydroxide before purification by preparative reverse phase HPLC on Nucleosil 100-7 C<sub>18</sub> column (4.6 &#x000d7; 250&#x02009;mm, Macherey-Nagel, D&#x000fc;ren, Germany). The structures of the phthalocyanines, phthalocyanine-oligonucleotide conjugate absorption maxima and the oligonucleotide sequences are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. Free oligonucleotide and the conjugates had different <italic>R</italic><sub>f</sub> values in HPLC as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. The conjugate UV&#x02013;Vis spectrum contained both oligonucleotide and phthalocyanine bands. After conjugation, the shape of the spectrum at 600&#x02013;70&#x02009;nm is significantly changed in comparison with the absorption spectrum of free phthalocyanine as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Structure of phthalocyanine conjugates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm042f1"/></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Reverse-phase HPLC data for preparation of oligonucleotide conjugates. A mixture of 20% acetonitrile (A) and water (B), both containing 0.05&#x02009;M triethylamine-acetate buffer (pH = 7.0) was used as the mobile phase. The following gradient elution was run: 0 to 50&#x02009;min: 0 to 100% A. The flow rate was 2.0&#x02009;ml/min, and the detection wavelength was 260&#x02009;nm. <bold>1</bold> &#x02013; starting oligonucleotide; <bold>2</bold> &#x02013; conjugate with PtcCo.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm042f2"/></fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Absorption spectra of free phthalocyanine (-&#x02009;-&#x02009;-&#x02009;-&#x02009;-) and its oligonucleotide conjugate (&#x02014;&#x02014;) for (<bold>A</bold>) Ptc Co, (<bold>B</bold>) Ptc Al and (<bold>C</bold>) Ptc Zn.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm042f3"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Silver nanoparticle preparation</title><p>Citrate-reduced silver nanoparticles were prepared in a colloidal suspension using a modified Lee and Meisel procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Instrumentation</title><p>The labelled oligonucleotides were analysed using three excitation wavelengths. A Renishaw inVIA microscope system with a 514.5&#x02009;nm argon ion laser, using a &#x000d7;20/0.4 long working distance objective to focus the laser beam into a microtitre plate well containing the sample was used. A Renishaw Ramascope system 2000 was used with a 632.8&#x02009;nm helium-neon laser or a 785&#x02009;nm Renishaw diode laser. A &#x000d7;20 objective was used to focus the laser beam using both these wavelengths into a microtitre plate containing the sample.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample preparation</title><p>For the determination of the limits of detection, the dye-labelled oligonucleotides were diluted to various concentrations using sterile water (18.2&#x02009;M&#x003a9;.&#x02009;cm). Samples were then prepared for SERRS analysis by adding 7&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of dye-labelled oligonucleotide and 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of 0.1&#x02009;mol&#x02009;dm<bold><sup>&#x02212;</sup></bold><sup>3</sup> spermine, followed by 175&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of water and finally 175&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of silver nanoparticles. The samples were analysed within 1&#x02009;min of the addition of the silver nanoparticles and each concentration was analysed five times. The aggregation process of the nanoparticles is dynamic and in order to provide reproducibility the measurements were carried out within the same time frame each time. The spectra were obtained with the spectrometer grating centred at 1400&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and with a 10&#x02009;s accumulation time. The spectra were baseline corrected using the GRAMS/32 software, and the average peak height of the strongest peak in the spectra was plotted against the concentration after being normalized to the silicon standard peak.</p><p>For the assessment of the suitability of the dye-labelled oligonucleotides for multiplexing, a mixture of two dye-labelled oligonucleotides was added, to a total volume of 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;L or less, to 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of 0.1&#x02009;mol&#x02009;dm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> spermine, followed by 175&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of water and finally 175&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of silver nanoparticles.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><p>Phthalocyanines were chosen as labels for this study as they are chemically and photochemically stable and have large extinction coefficients (&#x0003e;10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). In addition, they can be made either fluorescent or non-fluorescent depending on the choice of metal centre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). They are highly versatile as they can be modified via their metal centre or substituent side chains giving rise to distinct Raman spectra. The three phthalocyanine labels used in this study and the oligonucleotide sequences are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. Modification of the oligonucleotide sequence with propargylamine as in previous studies was not required for SERRS detection. Each of the phthalocyanine labels used had a different metal centre&#x02014;aluminium (PtcAl), zinc (PtcZn) and cobalt (PtcCo)&#x02014;and each had different side chains&#x02014;SO<sub>2</sub>NH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>COOH, SCH<sub>2</sub>COOH and COOH. The absorption maximum varies for each dye label as this is determined by the metal centre present and the substituents around the ring. The absorption maxima are as follows: PtcAl&#x02014;640&#x02009;nm, PtcZn&#x02014;680&#x02009;nm and PtcCo&#x02014;625&#x02009;nm. This indicates that the labels are more in resonance with the 632.8&#x02009;nm laser excitation source than the 514.5 or 785&#x02009;nm excitation.</p><p>A 0.1&#x02009;mol.&#x02009;dm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> solution of spermine, a naturally occurring tetramine, was used in this study as an aggregating agent as this had previously been shown to give maximum SERRS signal enhancement in the analysis of dye-labelled oligonucleotides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). The spermine neutralizes the negatively charged phosphate backbone of the oligonucleotide, which otherwise may inhibit attachment onto the negatively charged citrate-coated silver surface but will also aid hybridization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). It also aggregates the silver nanoparticles into discrete clusters producing the roughened metal surface required for the SERRS effect.</p><p>The SERRS spectra of the three-labelled oligonucleotides using the three excitation wavelengths are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>. Only weak SERRS was obtained using 785&#x02009;nm excitation and only at the highest concentration. The oligonucleotides labelled with PtcCo and PtcAl also only gave weak SERRS with the highest concentration at 514.5&#x02009;nm excitation. PtcZn, however, gave markedly stronger signals with a different pattern of relative intensities from that recorded at 632.8&#x02009;nm. The signals come from the phthalocyanine and are not affected by the oligonucleotide sequence. This is due to the resonance contribution from the label dominating the spectra.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>SERRS Spectra from the three phthalocyanine-labelled oligonucleotides using a 10&#x02009;s scan and excitation at (<bold>A</bold>) 514.5&#x02009;nm, (<bold>B</bold>) 632.8&#x02009;nm and (<bold>C</bold>) 785&#x02009;nm. The final concentration of sample for (A) and (C) was 1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>&#x02009;mol&#x02009;dm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> and for (B) was 3.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>&#x02009;mol&#x02009;dm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>. All spectra have been base line corrected.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm042f4"/></fig></p><p>The electronic spectrum in PtcZn has an extended shoulder from the B band up to about 520&#x02009;nm which is not present in the spectra of PtcCo and PtcAl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). This may permit a more effective resonance contribution to the surface enhancement by electronic coupling with the B band. The increased relative intensity of the bands at about 1600&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> is also observed in the resonance Raman spectra of phthalocyanines excited in the B band region.</p><p>The most effective SERRS spectra were obtained using 632.8&#x02009;nm excitation which is in resonance with the Q band of the dyes for which &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> ranged from 625 to 675&#x02009;nm. Within the band envelop of the plasmon resonance for some small clusters lies 632.8&#x02009;nm, which is also a frequency and therefore gives effective surface enhancement from the aggregated colloid. The most intense band in each spectrum was between 1510 and 1545&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and its position is directly related to the metal ion present in the complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). The major feature of this vibration is the large displacement on the C-N-C bridges between the benzopyrrole groups. The frequency shift is therefore dependent on both the strength of the bridge bonds and the effect that the metal ion has on the shape of the ring. For example, whereas CoPtc has a cavity diameter of 3.82&#x02009;&#x000c5; in its equilibrium state ZnPtc has a cavity diameter of around 3.96&#x02009;&#x000c5;. As well as affecting the frequency of the intense band at about 1510 and 1545&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the loss of effective D4h symmetry causes changes in the electronic spectra as discussed above for ZnPtc and differences between molecules in the relative intensity of some of the weaker peaks in the SERRS spectra.</p><p>The frequency dependence of the main peak on molecular structure provides multiplexing potential for this class of dyes. The most intense peaks are distinct enough to enable a mixture of two phthalocyanine-labelled oligonucleotides to be easily identified in a mixture as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>. The oligonucleotides labelled with PtcCo and PtcZn were analysed in two mixtures of differing ratios. Despite being in the same region, the major peak for each label could easily be identified and the peak height was seen to vary with the quantity of sample present. The instrument was set to provide a broad spectral range but by concentrating only on the 1500&#x02013;1550&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> region, greater numbers of phthalocyanines could be identified in a mixture.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Spectra of mixtures of PtcCo and PtcZn with the following ratios: A&#x02013;1:2 and B&#x02013;2:1. Spectra obtained using 632.8&#x02009;nm laser excitation with a 10s accumulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm042f5"/></fig></p><p>Limits of detection were determined for each of the labelled oligonucleotides using 632.8&#x02009;nm excitation and for PtcZn, using 514.5&#x02009;nm excitation. The concentration graphs obtained are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>. These show the linear concentration dependence of the labelled oligonucleotides using both excitation wavelengths. The error bars represent &#x000b1;1 SD and the R.S.D. for the data set varied between 3 and 17%. Again, as shown in other DNA detection studies with SERRS, the technique has been shown to deliver quantitative and reproducible results. The limits of detection obtained are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. Similar detection limits were seen for the three labels using 632.8&#x02009;nm excitation. As noted earlier, strong signals were obtained for PtcZn at 514.5&#x02009;nm allowing limits of detection to be determined. The limits of detection for the phthalocyanine-labelled oligonucleotides are comparable to those previously obtained from commonly available fluorescently labelled oligonucleotides. The limit of detection does vary with the nature of the label and in previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), this has ranged from 56 (TET) to 1 (Rhodamine 6G) pmoldm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> which are several orders of magnitude lower in limit of detection than achieved by fluorescence using routinely available instrumentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). An important feature of SERRS is that the detection limits in a multiplex are the same as for a labelled oligonucleotide on its own. This is highly significant as similar techniques such as fluorescence can experience a deterioration in sensitivity when multiplexed analyses are attempted.
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>The detection limits for phthalocyanine labelled oligonucleotides at each excitation frequency</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dye label</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Detection limit (mol&#x02009;dm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">514.5&#x02009;nm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">632.8&#x02009;nm</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtcCo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtcAl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtcZn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Calibration graph obtained for (<bold>A</bold>) PtcZn using 514.5&#x02009;nm laser excitation and (<bold>B</bold>) Ptc Co, Ptc Al and Ptc Zn using 632.8&#x02009;nm excitation. The error bars shown are &#x000b1;1 S.D. and each point is the average of five repeat samples.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm042f6"/></fig></p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Phthalocyanine dyes have been shown for the first time to be suitable labels for the detection of DNA by SERRS and were analysed at three wavelengths. Linear concentration-dependent graphs of SERRS intensity of three phthalocyanine labels using 632.8&#x02009;nm excitation were obtained from which limits of detection were determined. These were comparable to the detection limits reported using 514.5&#x02009;nm excitation by Faulds <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) and are at biologically relevant concentrations. The addition of phthalocyanines as a new group of SERRS-DNA labels will allow increased multiplexing abilities using this technique. This study has also demonstrated that a mixture of two phthalocyanine labelled oligonucleotides can easily be identified without separation. Larger multiplexes should also be possible using only phthalocyanine labels due to the significant change in main peak position depending on the metal centre present. This also demonstrates multiplexing using 632.8&#x02009;nm excitation rather than 514.5&#x02009;nm excitation used in the previous study by Graham <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). Thus, phthalocyanines have been assessed as labels for the SERRS detection of DNA at three wavelengths and their potential to enhance the multiplexing capacity of this technique has been demonstrated.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><p>The authors would like to thank the British Council for funding and forging the collaboration that led to this paper.Funding to pay for the open access publication charges for this article was provided by the Royal Society of Chemistry's Analytical Trust Fund through the award of the Analytical Grand Prix to DG.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faulds</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbagallo</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Keer</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SERRS as a more sensitive technique for the detection of labelled oligonucleotides compared to fluorescence</article-title><source>Analyst</source><year>2004</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15213819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Qualitative and semi-quantitative trace analysis of acidic monoazo dyes by surface-enhance resonance Raman</article-title><source>Analyst</source><year>1995</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stacy</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Duyne</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surface enhanced Raman and resonance Raman spectroscopy in a nonaqueous electrochemical environment: Tris(2,2&#x02032;-bipyridine)ruthenium(II) adsorbed on silver from acetonitrile</article-title><source>Phys. Chem. Lett</source><year>1983</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>370</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kneipp</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kneipp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelman</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Itzkan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dasari</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single molecule detection using surface-enhanced Raman scattering (SERS)</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett</source><year>1997</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1667</fpage><lpage>1670</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Emory</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probing single molecules and single nanoparticles by surface-enhanced Raman scattering</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>1102</fpage><lpage>1106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9027306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Edmondsun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surface-enhanced resonance-Raman scattering: An informative probe of surfaces</article-title><source>J. Chem. Soc. Dalton Trans</source><year>1996</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>799</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanoparticles with Raman spectroscopic fingerprints for DNA and RNA detection</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>1536</fpage><lpage>1540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12202825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faulds</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of Surface-enhanced resonance Raman scattering for quantitative DNA analysis</article-title><source>Anal. Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14719891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faulds</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative detection of dye labelled DNA using surface enhanced resonance Raman scattering (SERRS) from silver nanoparticles</article-title><source>Talanta</source><year>2005</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18970222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isola</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo-Dinh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surface enhanced Raman gene probe for HIV detection</article-title><source>Anal. Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1352</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9553492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallinder</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitcombe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single multiplex genotyping by surface-enhanced resonance Raman scattering</article-title><source>Anal. Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11924965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soper</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>asymmetrical, water-soluble Phthalocyanine dyes for covalent labeling of oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Bioconjugate Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1244</fpage><lpage>1252</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chernonosov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koval</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Knorre</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernenko</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Derkacheva</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukyanets</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorova</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conjugates of phthalocyanines with oligonucleotides as reagents for sensitized or catalytic DNA modification</article-title><source>Bioinorg. Chem. Appl</source><year>2006</year><volume>2006</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koval</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernonosov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramova</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorova</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>Derkacheva</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukyanets</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosenstized and catalytical oxidation of DNA by metallophthalocyanine-oligonucleotide conjugates</article-title><source>Nucleosides, Nucleotides and Nucleic Acids</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1259</fpage><lpage>1262</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adsorption and surface-enhanced Raman of silver and gold sols</article-title><source>J. Phys. Chem</source><year>1982</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>3391</fpage><lpage>3395</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Marton</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The interaction of spermine and pentamines with DNA</article-title><source>Biochem. J</source><year>1987</year><volume>244</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3663115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koval</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernonosov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramova</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorova</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>Knorre</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Synthesis of a Cobalt(II) Tetracarboxyphthalocyanine&#x02013;deoxyribooligonucleotide conjugate as a reagent for the directed DNA modification</article-title><source>Russ. J. Bioorg. Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>110</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tackley</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phthalocyanines: structure and vibrations</article-title><source>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1419</fpage><lpage>1426</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
