<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17626042</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1976440</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm514</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genomics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>High content of proteins containing 21st and 22nd amino acids, selenocysteine and pyrrolysine, in a symbiotic deltaproteobacterium of gutless worm <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>Vadim N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Biochemistry, University of Nebraska, Lincoln, NE 68588-0664, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed.<phone>+1 402 472 4948</phone><fax>+1 402 472 7842</fax><email>vgladyshev1@unl.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>4952</fpage><lpage>4963</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Selenocysteine (Sec) and pyrrolysine (Pyl) are rare amino acids that are cotranslationally inserted into proteins and known as the 21st and 22nd amino acids in the genetic code. Sec and Pyl are encoded by UGA and UAG codons, respectively, which normally serve as stop signals. Herein, we report on unusually large selenoproteomes and pyrroproteomes in a symbiont metagenomic dataset of a marine gutless worm, <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic>. We identified 99 selenoprotein genes that clustered into 30 families, including 17 new selenoprotein genes that belong to six families. In addition, several Pyl-containing proteins were identified in this dataset. Most selenoproteins and Pyl-containing proteins were present in a single deltaproteobacterium, &#x003b4;1 symbiont, which contained the largest number of both selenoproteins and Pyl-containing proteins of any organism reported to date. Our data contrast with the previous observations that symbionts and host-associated bacteria either lose Sec utilization or possess a limited number of selenoproteins, and suggest that the environment in the gutless worm promotes Sec and Pyl utilization. Anaerobic conditions and consistent selenium supply might be the factors that support the use of amino acids that extend the genetic code.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Selenium (Se) is an essential micronutrient due to its requirement for biosynthesis and function of the 21st amino acid, selenocysteine (Sec). This amino acid is typically found in the active sites of a small number of selenoproteins in all three domains of life: archaea, bacteria and eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3 B4">1&#x02013;4</xref>). Biosynthesis of Sec and its cotranslational insertion into polypeptides require a complex molecular machinery that recodes in-frame UGA codons, which normally function as stop signals, to serve as Sec codons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5 B6 B7 B8 B9">5&#x02013;9</xref>). Although the occurrence of selenoprotein genes is limited, the Sec UGA codon has become the first addition to the universal genetic code since the code was deciphered 40 years ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>).</p><p>The mechanism of Sec insertion differs in the three domains of life. In bacteria, this process has been most thoroughly elucidated in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Translation of bacterial selenoprotein mRNA requires both a selenocysteine insertion sequence (SECIS) element, which is a stem-loop structure immediately downstream of Sec-encoding UGA codon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>), and <italic>trans</italic>-acting factors dedicated to Sec incorporation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). In archaea and eukaryotes, SECIS elements are located in 3&#x02032;-UTRs and some factors involved in Sec biosynthesis and insertion are different. Recent identification of Sec synthase, SecS, in eukaryotes, which is different from the bacterial Sec synthase, SelA, provided important insights into Sec biosynthesis in these organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>).</p><p>Recently, an additional rare amino acid pyrrolysine (Pyl), was identified, which expanded the canonical genetic code to 22 amino acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Pyl is inserted in response to UAG codon in several methanogenic archaea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Although the mechanism of Pyl biosynthesis and incorporation into protein is not fully understood, the presence of a tRNA<sup>pyl</sup> gene (<italic>pylT</italic>) with the CUA anticodon and of class II aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase gene (<italic>pylS</italic>) argued for cotranslational incorporation of Pyl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). In <italic>Desulfitobacterium hafniense</italic>, a single bacterium, in which a Pyl-containing protein was found, PylS consists of two proteins: PylSn and PylSc (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>).</p><p>In recent years, large-scale genome sequencing projects, including both organism-specific and environmental metagenomic projects, provided a large volume of gene and protein sequence information. However, selenoprotein genes are almost universally misannotated in these datasets because UGA has the dual function of encoding Sec and terminating translation, and only the latter function is recognized by current annotation programs. Several bioinformatics tools have been developed to address this problem and can be used to identify selenoprotein genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16 B17 B18 B19 B20 B21 B22">16&#x02013;22</xref>). These programs have successfully identified many new selenoproteins in both prokaryotic and eukaryotic genomes, as well as in the Sargasso Sea environmental samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>).</p><p>Complex symbiotic relationships between bacteria and multicellular eukaryotes have evolved in several environments, but science has traditionally focused on interactions that are pathogenic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Recently, there has been increased recognition of symbiotic interactions that benefit both the microorganism and the host (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). A recent metagenomic analysis of the symbiotic microbial consortium of the marine oligochaete <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic>, a worm lacking a mouth, gut and nephridia, revealed four major co-occurring symbionts, which belong to <italic>Deltaproteobacteria</italic> (&#x003b4;1 and &#x003b4;4) and <italic>Gammaproteobacteria</italic> (&#x003b3;1 and &#x003b3;3), as well as one minor <italic>Spirochaete</italic> species. Since some <italic>Deltaproteobacteria</italic> are selenoprotein-rich organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>), we analyzed the selenoproteomes of these symbionts to examine a possible relationship between selenium and symbiosis.</p><p>To characterize selenoproteome in these symbionts, we adopted a Sec/cysteine(Cys) homology-based search approach, which has been successfully used to characterize the selenoproteomes of both prokaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) and one of the largest prokaryotic sequencing projects, the Sargasso Sea microbial sequencing project (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). We detected known selenoproteins present in this metagenomic dataset and identified several novel selenoproteins. Interestingly, one deltaproteobacterium, &#x003b4;1 symbiont, contains at least 57 selenoproteins, which is the largest number of selenoproteins reported to date in any organism. In addition, several Pyl-containing proteins were identified and most were also found in the same &#x003b4;1 symbiont. Our results provide new insights into understanding evolution and function of these rare amino acids.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Databases and resources</title><p>Assembled sequences of the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; metagenome were obtained from NCBI with the project accession number AASZ00000000 (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genbank/wgs/wgs.AASZ.1.gbff.gz">ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genbank/wgs/wgs.AASZ.1.gbff.gz</ext-link>). The database contained 5597 genomic sequences, which corresponded to a total of 23.7 million nucleotides. Non-redundant (NR) protein database was downloaded from NCBI ftp server. This dataset contained a total of 4 644 764 protein sequences (1 603 127 260 amino acids). BLAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) was also obtained from NCBI.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of Cys/TGA pairs in homologous sequences and minimal ORFs</title><p>Each Cys-containing protein sequence in the NR database was initially searched against the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; metagenomic database for possible TGA/TAG/TAA-containing homologs using TBLASTN with default parameters. Only local alignments, in which Cys in the query protein was aligned with TGA codon in the nucleotide sequence from the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; metagenomic database, were selected for further analysis. For each TGA-containing nucleotide sequence identified in the metagenomic database, regions upstream and downstream of the putative in-frame TGA codon were analyzed to identify a minimal ORF. If a stop codon was found between the in-frame TGA codon and an initiation codon (ATG or GTG), such a TGA-containing sequence was discarded.</p></sec><sec><title>Analyses of TGA-flanking regions and sequence clustering</title><p>We analyzed the conservation of TGA-flanking regions in all six reading frames using BLASTX. If the best hit, which covered the TGA codon with at least a 10-nt overlap, was in a different reading frame than the TGA codon, the corresponding sequence was filtered out. RPS-BLAST was then used to search against conserved domains database (CDD). If the best hit which covered the TGA codon with at least a five-residue overlap was in a different reading frame or additional stop codons appeared within the conserved domain in the same frame, the sequence was removed.</p><p>We used BL2SEQ to cluster remaining protein sequences into different groups. If a local alignment of two proteins had an E-value below 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> and was at least 20 amino acid long, as well as the predicted Sec residues were located at the same position or very close (no more than three residues apart) in the alignment, the two proteins were assigned to the same cluster.</p></sec><sec><title>Cysteine conservation and selenoprotein classification</title><p>All clusters were automatically searched against NCBI NR and microbial databases using BLASTX and TBLASTX. Each predicted ORF containing an in-frame TGA was considered further only if at least two corresponding Cys-containing homologs were detected and the proportion of TGA/Cys pairs in the set of homologs was &#x0003e;50%.</p><p>The remaining clusters were analyzed for occurrence of bacterial SECIS elements, located immediately downstream of the in-frame TGA codons, using bSECISearch program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). The final clusters were manually analyzed and divided into three groups: known selenoproteins, new selenoproteins (clusters containing at least two different sequences with conserved in-frame TGA codons) and selenoprotein candidates (clusters containing only one sequence). It should be noted that sequencing errors that generate in-frame UGA codons could not be excluded for selenoprotein candidates.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of Pyl operon proteins and known Pyl-containing proteins</title><p>PylT and PylS sequences from <italic>Methanosarcina barkeri</italic> (accession number AY064401) were used to search for possible homologs in the metagenomic dataset. Candidate tRNA<sup>Pyl</sup> was further analyzed to identify structural features associated with known tRNA<sup>Pyl</sup>, including a six base-pair acceptor stem and a base between the D and acceptor stems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Other genes in the Pyl operon (<italic>pylB</italic>, <italic>pylC</italic>, <italic>pylD</italic>) were also analyzed by comparative sequence analyses.</p><p>The TBLASTN program with default parameters was used to search for known Pyl-containing methylamine methyltransferases. Open reading frames (ORFs) and conservation of UAG-flanking regions were examined manually. Multiple alignments were generated with ClustalW (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>To identify selenoprotein genes in the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbiont metagenomic dataset, we employed an algorithm that we previously used to identify selenoproteins in the Sargasso Sea microbial dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). This technique takes advantage of the fact that almost all selenoproteins have Cys-containing homologs in different organisms. Intermediate results for each step in the search process are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. In addition, an independent BLAST homology search for Sec-containing homologs of all known selenoprotein families was performed.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>A schematic diagram of the search algorithm. Details of the search process are provided in Materials and methods section.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm514f1"/></fig></p><sec><title>Identification of known selenoproteins in the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; metagenome</title><p>A total of 82 selenoprotein genes, which belong to 24 previously described selenoprotein families, were identified (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Considering that only four major symbionts were identified in the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; metagenomic dataset, each selenoprotein could be mapped into the exact organism, from which the sequence was derived. Essentially all selenoproteins were found to map to symbionts &#x003b4;1 and &#x003b4;4. The former organism contained 44 homologs of known selenoproteins, already the largest number of selenoproteins reported to date in any organism [a previous record holder is also a deltaproteobacterium, <italic>Syntrophobacter fumaroxidans</italic>, which has 31 selenoprotein genes, see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>)]. In addition, several selenoproteins were found in sequences not mapped to any of the four symbionts (designated as unassigned sequences). In contract, no selenoprotein genes could be identified in symbionts &#x003b3;1 and &#x003b3;3. All identified selenoprotein genes were misannotated in the original dataset. Several selenoprotein families detected in the dataset were represented by 2&#x02013;12 selenoprotein genes, whereas six families, DsbG-like, peroxiredoxin (Prx), thioredoxin (Trx), glutaredoxin (Grx), NADH oxidase and UGSC-containing protein [unpublished data; this is a selenoprotein of unknown function that also occurs in <italic>Hyphomonas neptunium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) and detected in the environmental sequencing project of the microbial communities in the North Pacific Subtropical Gyre (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>)], were represented by single sequences. Sequencing errors that generate in-frame TGA codons in these sequences cannot be excluded; however, the fact that they correspond to known selenoproteins and possess strong predicted SECIS elements argue that they are true selenoproteins. Many of the detected selenoprotein families also had Cys-containing homologs in the metagenomic database (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Known selenoprotein families identified in the <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic> symbionts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein family</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total selenoproteins</th><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Cys homolog</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unassigned</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Detected selenoproteins (24 families)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F420-reducing hydrogenase, delta subunit (FrhD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterodisulfide reductase, subunit A (HdrA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhodanese-related sulfurtransferase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AhpD-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prx-like thiol:disulfide oxidoreductase<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proline reductase (PR)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Formate dehydrogenase alpha subunit (FdhA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfurtransferase COG2897</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DsrE-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DsbA-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F420-reducing hydrogenase, alpha subunit (FrhA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selenophosphate synthetase (SelD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HesB-like</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe-S oxidoreductase (GlpC)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distant AhpD homolog<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfurtransferase COG0607</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methione sulfoxide reductase A (MsrA)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methylated-DNA-protein-cysteine methyltransferase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DsbG-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroxiredoxin (Prx)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thioredoxin (Trx)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADH oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutaredoxin<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UGSC-containing protein<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Known selenoprotein families not detected (17 families)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SelW-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione peroxidase (GPx)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homolog of AhpF N-terminal domain<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiol:disulfide interchange protein<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycine reductase selenoprotein A (GrdA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycine reductase selenoprotein B (GrdB)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arsenate reductase<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molybdopterin biosynthesis MoeB protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione S-transferase (GST)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deiodinase-like<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiol-disulfide isomerase-like protein<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein 1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OsmC-like protein<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radical SAM domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative mercuric transport protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cation-transporting ATPase, E1-E2 family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>82</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>44</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>18</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>*Homologs of known thiol-based oxidoreductases or thioredoxin-like fold proteins.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Several selenoprotein families had a particularly high representation in the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts dataset. The most abundant family was F420-reducing hydrogenase delta subunit (FrhD), which included 12 selenoprotein genes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> shows a multiple alignment of this family. This selenoprotein family was previously found in both methanogenic archaea and bacteria. In archaea, its Sec-containing forms contain two Sec residues. In contrast, only one of the two Sec residues was found in different Sec-containing homologs in bacteria, including all metagenomic sequences in the current study. Such flexibility in replacing functionally important Cys with Sec has not been described previously.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Multiple sequence alignment of FrhD family. Conserved residues are highlighted. Sec (U) and the corresponding Cys (C) residues are shown in red and blue, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm514f2"/></fig></p><p>Heterodisulfide reductase subunit A (HdrA) was the second most abundant selenoprotein family, which was represented by 10 selenoprotein genes. It is interesting that most of the HdrA sequences were found to cluster with FrhD sequences. This finding is consistent with our previous hypothesis that the <italic>hdrA-frhD-frhG-frhA</italic> cluster could be laterally transferred between Sec-decoding archaea and <italic>Deltaproteobacteria</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). A rhodanese-related sulfurtransferase [8 genes, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>)], AhpD-like (7 genes), Prx-like thiol:disulfide oxidoreductase (6 genes) and proline reductase (PR, 5 genes) were the next most abundant selenoprotein families. These six families accounted for 58.5% of known selenoprotein sequences, suggesting importance of their functions in the symbiosis involving <italic>Deltaproteobacteria</italic> and the host worm. Other detected selenoprotein families included formate dehydrogenase alpha subunit (FdhA), F420-reducing hydrogenase alpha subunit (FrhA), selenophosphate synthetase (SelD), HesB-like, Fe-S oxidoreductase (GlpC), methionine sulfoxide reductase A (MsrA) and several other selenoprotein families.</p><p>Most of these selenoproteins were redox proteins, which used Sec either to coordinate redox-active metals or for thiol/disulfide-based redox catalysis. Moreover, among 24 selenoprotein families detected in the symbionts&#x02019; metagenomic dataset, at least 17 (67 sequences, 81.7%) were homologs of known thiol oxidoreductases or possessed Trx-like fold (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Many of these selenoproteins contained a conserved UxxC/UxxS/CxxU/TxxU redox motif.</p><p>In two known selenoprotein genes, new Sec positions were identified. Interestingly, in a rhodanese-related sulfurtransferase family, a new protein form was detected wherein a second Sec evolved in the protein, thus resulting in a UxU motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). In addition, a new Sec was observed in FrhA, which resulted in a CxxU motif compared to the previously known UxxC motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B).
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Multiple sequence alignment of several known selenoprotein families containing new features. New Sec positions are shown in pink. Contigs containing these new features are also highlighted in green background. (<bold>A</bold>) Rhodanese-related sulfurtransferase; (<bold>B</bold>) F420-reducing hydrogenase, alpha subunit.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm514f3"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>New selenoproteins identified in the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; metagenome</title><p>In addition to homologs of previously described selenoproteins, we identified six new selenoprotein families, which were represented by at least two individual TGA-containing ORFs (total of 17 genes, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Most of these new families did not correspond to domains of known function and were not homologous to protein families with known functions. Multiple alignments of these new selenoproteins and their Cys-containing homologs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>) highlight sequence conservation of Sec/Cys pairs and their flanking regions. All new selenoproteins contained stable stem-loop structures downstream of Sec-encoding TGA codons that resembled bacterial SECIS elements. Representative predicted SECIS elements found in these new selenoprotein families are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Multiple sequence alignments of new selenoproteins and their Cys homologs. The alignments show Sec-flanking regions in detected proteins. Both selenoprotein sequences detected in the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; metagenome dataset and their Sec/Cys-containing homologs present in indicated organisms are shown. Conserved residues are highlighted. Predicted Sec (U) and the corresponding Cys (C) residues in other homologs are shown in red and blue, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm514f4"/></fig>
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Predicted bacterial SECIS elements in representative sequences of new selenoprotein families. Only sequences downstream of in-frame UGA codons are shown. In-frame UGA codons and conserved guanosines in the apical loop are shown in red. (<bold>A</bold>) YHS domain protein, AASZ01000529; (<bold>B</bold>) Putative redox protein, AASZ01002486; (<bold>C</bold>) OS_HP1, AASZ01000351; (<bold>D</bold>) Conserved protein (COG1810), AASZ01000538; (<bold>E</bold>) OS_HP3, AASZ01001720.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm514f5"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Novel selenoproteins identified in the <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic> symbionts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein family</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total selenoproteins</th><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Cys homolog</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unassigned</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">YHS domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative redox protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS_HP1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved protein COG1810</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS_HP2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OS_HP3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>17</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2"><p>*OS_HP, <italic>Olavius</italic> symbiont's hypothetical protein.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>We also detected at least 15 additional TGA-containing sequences, which showed similarity neither to known and new selenoproteins nor to each other. No definitive conclusion can be made regarding these sequences because of the possibility of sequencing errors. However, some of them contained candidate SECIS elements. Moreover, a small number of TGA-containing homologs of candidate selenoproteins, which have no conserved Cys homologs, but were previously predicted in sequenced bacterial genomes using bSECISearch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), were identified. Future experimental verification is needed for these selenoprotein candidates.</p></sec><sec><title>Pyl-containing proteins detected in the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; dataset</title><p>Pyl has been identified in the active sites of several methylamine methyltransferase families, including monomethylamine methyltransferase (MtmB), dimethylamine methyltransferase (MtbB) and trimethylamine methyltransferase (MttB), in several methanogenic archaea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). However, only one gram-positive bacterium, <italic>D. hafniense</italic>, has been found that possesses a single Pyl-containing MttB homolog. Recently, a transposase family was identified as a new Pyl-containing protein family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Besides <italic>pylT</italic> and <italic>pylS</italic>, a <italic>pylB-pylC-pylD</italic> gene operon (especially <italic>pylD</italic>) was proposed to be specific for Pyl utilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). We examined the occurrence of both Pyl-containing proteins and Pyl operon genes. To our surprise, a total of 10 Pyl-containing methylamine methyltransferase sequences (belonging to MtbB and MttB families) were identified and eight were found in the &#x003b4;1 endosymbiont which also had <italic>pylT</italic>, <italic>pylSn</italic>, <italic>pylSc</italic> and <italic>pylB-pylC-pylD</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Several genes were clustered or were present in the same operon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). An alignment of these sequences and their homologs is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>.
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Occurrence of genes for Pyl-containing proteins and Pyl operon proteins in <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts&#x02019; metagenomic sequences. The <italic>mtbB</italic> and <italic>mttB</italic> genes and other Pyl operon genes are shown by the indicated color scheme in contigs containing these genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm514f6"/></fig>
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Multiple alignments of Pyl-flanking regions in methylamine methyltransferase families (MtbB and MttB). Pyl is shown by X and its location in the alignment is highlighted in red.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm514f7"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Known Pyl-containing proteins and Pyl operon proteins identified in the <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic> symbionts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein family</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sequences</th><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">The <italic>Olavius</italic> symbionts</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other homologs</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unassigned</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>Known Pyl-containing proteins</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MtmB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MtbB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MttB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>Pyl biosynthesis and insertion components</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PylSn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PylSc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PylB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PylC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PylD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PylT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>It was proposed that Pyl is inserted by UAG codons with the help of a putative <underline>py</underline>rro<underline>l</underline>ysine <underline>i</underline>nsertion <underline>s</underline>equence (PYLIS) element, which was predicted to be located downstream of the Pyl-encoding UAG codon in Pyl-containing protein mRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Although the presence of such element in archaea is questionable, it is reasonable that there should be a certain <italic>cis</italic>-element to distinguish the Pyl-encoding UAG codon from stop codon in bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). To search for candidate PYLIS elements in bacteria, sequences downstream of in-frame UAG codons and in putative 5&#x02032;- and 3&#x02032;-UTRs of methylamine methyltransferase mRNAs in both <italic>D. hafniense</italic> and the &#x003b4;1 symbiont were analyzed manually for possible conserved structures and sequence features within these structures. Our analyses revealed no obvious common structure shared by all members of these methylamine methyltransferase families.</p></sec><sec><title>Relationship between different symbiotic conditions and Sec utilization</title><p>Although &#x003b4;1 and &#x003b4;4 endosymbionts belong to the selenoprotein-rich phylum <italic>Deltaproteobacteria</italic>, they are host-associated organisms. In contrast, most selenoprotein-rich organisms identified previously are free-living organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). To investigate the relationships between habitats, genome/proteome size and Sec utilization in bacteria, we carried out an exhaustive homology search of all known selenoprotein families against 450 sequenced bacterial genomes. A total of 116 Sec-utilizing organisms were found. Characteristics of selenoproteomes, genome size, proteome size and habitats for these organisms are shown in Table S1, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref> illustrates correlations among these properties. For Sec-containing organisms, regardless of habitat, the proteome size was proportional to the genome size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>A). No obvious correlation was observed between the size of selenoproteome and the size of proteome. However, a trend could be seen wherein host-associated organisms possess the smallest selenoproteomes compared to free-living organisms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>B).
<fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Relationship among habitats, genome size, proteome size and selenoproteomes. Sec-containing organisms were classified into four groups based on different habitats: aquatic, host-associated, multiple and terrestrial. (<bold>A</bold>) Correlation between genome size and proteome size. (<bold>B</bold>) Correlation between proteome size and selenoproteomes. &#x003b4;1 and &#x003b4;4 symbionts are indicated in the figure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm514f8"/></fig></p><p>We found that &#x003b4;1 and &#x003b4;4 symbionts were outliers with respect to selenoproteome size, especially when compared with other host-associated bacteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>B). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref> shows a comprehensive list of sequenced host-associated selenoprotein-containing bacteria and their living conditions. In contrast to selenoprotein-rich &#x003b4;1 and &#x003b4;4 symbionts, most of these organisms had FdhA and/or SelD as their only selenoproteins. One possibility is that &#x003b4;1 and &#x003b4;4 symbionts are located below the worm cuticle, where essentially no oxygen is present, whereas other parasites, most of which are facultative anaerobic, microaerobic and aerobic, are located in mouth, respiratory tract or gastrointestinal tract, which are exposed to at least some oxygen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). We previously found that decrease in oxygen concentration correlates with increase in Sec utilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic> is the first marine host identified to date which lives in obligate and species-specific associations with Sec-containing bacterial symbionts. Presumably, these deltaproteobacterial symbionts take advantage of a relatively constant supply of selenium in sea water and have increased their demand for this trace element.
<table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Selenoproteins in sequenced symbiotic/host-associated bacteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phylum</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organism</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number of proteins</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of selenoproteins</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitat</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen requirement</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actinobacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Collinsella aerofaciens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2367</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human gut</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anaerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6716</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human smegma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mycobacterium avium</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Betaproteobacteria/ Burkholderiaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Burkholderia mallei</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mammals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Burkholderia multivorans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human lung</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Burkholderia phymatum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7845</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root nodules of tropical legumes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deltaproteobacteriadelta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lawsonia intracellularis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucosa of the lower intestinal tract in animals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>&#x003b4;1 symbiont</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12084</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>57</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Below the worm cuticle of <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Anaerobic</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>&#x003b4;4 symbiont</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3012</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>23</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Below the worm cuticle of <italic>Olavius algarvensis</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Anaerobic</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epsilonproteobacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Campylobacter concisus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human oral cavity and gastrointestinal tract</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microaerophilic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Campylobacter curvus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1921</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human oral cavity and gastrointestinal tract</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microaerophilic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Campylobacter fetus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1719</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human blood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microaerophilic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Helicobacter hepaticus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1875</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucosal layer of the gastrointestinal tract</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microaerophilic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wolinella succinogenes</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2043</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal tract</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microaerophilic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gammaproteobacteria/ Enterobacteriales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower intestine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Photorhabdus luminescens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4683</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The gut of an entomopathogenic nematode</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Salmonella enterica</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4427</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal tract in animals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4425</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal tract in animals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Shigella boydii</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4136</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal tract in animals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Shigella dysenteriae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4274</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal tract in animals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Shigella flexneri 2a</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal tract in animals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Shigella sonnei</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4223</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal tract in animals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gammaproteobacteria/ Pasteurellaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacillus pleuropneumoniae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower respiratory tract of pigs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacillus succinogenes</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1883</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bovine rumen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anaerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Haemophilus ducreyi</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1717</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal mucous membranes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anaerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1791</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal mucous membranes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mannheimia succiniciproducens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2380</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bovine rumen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anaerobic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pasteurella multocida</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucous membranes of the intestinal, genital and respiratory tissues</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spirochaetales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Treponema denticola</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2767</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral cavity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anaerobic</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Whole-genome shotgun and metagenomic sequencing projects have provided a new and powerful tool in the study of community organization and metabolism in natural microbial communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35 B36 B37">35&#x02013;37</xref>). Recently, such methods have been extended to analyze symbiotic relationships. One project involved an analysis of microbes from a marine oligochaete <italic>O. algarvensis</italic>, which lacks a mouth, gut, anus or nephridial excretory system, and contains several bacterial endosymbionts that are located just below the worm cuticle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). These endosymbionts include two sulfur-oxidizing gammaproteobacteria (&#x003b3;1 and &#x003b3;3) and two sulfate-reducing deltaproteobacteria (&#x003b4;1 and &#x003b4;4). Identification of selenoprotein genes in such an unusual symbiotic system may help understand the role of selenium and other micronutrients in the intricate interactions that form such a complex, adaptive consortium.</p><p>In the present study, we employed a procedure that analyzes Sec/Cys pairs in homologous sequences to characterize the selenoproteomes of symbiotic microorganisms in the gutless worm. A total of 82 genes that belonged to 24 previously described prokaryotic selenoprotein families and 17 sequences that belonged to six new selenoprotein families were identified. Most selenoproteins were found to occur in &#x003b4;1 symbiont, which contained 44 known selenoproteins (21 families) and 13 new selenoproteins (6 families). Although the genome size of &#x003b4;1 symbiont is &#x0223c;13.5&#x02009;Mb, which is larger than most other deltaproteobacteria, its reconstruction revealed a single species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). If this is the case, then our study identified an organism, which has the largest selenoproteome reported to date (57 selenoproteins) of any organism, including eukaryotes and archaea.</p><p>Most detected selenoproteins were homologs of thiol-based redox enzymes and contained conserved redox motifs. In contrast, such known redox motifs were largely absent in new selenoproteins identified in the metagenomic dataset. In addition, analysis of secondary structures revealed that these new selenoproteins did not contain thioredoxin-like fold, which is a dominant fold in selenoproteins identified in several marine environmental sequencing projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Perhaps, additional redox reactions that are carried out by new selenoproteins occur in these symbionts.</p><p>Besides the unusually high number of selenoproteins, 10 Pyl-containing proteins were identified in the metagenomic dataset. &#x003b4;1 contained eight of these sequences that belonged to MtbB and MttB families. Thus, the &#x003b4;1 symbiont is also the organism, which has the largest number of Pyl-containing proteins in bacteria. Previously, only one bacterial protein, from <italic>D. hafniense</italic>, was known to possess Pyl. Therefore, identifying so many pyrroproteins in the same bacterium is truly remarkable.</p><p>We previously proposed that UAG may be an ambiguous codon in some archaea, wherein it could serve as either Pyl codon or a stop signal. However, in <italic>D. hafniense</italic>, UAG is frequently used as a stop signal, suggesting an unknown mechanism that allows ribosomes to recognize function of specific UAG codons. By analogy to Sec, which is inserted with the help of SECIS elements, PYLIS elements may be present in bacterial pyrroprotein genes. However, our analysis of genes coding for Pyl-containing proteins revealed no common RNA structures. Additional RNA structure searches should be carried out in the future. The current set of Pyl-containing proteins provides an excellent dataset for further interrogation.</p><p>Given that most symbiotic and host-associated bacteria have lost the ability to utilize Sec or only possess a limited number of selenoproteins, the dramatic abundance of selenoproteins in the two endosymbiotic deltaproteobacteria, especially &#x003b4;1 that also contains many Pyl-containing proteins, is remarkable, raising a series of questions regarding evolution and function of these proteins, as well as their roles in symbiosis. It has been suggested that most selenoproteins evolved from their Cys-containing homologs and anaerobic environments could support the use of Sec (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Compared to most other symbionts and host-associated organisms, which seem to live under aerobic or microaerobic conditions, the obligate anaerobic environment of the two symbionts may be one reason for evolution of new selenoproteins. In addition, compared to the environments where other hosts live, seawater could provide a constant supply of selenium for Sec biosynthesis in these symbionts. An alternative hypothesis is that the host worm needs more efficient metabolism and waste management, which are provided by its symbionts because of the lack of digestive and excretory systems. These special needs might have led to selective advantage of harboring multiple symbionts that utilize amino acids that provide catalytic advantages to various metabolic systems, such as Sec in many redox proteins and Pyl in methylamine methyltransferases.</p><p>Symbiotic deltaproteobacteria in the gutless worm evolved as organisms that support the broadest use of the genetic code, utilizing 63 of 64 codons to code for 22 amino acids. It would be interesting to examine if this and other symbiotic systems provide selective advantage to further expand the genetic code, either utilizing a third stop signal, UAA, or using some codons to insert multiple non-canonical or common amino acids.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>In this study, we report a comprehensive analysis of Sec and Pyl utilization in the <italic>Olavius</italic> symbiont metagenomic database by identifying selenoproteins and Pyl-containing proteins. An organism, &#x003b4;1 symbiont, which contains the largest number of both selenoproteins and pyrroproteins in any organism was identified. This dataset provides opportunities for addressing critical questions regarding evolutionary factors that influence utilization of Sec and Pyl, further extension of the genetic code and understanding of molecular mechanisms of recoding.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR online.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>Supported by NIH GM061603 to V.N.G. We thank the Research Computing Facility of the University of Nebraska &#x02013; Lincoln for the use of Prairiefire supercomputer, and Drs Dmitri Fomenko and Alexey Lobanov for helpful comments. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for the article was provided by NIH GM061603.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Forchhammer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heider</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leinfelder</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Veprek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinoni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selenocysteine: the 21st amino acid</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1828528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stadtman</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selenocysteine</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem</source><year>1996</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8811175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selenocysteine-containing proteins in mammals</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10343164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How selenium has altered our understanding of the genetic code</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3565</fpage><lpage>3576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11997494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowing when not to stop: selenocysteine incorporation in eukaryotes</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8744353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of selenoproteins&#x02014;an overview</article-title><source>Biofactors</source><year>2000</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10705967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rother</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Resch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilting</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selenoprotein synthesis in archaea</article-title><source>Biofactors</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11568443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism and regulation of selenoprotein synthesis</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Nutr</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12524431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepanik</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insight into mammalian selenocysteine insertion: domain structure and ribosome binding properties of Sec insertion sequence binding protein 2</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nirenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caskey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brimacombe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Doctor</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The RNA code in protein synthesis</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb. Symp. Quant. Biol</source><year>1966</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5237186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thanbichler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The function of SECIS RNA in translational control of gene expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>6925</fpage><lpage>6934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12486013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Reches</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Groisman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelberg-Kulka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nature of the minimal &#x02018;selenocysteine insertion sequence&#x02019; (SECIS) in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>896</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mix</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saira</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of selenocysteine on its tRNA in eukaryotes</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17194211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Krzycki</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new UAG-encoded residue in the structure of a methanogen methyltransferase</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>296</volume><fpage>1462</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Krzycki</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyrrolysine encoded by UAG in Archaea: charging of a UAG-decoding specialized tRNA</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>296</volume><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kryukov</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kryukov</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New mammalian selenocysteine-containing proteins identified with an algorithm that searches for selenocysteine insertion sequence elements</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>33888</fpage><lpage>33897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10567350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lescure</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautheret</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Krol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel selenoproteins identified in silico and in vivo by using a conserved RNA structural motif</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>38147</fpage><lpage>38154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10608886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castellano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morozova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Morey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Serras</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Corominas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guigo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In silico</italic> identification of novel selenoproteins in the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> genome</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11493597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An algorithm for identification of bacterial selenocysteine insertion sequence elements and selenoprotein genes</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>2580</fpage><lpage>2589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15797911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kryukov</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Castellano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Novoselov</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobanov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zehtab</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Guigo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of mammalian selenoproteomes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>1439</fpage><lpage>1443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12775843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castellano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Novoselov</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kryukov</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lescure</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Krol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Guigo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconsidering the evolution of eukaryotic selenoproteins: a novel nonmammalian family with scattered phylogenetic distribution</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14710190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kryukov</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prokaryotic selenoproteome</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15105824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fomenko</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The microbial selenoproteome of the Sargasso Sea</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>R37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15833124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossman</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>This place is big enough for both of us</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17225354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McFall-Ngai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>We get by with a little help from our (little) friends</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>303</volume><fpage>1305</fpage><lpage>1307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14988540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woyke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Teeling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Huntemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gloeckner</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>Boffelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symbiosis insights through metagenomic analysis of a microbial consortium</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>443</volume><fpage>950</fpage><lpage>955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16980956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic evolution of selenocysteine utilization in bacteria: a balance between selenoprotein loss and evolution of selenocysteine from redox active cysteine residues</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>R94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17054778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4673</fpage><lpage>4680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Laub</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexandre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mrazek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomic evidence for a close relationship between the dimorphic prosthecate bacteria <italic>Hyphomonas neptunium</italic> and <italic>Caulobacter crescentus</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2006</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>6841</fpage><lpage>6850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16980487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mincer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frigaard</surname><given-names>NU</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Community genomics among stratified microbial assemblages in the ocean's interior</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>311</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranov</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyrrolysine and selenocysteine use dissimilar decoding strategies</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>20740</fpage><lpage>20751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15788401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Longstaff</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Blight</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Green-Church</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Krzycki</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> contextual requirements for UAG translation as pyrrolysine</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17140411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhebri</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Afify</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free gas in the peritoneal cavity: the final hazard of diathermy</article-title><source>Postgrad. Med. J</source><year>2002</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12185229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Detter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokhsar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reverse methanogenesis: testing the hypothesis with environmental genomics</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>305</volume><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15353801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tringe</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>von Mering</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Podar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative metagenomics of microbial communities</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>308</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deboy</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckburg</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Relman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser-Liggett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metagenomic analysis of the human distal gut microbiome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>312</volume><fpage>1355</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16741115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fomenko</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Adair</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-throughput identification of catalytic redox-active cysteine residues</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2007</year><volume>315</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17234949</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
