<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142226</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1669711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl795</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>POGs/PlantRBP: a resource for comparative genomics in plants</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>Nigel S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stiffler</surname><given-names>Nicholas</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barkan</surname><given-names>Alice</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff><institution>Institute of Molecular Biology, University of Oregon</institution><addr-line>Eugene, OR 97403, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 541 346 5145; Fax: +1 541 346 5891; Email: <email>abarkan@molbio.uoregon.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D852</fpage><lpage>D856</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2006 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>POGs/PlantRBP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plantrbp.uoregon.edu/"/>) is a relational database that integrates data from rice, Arabidopsis, and maize by placing the complete Arabidopsis and rice proteomes and available maize sequences into &#x02018;putative orthologous groups&#x02019; (POGs). Annotation efforts will focus on predicted RNA binding proteins (RBPs): i.e. those with known RNA binding domains or otherwise implicated in RNA function. POGs form the heart of the database, and were assigned using a mutual-best-hit-strategy after performing BLAST comparisons of the predicted Arabidopsis and rice proteomes. Each POG entry includes orthologs in Arabidopsis and rice, annotated with domain organization, gene models, phylogenetic trees, and multiple intracellular targeting predictions. A graphical display maps maize sequences on to their most similar rice gene model. The database can be queried using any combination of gene name, accession, domain, and predicted intracellular location, or using BLAST. Useful features of the database include the ability to search for proteins with both a specified domain content and intracellular location, the concurrent display of mutual best hits and phylogenetic trees which facilitates evaluation of POG assignments, the association of maize sequences with POGs, and the display of targeting predictions and domain organization for all POG members, which reveals consistency, or lack thereof, of those predictions.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Comparative analysis of orthologous genes is a powerful method for elucidating gene structure, function and evolution. Identification of orthologs on a gene-by-gene basis can be labor-intensive, and accessing the data available for orthologous genes typically requires visits to multiple species-specific databases. Thus, there is a need for resources that predict orthologous groups and bring together information about the orthologs in a manner that simplifies comparative analyses.</p><p>To facilitate cross-species comparisons among the major model plant species <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis), <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (rice) and <italic>Zea mays</italic> (maize), we developed the database POGs/PlantRBP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plantrbp.uoregon.edu/"/>). POGs/PlantRBP clusters proteins in the rice and Arabidopsis proteomes into putative orthologous groups (POGs) based on a mutual-best-hits strategy, with POG assignments subsequently evaluated by phylogenetic analysis. Each POG display page includes a graphical representation of the domain organization of POG members, the results of two targeting predictors for each of the nucleus, chloroplast, mitochondrion, and secretory system, and a phylogenetic tree from which users can navigate to related POGs. Maize genomic and cDNA sequences are associated with the POG containing the rice gene with which they are most similar. The design of the database is illustrated in Supplementary Figure 1.</p><p>A web interface allows searches that combine search terms for different feature types (e.g. predicted intracellular location and predicted domain content), and displays data in a form that aids comparisons among orthologs. Annotation efforts are focusing on &#x02018;RNA binding proteins&#x02019; (RBPs), i.e. those proteins predicted to interact with RNA and/or influence RNA function. This protein class is more complex in plants than in metazoa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>) and includes several protein families that are largely specific to plants [e.g. the PPR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>) and CRM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>) families]. A prerequisite for a comprehensive understanding of the network of RNA&#x02013;protein interactions in plants is a catalog of plant RBPs. POGs/PlantRBP provides a new tool for this purpose.</p></sec><sec><title>DATABASE CONSTRUCTION</title><sec><title>POG assignment</title><p>Predicted rice and Arabidopis proteins were assigned to POGs in the following manner. The proteins predicted by all gene models in both species were compared to one another using WU-Blast 2.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.wustl.edu/"/>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). For each of the &#x0223c;90&#x02009;000 gene models, the top 20 blast hits with an <italic>E</italic>-value &#x0003c;1e&#x02212;5 were re-aligned using NEEDLE, an implementation of the Needleman&#x02013;Wunsch algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>) distributed with the EMBOSS package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>). These global alignments were used to cluster the gene-models into POGs via the mutual-best-hits strategy summarized in Supplementary Figure 2. This strategy yields both one-to-one and many-to-one orthology relationships. It also yields clusters in which no gene is in more than one cluster. All gene-models for a particular locus were placed in the same POG when at least one of the gene models met the mutual-best-hits criterion.</p><p>A phylogenetic approach was used to complement the mutual-best-hit method and aid evaluation of POG assignments (see Supplementary Figure 3). The top blast hits for each protein in a POG that met an <italic>E</italic>-value cutoff of &#x0003c;1e&#x02212;5 (up to 20 such proteins) were examined, and those with &#x0003e;50% coverage (either hit/query or query/hit) were designated &#x02018;closely related&#x02019;. The &#x02018;closely related&#x02019; protein sets for all members of a POG were combined, and this combined set of proteins was used as input to MUSCLE version 3.6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>) to produce a multiple alignment and corresponding guide tree. Where the tree topology supports the POG assignments, the POG is marked as &#x02018;well-supported&#x02019;. POGs containing only proteins that are not &#x02018;closely-related&#x02019; to any other protein (<italic>E</italic>-value &#x0003c; 1e&#x02212;5) in either species are also marked as &#x02018;well-supported&#x02019;. Trees and multiple alignments were stored for later display.</p></sec><sec><title>POG annotation</title><p>Each predicted protein was analyzed for predicted intracellular localization using Predotar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>), TargetP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>), NucPred (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sbc.su.se/~maccallr/nucpred/"/>), and PredictNLS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>). This set of algorithms provides two independent predictions for targeting to each of the chloroplast (TargetP and Predotar), mitochondrion (TargetP and Predotar), nucleus (PredictNLS and NucPred) and secretory system (TargetP and Predotar). Searches can be performed for proteins predicted by either one or both of the &#x02018;redundant&#x02019; algorithms to localize to a specific compartment. Each predicted protein was analyzed for domain content using InterproScan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>) version 3.3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/index.html"/>) with Pfam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>) version 19 and SuperFamily (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>) version 1.69 models. POGs were annotated as &#x02018;putative RNA binding&#x02019; based on a hand-curated list of Interpro domains related to RNA metabolism (Supplementary Table 1), and on entries in the Arabidopsis Splicing Related Genes (ASRG) Database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantgdb.org/SRGD/ASRG/"/>). Available maize genomic and expressed sequence tag (EST) assemblies and ESTs from the maize full-length cDNA project (see Source Sequences below) were associated with their closest rice counterpart using BLASTn against rice genomic DNA with an <italic>E</italic>-value cutoff of &#x0003c; 1e&#x02212;10. BLASTn was chosen for this purpose because nucleotide similarity provides greater resolution than amino acid similarity for species as closely-related as maize and rice.</p></sec><sec><title>Source Sequences</title><p>Sequences incorporated into PlantRBP were derived from the following sources. Arabidopsis sequences are from version 6 of the Arabidopsis genome annotation and were downloaded from TAIR (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.arabidopsis.org/"/>). Rice sequences (version 4) were downloaded from TIGR (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.tigr.org/"/>). Maize genomic assemblies (MAGI version 4) were downloaded from (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://magi.plantgenomics.iastate.edu/"/>), maize EST assemblies from PlantGDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plantgdb.org/"/>) and ESTs associated with the Arizona full-length cDNA project from (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.maizecDNA.org/download"/>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>USER INTERFACE</title><sec><title>Searches</title><p>A search page includes fields for searching by gene (gene name, gene description, or gene identifier), domain, and predicted intracellular location. Multiple search criteria entered in the same or different field are linked with &#x02018;and&#x02019;, serving to narrow the search. For example, entering &#x02018;RRM PPR&#x02019; under domain, and &#x02018;chloroplast&#x02019; under targeting prediction returns POGs containing proteins with both an RRM and PPR domain that are predicted by either Predotar or TargetP to be targeted to chloroplasts. Searches can be further limited to return proteins predicted by two different algorithms to be targeted to either the chloroplast, mitochondrion, nucleus, or secretory system. A search can be broadened by adding a wild card symbol (*) to a truncated term. For example, typing &#x02018;At*&#x02019; in the Gene field will limit the search to Arabidopsis proteins. A BLAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>) interface is also available. The BLAST results are parsed and displayed using Bioperl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>). Each entry within the BLAST results is linked to the POG with which the gene is associated.</p><p>Search results are returned as a list of POGs that include any proteins that meet the search criteria. POGs in the list are annotated with domains shared by all POG members, protein name (where assigned), and an indication of whether the POG is &#x02018;well-supported&#x02019; according to the criteria described above. Each POG on the list is linked to a more detailed &#x02018;POG View&#x02019; annotation page.</p></sec><sec><title>POG View</title><p>The POG View page (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>) summarizes information about members of each POG in a format that facilitates comparative analyses. The page starts with a list of the component gene models linked to either TIGR (rice) or TAIR (Arabidopsis), and annotated with gene descriptions derived from TIGR (rice) or TAIR (Arabidopsis). Experimental data and literature citations for the RBP subset will be displayed on this page, after manual curation by POGs curators and with community input (see Future Work). The sequences and multiple alignments of POG members can be viewed or downloaded. The alignments are displayed using Mview (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>). For each rice gene model, a pop-up window presents the putative maize ortholog(s) in a graphical alignment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The POG view page. The POG shown includes two Arabidopsis inparalogs and one rice protein, and is supported by the topology of the tree. The information displayed includes (from upper to lower panel) a list of gene models with the rice model linked to putative maize orthologs (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>), a representation of the conserved domains in POG members, a phylogenetic tree that includes POG members (indicated with an asterisk) and other closely-related proteins, and the results of four targeting prediction algorithms. Pop-up windows provide access to protein alignments for POG members (upper panel), the domain organization of all proteins in the tree (lower panel), and an alignment of all proteins in the tree (data not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl795f1"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Pop-up window showing putative maize orthologs. Rice loci in each POG are linked to a graphical representation of putative maize orthologs. Maize genomic assemblies (MAGI's at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://magi.plantgenomics.iastate.edu/"/>), EST assemblies (PlantGDB PUTs at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plantgdb.org/"/>), and ESTs from the maize full-length cDNA project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.maizecdna.org"/>) are displayed below the TIGR gene model for their best rice hit in BLASTn searches against TIGR's rice pseudochromosomes, version 4.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl795f2"/></fig><p>Below the table of gene models is a graphical representation of the conserved domains in each predicted protein. This display highlights inconsistent gene models and inconsistent domain predictions among orthologs. Each domain is linked to its Interpro page. A phylogenetic tree of rice and Arabidopsis proteins related to POG members (see criteria for &#x02018;related&#x02019; proteins above) is displayed beneath the domain maps. Each gene model in the tree is linked to its respective POG, simplifying navigation to related POGs. The sequences, multiple alignment and domain maps of the related genes can be viewed or downloaded. Finally, a summary of the predictions from the four targeting prediction algorithms is shown in a table at the bottom of the page, in a manner that highlights the consistency, or lack thereof, of those predictions.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</title><p>The efficient exploitation of information gleaned with different model organisms, each with unique experimental attributes, requires the identification of orthologous gene sets, representations of data that facilitate comparisons among orthologs, and user-friendly interfaces that aid searches for orthologous groups with specified properties. Previously, two databases have been described that aim to achieve the first of these purposes for model plant species: OrthologID (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nypg.bio.nyu.edu/orthologid/"/>) uses a rigorous phylogenetic method to predict orthologs in the fully-sequenced genomes of Arabidopsis, rice, and poplar, and displays phylogenetic data for each orthologous group; the Genome Cluster Database (GCD) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.ucr.edu/projects/GCD"/>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>) clusters proteins in rice and Arabidopsis based on BLAST similarity and domain organization but does not aim to distinguish orthologs from paralogs. Genes in GCD are linked to protein alignments and expression profiling data. POGs/PlantRBP is distinct from these and other available resources in its use of both mutual-best-hit and phylogenetic analysis to assign orthologous groups, in the types of data that are displayed concurrently for orthologous proteins (domain organization, targeting predictions, literature citations, phylogenetic trees, links to putative maize orthologs), and in the types of searches that are easily accomplished (e.g. searches for orthologous groups containing proteins with both a specified domain content and predicted intracellular location). In addition, this database has a unique emphasis on the annotation of &#x02018;RNA binding&#x02019; proteins, a protein class that is particularly complex in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>).</p><p>Future work will focus on three areas:
<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>An immediate priority is to enhance the annotations of POGs for predicted RBPs. In addition to the annotations available for all POGs (e.g. domains and targeting predictions), annotations for RBPs will include literature citations, mutant phenotypes, and established intracellular locations. Where appropriate, POGs will be linked to subcellular proteome databases [e.g. mitochondria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>) and plastids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>)] and to smaller databases that focus on RBP subsets [e.g. the ASRG Database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>)]. In addition, gene models will be displayed simultaneously for all POG members, to highlight differences in gene prediction. An interface will be provided for community input.</p></list-item><list-item><p>High quality POG assignments are essential for comparative analyses. Currently, the mutual-best-hit and phylogenetic approaches agree for &#x0223c;65% of the POGs; these POGs are designated as &#x02018;well-supported&#x02019;. A priority for the future is to increase the number of well-supported POGs by modifying the strategies used for defining mutual-best-hits and by using more rigorous methods for building phylogenetic trees. Those POGs encoding RBPs and for which the POG is not supported by the tree will be manually curated to resolve the discrepancy. Users with an interest in a POG that is not supported by the tree can assess orthology by downloading the sequences of closely-related proteins from the POG View page, generating and editing global protein alignments and using the edited alignments to calculate trees that include bootstrap values. Users who take this step will be encouraged to share their results through the community annotation interface.</p></list-item><list-item><p>New maize genome and cDNA sequence data are deposited in public repositories on a frequent basis. To maintain an up-to-date representation of putative maize orthologs, we will develop a pipeline to automate the incorporation of new maize genome and EST sequence data. In addition, the database will be updated with recalculated POGs, protein domains, and targeting predictions when new versions of the rice and Arabidopsis gene sets are released.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank John Robbins, Kenny Watkins, and Rosalind Williams-Carrier for helpful input on database functionalities. This work was supported by grant DBI-0421799 from the National Science Foundation. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by grant DBI-0421799 from the National Science Foundation.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brendel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ASRG database: identification and survey of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> genes involved in pre-mRNA splicing</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15575968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belostotsky</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unexpected complexity of Poly(A)-binding protein gene families in flowering plants: three conserved lineages that are at least 200 million years old and possible auto- and cross-regulation</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2003</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12586718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorkovic</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome analysis: RNA recognition motif (RRM) and K homology (KH) domain RNA-binding proteins from the flowering plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11809873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vermel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guermann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delage</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grienenberger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marechal-Drouard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gualberto</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A family of RRM-type RNA-binding proteins specific to plant mitochondria</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>5866</fpage><lpage>5871</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lurin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubourg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellaoui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitton</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruyere</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caboche</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debast</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gualberto</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of Arabidopsis pentatricopeptide repeat proteins reveals their essential role in organelle biogenesis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2089</fpage><lpage>2103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15269332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barkan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klipcan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostersetzer</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CRM domain: an RNA binding module derived from an ancient ribosome-associated protein</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2007</year><comment>in press</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Needleman</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunsch</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A general method applicable to the search for similarities in the amino acid sequence of two proteins</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1970</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5420325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Longden</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleasby</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EMBOSS: the European Molecular Biology Open Software Suite</article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10827456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MUSCLE: a multiple sequence alignment method with reduced time and space complexity</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>113</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15318951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Legeai</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predotar: a tool for rapidly screening proteomes for N-terminal targeting sequences</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1581</fpage><lpage>1590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15174128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heijne</surname><given-names>G.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of organellar targeting signals</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2001</year><volume>1541</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11750667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cokol</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Finding nuclear localization signals</article-title><source>EMBO Rep.</source><year>2000</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11258480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quevillon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silventoinen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harte</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>InterProScan: protein domains identifier</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W116</fpage><lpage>W120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollich</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Pfam protein families database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>D138</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chothia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assignment of homology to genome sequences using a library of hidden Markov models that represent all proteins of known structure</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>313</volume><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11697912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulez</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chervitz</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagdigian</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuellen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapp</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Bioperl toolkit: Perl modules for the life sciences</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1611</fpage><lpage>1618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MView: a web-compatible database search or multiple alignment viewer</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>I.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coruzzi</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeSalle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrthologID: automation of genome-scale ortholog identification within a parsimony framework</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16410324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauricha</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey-Serres</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raikhel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Girke</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome cluster database. A sequence family analysis platform for Arabidopsis and rice</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15888677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heazlewood</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AMPDB: the Arabidopsis Mitochondrial Protein Database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>D605</fpage><lpage>D610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of curated and predicted plastid subproteomes of Arabidopsis. Subcellular compartmentalization leads to distinctive proteome properties</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208420</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
