<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17341464</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1895885</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm025</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Structural Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Biophysical studies of DNA modified with conformationally constrained nucleotides: comparison of 2&#x02032;-<italic>exo</italic> (north) and 3&#x02032;-<italic>exo</italic> (south) &#x02018;locked&#x02019; templates</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maderia</surname><given-names>Melissa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>Shilpa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Van</surname><given-names>Que N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>Victor E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>Joseph J.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Laboratory of Medicinal Chemistry, Center for Cancer Research, National Cancer Institute at Frederick, Frederick, MD, 21702 USA, <sup>2</sup>Molecular Targets Development Program and <sup>3</sup>Laboratory of Proteomics and Analytical Technologies, SAIC-Frederick, Inc., Frederick, MD 21702 USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+1&#x02009;301&#x02009;846&#x02009;5905</phone><fax>+1&#x02009;301&#x02009;846&#x02009;6033</fax><email>barchi@helix.nih.gov</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1978</fpage><lpage>1991</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The biophysical properties of oligodeoxyribonucleotides (ODNs) selectively modified with conformationally &#x02018;locked&#x02019; bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane pseudosugars (Maier,M.A., Choi,Y., Gaus,H., Barchi,J.J. Jr, Marquez,V.E., Manoharan,M. (2004) Synthesis and characterization of oligonucleotides containing conformationally constrained bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane pseudosugar analogs <italic>Nucleic Acids Res.</italic>, 32, 3642&#x02013;3650) have been studied by various techniques. Six separate synthetic ODNs based on the Dickerson Drew dodecamer sequence (CGCGAAT*T*CGCG) were examined where each one (or both) of the thymidines (T*) were substituted with a bicyclic pseudosugar locked in either a <italic>North</italic> (2&#x02032;-<italic>exo</italic>) or <italic>South</italic> (3&#x02032;-<italic>exo</italic>) ring pucker. Circular dichroism spectroscopy, differential scanning calorimetry and <sup>1</sup>H NMR spectroscopy were used to examine the duplex stability and conformational properties of the ODNs. Replacement of one or both thymidines with North-locked sugars (RNA-like) into the dodecamer did not greatly affect duplex formation or melt temperatures but distinct differences in thermodynamic parameters were observed. In contrast, incorporation of <italic>South</italic>-locked sugar derivatives that were predicted to stabilize this standard B-DNA, had the unexpected effect of causing a conformational equilibrium between different duplex forms at specific strand and salt concentrations. Our data and those of others suggest that although DNA can tolerate modifications with RNA-like (North) nucleotides, a more complicated spectrum of changes emerges with modifications restricted to South (DNA-like) puckers.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The design and construction of novel DNA oligomers with tunable structural and hybridization properties have recently been the topics of intense research interest. Nucleotide building blocks with synthetic modification in either the furanose ring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) or the nucleobase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) have been used for the design of novel oligonucleotides (ONs) and oligodeoxyribonucleotides (ODNs). Many of these constructs have been found to be useful biochemical and pharmacological tools in antisense and antigene strategies. Basic research in this area has produced an increasing number of synthetically accessible nucleoside analogs and these building blocks will continue to lead to new oligomers with exciting biophysical and therapeutic features.</p><p>There are several structural features of ODNs that combine to form the characteristic global folds of DNA and RNA, including (a) base pair hydrogen bonding and stacking, (b) backbone torsion angle preferences and (c) the conformation of the ribo-or deoxyribofuranose ring. Regarding point (c), most nucleoside monomers exist in a dynamic equilibrium between two furanose puckering forms: The characteristic 3&#x02032;-<italic>endo</italic>/2&#x02032;-<italic>exo</italic> or &#x02018;<italic>North&#x02019;</italic> (<italic>N</italic>) and 2&#x02032;-<italic>endo</italic>/3&#x02032;-<italic>exo</italic> or &#x02018;<italic>South&#x02019;</italic> (<italic>S</italic>) ring conformations. When subjected to the constraints of an ODN duplex, the sugar rings adopt either of the two forms, B-DNA oligomers favoring <italic>S</italic> puckers while A-DNA and RNA favor <italic>N</italic> puckers. Furthermore, the crystal structures of enzymes involved in cellular nucleoside metabolism pathways in complex with their substrates reveal a distinct preference for a particular furanose pucker that is protein dependent. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) Based on these findings, our laboratory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5 B6 B7">5&#x02013;7</xref>) and others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8 B9 B10 B11">8&#x02013;11</xref>) have focused on the synthesis of novel nucleoside analogs that are biased toward one specific ring pucker as potential therapeutic agents. The concept of &#x02018;locking&#x02019;(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) the furanose ring pucker by various synthetic manipulations began about 13 years ago and gave rise to a range of different analogs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Notable examples in the field derive from the bridged nucleic acids (BNAs) concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), where analogs contain an added ring that bridges two atoms of the furanose. One of the most widely studied of these BNAs is one that contains a methylene bridge between the 2&#x02032; oxygen and the 4&#x02032; carbon that confers conformational restriction. These derivatives and ONs containing these monomers have been coined &#x02018;locked nucleic acids&#x02019; (LNAs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>) since the conformation of the bicyclic furanose system is &#x02018;locked&#x02019; in the <italic>N</italic> quadrant of the pseudorotational cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Extensive work has been carried out proving the added thermodynamic stability of LNA&#x02013;RNA duplexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) as well as the triplex-forming ability of these constructs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Pseudorotational cycle for nucleoside furanose ring puckers. Ring puckers for standard nucleosides are typically either in the &#x02018;Northern&#x02019; or &#x02018;Southern&#x02019; hemispheres (illustrated by blue cones). Depictions of the <italic>N</italic> and <italic>S</italic> conventions along with the structure of an LNA monomer are shown. The pseudorotational positions for the <italic>N</italic>-MCT and <italic>S</italic>-MCT analogs are shown on the left half of the wheel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f1"/></fig></p><p>In 1993, our laboratory published the first synthesis of a &#x02018;locked&#x02019; (dideoxy) nucleoside analog based on the carbocyclic bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane (methanocarba (MC) nucleoside) systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>) shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. An advantage of this system is that both <italic>N</italic>- and <italic>S</italic>-locked (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) platforms can be prepared by shifting the position of the fused cyclopropane ring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). A range of nucleoside monomers based on this template have been synthesized and used to query the preferred substrate ring pucker of specific enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). In addition, a single-stranded DNA containing several <italic>N</italic>-locked MC thymidine (<italic>N</italic>-MCT) units has also been shown to hybridize efficiently with a complementary RNA strand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>).</p><p>Based on the hybridization efficiency of many <italic>N</italic>-locked ONs with RNA, there is great therapeutic potential for synthetic ONs in antisense and antigene technologies where regulation of specific gene translation may slow or halt the progression of disease. Recent work has shown that ONs containing <italic>N</italic>-locked LNA units can substitute for small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) in the process of post-transcriptional gene silencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>) adding to the usefulness of these analogs. In addition, binding of ODNs to proteins such as transcription factors often leads to structural adjustments in the helical parameters that may induce bends or kinks in the duplex. During bending of B-DNA, there is an obligatory adjustment of the sugar pucker from <italic>S</italic> toward <italic>N</italic> to relieve torsional and angular strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26 B27 B28">26&#x02013;28</xref>). The ability to pre-organize ONs/ODNs to specific global folds that mimic these adjustments may lead to surrogates that could perturb protein production at the level of transcription. Recent data from our lab suggests that the addition of bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane nucleoside analogs to a standard B-DNA duplex can cause bending toward the minor groove (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>).</p><p>In order to gain a better understanding of how structural variations in the sugar moiety can contribute to both the local and global structural fold of ODNs, both <italic>S</italic>- and <italic>N</italic>-MCT analogs were inserted into a structurally well-characterized self-complementary B-DNA sequence (Dickerson Drew dodecamer, DD) known to contain only <italic>S</italic>-disposed sugar rings. The conformational and thermodynamic changes resulting from inserting either a single modified thymidine or two modified thymidine residues in positions 7 and/or 8 of the CGCGAAT*T*CGCG sequence is the subject of this work.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Synthesis of modified DNA</title><p>Thymidine monomers containing the bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane system were synthesized as described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) and incorporated into the DD by procedures that required modification of the coupling for the addition of the <italic>N</italic>-monomers due to some unexpected side reactions during the oligomer synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Samples were purified by HPLC as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>) and further purified by EtOH precipitation. The precipitant was resuspended in water and lyophilized three times, then taken up in 10&#x02009;mM phosphate buffer containing 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA and varying concentrations of Na<sup>+</sup> (100, 500, or 1000&#x02009;mM) at pH 7.0. DNA concentrations were determined by measuring the UV absorbance at 260&#x02009;nm and fitting to Beer's Law using &#x003b5; = 110&#x02009;700&#x02009;l/mol &#x000b7; cm (Schepartz Lab Biopolymer Calculator at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://paris.chem.yale.edu/extinct.html">http://paris.chem.yale.edu/extinct.html</ext-link>). The wild-type DD sequence was synthesized by the Laboratory of Molecular Technology Oligonucleotide Synthesis core facility at the NCI Frederick (Dr Leo Lee, Head, Frederick, Maryland).</p></sec><sec><title>Differential scanning calorimetry</title><p>Differential Scanning Calorimetry (DSC) data were acquired on a VP-DSC differential scanning calorimeter (Microcal, Inc., Northampton, MA). In a typical experiment, a 25&#x02013;40&#x02009;&#x003bc;M DNA (0.51&#x02009;ml cell volume) solution was scanned from 10 to 90&#x000b0;C at a rate of 1&#x000b0;C/min. A 16-s filter period was used for all data acquisitions. A total of eight alternating scans (four up- and four down-scans) were recorded per experiment. A buffer versus buffer scan was obtained with 10&#x02009;mM phosphate buffer containing 0.1&#x02009;mM EDTA and NaCl (0.1, 0.5 or 1.0&#x02009;M) placed in both of the calorimetric cells. This reference scan was subtracted from each corresponding experimental scan. The resulting thermogram was plotted as heat capacity (<italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub>) versus temperature. From the pre- and post-transition baselines, a cubic baseline was extrapolated under each melting transition. Values for <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> and &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>cal</sub> were obtained after baseline subtraction, and by fitting the thermograms to a two-state model, according to the manufacturer's protocols (OriginLab, Northampton, MA). &#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub> was obtained as the difference between the pre- and post-transition baselines, prior to baseline subtraction, using a step at peak with no baseline subtraction. The Gibbs free energy of binding at 25&#x000b0;C (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b25</sub>) was derived from &#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub>, &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>cal</sub>, and <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> values using the following equations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>)
<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="gkm025um1"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> is total strand concentration (29&#x02013;40&#x02009;&#x003bc;M) determined as described above and <italic>R</italic> is 1.987&#x02009;cal/mol &#x000b7; K.&#x02009;<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> and <italic>T</italic> were in absolute temperature values (K). &#x00394;<italic>S</italic><sub>cal</sub> was determined by taking the difference between &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b</sub>
<italic><sub>T</sub></italic><sub>m</sub> and &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>cal</sub> at the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Circular dichroism</title><p>Circular dichroism (CD) spectra were recorded on a JASCO J-715 spectrometer using a quartz cell with a 1-mm optical path length. Data were recorded in the range of 190&#x02013;350&#x02009;nm at 1.0&#x02009;nm bandwidth, 100&#x02009;mdeg of sensitivity, 0.1&#x02009;nm resolution, 1&#x02009;s response time, a speed of 50&#x02009;nm/min and an average of two scans. A Haake D1 constant temperature bath interfaced to a Jasco controller was used to adjust the sample temperature between 5 and 65&#x000b0;C. Sample concentrations were 90&#x02013;135&#x02009;&#x003bc;M DNA in a total volume of 250&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of phosphate buffer (pH 7.0), with varying concentrations of Na<sup>+</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>NMR spectroscopy</title><p><sup>1</sup>H NMR spectra were acquired on a Varian Inova spectrometer operating at 500&#x02009;MHz using an inverse triple resonance Nalorac (IDTG) variable temperature probe with <italic>z</italic>-gradients. DNA concentrations for NMR studies were 2&#x02009;mM, 0.2&#x02009;mM or 0.04&#x02009;mM for the modified DNA species and 0.9&#x02009;mM for the wild-type dodecamer DNA in pH 7.0 phosphate buffer containing 100&#x02009;mM Na<sup>+</sup> and 10% D<sub>2</sub>O. One-dimensional spectra were acquired with 128 transients using the &#x02018;water&#x02019; macro from the Varian RNAPack suite of pulse sequences. Suppression of the H<sub>2</sub>O signal was performed with WATERGATE using a <italic>sinc</italic> shape for the 90&#x000b0; selective pulse on water. Spectra were acquired with a 12&#x02009;000&#x02009;Hz sweep width, an acquisition time of 2.7&#x02009;s and a preacquisition delay of 1&#x02009;s. Other parameters (power levels, offsets and pulse widths) were optimized for each individual sample. Spectra were acquired at intervals of 5&#x000b0;C from 5 to 65&#x000b0;C and were referenced to external 2,2-Dimethyl-2-silapentane-5-sulfonate sodium salt (DSS). Assignments of the imino protons were obtained by collecting standard COSY, TOCSY and NOESY spectra for each oligomer and using established ON sequential assignment techniques. The assignments were facilitated by comparison with spectra obtained for the wild-type DD. Raw NMR data were processed on a Sun Ultra10&#x02009;440&#x02009;MHz offline workstation using NMRPipe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>Six modified DD ODNs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) were synthesized and studied by a variety of biophysical techniques. The self-complementary single-stranded ODNs contained either an <italic>N</italic>- or <italic>S</italic>-MCT nucleotide in either a single substitution at position T7 or T8, or a double substitution at both positions T7 and T8. N and S superscripts indicate the puckering of each thymidine substitution. After annealing, the resulting double-stranded helix would have an <italic>N</italic>- or <italic>S</italic>-MCT at positions T7/T19 (designated T7<sup>N</sup> or T7<sup>S</sup>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), T8/T20 (designated T8<sup>N</sup> or T8<sup>S</sup>) and T7,8/T19,20 (designated T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup> or T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup>) paired with normal 2&#x02032;-deoxyadenosines. Our assumptions were the following: The presence of one or two residues restricted in the &#x02018;<italic>South</italic>&#x02019; conformation in an all &#x02018;<italic>South</italic>&#x02019; DNA should, in effect, stabilize the duplex whereas perturbations to the local and/or global duplex structure may result from inclusion of nucleotides locked in the &#x02018;<italic>North</italic>&#x02019; conformation. Various experiments were conducted to address the following questions: (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) Do the <italic>S</italic>-modifications help stabilize the duplex? (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) Do the <italic>N</italic>-modifications prevent formation of a stable duplex? (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>) If a duplex is formed, do these perturbations remain localized to the site of modification? The following data supplied some intriguing answers to these questions.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Structures used in this study. The bicyclo [3.1.0] hexane nucleosides that were incorporated into the DNA are shown along with an illustration and nomenclature of the extra protons of these systems (in red).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f2"/></fig></p><sec><title>Circular dichroism</title><p>CD was used to qualitatively assess the conformations populated by the ODNs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. To fully explore the duplex behavior of the analogs, we performed CD measurements at several temperatures and salt concentrations. The CD spectra of all ODNs exhibited characteristics typical of B-type duplex DNA with some minor differences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Typical CD signatures for B-DNA include a positive long wave (275&#x02013;280&#x02009;nm) band and negative shorter wave (&#x0223c;250&#x02009;nm) band of almost equal magnitude often followed by a second zero cross-over point and a small negative band at &#x0223c;210&#x02009;nm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). In CD spectra of A-DNA and RNA, the long-wave positive band shifts to lower wavelength and has significantly higher magnitude than the short-wave negative band; a concomitant increase in the negative band at 210&#x02009;nm is also observed. The native DD, T7<sup>S</sup>, T8<sup>S</sup> and T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> all have typical B-DNA signatures at 25&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A) with the <italic>S</italic>-modified ODNs displaying higher magnitude negative bands at 210&#x02009;nm. The significance of this band with respect to the CD signatures of RNA and RNA-like ODNs (A-DNA) has been under-appreciated according to some (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) but in our case it is difficult to evaluate since all modified ODNs showed an increase in this band. Overall, except for the negative band at 210&#x02009;nm, the CD features of all the <italic>S</italic>-modified ODNs showed little change from the native DD. On the other hand, the spectra of each of the <italic>N</italic>-modified duplexes tend slightly toward a more A-like signature as evidenced by the increased magnitude and hypsochromic shift of the first positive band as well as an increase in magnitude of the negative band at 210&#x02009;nm. These features were shown to increase in the order T7<sup>N</sup> &#x0223c; T8<sup>N</sup> &#x0003c; T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup>, with the double mutant showing the most significant change in both positive and negative band magnitudes as well as a more enhanced hypsochromic shift of the positive long-wavelength band (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). The overall shape, cross-over points, wavelength at maximum ellipticity change and band maxima are similar to those shown previously for the DD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). Temperature-dependent CD spectra also revealed that at temperatures above the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>, the spectra acquired features that were reminiscent of other single-stranded ODNs (data not shown).
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>CD spectra of <italic>S</italic>-MCT- (<bold>A</bold>) and <italic>N</italic>-MCT- (<bold>B</bold>) modified DNAs at 25&#x000b0;C, at 100&#x02009;mM Na<sup>+</sup>, pH 7.0 (phosphate buffer).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f3"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Differential scanning calorimetry</title><p>DSC was used to understand the thermodynamic consequences resulting from incorporation of the bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane-modified bases into the DD. DSC provides an accurate measurement of the thermodynamic quantities describing the melting or dissociation of DNA duplexes such as the change in heat capacity (&#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub>) that accompanies the transition, the melting transition temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>), and the calorimetric enthalpy of dissociation (&#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>cal</sub>). From these values, the Gibbs free energy of binding (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b25</sub>) and the entropy of dissociation (&#x00394;<italic>S</italic><sub>cal</sub>) can be derived. Previous studies of the native DD have shown that increased concentrations of Na<sup>+</sup> ions lead to the stabilization of a duplex structure, while at &#x02264;10&#x02009;mM Na<sup>+</sup> and DNA concentrations &#x02264;50&#x02009;&#x003bc;M, a biphasic transition in the melt curves was obtained with the tentative assignment of the first intermediate as a hairpin loop structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). Therefore, the effect of Na<sup>+</sup> concentration was also examined. A summary of the thermodynamic parameters calculated from the calorimetric data is listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. An enthalpy&#x02013;entropy compensation plot (&#x02212;&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> versus &#x02013;<italic>T</italic>&#x00394;<italic>S</italic>) showed a linear correlation (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.99) and an observed slope of 1.14 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). This compensation demonstrated that the enthalpy and entropy terms were approximately equal in magnitude for all the ODN species, but that the enthalpies were favorable enough to offset the unfavorable dissociation entropies, resulting in moderately strong free energies of duplex formation for all ODN species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B).
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Enthalpy&#x02013;entropy compensation plot for the ODNs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Bar plot of &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>C</sub>, <italic>T</italic>&#x00394;<italic>S</italic><sub>c</sub> and &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>25</sub>. Each bar shows the comparison of the three thermodynamic parameters. The three bars in each cluster represent (from left to right) the data for the labeled ODN in 0.1, 0.5 and 1.0&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f4"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Thermodynamic data for the ODNs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Na<sup>+</sup>] (mM)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> (&#x000b0;C)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub>p</sub> (kcal/mol/&#x000b0;C)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;&#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>c</sub> (kcal/mol)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;&#x00394;<italic>S</italic><sub>c</sub> (cal/mol/K)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b25</sub> (kcal/mol)</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">153.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.780</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.810</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T7<sup>N</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.430</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.820</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">251.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T8<sup>N</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.410</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.780</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.880</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">194.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.803</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">229.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T7<sup>S</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.91</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.280</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.867</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">495.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T8<sup>S</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.702</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.712</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.385</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.807</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">598.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.459</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.440</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">257.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">775.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.923</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.313</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.202</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">488.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.856</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.86</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">575.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.30</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec><title>DSC of N-modified DDs</title><p>The thermodynamic properties of the native DD duplex in 100&#x02009;mM Na<sup>+</sup> were consistent with those obtained earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). Incorporation of either one or two <italic>N</italic>-MCT units slightly destabilized the duplex with <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>s of 60.7 to 62.9&#x000b0;C, while the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of the native DNA measured 65.3&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The T7<sup>N</sup> DNA was the most enthalpically stable species in that series with progressively lower negative values of &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>cal</sub> for the T8<sup>N</sup> and T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup> molecule, respectively. In the case of T7<sup>N</sup>, although its enthalpy of duplex formation was almost 2-fold greater than that of the native DD species, the accompanying entropy change was less favorable, thereby yielding a comparable free energy change (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b25</sub>(native) = &#x02212;11.56 versus &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b25</sub>(T7<sup>N</sup>) = &#x02212;12.33). Overall, the thermodynamic data were relatively similar for the native and <italic>N</italic>-modified species. The data indicated that stable duplexes were formed upon incorporation of the <italic>N</italic>-modified bases and that only minor disruptions in conformation were produced by substituting the central residues with RNA-like furanose surrogates.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>DSC data for the native DD, T7<sup>N</sup>, T8<sup>N</sup> and T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup> ODNs at 0.1&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> (black), 0.5&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> (red), 1.0&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> (blue), pH 7.0 (phosphate buffer). Exact conditions are given in the experimental section.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f5"/></fig></p><p>As expected, at 0.5&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> an increase in the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> value of all <italic>N</italic>-modified DNA species was observed. There was also an associated increase in the calorimetric enthalpy and the change in heat capacity, leading to a more stabilized DNA species in 0.5&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> compared to 0.1&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup>. At 0.5&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup>, the native DNA was slightly more stable (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b25</sub> of &#x02013;12.01&#x02009;kcal) than the modified DNA species (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b25</sub> = &#x02013;10.04 to &#x02013;11.80). Increasing the salt concentration to 1.0&#x02009;M resulted in a concomitant increase in the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> values for the DNA species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A&#x02013;D). However, the high salt concentration led to a paradoxical decrease in the calorimetric enthalpy for the native DD back near the value obtained at 0.1&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> with a compensating increase in entropic stabilization. In addition, the change in heat capacity also decreased for all species, particularly for the native, T7<sup>N</sup> and T8<sup>N</sup> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A&#x02013;C). Interestingly, the T7<sup>N</sup> species seemed to be the most stable ODN overall and at all salt concentrations. All DSC data were fit to a single transition (two-state model) and reasonably low errors to the fit were obtained. Data obtained earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) had postulated the presence of a hairpin structure at low salt and DNA concentrations at a <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> higher than that of the duplex. Although we did not examine the ODNs under these conditions, both the calorimetric and NMR data (see below) obtained here did not indicate the presence of any hairpin structures.</p></sec><sec><title>DSC of S-modified ODNs</title><p>As discussed above, there was nothing extraordinary in the CD data of the <italic>S</italic>-modified DDs and it was thought these analogs would stabilize the canonical, B-DNA duplex described previously for the DD. The most striking difference was in the melting behavior (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>) of each duplex. Biphasic-type transitions were observed for all <italic>S</italic>-modified ODNs in standard duplex milieus (0.1&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup>) where low melting species at temperatures between 30 and 36&#x000b0;C were observed followed by higher temperature transitions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). In addition, these lower melting transitions were small with a decreased enthalpy of duplex dissociation on the order of 2&#x02013;8&#x02009;kcal/mol, almost 6-fold lower than that of the native DD. Interestingly, whereas biophysical measurements at varying strand concentrations of the <italic>N</italic>-modified ODN species did not alter the population of structures present (data not shown), the presence and stability of the low-melting species in the <italic>S</italic>-modified ODN species was concentration dependent. At concentrations that are typical for DSC (30&#x02013;50&#x02009;&#x003bc;M) or UV (1&#x02013;10&#x02009;&#x003bc;M) measurements, multiple species were observed. At higher concentrations that are standard in NMR spectroscopy of ODN species (1&#x02013;2&#x02009;mM), only the higher melting duplex form was observed (<italic>vide infra</italic>).
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>DSC data for the native DD, T7<sup>S</sup>, T8<sup>S</sup> and T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> ODNs at 0.1&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> (black), 0.5&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> (red), 1.0&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> (blue), pH 7.0 (phosphate buffer). Exact conditions are given in the experimental section.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f6"/></fig></p><p>For all <italic>S</italic>-modified ODNs, the second melting transitions all had higher <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> values than that of the native DD by at least 1.7&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). These data suggested that inclusion of the <italic>S</italic>-modified base pairs into the DD stabilized the &#x02018;major&#x02019; duplex conformation formed, although additional species were present at equilibrium with incorporation of the <italic>S</italic>-MCT nucleotides into the strand. At higher salt concentrations (0.5 and 1.0&#x02009;M NaCl) the higher melting transitions were enhanced dramatically, evidently at the expense of the lower temperature transitions which virtually disappeared. Hence, the calorimetric enthalpy increased 4&#x02013;10-fold by increasing the salt concentration from 0.1 to 1.0&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> for each <italic>S</italic>-modified species and as much as 4-fold over the &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>cal</sub> of the native DD. In direct contrast to the cooperative unfolding events of the <italic>N</italic>-modified ODN species, the melting transitions were broad for the <italic>S</italic>-modified ODN species at the 0.5 and 1.0&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup>. This suggested that multiple unfolding intermediates were present. Given such broad transitions at the 0.5 and 1.0&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup>, the derived melting temperatures most probably reflected an average of multiple similar species melting at or near the same <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> value. Therefore, the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> values for the <italic>S</italic>-modified ODNs appeared to remain fairly constant with increasing salt, with the exception of the T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> species which showed a 4&#x02013;5&#x000b0;C drop in <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> from 0.1 to 1.0&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> concentrations.</p><p>As with the <italic>N</italic>-modified species, the duplex formation/dissociation of the <italic>South</italic> counterparts revealed an enthalpy&#x02013;entropy compensation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). However, in the case of the T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> species (in 0.5 and 1.0&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B) greater entropy compensation resulted in a less favored &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sub>b25</sub> of duplex formation as compared to the T7<sup>S</sup> or the T8<sup>S</sup> species. This suggested that the incorporation of the modified carbocyclic sugars in the T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> may have caused perturbation of structure and prevented the proper annealing of the duplex. This finding was supported by NMR results where the T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> imino protons showed larger chemical shift changes as compared to the other modified ODN species.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR)</title><sec><title><sup>1</sup>H NMR: global melting of DNA</title><p>Proton NMR spectroscopy at variable temperatures was used to assess structural features and duplex stability of the modified ODN species. Assignments of imino protons and the entire proton network of all ODNs were determined based on standard 2D NMR data ((<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>) and Barchi and Maderia, unpublished results). At 5&#x000b0;C, each ODN from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> revealed all six imino protons (from base pairs G2, G4, T7, T8, G10 and G12) of those anticipated for a duplex formed from this self-complementary sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>), while warming to 25&#x000b0;C caused the imino proton assigned to G12 to fade, perhaps due to fraying at the end of the helix. All imino protons resonated between 12 and 14&#x02009;ppm, chemical shifts that are indicative of duplex formation. Imino protons resonating in the 10&#x02013;11&#x02009;ppm range, which would serve as evidence for hairpin structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>), were not observed at any temperature. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figures 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> show the temperature profiles of the imino resonances for the <italic>N</italic>- and <italic>S</italic>-modified ODNs, respectively. In general, trends for the disappearance of each proton followed those observed in previous studies of the DD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). For example, the protons of base pairs closer to the ends of the duplex were only observed at low temperatures whereas those toward the center of the duplex persisted until close to the melting temperatures.
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>NMR spectra of the imino <sup>1</sup>H region of the <italic>N</italic>-MCT modified oligos at various temperatures. The assignments are as follows: filled diamond T8, filled square T7, filled triangle G2, circle G4, star G10 and double dagger, G12.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f7"/></fig>
<fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>NMR spectra of the imino <sup>1</sup>H region of the <italic>S</italic>-MCT modified oligos at various temperatures. The assignments are as follows: filled diamond T8, filled square T7, filled triangle G2, filled circle G4, star G10 and double dagger, G12.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f8"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title><sup>1</sup>H chemical shifts: effect of temperature</title><p>Differences in <sup>1</sup>H NMR chemical shifts are exquisite indicators of structural/conformational changes. By monitoring the changes in the chemical shifts (&#x00394;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic>) of the protons as a function of temperature, information can be obtained about changes in the chemical environment upon dissociation of the duplex. With increasing temperature, the imino protons primarily shifted upfield and broadened (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figures 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). In general, the T7 and T8 imino protons showed a larger change in chemical shift from 5 to 65&#x000b0;C (&#x00394;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> &#x02264; 0.4&#x02009;ppm for <italic>N</italic>-ODNs; &#x02264;0.8 for <italic>S</italic>-ODNs) compared to the G2, G4 and G10 imino protons (&#x02264;0.15&#x02009;ppm, for <italic>N</italic>-ODNs and &#x02264;0.4&#x02009;ppm for <italic>S</italic>-ODNs) which was consistent with changes observed in the native DD. Non-exchangeable protons, such as the H6 aromatic proton of thymidine and the T7 and T8 methyl protons, which are near the center of the duplex at the site of modification exhibited less than 0.08&#x02009;ppm changes in chemical shifts as a function of temperature from 5 to 65&#x000b0;C in both native and all six T-modified DNA species. This data suggests that the global unfolding of the DNA was not greatly affected by modification of the sugars of the thymidine residues.</p></sec><sec><title><sup>1</sup>H chemical shifts: comparisons to native DD</title><p>At 5&#x000b0;C, the chemical shift of each imino proton of the native DNA was compared to those of the imino protons of each T-modified DNA species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>). Upon incorporation of an <italic>N</italic>-modified thymidine at position 7 (T7<sup>N</sup>), there was a difference of &#x02212;0.40&#x02009;ppm in the chemical shift of the T8 imino proton, but little differences (&#x00394;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> &#x0003c; 0.1&#x02009;ppm) were observed for other imino protons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>A). For the T8<sup>N</sup> DNA, there was a &#x00394;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> of &#x02212;0.23&#x02009;ppm in the chemical shift of T7 compared to the native imino proton as well as a +0.34&#x02009;ppm difference for the <italic>&#x003b4;</italic> of the T8 imino proton. There were only slight changes in the chemical shifts of the guanosine imino protons (less than 0.1&#x02009;ppm) in the T8<sup>N</sup> DNA. However, the double T<sup>N</sup> modification (T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup> ODN) showed changes in chemical shifts for the T7 and T8 imino protons that are similar to the native DD, with the largest difference in chemical shift assigned to the G10 imino proton at &#x00394;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> = 0.17&#x02009;ppm. These same trends were also observed at 25&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>B).
<fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Changes in the chemical shift of the imino protons between the <italic>N</italic>-MCT- and <italic>S</italic>-MCT- modified ODN species and the native DD at 5&#x000b0;C (<bold>A</bold>) and at 25&#x000b0;C (<bold>B</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f9"/></fig></p><p>A contrasting picture emerged from the <italic>S</italic>-modified oligos. For the T7<sup>S</sup> structure, at 5&#x000b0;C, the T7 imino proton experienced a &#x02212;0.42&#x02009;ppm shift while for the T8 imino proton the shift was only 0.08&#x02009;ppm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>A). For T8<sup>S</sup>, very little change was observed for most imino protons in contrast to the T8<sup>N</sup> ODN which showed both upfield and downfield changes for the T7 and T8 imino protons, respectively. The most startling change was seen for the T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> compared to its <italic>N</italic> counterpart. Very little change was observed in the &#x00394;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> for T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup> ODN while the T7 imino proton of T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> shifted by greater than &#x02212;0.8&#x02009;ppm and T8 shifted by &#x02212;0.23&#x02009;ppm relative to the native DD. The changes were consistent from 5 to 25&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>A and B). Based on the DSC data described above, this result is perhaps not surprising. There seem to be extensive local structural rearrangements taking place due to the presence of the modified nucleotides. These may be due to accommodations made for the cyclopropane ring of the modified carbocyclic sugar in the unusual 1&#x02032;-O4&#x02032; position (see discussion).</p><p>Changes in the chemical shift of the non-exchangeable protons between the native DNA and those from the modified DNAs are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10</xref>. The local environment around the aromatic H6 proton and methyl group of the T7 residue in each <italic>N</italic>-modified ODN was slightly modified with the largest &#x00394;<italic>&#x003b4;</italic> observed for the methyl group of the T8 residue in the T7<sup>N</sup> and T8<sup>N</sup> ODNs (&#x02212;0.23 and &#x02212;0.21&#x02009;ppm, respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10</xref>A). Significant shifts were seen for the H6 protons of the T8 residue in both the T7<sup>N</sup> (&#x02212;0.49&#x02009;ppm) and T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup> (0.48&#x02009;ppm) ODNs. For the <italic>S</italic>-MCT-modified structures, the T7<sup>S</sup> ODN displayed the largest change in chemical shift, and this occurred in the T8 residue: H6 and the CH<sub>3</sub> group shifted by 0.22 and 0.18&#x02009;ppm, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10</xref>B). Interestingly, the double-modified duplex, T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup>, showed very little change in the chemical shifts of the aromatic protons, which suggested that the magnetic environment of this duplex was similar to that of the native DD. These changes were consistent with temperature (5&#x02013;25&#x000b0;C, data not shown).
<fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Changes in the chemical shift of select non-exchangeable protons between the <italic>N</italic>-MCT- (<bold>A</bold>) and <italic>S</italic>-MCT- (<bold>B</bold>) modified ODN species and the native DD at 25&#x000b0;C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f10"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Concentration-dependent NMR of S-modified DNA</title><p>In an attempt to obtain more information regarding the various transitions obtained from the DSC data of the <italic>S</italic>-modified ODN species, NMR spectra were collected at the concentrations used to acquire the calorimetric data, i.e. 40 and 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. Interestingly, new peaks in the imino proton region of the spectra were observed at these concentrations. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figure 11</xref> shows the imino proton regions of the spectra for the T7<sup>S</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figure 11</xref>A) and T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figure 11</xref>B) ODNs with the additional peaks indicated by arrows. As before, there were no new resonances in any other region of the spectra that may indicate hairpin structures. No attempt was made to assign these new peaks to a particular structure, but this information corroborated the observed DSC behavior of the <italic>S</italic>-modified DNA species at low single-strand concentrations. As described above, when the DSC data was run at higher salt concentrations which is known to stabilize duplexes, clean transitions were observed at temperatures that were similar to the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>'s of the native DD. To confirm the presence of only one stable species, NMR spectra of the actual lyophilized DSC samples of the <italic>S</italic>-modified DNAs at these salt concentrations were collected at various temperatures. Resonances observed in the imino region of the spectra (12&#x02013;14) were similar to those observed for the major species at other DNA and salt concentrations (not shown).
<fig id="F11" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>1D NMR spectra of (<bold>A</bold>) T7<sup>S</sup> and (<bold>B</bold>) T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> imino regions at 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;M strand concentration. Additional peaks that were not observed in 1&#x02013;2&#x02009;mM solutions are indicated with arrows.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f11"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane system has emerged as an extremely useful template for the study of nucleosides and nucleic acids with a rigidified five-membered ring employed as a surrogate for a standard (deoxy)ribose system. In this article, we presented several biophysical measurements on a series of Dickerson dodecamer DNA sequences where one or two thymidines have been substituted with nucleotides constructed on this template. The template effectively locks the ring pucker of the fused cyclopentane ring into either the Northern (<italic>N</italic>) or Southern (<italic>S</italic>) hemisphere of the pseudorotational cycle. The concept of conformational &#x02018;locking&#x02019; furanose rings in this manner has greatly clarified many aspects of nucleoside and ON/ODN biochemistry for a variety of systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41 B42 B43 B44">41&#x02013;44</xref>). These data confirm the utility of this template as a unique biochemical tool for probing structure&#x02013;activity relationships in ON biology.</p><p>Since the ribose rings of the native DD are puckered primarily in the standard B-type (<italic>S</italic>) conformation, it was anticipated that these substitutions may either stabilize or disrupt the local/global structure accordingly. Our thought experiment was to use the <italic>S</italic>-locked nucleotides as a &#x02018;control&#x02019; unit to stabilize an otherwise B-duplex by pre-organization of the proper sugar ring conformation prior to duplex formation. The <italic>N</italic>-type analogs were thought to disrupt the otherwise B-type helix and introduce a possible nucleation point for transmission of <italic>N</italic>-like conformational information along the sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). Results from CD, NMR and DSC measurements all combined to paint a descriptive picture of the effect of either modified nucleoside on duplex formation and stability. As is shown here and in previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>), the incorporation of <italic>N</italic>-locked analogs only minimally perturbed the DD system with regard to duplex formation and thermodynamics. However, we can now conclude that replacing the middle thymidine nucleotides with <italic>S</italic>-locked analogs leads to a more complex equilibrium of species rather than the idealized (and overly simplistic) assumption of an all B-DNA &#x02018;stabilization&#x02019; in a manner that was predicted <italic>a priori</italic>. The data has made the interpretation of the effects of incorporating the <italic>S</italic>-locked analogs significantly more difficult, especially in light of the concentration dependence of the aforementioned equilibrium. However, the major conformation formed was a duplex with a slightly higher thermodynamic stability compared to the native DD.</p><p>An encouraging conclusion to the data described here was that all of the modified ODN species can form stable duplexes under either standard conditions or with slightly elevated salt concentrations. Thus, incorporation of <italic>N</italic>-locked nucleotides into an otherwise B-DNA (<italic>S</italic>-puckered sugars) does not greatly affect duplex formation, at least for the constructs described here. In addition, although the sequence of the DD is self-complimentary and under certain conditions has a tendency to form hairpin structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>), there was no indication of these folds for any of the ODN species studied. However, we have shown earlier that <italic>N</italic>-modified ODNs have a propensity to bend at the central residues more than the native DD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). A recent detailed molecular modeling study of the three <italic>N</italic>-locked DNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>) was in solid agreement with the experimental results in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Hence, it may be surmised that along with their ability to form stable helices, these analogs serve to adjust the local structural environment (bend) in response to conformational restriction in the 2&#x02032;-<italic>exo</italic> puckering regime.</p><p>The data described here suggests that incorporation of the <italic>S</italic>-modified nucleotides into the DD complicate the conformational equilibrium of the ODN species. These were designed to &#x02018;pre-organize&#x02019; a canonical, all B-DNA to a standard duplex fold. However, multiple transitions were observed at particular low salt and strand concentrations. We have not fully characterized the lower temperature transition from these ODN species but as suggested above, it is not a hairpin structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>). NMR analysis showed that multiple species are present but they are limited to solutions that are of low micromolar strand concentrations at salt concentrations of 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. At higher salt concentrations, these lower temperature melting species seem to be replaced solely by duplex structures that melt as broad transitions at a higher temperature and with a large change in &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>cal</sub>. The specific disposition of this duplex may be important to its characteristic change in heat capacity. It may be surmised that the <italic>S</italic>-modified nucleotides actually do stabilize a B-like helix and that the more hydrated environment associated with this type of helix requires a larger enthalpic change upon melting (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Concomitantly, the melting of the putative well-ordered hydration sphere of this type of helix would be accompanied by an unfavorable entropic contribution (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). The validity of these proposals may be supported by recalling that the modified nucleotides are <italic>carbocyclic</italic> in nature, lacking the 4&#x02032;-oxygen atom that may be important for DNA hydration; disruption by intervening carbon atoms could lead to destabilization. Equally important is the presence of additional atoms in the modified templates which may differentially influence the steric environment around the fused cyclopropane. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figure 12</xref> shows a comparison of the central base pairs of the DD highlighting the cyclopropane rings of the T7<sup>S</sup> and T8<sup>S</sup> and the potential steric clashes they may engender with neighboring H5&#x02032;, H5&#x02033; protons. These interactions could potentially cause adjustments in the backbone torsion angles that may serve to destabilize the initial folding of a stable helical conformation. In addition, both solid state and solution structural information on <italic>S</italic>-locked monomers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>) and DNA where an <italic>S</italic>-locked abasic site was incorporated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>) suggested that the rotamer distribution about the anomeric C-N bond (angle &#x003c7;) prefers a <italic>syn</italic> orientation rather than <italic>anti</italic>. Thus, it is perhaps not surprising that &#x02018;forcing&#x02019; a south conformation into the DD is not as well accommodated as a north-locked template. We may conclude that the <italic>S</italic>-modified ODNs resemble the native DD at low strand and Na<sup>+</sup> concentrations; higher concentrations and additional salt is necessary to overcome thermodynamically unfavorable barriers and allow formation of highly stabilized duplexes.
<fig id="F12" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>Side-by-side view of (<bold>A</bold>) T7<sup>S</sup>T8<sup>S</sup> (with residues labeled) and (<bold>B</bold>) the native dodecamer to illustrate the position and potential contacts of the additional atoms in the bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane systems compared to standard furanose rings. Only residues G4-T8 (3&#x02032;-5&#x02032;) and C9-A5 (5&#x02032;-3&#x02032;) are displayed for clarity. Backbone atoms are cyan; H5&#x02032;, H5&#x02032;&#x02032; of selected residues are dark blue; carbon and hydrogen atoms of the cyclopropane ring are shown in red and green, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm025f12"/></fig></p><p>The results obtained here for the <italic>N</italic>-locked DNAs complement the already highly studied systems of &#x02018;locked&#x02019; nucleic acid oligomers constructed with the 2&#x02032;&#x02013;4&#x02032; bridged bicyclic nucleosides developed earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>). These constructs have been employed as hybridizing partners with RNA to potentially elicit a biological response akin to that of antigene therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,55) or RNAi technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Similar hybridization with RNA is achievable with the MCT ONs and it remains to be seen if this technology could be used for gene silencing in a similar manner or via other mechanisms. From our previous results that showed that the T7<sup>N</sup>T8<sup>N</sup> system can induce bending in the DD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>), we feel it is conceptually possible to design ODNs with specific bending properties that would mimic those induced by transcription factor binding to particular DNA sequences. Hence, a judiciously prepared <italic>N</italic>-modified oligo may inhibit this binding through highly specific substitution of the transcribing sequence. However, this will require the high-resolution structural characterization of each ODN separately to define the atomic coordinates of specific modified sequences. Work in this area is currently in progress.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank Professor Alex MacKerrell, University of Maryland, Baltimore, for model structures of the DD and /S/-modified DNA used for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figure 12</xref>. This project has been funded in whole or in part with federal funds from the National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, under contract N01-CO-12400. The content of this publication does not necessarily reflect the views or policies of the Department of Health and Human Services, nor does mention of trade names, commercial products, or organizations imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. This Research was supported in part by the Intramural Research Program of the NIH, National Cancer Institute, Center for Cancer Research. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charge was also provided under contract N01-CO-12400.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herdewijn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conformationally restricted carbohydrate-modified nucleic acids and antisense technology</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>1999</year><volume>1489</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10807006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replacing the nucleobases in DNA with designer molecules</article-title><source>Acc. Chem. Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>936</fpage><lpage>943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12437318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezzitouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Russ</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hiv-1 reverse transcriptase can discriminate between two conformationally locked carbocyclic AZT triphosphate analogs</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>1998</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>2780</fpage><lpage>2789</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Kasus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicklaus</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbaria</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental and structural evidence that herpes 1 kinase and cellular DNA polymerase(S) discriminate on the basis of sugar pucker</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14719951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, conformational analysis, and biological activity of a rigid carbocyclic analog Of 2&#x02032;-deoxyaristeromycin built on a bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane template</article-title><source>Nucleosides Nucleotides</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>250</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicklaus</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conformationally locked nucleoside analogs &#x02013; synthesis of dideoxycarbocyclic nucleoside analogs structurally related to neplanocin-C</article-title><source>J. Med. Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7932567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicklaus</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of cyclopropane-fused dideoxycarbocyclic nucleosides structurally related to neplanocin-C</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett</source><year>1993</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>6233</fpage><lpage>6236</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obika</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of bridged nucleic acid analogs for antigene technology</article-title><source>Chem. Pharma. Bull</source><year>2004</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>1399</fpage><lpage>1404</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koshkin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajwanshi</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel convenient syntheses of lna [2.2.1]bicyclo nucleosides</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>4381</fpage><lpage>4384</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opalinska</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gifford</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jen</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradeepkumar</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Barman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oxetane modified, conformationally constrained, antisense oligodeoxyribonucleotides function efficiently as gene silencing molecules</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>5791</fpage><lpage>5799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15514112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renneberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouliong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Reber</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumperli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leumann</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antisense properties of tricyclo-DNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2751</fpage><lpage>2757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12087157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Locked nucleic acid: a potent nucleic acid analog in therapeutics and biotechnology</article-title><source>Oligonucleotides</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15294076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leumann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleic-acid analogs with restricted conformational flexibility in the sugar-phosphate backbone (&#x02018;bicyclo-DNA&#x02019;). 5. synthesis, characterization, and pairing properties of oligo-alpha-d-(bicyclodeoxynucleotides) of the bases adenine and thymine (Alpha-Bicyclo-DNA)</article-title><source>Helv. Chim. Acta</source><year>1995</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>2077</fpage><lpage>2096</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajwanshi</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kofodhansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and restricted furanose conformations of three novel bicyclic thymine nucleosides: A xylo-lna nucleoside, a 3&#x02032;-o,5&#x02032;- c-methylene-linked nucleoside, and A 2&#x02032;-O,5&#x02032;-C- methylene- linked nucleoside</article-title><source>J. Chem. Soc. Perkin Trans. I</source><year>1999</year><fpage>1407</fpage><lpage>1414</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshkin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LNA (Locked Nucleic Acids): Synthesis and high-affinity nucleic acid recognition</article-title><source>Chem. Commun</source><year>1998</year><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>456</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altona</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaral</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conformational-analysis of sugar ring in nucleosides and nucleotides &#x02013; improved method for interpretation of proton magnetic-resonance coupling-constants</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>1973</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>2333</fpage><lpage>2344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4709237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universality of lna-mediated high-affinity nucleic acid recognition</article-title><source>Chem. Commun</source><year>1998</year><fpage>1247</fpage><lpage>1248</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondensgaard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Locked nucleic acid (LNA) recognition of RNA:NMR solution structures of LNA:RNA hybrids</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2002</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>5974</fpage><lpage>5982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12022830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obika</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hari</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Morio</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Imanishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triplex formation by an oligonucleotide containing conformationally locked C-nucleoside, 5-(2-O,4-C-methylene-beta-d-ribofuranosyl)oxazole</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>224</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezzitouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Russ</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Matteucci</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleosides with A twist. can fixed forms of sugar ring pucker influence biological activity in nucleosides and oligonucleotides?</article-title><source>J. Med. Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>3739</fpage><lpage>3747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8809162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ezzitouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conformationally locked carbocyclic nucleosides built on a bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane template with a fixed southern conformation. synthesis and antiviral activity</article-title><source>J. Chem. Soc. Perkin Trans. I</source><year>1997</year><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddileti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harden</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2-Substitution of adenine nucleotide analogs containing a bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane ring system locked in a northern conformation: enhanced potency as P2y(1) receptor antagonists</article-title><source>J. Med. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>4974</fpage><lpage>4987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14584948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in the synthesis of conformationally locked nucleosides and their success in probing the critical question of conformational preferences by their biological targets</article-title><source>Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14565229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elmen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thonberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljungberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Frieden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Westergaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Urum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Locked nucleic acid (LNA) mediated improvements in sirna stability and functionality</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LNA-antisense rivals sirna for gene silencing</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Drug Discov. Devel</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>194</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakked</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A-form conformational motifs in ligand-bound DNA structures</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10891271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhurkin</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling DNA deformations</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struc. Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>297</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of an ihf-DNA complex: a protein-induced DNA u-turn</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1295</fpage><lpage>1306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8980235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maderia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in DNA bending induced by restricting nucleotide ring pucker studied by weak alignment NMR spectroscopy</article-title><source>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ezzitouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple approach to 1&#x02032;,1&#x02032;a-methano carbocyclic thymidine</article-title><source>J. Chem. Soc. Chem. Commun</source><year>1995</year><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>1346</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enantioselective synthesis of bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane carbocyclic nucleosides via a lipase-catalyzed asymmetric acetylation. characterization of an unusual acetal byproduct</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>5938</fpage><lpage>5945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12182625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of oligonucleotides containing conformationally constrained bicyclo[3.1.0]hexane pseudosugar analogs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>3642</fpage><lpage>3650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15247346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakrabarti</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermal stability of PNA/DNA and DNA/DNA duplexes by differential scanning calorimetry</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>4801</fpage><lpage>4806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10572181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaglio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grzesiek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuister</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nmrpipe &#x02013; a multidimensional spectral processing system based on unix pipes</article-title><source>J. Biomol. NMR</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8520220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Minchenk</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schyolki</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Poletaye</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different conformations of double-stranded nucleic-acid in solution as revealed by circular-dichroism</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>1973</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4687151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tinoco</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maestre</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The optical-activity of nucleic-acids and their aggregates</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biophy. Bioeng</source><year>1980</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>141</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marky</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenfeld</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Breslauer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Salt-dependent conformational transitions in the self-complementary deoxydodecanucleotide D(Cgcaattcgcg) &#x02013; evidence for hairpin formation</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>1983</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1247</fpage><lpage>1257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6850063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlowski</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marky</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Broka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Itakura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Breslauer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Premelting and melting transitions in the D(Cgcgaattcgcg) self-complementary duplex in solution</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1982</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7066294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maderia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in DNA bending induced by restricting nucleotide ring pucker studied by weak alignment NMR spectroscopy</article-title><source>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blommers</surname><given-names>MJJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>JALI</given-names></name><name><surname>Haasnoot</surname><given-names>CAG</given-names></name><name><surname>Aelen</surname><given-names>JMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandermarel</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanboom</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilbers</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of base sequence on the loop folding in DNA hairpins</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1989</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>7491</fpage><lpage>7498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2819083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandanan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Moro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ribose modified nucleosides and nucleotides as ligands for purine receptors</article-title><source>Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11563046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Melman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methanocarba analogs of purine nucleosides as potent and selective adenosine receptor agonists</article-title><source>J. Med. Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2196</fpage><lpage>2203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10841798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicklaus</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Christman</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Banavali</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackerell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of (Cytosine C5)-methyltransferase by oligonucleotides containing flexible (Cyclopentane) and conformationally constrained (Bicyclo[3.1.0]Hexane) abasic sites</article-title><source>Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11563060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Brank</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Banavali</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicklaus</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Christman</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackerell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of oligodeoxyribonucleotides with conformationally constrained abasic sugar targets to probe the mechanism of base flipping by hhai DNA (Cytosine C5)-methyltransferase</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2000</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>12422</fpage><lpage>12434</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pradeepkumar</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamaratski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Foldesi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chattopadhyaya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conformation-specific cleavage of antisense oligonucleotide-rna duplexes by rnase H</article-title><source>J. Chem. Soc. Perkin Trans. II</source><year>2001</year><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maderia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O'keefe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engineering DNA topology with locked nucleosides: a structural study</article-title><source>Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16248015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maderia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O'keefe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manipulating DNA structure with &#x02018;locked&#x02019; nucleosides</article-title><source>Biophys. J</source><year>2004</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>188a</fpage><lpage>189a</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macias</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Banavali</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKerell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA bending induced by carbocyclic sugar analogues constrained to the north conformation</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>2007</year><comment>(Early View Online, 8 January 2007).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braunlin</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Beadling</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Breslauer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conformational screening of oligonucleotides by variable-temperature high performance liquid chromatography: dissecting the duplex-hairpin-coil equilibria of D(Cgcgaattcgcg)</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>2004</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15150797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Kasus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicklaus</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbaria</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental and structural evidence that herpes 1 kinase and cellular DNA polymerase(S) discriminate on the basis of sugar pucker</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14719951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezzitouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Russ</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hiv-1 reverse transcriptase can discriminate between two conformationally locked carbocyclic azt triphosphate analogs</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc</source><year>1998</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>2780</fpage><lpage>2789</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Banavali</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackerell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caught in the act: visualization of an intermediate in the DNA base-flipping pathway induced by hhal methyltransferase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>3877</fpage><lpage>3886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15273274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajwanshi</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Skouv</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LNA (locked nucleic acid)</article-title><source>Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1365</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leumann</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent improvements in antigene technology</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14644181</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
